>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
RICK HOULIHAN: All right.
Hi, everybody.
My name is Rick Houlihan.
I'm a senior principal
solutions architect at AWS.
I focus on NoSQL and
DynamoDB technologies.
I'm here today to talk to
you a little bit about those.
>> My background is
primarily in data layer.
I spent half my development
career writing database,
data access, solutions
for various applications.
I've been in Cloud virtualization
for about 20 years.
So before the Cloud was the Cloud,
we used to call it utility computing.
And the idea was, it's like
PG&E, you pay for what you use.
Today we call it the cloud.
>> But over the years, I've worked
for a couple of companies
you've probably never heard of.
But I've compiled a list of technical
accomplishments, I guess you'd say.
I have eight patents in Cloud systems
virtualization, microprocessor design,
complex event processing,
and other areas as well.
>> So these days, I focus mostly on NoSQL
technologies and the next generation
database.
And that's generally what I'm going
to be here talking to you today about.
So what you can expect
from this session,
we'll go through a brief
history of data processing.
It's always helpful to
understand where we came from
and why we're where we are.
And we'll talk a little
bit about NoSQL technology
from a fundamental standpoint.
>> We will get into some of
the DynamoDB internals.
DynamoDB is AWS's no flavor.
It's a fully managed and
hosted NoSQL solution.
And we'll talk a little bit about table
structure, APIs, data types, indexes,
and some of the internals
of that DynamoDB technology.
We'll get into some of the design
patterns and best practices.
We'll talk about how you
use this technology for some
of today's applications.
And then we'll talk a little bit
about the evolution or the emergence
of a new paradigm in programming
called event-driven applications
and how DynamoDB plays in that as well.
And we'll leave you a little bit of
a reference architecture discussion
so we can talk about some of
the ways you can use DynamoDB.
>> So first off-- this is a question
I hear a lot is, what's a database.
A lot of people think they
know what a database is.
If you Google, you'll see this.
It's a a structured set of data held
in a computer, especially one that
is accessible in various ways.
I suppose that's a good
definition of a modern database.
But I don't like it, because
it implies a couple of things.
It implies structure.
And it implies that it's on a computer.
And databases didn't
always exist on computers.
Databases actually existed in many ways.
>> So a better definition of a
database is something like this.
A database is an organized
mechanism for storing, managing,
and retrieving information.
This is from About.com.
So I like this because it really talks
about a database being a repository,
a repository of
information, not necessarily
something that sits on a computer.
And throughout history, we
haven't always had computers.
>> Now, if I ask the average
developer today what's
a database, that's the answer I get.
Somewhere I can stick stuff.
Right?
And it's true.
But it's unfortunate.
Because the database is really
the foundation of the modern app.
It's the foundation
of every application.
And how you build that
database, how you structure
that data is going to dictate how that
application performs as you scale.
>> So a lot of my job today
is dealing with what
happens when developers
take this approach
and dealing with the aftermath
of an application that
is now scaling beyond the original
intent and suffering from bad design.
So hopefully when you
walk away today, you'll
have a couple of tools in
your belt that'll keep you
from making those same mistakes.
All right.
So let's talk about a little bit of
the timeline of database technology.
I think I read an
article not that long ago
and it said something on the lines--
it's a very poetic statement.
It said the history
of data processing is
full of high watermarks
of data abundance.
OK.
Now, I guess that's kind of true.
But I actually look at is as
the history is actually filled
with high watermark of data pressure.
Because the data rate of
ingestion never goes down.
It only goes up.
>> And innovation occurs when
we see data pressure, which
is the amount of data that is
now in coming into the system.
And it cannot be processed
efficiently either in time or in cost.
And that's when we start
to look at data pressure.
>> So when we look at the
first database, this
is the one that was between our ears.
We're all born with it.
It's a nice database.
It has a high availability.
It's always on.
You can always get it.
>> But it's single user.
I can't share my thoughts with you.
You can't get my thoughts
when you want them.
And their abilitiy is not so good.
We forget things.
Every now and then, one of us leaves
and moves on to another existence
and we lose everything
that was in that database.
So that's not all that good.
>> And this worked well over time
when we were back in the day
when all we really needed to know is
where are we going to go on tomorrow
or where we gather the best food.
But as we started to grow as a
civilization and government started
to come into being, and
businesses started to evolve,
we started to realize we
need a little more than what
we could put in our head.
All right?
>> We needed systems of record.
We needed places to be able store data.
So we started writing documents,
creating libraries and archives.
We started developing a
system a ledger accounting.
And that system of ledger counting
ran the world for many centuries,
and maybe even millennia as
we kind of grew to the point
where that data load surpassed
the ability of those systems
to be able to contain it.
>> And this actually happened in the 1880s.
Right?
In the 1880 US Census.
This is really where the turning
point modern data processing.
This is the point at
which the amount of data
that was being collected by the
US government got to the point
where it took eight years to process.
>> Now, eight years-- as
you know, the census
runs every 10 years-- so it's
pretty obvious that by time we
got the 1890 census,
the amount of data that
was going to be processed
by government was
going to exceed the 10 years that it
would take to launched the new census.
This was a problem.
>> So a guy named Herman
Hollerith came along
and he invented unit record punch
cards, punch card reader, punch card
tabulator, and the collation of
the mechanisms for this technology.
And that company that he formed at the
time, along with a couple of others,
actually became one of the pillars of a
small company we know today called IBM.
>> So IBM originally was in
the database business.
And that's really what they did.
They did data processing.
>> As so the proliferation of punch
cards, an ingenious mechanisms
of being able to leverage that
technology to poll sorted result sets.
You can see in this picture
there we have a little--
it's a little small-- but you can see
a very ingenious mechanical mechanism
where we have a punch card deck.
And somebody's taking
a little screwdriver
and sticking through the
slots and lifting it up
to get that match, that
sorted results set.
>> This is an aggregation.
We do this all the time
today in the computer,
where you do it in the database.
We used to do it manually, right?
People put these things together.
And it was the proliferation
of these punch cards
into what we called data drums
and data reels, paper tape.
>> The data processing industry took
a lesson from the player pianos.
Player pianos back at
the turn of the century
used to use paper reels with slots
on to tell it which keys to play.
So that technology was adapted
eventually to store digital data,
because they could put that data
onto those paper tape reels.
>> Now, as a result, data
was actually-- how
you access this data was directly
dependent on how you stored it.
So if I put the data on a tape,
I had access the data linearly.
I had to roll the whole
tape to access all the data.
If I put the data in punch
cards, I could access it
in a little more random
fashion, maybe not as quickly.
>> But there were limitations in how we
access to data based on how was stored.
And so this was a problem
going into the '50s.
Again, we can start to see that as we
develop new technologies to process
the data, right, it opens up
the door for new solutions,
for new programs, new
applications for that data.
And really, governance
may have been the reason
why we developed some of these systems.
But business rapidly became
the driver behind the evolution
of the modern database and
the modern file system.
>> So the next thing that
came up was in the '50s
was the file system and the
development of random access storage.
This was beautiful.
Now, all of sudden, we can put our
files anywhere on these hard drives
and we can access this data randomly.
We can parse that
information out of files.
And we solved all the world's
problems with data processing.
>> And that lasted about 20 or
30 years until the evolution
of the relational database, which
is when the world decided we now
need to have a repository that defeats
the sprawl of data across the file
systems that we've built. Right?
Too much data distributed in too many
places, the de-duplication of data,
and the cost of storage was enormous.
>> In the '70s, the most expensive resource
that a computer had was the storage.
The processor was
viewed as a fixed cost.
When I buy the box,
the CPU does some work.
It's going to be spinning whether
it's actually working or not.
That's really a sunk cost.
>> But what cost me as a
business is storage.
If I have to buy more disks next
month, that's a real cost that I pay.
And that storage is expensive.
>> Now we fast forward 40 years
and we have a different problem.
The compute is now the
most expensive resource.
The storage is cheap.
I mean, we can go anywhere on the
cloud and we can find cheap storage.
But what I can't find is cheap compute.
>> So the evolution of today's
technology, of database technology,
is really focused around
distributed databases
that don't suffer from
the same type of scale
limitations of relational databases.
We'll talk a little bit about
what that actually means.
>> But one of the reasons and
the driver behind this-- we
talked about the data pressure.
Data pressure is something
that drives innovation.
And if you look at over
the last five years,
this is a chart of what the data
load across the general enterprise
looks like in the last five years.
>> And the general rule of thumb
these days-- if you go Google--
is 90% of the data that
we store today, and it was
generated within the last two years.
OK.
Now, this is not a trend that's new.
This is a trend that's been
going out for 100 years.
Ever since Herman Hollerith
developed the punch card,
we've been building data repositories
and gathering data at phenomenal rates.
>> So over the last 100 years,
we've seen this trend.
That's not going to change.
Going forward, we're going to see
this, if not an accelerated trend.
And you can see what that looks like.
>> If a business in 2010 had one
terabyte of data under management,
today that means they're
managing 6.5 petabytes of data.
That's 6,500 times more data.
And I know this.
I work with these businesses every day.
Five years ago, I
would talk to companies
who would talk to me about what a pain
it is to manage terabytes of data.
And they would talk
to me about how we see
that this is probably going
to be a petabyte or two
within a couple of years.
>> These same companies
today I'm meeting with,
and they're talking to me about the
problem are there having managing
tens, 20 petabytes of data.
So the explosion of the
data in the industry
is driving the enormous
need for better solutions.
And the relational database is
just not living up to the demand.
>> And so there's a linear
correlation between data pressure
and technical innovation.
History has shown us
this, that over time,
whenever the volume of data
that needs to be processed
exceeds the capacity of the system
to process it in a reasonable time
or at a reasonable cost,
then new technologies
are invented to solve those problems.
Those new technologies,
in turn, open the door
to another set of problems, which
is gathering even more data.
>> Now, we're not going to stop this.
Right?
We're not going to stop this.
Why?
Because you can't know everything
there is to know in the universe.
And as long as we've been alive,
throughout the history of man,
we have always driven to know more.
>> So it seems like every inch we move
down the path of scientific discovery,
we are multiplying the amount of data
that we need to process exponentially
as we uncover more and more and more
about the inner workings of life,
about how the universe works, about
driving the scientific discovery,
and the invention that
we're doing today.
The volume of data just
continually increases.
So being able to deal with
this problem is enormous.
>> So one of the things
we look as why NoSQL?
How does NoSQL solve this problem?
Well, relational databases,
Structured Query Language,
SQL-- that's really a construct of the
relational database-- these things are
optimized for storage.
>> Back in the '70s, again,
disk is expensive.
The provisioning exercise of storage
in the enterprise is never-ending.
I know.
I lived it.
I wrote storage drivers for an
enterprised superserver company
back in the '90s.
And the bottom line is racking another
storage array was just something that
happened every day in the enterprise.
And it never stopped.
Higher density storage, demand
for high density storage,
and for more efficient storage
devices-- it's never stopped.
>> And NoSQL is a great technology
because it normalizes the data.
It de-duplicates the data.
It puts the data in a structure that
is agnostic to every access pattern.
Multiple applications can hit that
SQL database, run ad hoc queries,
and get data in the shape that they
need to process for their workloads.
That sounds fantastic.
But the bottom line is with any
system, if it's agnostic to everything,
it is optimized for nothing.
OK?
>> And that's what we get with
the relational database.
It's optimized for storage.
It's normalized.
It's relational.
It supports the ad hoc queries.
And it and it scales vertically.
>> If I need to get a bigger SQL database
or a more powerful SQL database,
I go buy a bigger piece of iron.
OK?
I've worked with a lot of customers
that have been through major upgrades
in their SQL infrastructure only
to find out six months later,
they're hitting the wall again.
And the answer from Oracle or MSSQL
or anybody else is get a bigger box.
Well sooner or later, you can't buy a
bigger box, and that's real problem.
We need to actually change things.
So where does this work?
It works well for offline
analytics, OLAP-type workloads.
And that's really where SQL belongs.
Now, it's used today in many online
transactional processing-type
applications.
And it works just fine at
some level of utilization,
but it just doesn't scale
the way that NoSQL does.
And we'll talk a little
bit about why that is.
>> Now, NoSQL, on the other hand,
is more optimized for compute.
OK?
It is not agnostic to
the access pattern.
Is what we call de-normalized
structure or a hierarchical structure.
The data in a relational database is
joined together from multiple tables
to produce the view that you need.
The data in a NoSQL database
is stored in a document that
contains the hierarchical structure.
All of the data that would normally be
joined together to produce that view
is stored in a single document.
And we'll talk a little bit about
how that works in a couple of charts.
>> But the idea here is that you store
your data as these instantiated views.
OK?
You scale horizontally.
Right?
If I need to increase the
size of my NoSQL cluster,
I don't need to get a bigger box.
I get another box.
And I cluster those together,
and I can shard that data.
We'll talk a bit about
what sharding is, to be
able to scale that database
across multiple physical devices
and remove the barrier that
requires me to scale vertically.
>> So it's really built for online
transaction processing and scale.
There's a big distinction
here between reporting, right?
Reporting, I don't know the
questions I'm going to ask.
Right?
Reporting-- if someone from
my marketing department
wants to just-- how many of my customers
have this particular characteristic who
bought on this day-- I don't know
what query they're going to ask.
So I need to be agnostic.
>> Now, in a online
transactional application,
I know what questions I'm asking.
I built the application for
a very specific workflow.
OK?
So if I optimize the data
store to support that workflow,
it's going to be faster.
And that's why NoSQL can
really accelerate the delivery
of those types of services.
All right.
>> So we're going to get into
a little bit of theory here.
And some of you, your eyes
might roll back a little bit.
But I'll try to keep it
as high level as I can.
So if you're in project
management, there's
a construct called the
triangle of constraints.
OK.
The triangle of constrains dictates
you can't have everything all the time.
Can't have your pie and eat it too.
So in project management, that triangle
constraints is you can have it cheap,
you can have it fast,
or you can have it good.
Pick two.
Because you can't have all three.
Right?
OK.
>> So you hear about this a lot.
It's a triple constraint,
triangle of triple constraint,
or the iron triangle is oftentimes--
when you talk to project managers,
they'll talk about this.
Now, databases have
their own iron triangle.
And the iron triangle of data
is what we call CAP theorem.
OK?
>> CAP theorem dictates
how databases operate
under a very specific condition.
And we'll talk about
what that condition is.
But the three points of the triangle,
so to speak, are C, consistency.
OK?
So in CAP, consistency means that all
clients who can access the database
will always have a very
consistent view of data.
Nobody's gonna see two different things.
OK?
If I see the database,
I'm seeing the same view
as my partner who sees
the same database.
That's consistency.
>> Availability means that if the
database online, if it can be reached,
that all clients will always
be able to read and write.
OK?
So every client that
can read the database
will always be able read
data and write data.
And if that's the case,
it's an available system.
>> And the third point is what
we call partition tolerance.
OK?
Partition tolerance means
that the system works well
despite physical network
partitions between the nodes.
OK?
So nodes in the cluster can't
talk to each other, what happens?
All right.
>> So relational databases choose--
you can pick two of these.
OK.
So relational databases choose
to be consistent and available.
If the partition happens between
the DataNodes in the data store,
the database crashes.
Right?
It just goes down.
OK.
>> And this is why they have
to grow with bigger boxes.
Right?
Because there's no-- usually, a cluster
database, there's not very many of them
that operate that way.
But most databases scale
vertically within a single box.
Because they need to be
consistent and available.
If a partition were to be injected,
then you would have to make a choice.
You have to make a choice between
being consistent and available.
>> And that's what NoSQL databases do.
All right.
So a NoSQL database, it
comes in two flavors.
We have-- well, it
comes in many flavors,
but it comes with two basic
characteristics-- what
we would call CP database, or a
consistent and partition tolerance
system.
These guys make the choice that when
the nodes lose contact with each other,
we're not going to allow
people to write any more.
OK?
>> Until that partition is removed,
write access is blocked.
That means they're not available.
They're consistent.
When we see that
partition inject itself,
we are now consistent,
because we're not going
to allow the data change on two
sides of the partition independently
of each other.
We will have to
reestablish communication
before any update to
the data is allowed.
OK?
>> The next flavor would be an AP system,
or an available and partitioned
tolerance system.
These guys don't care.
Right?
Any node that gets a
write, we'll take it.
So I'm replicating my data
across multiple nodes.
These nodes get a client, client comes
in, says, I'm going to write some data.
Node says, no problem.
The node next to him gets
a write on the same record,
he's going to say no problem.
Somewhere back on the back end,
that data's going to replicate.
And then someone's going to realize,
uh-oh, they system will realize, uh-oh,
there's been an update to two sides.
What do we do?
And what they do then is
they do something which
allows them to resolve that data state.
And we'll talk about
that in the next chart.
>> Thing to point out here.
And I'm not going to get too
much into this, because this
gets into deep data theory.
But there's a transactional
framework that
runs in a relational system that
allows me to safely make updates
to multiple entities in the database.
And those updates will occur
all at once or not at all.
And this is called ACID transactions.
OK?
>> ACID gives us atomicity, consistency,
isolation, and durability.
OK?
That means atomic, transactions, all
my updates either happen or they don't.
Consistency means that
the database will always
be brought into a consistent
state after an update.
I will never leave the database in a
bad state after applying an update.
OK?
>> So it's a little different
than CAP consistency.
CAP consistency means all my
clients can always see the data.
ACID consistency means that when
a transaction's done, data's good.
My relationships are all good.
I'm not going to delete a parent row
and leave a bunch of orphan children
in some other table.
It can't happen if I'm consistent
in an acid transaction.
>> Isolation means that transactions
will always occur one after the other.
The end result of the data
will be the same state
as if those transactions
that were issued concurrently
were executed serially.
So it's concurrency
control in the database.
So basically, I can't increment the
same value twice with two operations.
>> But if I say add 1 to this value,
and two transactions come in
and try to do it, one's
going to get there first
and the other one's
going to get there after.
So in the end, I added two.
You see what I mean?
OK.
>> Durability is pretty straightforward.
When the transaction
is acknowledged, it's
going to be there even
if the system crashes.
When that system recovers, that
transaction that was committed
is actually going to be there.
So that's the guarantees
of ACID transactions.
Those are pretty nice guarantees
to have on a database,
but they come at that cost.
Right?
>> Because the problem
with this framework is
if there is a partition in the data
set, I have to make a decision.
I'm going to have to allow
updates on one side or the other.
And if that happens,
then I'm no longer going
to be able to maintain
those characteristics.
They won't be consistent.
They won't be isolated.
This is where it breaks down
for relational databases.
This is the reason relational
databases scale vertically.
>> On the other hand, we have
what's called BASE technology.
And these are your NoSQL Databases.
All right.
So we have our CP, AP databases.
And these are what you call basically
available, soft state, eventually
consistent.
OK?
>> Basically available, because
they're partition tolerant.
They will always be
there, even if there's
a network partition between the nodes.
If I can talk to a node, I'm
going to be able to read data.
OK?
I might not always be able to write
data if I'm a consistent platform.
But I'll be able to read data.
>> The soft state indicates
that when I read that data,
it might not be the same as other nodes.
If a right was issued on a node
somewhere else in the cluster
and it hasn't replicated across the
cluster yet when I read that data,
that state might not be consistent.
However, it will be
eventually consistent,
meaning that when a write
is made to the system,
it will replicate across the nodes.
And eventually, that state
will be brought into order,
and it will be a consistent state.
>> Now, CAP theorem really
plays only in one condition.
That condition is when this happens.
Because whenever it's operating in
normal mode, there's no partition,
everything's consistent and available.
You only worry about CAP
when we have that partition.
So those are rare.
But how the system reacts when those
occur dictate what type of system
we're dealing with.
>> So let's take a look at what
that looks like for AP systems.
OK?
AP systems come in two flavors.
They come in the flavor that is a
master master, 100%, always available.
And they come in the
other flavor, which says,
you know what, I'm going to worry
about this partitioning thing
when an actual partition occurs.
Otherwise, there's going to be primary
nodes who's going to take the rights.
OK?
>> So if we something like Cassandra.
Cassandra would be a master
master, let's me write to any node.
So what happens?
So I have an object in the
database that exists on two nodes.
Let's call that object S.
So we have state for S.
We have some operations
on S that are ongoing.
Cassandra allows me to
write to multiple nodes.
So let's say I get a
write for s to two nodes.
Well, what ends up happening is
we call that a partitioning event.
There may not be a
physical network partition.
But because of the design
of the system, it's
actually partitioning as soon
as I get a write on two nodes.
It's not forcing me to
write all through one node.
I'm writing on two nodes.
OK?
>> So now I have two states.
What's going to happen
is sooner or later,
there's going to be a replication event.
There's going to be what we
called a partition recovery, which
is where these two
states come back together
and there's going to be an algorithm
that runs inside the database,
decides what to do.
OK?
By default, last update
wins in most AP systems.
So there's usually a
default algorithm, what
they call a callback
function, something that
will be called when this condition
is detected to execute some logic
to resolve that conflict.
OK?
The default callback and default
resolver in most AP databases
is, guess what, timestamp wins.
This was the last update.
I'm going to put that update in there.
I may dump this record that I
dumped off into a recovery log
so that the user can come back later
and say, hey, there was a collision.
What happened?
And you can actually dump a record of
all the collisions and the rollbacks
and see what happens.
>> Now, as a user, you can also
include logic into that callback.
So you can change that
callback operation.
You can say, hey, I want
to remediate this data.
And I want to try and
merge those two records.
But that's up to you.
The database doesn't know how to
do that by default. Most the time,
the only thing the database
knows how to do is say,
this one was the last record.
That's the one that's going to win,
and that's the value I'm going to put.
Once that partition recovery
and replication occurs,
we have our state, which
is now S prime, which is
the merge state of all those objects.
So AP systems have this.
CP systems don't need
to worry about this.
Because as soon as a partition comes
into play, they just stop taking
writes.
OK?
So that's very easy to
deal with being consistent
when you don't accept any updates.
That's with CP systems do.
All right.
>> So let's talk a little
bit about access patterns.
When we talk about NoSQL, it's
all about the access pattern.
Now, SQL is ad hoc, queries.
It's relational store.
We don't have to worry
about the access pattern.
I write a very complex query.
It goes and gets the data.
That's what this looks
like, normalization.
>> So in this particular structure,
we're looking at a products catalog.
I have different types of products.
I have books.
I have albums.
I have videos.
The relationship between products
and any one of these books, albums,
and videos tables is 1:1.
All right?
I've got a product ID,
and that ID corresponds
to a book, an album, or a video.
OK?
That's a 1:1 relationship
across those tables.
>> Now, books-- all they
have is root properties.
No problem.
That's great.
One-to-one relationship, I get all
the data I need to describe that book.
Albums-- albums have tracks.
This is what we call one to many.
Every album could have many tracks.
So for every track on
the album, I could have
another record in this child table.
So I create one record
in my albums table.
I create multiple records
in the tracks table.
One-to-many relationship.
>> This relationship is what
we call many-to-many.
OK?
You see that actors could be
in many movies, many videos.
So what we do is we put this mapping
table between those, which it just
maps the actor ID to the video ID.
Now I can create a query the joins
videos through actor video to actors,
and it gives me a nice list of
all the movies and all the actors
who were in that movie.
>> OK.
So here we go.
One-to-one is the top-level
relationship; one-to-many,
albums to tracks; many-to-many.
Those are the three top-level
relationships in any database.
If you know how those
relationships work together,
then you know a lot
about database already.
So NoSQL works a little differently.
Let's think about for a second what it
looks like to go get all my products.
>> In a relational store, I
want to get all my products
on a list of all my products.
That's a lot of queries.
I got a query for all my books.
I got a query from my albums.
And I got a query for all my videos.
And I got to put it
all together in a list
and serve it back up to the
application that's requesting it.
>> To get my books, I join
Products and Books.
To get my albums, I got to join
Products, Albums, and Tracks.
And to get my videos, I have
to join Products to Videos,
join through Actor Videos,
and bring in the Actors.
So that's three queries.
Very complex queries to
assemble one result set.
>> That's less than optimal.
This is why when we talk
about a data structure that's
built to be agnostic to the access
pattern-- well that's great.
And you can see this is really
nice how we've organized the data.
And you know what?
I only have one record for an actor.
>> That's cool.
I've deduplicated all my actors,
and I maintained my associations
in this mapping table.
However, getting the data
out becomes expensive.
I'm sending the CPU all over the system
joining these data structures together
to be able to pull that data back.
>> So how do I get around that?
In NoSQL it's about
aggregation, not normalization.
So we want to say we want to
support the access pattern.
If the access pattern
to the applications,
I need to get all my products.
Let's put all the products in one table.
If I put all the products in one table,
I can just select all the products
from that table and I get it all.
Well how do I do that?
Well in NoSQL there's no
structure to the table.
We'll talk a little bit about
how this works in Dynamo DB.
But you don't have the same
attributes and the same properties
in every single row, in every single
item, like you do in an SQL table.
And what this allows me
to do is a lot of things
and give me a lot of flexibility.
In this particular case, I
have my product documents.
And in this particular
example, everything
is a document in the Products table.
And the product for a book might
have a type ID that specifies a book.
And the application
would switch on that ID.
>> At the application tier, I'm going
to say oh, what record type is this?
Oh, it's a book record.
Book records have these properties.
Let me create a book object.
So I'm going to fill the
book object with this item.
Next item comes and
says, what's this item?
Well this item is an album.
Oh, I got a whole different
processing routine for that,
because it's an album.
You see what I mean?
>> So the application tier-- I
just select all these records.
They all start coming in.
They could be all different types.
And it's the application's logic
that switches across those types
and decides how to process them.
>> Again, so we're optimizing the
schema for the access pattern.
We're doing it by
collapsing those tables.
We're basically taking
these normalized structures,
and we're building
hierarchical structures.
Inside each one of these records
I'm going to see array properties.
>> Inside this document for Albums,
I'm seeing arrays of tracks.
Those tracks now become-- it's
basically this child table that
exists right here in this structure.
So you can do this in DynamoDB.
You can do this in MongoDB.
You can do this in any NoSQL database.
Create these types of
hierarchical data structures
that allow you retrieve data
very quickly because now I
don't have to conform.
When I insert a row into the Tracks
table, or a row into the Albums table,
I have to conform to that schema.
I have to have the attribute or the
property that is defined on that table.
Every one of them,
when I insert that row.
That's not the case in NoSQL.
>> I can have totally different
properties in every document
that I insert into the collection.
So very powerful mechanism.
And it's really how you
optimize the system.
Because now that query, instead
of joining all these tables
and executing a half a dozen queries
to pull back the data I need,
I'm executing one query.
And I'm iterating
across the results set.
it gives you an idea
of the power of NoSQL.
I'm going to kind of go sideways here
and talk a little bit about this.
This is more kind of the
marketing or technology--
the marketing of technology
type of discussion.
But it's important to understand
because if we look at the top
here at this chart,
what we're looking at
is what we call the
technology hype curve.
And what this means is
new stuff comes into play.
People think it's great.
I've solved all my problems.
>> This could be the end
all, be all to everything.
And they start using it.
And they say, this stuff doesn't work.
This is not right.
The old stuff was better.
And they go back to doing
things the way they were.
And then eventually
they go, you know what?
This stuff is not so bad.
Oh, that's how it works.
And once they figure out how it
works, they start getting better.
>> And the funny thing about it
is, it kind of lines up to what
we call the Technology Adoption Curve.
So what happens is we have
some sort technology trigger.
In the case of databases,
it's data pressure.
We talked about the high water points
of data pressure throughout time.
When that data pressure hits a certain
point, that's a technology trigger.
>> It's getting too expensive.
It takes too long to process the data.
We need something better.
You get the innovators
out there running around,
trying to find out what's the solution.
What's the new idea?
>> What's the next best
way to do this thing?
And they come up with something.
And the people with the real pain,
the guys at the bleeding edge,
they'll jump all over it,
because they need an answer.
Now what inevitably happens-- and
it's happening right now in NoSQL.
I see it all the time.
>> What inevitably happens is
people start using the new tool
the same way they used the old tool.
And they find out it
doesn't work so well.
I can't remember who I was
talking to earlier today.
But it's like, when the
jackhammer was invented,
people didn't swing it over
their head to smash the concrete.
>> But that is what's
happening with NoSQL today.
If you walk in to most shops,
they are trying to be NoSQL shops.
What they're doing is
they're using NoSQL,
and they're loading it
full of relational schema.
Because that's how
they design databases.
And they're wondering, why is
it not performing very well?
Boy, this thing stinks.
I had to maintain all my
joins in-- it's like, no, no.
Maintain joins?
Why are you joining data?
You don't join data in NoSQL.
You aggregate it.
>> So if you want to avoid this, learn
how the tool works before you actually
start using it.
Don't try and use the new tools the
same way you used the old tools.
You're going to have a bad experience.
And every single time
that's what this is about.
When we start coming up here,
it's because people figured out
how to use the tools.
>> They did the same thing when
relational databases were invented,
and they were replacing file systems.
They tried to build file systems
with relational databases
because that's what people understood.
It didn't work.
So understanding the best practices
of the technology you're working with
is huge.
Very important.
>> So we're going to get into DynamoDB.
DynamoDB is AWS's
fully-managed NoSQL platform.
What does fully-managed mean?
It means you don't need to
really worry about anything.
>> You come in, you tell
us, I need a table.
It needs this much capacity.
You hit the button, and we provision
all the infrastructure behind the scene.
Now that is enormous.
>> Because when you talk
about scaling a database,
NoSQL data clusters at
scale, running petabytes,
running millions of
transactions per second,
these things are not small clusters.
We're talking thousands of instances.
Managing thousands of instances,
even virtual instances,
is a real pain in the butt.
I mean, think about every time an
operating system patch comes out
or a new version of the database.
What does that mean
to you operationally?
That means you got 1,200
servers that need to be updated.
Now even with automation,
that can take a long time.
That can cause a lot of
operational headaches,
because I might have services down.
>> As I update these databases, I
might do blue green deployments
where I deploy and upgrade half my
nodes, and then upgrade the other half.
Take those down.
So managing the infrastructure
scale is enormously painful.
And AWS take that pain out of it.
And NoSQL databases can
be extraordinarily painful
because of the way they scale.
>> Scale horizontally.
If you want to get a bigger NoSQL
database, you buy more nodes.
Every node you buy is
another operational headache.
So let somebody else do that for you.
AWS can do that.
>> We support document key values.
Now we didn't go too much
into on the other chart.
There's a lot of different
flavors of NoSQL.
They're all kind of getting
munged together at this point.
You can look at DynamoDB and say yes,
we're both a document and a key value
store this point.
And you can argue the features
of one over the other.
To me, a lot of this is really six
of one half a dozen of the other.
Every one of these technologies is a
fine technology and a fine solution.
I wouldn't say MongoDB is better or
worse than Couch, then Cassandra,
then Dynamo, or vice versa.
I mean, these are just options.
>> It's fast and it's
consistent at any scale.
So this is one of the biggest
bonuses you get with AWS.
With DynamoDB is the ability
to get a low single digit
millisecond latency at any scale.
That was a design goal of the system.
And we have customers that are doing
millions of transactions per second.
>> Now I'll go through some of those
use cases in a few minutes here.
Integrated access control--
we have what we call
Identity Access Management, or IAM.
It permeates every system,
every service that AWS offers.
DynamoDB is no exception.
You can control access
to the DynamoDB tables.
Across all your AWS accounts by
defining access roles and permissions
in the IAM infrastructure.
>> And it's a key and integral component in
what we call Event Driven Programming.
Now this is a new paradigm.
>> AUDIENCE: How's your rate of true
positives versus false negatives
on your access control system?
RICK HOULIHAN: True positives
versus false negatives?
AUDIENCE: Returning what
you should be returning?
As opposed to once in a while it
doesn't return when it should validate?
>> RICK HOULIHAN: I couldn't tell you that.
If there's any failures
whatsoever on that,
I'm not the person to ask
that particular question.
But that's a good question.
I would be curious to know
that myself, actually.
>> And so then again, new paradigm
is event driven programming.
This is the idea that you can
deploy complex applications that
can operate a very, very high scale
without any infrastructure whatsoever.
Without any fixed
infrastructure whatsoever.
And we'll talk a little bit
about what that means as we
get on to the next couple of charts.
>> The first thing we'll do
is we'll talk about tables.
API data types for Dynamo.
And the first thing you'll
notice when you look at this,
if you're familiar with any database,
databases have really two kind of APIs
I'd call it.
Or two sets of API.
One of those would be
administrative API.
>> The things they take care of
the functions of the database.
Configuring the storage engine,
setting up and adding tables.
creating database
catalogs and instances.
These things-- in DynamoDB, you
have very short, short lists.
>> So in other databases,
you might see dozens
of commands, of administrative
commands, for configuring
these additional options.
In DynamoDB you don't need those because
you don't configure the system, we do.
So the only thing you need to do is
tell me what size table do I need.
So you get a very
limited set of commands.
>> You get a Create Table Update, Table,
Delete Table, and Describe Table.
Those are the only things
you need for DynamoDB.
You don't need a storage
engine configuration.
I don't need to worry about replication.
I don't need to worry about sharding.
>> I don't need to worry
about any of this stuff.
We do it all for you.
So that's a huge amount of overhead
that's just lifted off your plate.
Then we have the CRUD operators.
CRUD is something what we
call in database that's
Create, Update, Delete operators.
These are your common
database operations.
Things like put item, get item, update
items, delete items, batch query, scan.
If you want to scan the entire table.
Pull everything off the table.
One of the nice things about DynamoDB
is it allows parallel scanning.
So you can actually let me know how many
threads you want to run on that scan.
And we can run those threads.
We can spin that scan up
across multiple threads
so you can scan the entire table
space very, very quickly in DynamoDB.
>> The other API we have is
what we call our Streams API.
We're not going to talk too
much about this right now.
I've got some content later
on in the deck about this.
But Streams is really a running--
think of it as the time ordered
and partition change log.
Everything that's happening on
the table shows up on the stream.
>> Every write to the table
shows up on the stream.
You can read that stream, and
you can do things with it.
We'll talk about what
types of things you
do with the things like replication,
creating secondary indexes.
All kinds of really cool
things you can do with that.
>> Data types.
In DynamoDB, we support both key
value and document data types.
On the left hand side of the screen
here, we've got our basic types.
Key value types.
These are strings,
numbers, and binaries.
>> So just three basic types.
And then you can have sets of those.
One of the nice things about NoSQL is
you can contain arrays as properties.
And with DynamoDB you can contain arrays
of basic types as a root property.
>> And then there's the document types.
How many people are familiar with JSON?
You guys familiar with JSON so much?
It's basically JavaScript,
Object, Notation.
It allows you to basically
define a hierarchical structure.
>> You can store a JSON document on
DynamoDB using common components
or building blocks that are available
in most programming languages.
So if you have Java, you're
looking at maps and lists.
I can create objects that area map.
A map as key values
stored as properties.
And it might have lists of
values within those properties.
You can store this complex
hierarchical structure
as a single attribute
of a DynamoDB item.
>> So tables in DynamoDB, like most
NoSQL databases, tables have items.
In MongoDB you would
call these documents.
And it would be the couch base.
Also a document database.
You call these documents.
Documents or items have attributes.
Attributes can exist or
not exist on the item.
In DynamoDB, there's
one mandatory attribute.
Just like in a relational database,
you have a primary key on the table.
>> DynamoDB has what we call a hash key.
Hash key must be unique.
So when I define a hash table,
basically what I'm saying
is every item will have a hash key.
And every hash key must be unique.
>> Every item is defined
by that unique hash key.
And there can only be one.
This is OK, but oftentimes
what people need
is they want is this hash
key to do a little bit more
than just be a unique identifier.
Oftentimes we want to use that hash key
as the top level aggregation bucket.
And the way we do that is by
adding what we call a range key.
>> So if it's a hash only
table, this must be unique.
If it's a hash and range table, the
combination of the hash and the range
must be unique.
So think about it this way.
If I have a forum.
And the form has topics, it has
posts, and it has responses.
>> So I might have a hash
key, which is the topic ID.
And I might have a range key,
which is the response ID.
That way if I want to get all the
responses for particular topic,
I can just query the hash.
I can just say give me all
the items that have this hash.
And I'm going to get every question
or post for that particular topic.
These top level aggregations
are very important.
They support the primary access
pattern of the application.
Generally speaking, this
is what we want to do.
We want that table--
as you load the table,
we want to structure the data
within the table in such a way
that the application can very
quickly retrieve those results.
And oftentimes the way to do that is
to maintain these aggregations as we
insert the data.
Basically, we're spreading the data
into the bright bucket as it comes in.
>> Range keys allow me-- hash
keys have to be equality.
When I query a hash, I have to say
give me a hash that equals this.
When I query a range, I
can say give me a range
that is using any kind of
rich operator that we support.
Give me all the items for a hash.
Is it equal, greater than,
less than, does it begin with,
does it exist between these two values?
So these types of range queries
that we're always interested in.
Now one thing about data, when
you look at accessing data, when
you access the data, it's
always about an aggregation.
It's always about the records
that are related to this.
Give me everything here that's-- all
the transactions on this credit card
for the last month.
That's an aggregation.
>> Almost everything you do in the
database is some kind of aggregation.
So being able to be able to define
these buckets and give you these range
attributes to be able to query on,
those rich queries support many,
many, many application access patterns.
>> So the other thing the hash key
does is it gives us a mechanism
to be able to spread the data around.
NoSQL databases work best
when the data is evenly
distributed across the cluster.
How many people are familiar
with hashing algorithms?
When I say hash and a hashing--
because a hashing algorithm
is a way of being able to generate
a random value from any given value.
So in this particular case, the
hash algorithm we run is ND 5 based.
>> And if I have an ID, and this
is my hash key, I have 1, 2, 3.
When I run the hash algorithm,
it's going to come back and say,
well 1 equals 7B, 2
equals 48, 3 equals CD.
They're spread all over the key space.
And why do you do this?
Because that makes sure that I can
put the records across multiple nodes.
>> If I'm doing this
incrementally, 1, 2, 3.
And I have a hash range that
runs in this particular case,
a small hash space,
it runs from 00 to FF,
then the records are going to come in
and they're going to go 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.
What happens?
Every insert is going to the same node.
You see what I mean?
>> Because when I split the space,
and I spread these records across,
and I partition, I'm going to say
partition 1 has key space 0 to 54.
Partition 2 is 55 to 89.
Partition 3 is AA to FF.
So if I'm using linearly incrementing
IDs, you can see what's happening.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, all way up to 54.
So as I'm hammering the
records into the system,
everything ends up going to one node.
>> That's not good.
That's an antipattern.
In MongoDB they have this problem
if you don't use a hash key.
MongoDB gives you the option
of hashing the key value.
You should always do that, if
you're using an incrementing hash
key in MongoDB, or you'll be
nailing every write to one node,
and you will be limiting
your write throughput badly.
>> AUDIENCE: Is that A9 169 in decimal?
>> RICK HOULIHAN: Yeah, it's
somewhere around there.
A9, I don't know.
You'd have to get my binary
to decimal calculator.
My brain doesn't work like that.
AUDIENCE: Just a quick one
of your Mongo comments.
So is the object ID that comes
natively with Mongo do that?
RICK HOULIHAN: Does it do that?
If you specify it.
With MongoDB, you have the option.
You can specify-- every document in
MongoDB has to have an underscore ID.
That's the unique value.
>> In MongoDB you can specify
whether to hash it or not.
They just give you the option.
If you know that it's
random, no problem.
You don't need to do that.
If you know that it's not random, that
it's incrementing, then do the hash.
>> Now the thing about
hashing, once you hash
a value-- and this is
why hash keys are always
unique queries, because I've changed
the value, now I can't do a range query.
I can't say is this
between this or that,
because the hash value is not going
to be equivalent to the actual value.
So when you hash that
key, it's equality only.
This is why in DynamoDB hash key
queries are always equality only.
>> So now in a range key--
when I add that range key,
those range key records all come in and
they get stored on the same partition.
So they are very quickly, easily
retrieved because this is the hash,
this is the range.
And you see everything
with the same hash
gets stored on the same partition space.
You can use that range key to help
locate your data close to its parent.
So what am I really doing here?
This is a one to many relationship.
The relationship between a hash key
and the range key is one to many.
I can have multiple hash keys.
I can only have multiple range
keys within every hash key.
>> The hash defines the parent,
the range defines the children.
So you can see there's analog here
between the relational construct
and the same types of
constructs in NoSQL.
People talk about
NoSQL as nonrelational.
It's not nonrelational.
Data always has relationships.
Those relationships just
are modeled differently.
Let's talk a little
bit about durability.
When you write to DynamoDB, writes
are always three-way replicated.
Meaning that we have three AZ's.
AZ's are Availability Zones.
You can think of an Availability
Zone as a data center
or a collection of data centers.
These things are geographically
isolated from each other
across different fault zones, across
different power grids and floodplains.
A failure in one AZ is not
going to take down another.
They are also linked
together with dark fiber.
It supports one sub 1
millisecond latency between AZs.
So real time data replications
capable in multi AZs.
>> And oftentimes multi AZ deployments
meet the high availability requirements
of most enterprise organizations.
So DynamoDB is spread
across three AZs by default.
We're only going to knowledge the write
when two of those three nodes come back
and say, Yeah, I got it.
Why is that?
Because on the read side we're only
going to give you the data back when
we get it from two nodes.
>> If I'm replicating across
three, and I'm reading from two,
I'm always guaranteed
to have at least one
of those reads to be the
most current copy of data.
That's what makes DynamoDB consistent.
Now you can choose to turn
those consistent reads off.
In which case I'm going to say,
I'll only read from one node.
And I can't guarantee it's going
to be the most current data.
>> So if a write is coming in,
it hasn't replicated yet,
you're going to get that copy.
That's an eventually consistent read.
And what that is is half the cost.
So this is something to think about.
When you're reading out DynamoDB, and
you're setting up your read capacity
units, if you choose eventually
consistent reads, it's a lot cheaper,
it's about half the cost.
>> And so it saves you money.
But that's your choice.
If you want a consistent read or
an eventually consistent read.
That's something that you can choose.
>> Let's talk about indexes.
So we mentioned that
top level aggregation.
We've got hash keys, and
we've got range keys.
That's nice.
And that's on the primary table, I
got one hash key, I got one range key.
>> What does that mean?
I've got one attribute that I
can run rich queries against.
It's the range key.
The other attributes on that item--
I can filter on those attributes.
But I can't do things like, it
begins with, or is greater than.
>> How do I do that?
I create an index.
There's two types of
indexes in DynamoDB.
An index is really
another view of the table.
And the local secondary index.
>> The first one we'll talk about.
So local secondaries are coexisted
on the same partition as the data.
And as such, they are on
the same physical node.
They are what we call consistent.
Meaning, they will acknowledge
the write along with the table.
When the write comes in,
we'll write through the index.
We'll write up to the table,
and then we will acknowledge.
So that's consistent.
Once the write has been
acknowledged from the table,
it's guaranteed that the
local secondary index
will have the same vision of data.
But what they allow you do is
define alternate range keys.
>> Have to use the same hash
key as the primary table,
because they are co-located on the
same partition, and they're consistent.
But I can create an index
with different range keys.
So for example, if I had a manufacturer
that had a raw parts table coming in.
And raw parts come in, and
they're aggregated by assembly.
And maybe there's a recall.
>> Any part that was made by this
manufacturer after this date,
I need to pull from my line.
I can spin an index
that would be looking,
aggregating on the date of
manufacture of that particular part.
So if my top level table was
already hashed by manufacturer,
maybe it was arranged on part ID, I
can create an index off that table
as hashed by manufacturer and
ranged on date of manufacture.
And that way I could say, anything that
was manufactured between these dates,
I need to pull from the line.
So that's a local secondary index.
>> These have the effect of
limiting your hash key space.
Because they co-existed
on the same storage node,
they limit the hash key
space to 10 gigabytes.
DynamoDB, under the
tables, will partition
your table every 10 gigabytes.
When you put 10 gigs of data in, we
go [PHH], and we add another node.
>> We will not split the LSI
across multiple partitions.
We'll split the table.
But we won't split the LSI.
So that's something
important to understand
is if you're doing very,
very, very large aggregations,
then you're going to be limited
to 10 gigabytes on your LSIs.
>> If that's the case, we can
use global secondaries.
Global secondaries are
really another table.
They exist completely off to
the side of your primary table.
And they allow me to find a
completely different structure.
So think of it as data is being inserted
into two different tables, structured
in two different ways.
>> I can define a totally
different hash key.
I can define a totally
different range key.
And I can run this
completely independently.
As a matter of fact, I've
provisioned my read capacity
and write capacity for my
global secondary indexes
completely independently
of my primary table.
If I define that index, I tell
it how much read and write
capacity it's going to be using.
>> And that is separate
from my primary table.
Now both of the indexes allow us to
not only define hash and range keys,
but they allow us to
project additional values.
So if I want to read off the index,
and I want to get some set of data,
I don't need to go back to the main
table to get the additional attributes.
I can project those additional
attributes into the table
to support the access pattern.
I know we're probably getting into some
really, really-- getting into the weeds
here on some of this stuff.
Now I got to drift out of this.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
--table key meant was a hash?
The original hash?
Multi-slats?
>> RICK HOULIHAN: Yes.
Yes.
The table key basically
points back to the item.
So an index is a pointer back to
the original items on the table.
Now you can choose to build an
index that only has the table key,
and no other properties.
And why might I do that?
Well, maybe I have very large items.
>> I really only need to know which--
my access pattern might say,
which items contain this property?
Don't need to return the item.
I just need to know
which items contain it.
So you can build indexes
that only have the table key.
>> But that's primarily what
an index in database is for.
It's for being able to quickly
identify which records,
which rows, which
items in the table have
the properties that I'm searching for.
>> GSIs, so how do they work?
GSIs basically are asynchronous.
The update comes into the table,
table is then asynchronously updated
all of your GSIs.
This is why GSIs are
eventually consistent.
>> It is important to note that
when you're building GSIs,
and you understand you're creating
another dimension of aggregation--
now let's say a good example
here is a manufacturer.
I think I might have talked about
a medical device manufacturer.
Medical device manufacturers
oftentimes have serialized parts.
The parts that go into
a hip replacement all
have a little serial number on them.
And they could have millions and
millions and billions of parts
in all the devices that they ship.
Well, they need to aggregate under
different dimensions, all the parts
in an assembly, all the
parts that were made
on a certain line, all
the parts that came
in from a certain manufacturer
on a certain date.
And these aggregations sometimes
get up into the billions.
>> So I work with some of
these guys who are suffering
because they're creating
these ginormous aggregations
in their secondary indexes.
They might have a raw parts
table that comes as hash only.
Every part has a unique serial number.
I use the serial number as the hash.
It's beautiful.
My raw data table is spread
all across the key space.
My [? write ?]
[? ingestion ?] is awesome.
I take a lot of data.
Then what they do is they create a GSI.
And I say, you know what, I need to see
all the parts for this manufacturer.
Well, all of a sudden I'm
taking a billion rows,
and stuff them onto
one node, because when
I aggregate as the
manufacturer ID as the hash,
and part number as the range,
then all of the sudden I'm
putting a billion parts into what
this manufacturer has delivered me.
>> That can cause a lot
of pressure on the GSI,
again, because I'm hammering one node.
I'm putting all these
inserts into one node.
And that's a real problematic use case.
Now, I got a good design
pattern for how you avoid that.
And that's one of the problems
that I always work with.
But what happens, is the GSI might
not have enough write capacity
to be able to push all those
rows into a single node.
And what happens then is the
primary, the client table,
the primary table will be throttled
because the GSI can't keep up.
So my insert rate will
fall on the primary table
as my GSI tries to keep up.
>> All right, so GSI's, LSI's,
which one should I use?
LSI's are consistent.
GSI's are eventually consistent.
If that's OK, I recommend using a
GSI, they're much more flexible.
LSI's can be modeled as a GSI.
And if the data size per hash keys in
your collection exceeds 10 gigabytes,
then you're going to want to use that
GSI because it's just a hard limit.
>> All right, so scaling.
Throughput in Dynamo DB, you
can provision [INAUDIBLE]
throughput to a table.
We have customers that have
provisioned 60 billion--
are doing 60 billion requests, regularly
running at over a million requests
per second on our tables.
There's really no
theoretical limit to how much
and how fast the table
can run in Dynamo DB.
There are some soft
limits on your account
that we put in there so
that you don't go crazy.
If you want more than
that, not a problem.
You come tell us.
We'll turn up the dial.
>> Every account is limited to some level
in every service, just off the bat
so the people don't go crazy
get themselves into trouble.
No limit in size.
You can put any number
of items on a table.
The size of an item is
limited to 400 kilobytes each,
that would be item not the attributes.
So the sum of all attributes
is limited to 400 kilobytes.
And then again, we have
that little LSI issue
with the 10 gigabyte limit per hash.
AUDIENCE: Small number, I'm missing
what you're telling me, that is--
AUDIENCE: Oh, 400 kilobyte
is the maximum size per item.
So an item has all the attributes.
So 400 k is the total size
of that item, 400 kilobytes.
So of all the attributes
combined, all the data
that's in all those attributes,
rolled up into a total size,
currently today the item limit is 400 k.
So scaling again, achieved
through partitioning.
Throughput is provisioned
at the table level.
And there's really two knobs.
We have read capacity
and write capacity.
>> So these are adjusted
independently of each other.
RCU's measure strictly consistent reads.
OK, so if you're saying I want 1,000
RCU's those are strictly consistent,
those are consistent reads.
If you say I want
eventual consistent reads,
you can provision 1,000
RCU's, you're going
to get 2,000 eventually
consistent reads.
And half the price for those
eventually consist in reads.
>> Again, adjusted
independently of each other.
And they have the throughput--
If you consume 100% of your RCU,
you're not going to impact the
availability of your rights.
So they are completely
independent of each other.
All right, so one of the things that
I mentioned briefly was throttling.
Throttling is bad.
Throttling indicates bad no SQL.
There are things we can do to help
you alleviate the throttling that you
are experiencing.
But the best solution
to this is let's take
a look at what you're doing, because
there's an anti-pattern in play here.
>> These things, things like non-uniform
workloads, hot keys, hot partitions.
I'm hitting a particular key space
very hard for some particular reason.
Why am I doing this?
Let's figure that out.
I'm mixing my hot data with cold data.
I'm letting my tables get
huge, but there's really
only some subset of the data
that's really interesting to me.
So for log data, for example, a lot of
customers, they get log data every day.
They got a huge amount of log data.
>> If you're just dumping all that log
data into one big table, over time
that table's going to get massive.
But I'm really only interested in
last 24 hours, the last seven days,
the last 30 days.
Whatever the window of time
that I'm interested in looking
for the event that bothers me, or
the event that's interesting to me,
that's the only window time that I need.
So why am I putting 10 years
worth of log data in the table?
What that causes is
the table the fragment.
>> It gets huge.
It starts spreading out
across thousands of nodes.
And since your capacity
is so low, you're
actually rate limiting on each
one of those individual nodes.
So let's start looking at how
do we roll that table over.
How do we manage that data a little
better to avoid these problems.
And what does that look like?
This is what that looks like.
This is what bad NoSQL looks like.
>> I got a hot key here.
If you look on the side here,
these are all my partitions.
I got 16 partitions up here
on this particular database.
We do this all the time.
I run this for customers all time.
It's called the heat map.
Heat map tells me how you're
accessing your key space.
And what this is telling me is
that there's one particular hash
that this guy likes an
awful lot, because he's
hitting it really, really hard.
>> So the blue is nice.
We like blue.
We don't like red.
Red's where the pressure
gets up to 100%.
100%, now you're going to be throttled.
So whenever you see any red lines like
this-- and it's not just Dynamo DB--
every NoSQL database has this problem.
There are anti-patterns that can
drive these types of conditions.
What I do is I work with customers
to alleviate these conditions.
>> And what does that look like?
And this is getting the most
out of Dynamo DB throughput,
but it's really getting
the most out of NoSQL.
This is not restricted to Dynamo.
This is definitely-- I
used to work at Mongo.
I'm familiar with many NoSQL platforms.
Every one has these types
of hot key problems.
To get the most out of any NoSQL
database, specifically Dynamo DB,
you want to create the tables
where the hash key element has
a large number of distinct values,
a high degree of cardinality.
Because that means I'm writing
to lots of different buckets.
>> The more buckets I'm
writing to, the more likely
I am to spread that write load or
read load out across multiple nodes,
the more likely I am to have a
high throughput on the table.
And then I want the values to be
requested fairly evenly over time
and uniformly as randomly as possible.
Well, that's kind of interesting,
because I can't really
control when the users come.
So suffice to say, if we spread
things out across the key space,
we'll probably be in better shape.
>> There's a certain
amount of time delivery
that you're not going
to be able control.
But those are really the
two dimensions that we have,
space, access evenly
spread, time, requests
arriving evenly spaced in time.
And if those two
conditions are being met,
then that's what it's
going to look like.
This is much nicer.
We're really happy here.
We've got a very even access pattern.
Yeah, maybe you're getting a
little pressure every now and then,
but nothing really too extensive.
So it's amazing how many times,
when I work with customers,
that first graph with the big red
bar and all that ugly yellow it's
all over the place, we
get done with the exercise
after a couple of months
of re-architecture,
they're running the exact same
workload at the exact same load.
And this is what it's looking like now.
So what you get with NoSQL is a
data schema that is absolutely
tied to the access pattern.
>> And you can optimize that data schema
to support that access pattern.
If you don't, then you're going
to see those types of problems
with those hot keys.
>> AUDIENCE: Well, inevitably some places
are going to be hotter than others.
>> RICK HOULIHAN: Always.
Always.
Yeah, I mean there's always
a-- and again, there's
some design patterns we'll get through
that will talk about how you deal
with these super large aggregations.
I mean, I got to have them,
how do we deal with them?
I got a pretty good use case
that we'll talk about for that.
>> All right, so let's talk
about some customers now.
These guys are AdRoll.
I don't know if you're
familiar with AdRoll.
You probably see them
a lot on the browser.
They're ad re-targeting, they're
the largest ad re-targeting business
out there.
They normally regularly run over
60 billion transactions per day.
They're doing over a million
transactions per second.
They've got a pretty simple table
structure, the busiest table.
It's basically just a
hash key is the cookie,
the range is the demographic
category, and then
the third attribute is the score.
>> So we all have cookies in
our browser from these guys.
And when you go to a
participating merchant,
they basically score you across
various demographic categories.
When you go to a website and
you say I want to see this ad--
or basically you don't say that--
but when you go to the website
they say you want to see this ad.
And they go get that ad from AdRoll.
AdRoll looks you up on their table.
They find your cookie.
The advertisers telling
them, I want somebody
who's middle-aged,
40-year-old man, into sports.
And they score you in those demographics
and they decide whether or not
that's a good ad for you.
>> Now they have a SLA with
their advertising providers
to provide sub-10 millisecond
response on every single request.
So they're using Dynamo DB for this.
They're hitting us a
million requests per second.
They're able to do all their
lookups, triage all that data,
and get that add link back to that
advertiser in under 10 milliseconds.
It's really pretty phenomenal
implementation that they have.
>> These guys actually--
are these the guys.
I'm not sure if it's these guys.
Might be these guys.
Basically told us-- no, I
don't think it was them.
I think it was somebody else.
I was working with a
customer that told me
that now that they've
gone to Dynamo DB, they're
spending more money on snacks for
their development team every month
than they spend on their database.
So it'll give you an
idea of the cost savings
that you can get in Dynamo DB is huge.
All right, dropcam's another company.
These guy's kind of-- if you think
of internet of things, dropcam
is basically internet security video.
You put your camera out there.
Camera has a motion detector.
Someone comes along,
triggers a cue point.
Camera starts recording for a while till
it doesn't detect any motion anymore.
Puts that video up on the internet.
>> Dropcam was a company that is
basically switched to Dynamo DB
because they were experiencing
enormous growing pains.
And what they told us,
suddenly petabytes of data.
They had no idea their service
would be so successful.
More inbound video than YouTube
is what these guys are getting.
They use DynamoDB to track all the
metadata on all their video key points.
>> So they have S3 buckets they push
all the binary artifacts into.
And then they have
Dynamo DB records that
point people to those S3 three objects.
When they need to look at a video,
they look up the record in Dynamo DB.
They click the link.
They pull down the video from S3.
So that's kind of what this looks like.
And this is straight from their team.
>> Dynamo DB reduces their
delivery time for video events
from five to 10 seconds.
In their old relational store,
they used to have to go and execute
multiple complex queries to figure
out which videos to pull down,
to less than 50 milliseconds.
So it's amazing, amazing
how much performance
you can get when you optimize and
you tune the underlying database
to support the access pattern.
Halfbrick, these guys, what is it,
Fruit Ninja I guess is their thing.
That all runs on Dynamo DB.
And these guys, they are a great
development team, great development
shop.
>> Not a good ops team.
They didn't have a lot
of operation resources.
They were struggling trying to keep
their application infrastructure up
and running.
They came to us.
They looked at that Dynamo DB.
They said, that's for us.
They built their whole
application framework on it.
Some really nice comments here
from the team on their ability
to now focus on building
the game and not
having to maintain the
infrastructure, which
was becoming an enormous amount
of overhead for their team.
So this is something that-- the
benefit that you get from Dynamo DB.
>> All right, getting into
data modeling here.
And we talked a little about
this one to one, one to many,
and many to many type relationships.
And how do you maintain those in Dynamo.
In Dynamo DB we use
indexes, generally speaking,
to rotate the data from
one flavor to the other.
Hash keys, range keys, and indexes.
>> In this particular
example, as most states
have a licensing requirement that
only one driver's license per person.
You can't go to get two driver's
licenses in the state of Boston.
I can't do it in Texas.
That's kind of the way it is.
And so at the DMV, we have lookups, we
want to look up the driver's license
by the social security number.
I want to look up the user details
by the driver's license number.
>> So we might have a user's table that
has a hash key on the serial number,
or the social security number, and
various attributes defined on the item.
Now on that table I
could define a GSI that
flips that around that says I want
a hash key on the license and then
all the other items.
Now if I want to query and find the
license number for any given Social
Security number, I can
query the main table.
>> If I want to query and I want
to get the social security
number or other attributes by a
license number, I can query the GSI.
That model is that one
to one relationship.
Just a very simple GSI,
flip those things around.
Now, talk about one to many.
One to many is basically
your hash range key.
Where we get a lot with this
use case is monitor data.
Monitor data comes in regular
interval, like internet of things.
We always get all these
records coming in all the time.
>> And I want to find all the readings
between a particular time period.
It's a very common query in
monitoring infrastructure.
The way go about that is to find a
simple table structure, one table.
I've got a device measurements table
with a hash key on the device ID.
And I have a range key on the
timestamp, or in this case, the epic.
And that allows me execute complex
queries against that range key
and return those records that
are relative to the result
set that I'm looking for.
And it builds that one
to many relationship
into the primary table using the
hash key, range key structure.
>> So that's kind of built
into the table in Dynamo DB.
When I define a hash
and range t table, I'm
defining a one to many relationship.
It's a parent-child relationship.
>> Let's talk about many
to many relationships.
And for this particular example,
again, we're going to use GSI's.
And let's talk about gaming
scenario where I have a given user.
I want to find out all the games that
he's registered for or playing in.
And for a given game, I
want to find all the users.
So how do I do that?
My user games table, I'm going
to have a hash key of user ID
and a range key of the game.
>> So a user can have multiple games.
It's a one to many relationship between
the user and the games he plays.
And then on the GSI,
I'll flip that around.
I'll hash on the game and
I'll range on the user.
So if I want to get all the
game the user's playing in,
I'll query the main table.
If I want to get all the users
that are playing a particular game,
I query the GSI.
So you see how we do this?
You build these GSI's to support the
use case, the application, the access
pattern, the application.
>> If I need to query on
this dimension, let
me create an index on that dimension.
If I don't, I don't care.
And depending on the use case, I
may need the index or I might not.
If it's a simple one to many,
the primary table is fine.
If I need to do these many to
many's, or I need to do one to ones,
then maybe I do need
to second the index.
So it all depends on
what I'm trying to do
and what I'm trying to get accomplished.
>> Probably I'm not going to spend too
much time talking about documents.
This gets a little bit, probably,
deeper than we need to go into.
Let's talk a little bit
about rich query expression.
So in Dynamo DB we have
the ability to create
what we call projection expressions.
Projection expressions are simply
picking the fields or the values
that you want to display.
OK, so I make a selection.
I make a query against Dynamo DB.
And I say, you know what, show
me only the five star reviews
for this particular product.
So that's all I want to see.
I don't want to see all the
other attributes of the row,
I just want to see this.
It's just like in SQL when you
say select star or from table,
you get everything.
When I say select name from
table, I only get one attribute.
It's the same kind of thing in
Dynamo DB or another NoSQL databases.
Filter expressions allow me to
basically cut the result set down.
So I make a query.
Query may come back with 500 items.
But I only want the items that
have an attribute that says this.
OK, so let's filter out those items
that don't match that particular query.
So we have filter expressions.
>> Filter expressions can
be run on any attribute.
They're not like range queries.
Raise queries are more selective.
Filter queries require me to go
get the entire results set and then
carve out the data I don't want.
Why is that important?
Because I read it all.
In a query, I'm going to read and
it's going to be a giant about data.
And then I'm going to
carve out what I need.
And if I'm only carving out a
couple of rows, then that's OK.
It's not so inefficient.
>> But if I'm reading a whole pile of
data, just to carve out one item,
then I'm going to be better
off using a range query,
because it's much more selective.
It's going to save me a lot of
money, because I pay for that read.
Where the results that comes back
cross that wire might be smaller,
but I'm paying for the read.
So understand how
you're getting the data.
That's very important in Dynamo DB.
>> Conditional expressions, this is what
you might call optimistic locking.
Update IF EXISTS, or if this value
is equivalent to what I specify.
And if I have a time stamp on a
record, I might read the data.
I might change that data.
I might go write that
data back to the database.
If somebody has changed the record,
the timestamp might have changed.
And that way my conditional
update could say update
if the timestamp equals this.
Or the update will fail because somebody
updated the record in the meantime.
>> That's what we call optimistic locking.
It means that somebody
can come in and change it,
and I'm going to detect it
when I go back to write.
And then I can actually read that
data and say, oh, he changed this.
I need to account for that.
And I can change the data in my
record and apply another update.
So you can catch those incremental
updates that occur between the time
that you read the data and the
time you might write the data.
>> AUDIENCE: And the filter
expression actually means not
in the number or not--
>> [INTERPOSING VOICES]
RICK HOULIHAN: I won't
get too much into this.
This Is a reserved keyword.
The pound view is a reserved
keyword in Dynamo DB.
Every database has its own reserved
names for collections you can't use.
Dynamo DB, if you specify
a pound in front of this,
you can define those names up above.
This is a referenced value.
It's probably not the best syntax to
have up there for this discussion,
because it gets into some real--
I would have been talking more
about that at a deeper level.
>> But suffice to say, this could
be query scan where they views--
nor pound views is greater than 10.
It is a numerical value, yes.
If you want, we can talk about
that after the discussion.
All right, so we're getting into
some scenarios in best practices
where we're going to talk
about some apps here.
What are the use cases for Dynamo DB.
What are the design
patterns in Dynamo DB.
>> And the first one we're going to
talk about is the internet of things.
So we get a lot of-- I guess,
what is it-- more than 50%
of traffic on the internet these days
is actually generated by machines,
automated processes, not by humans.
I mean this thing this thing that
you carry around in your pocket,
how much data that that thing is
actually sending around without you
knowing it is absolutely amazing.
Your location, information
about how fast you're going.
How do you think Google Maps works
when they tell you what the traffic is.
It's because there are millions and
millions of people driving around
with phones that are sending
data all over place all the time.
So one of the things
about this type of data
that comes in, monitor data, log
data, time series data, is it's
usually only interesting
for a little bit of time.
After that time, it's
not so interesting.
So we talked about, don't let
those tables grow without bounds.
The idea here is that maybe I've got 24
hours worth of events in my hot table.
And that hot table is going to be
provisioned at a very high rate,
because it's taking a lot of data.
It's taking a lot of data
in and I'm reading it a lot.
I've got a lot of operation
queries running against that data.
>> After 24 hours, hey, you
know what, I don't care.
So maybe every midnight I roll
my table over to a new table
and I deprovision this table.
And I'll take the RCU's and
WCU's down because 24 hours later
I'm not running as many
queries against that data.
So I'm going to save money.
And maybe 30 days later I don't
even need to care about it all.
I could take the WCU's
all the way down to one,
because you know what, it's
never going to get written to.
The data is 30 days old.
It never changes.
>> And it's almost never going to get read,
so let's just take that RCU down to 10.
And I'm saving a ton of money on this
data, and only paying for my hot data.
So that's the important thing to look
at when you look at a time series
data coming in in volume.
These are strategies.
Now, I could just let it
all go to the same table
and just let that table grow.
Eventually, I'm going to
see performance issues.
I'm going to have to start to archive
some of that data off the table,
what not.
>> Let's much better
design your application
so that you can operate this way right.
So it's just automatic
in the application code.
At midnight every night
it rolls the table.
Maybe what I need is a sliding
window of 24 hours of data.
Then on a regular basis I'm
calling data off the table.
I'm trimming it with a
Cron job and I'm putting it
onto these other tables,
whatever you need.
So if a rollover works, that's great.
If not, trim it.
But let's keep that hot data
away from your cold data.
It'll save you a lot of money and
make your tables more performing.
So the next thing we'll talk
about is product catalog.
Product catalog is
pretty common use case.
This is actually a very common pattern
that we'll see in a variety of things.
You know, Twitter for
example, a hot tweet.
Everyone's coming and
grabbing that tweet.
Product catalog, I got a sale.
I got a hot sale.
I got 70,000 requests per
second coming for a product
description out of my product catalog.
We see this on the retail
operation quite a bit.
So how do we deal with that?
There's no way to deal with that.
All my users want to see
the same piece of data.
They're are coming in, concurrently.
And they're all making requests
for the same piece of data.
This gives me that hot key, that big red
stripe on my chart that we don't like.
And that's what that looks like.
So across my key space I'm getting
hammered in the sale items.
I'm getting nothing anywhere else.
>> How do I alleviate this problem?
Well, we alleviate this with cache.
Cache, you put basically an in-memory
partition in front of the database.
We have managed
[INAUDIBLE] cache, how you
can set up your own cache, [INAUDIBLE]
cache [? d, ?] whatever you want.
Put that up in front of the database.
And that way you can store that data
from those hot keys up in that cache
space and read through the cache.
>> And then most of your reads
start looking like this.
I got all these cache hits up here
and I got nothing going on down here
because database is sitting behind the
cache and the reads never come through.
If I change the data in the
database, I have to update the cache.
We can use something
like steams to do that.
And I'll explain how that works.
All right, messaging.
Email, we all use email.
>> This is a pretty good example.
We've got some sort of messages table.
And we got inbox and outbox.
This is what the SQL would
look like to build that inbox.
We kind of use the same kind
of strategy to use GSI's, GSI's
for my inbox and my outbox.
So I got raw messages coming
into my messages table.
And the first approach to this
might be, say, OK, no problem.
I've got raw messages.
Messages coming [INAUDIBLE],
message ID, that's great.
That's my unique hash.
I'm going to create two GSI's, one
for my inbox, one for my outbox.
And the first thing I'll do
is I'll say my hash key is
going to be the recipient and
I'm going to arrange on the date.
This is fantastic.
I got my nice view here.
But there's a little issue here.
And you run into this in
relational databases as well.
They called vertically partitioning.
You want to keep your big data
away from your little data.
>> And the reason why is because I gotta
go read the items to get the attributes.
And if my bodies are all on here,
then reading just a few items
if my body length is
averaging 256 kilobytes each,
the math gets pretty ugly.
So say I want to read David's inbox.
David's inbox has 50 items.
The average and size is 256 kilobytes.
Here's my conversion ratio
for RCU's is four kilobytes.
>> OK, let's go with
eventually consistent reads.
I'm still eating 1600 RCU's
just to read David's inbox.
Ouch.
OK, now let's think
about how the app works.
If I'm in an email app and
I'm looking at my inbox,
and I look at the body of every message,
no, I'm looking at the summaries.
I'm looking at only the headers.
So let's build a table structure
that looks more like that.
>> So here's the information
that my workflow needs.
It's in my inbox GSI.
It's the date, the sender,
the subject, and then
the message ID, which points
back to the messages table
where I can get the body.
Well, these would be record IDs.
They would point back to the
item IDs on the Dynamo DB table.
Every index always creates--
always has the item
ID as part of-- that
comes with the index.
>> All right.
AUDIENCE: It tells it where it's stored?
RICK HOULIHAN: Yes, it tells
exactly-- that's exactly what it does.
It says here's my re record.
And it'll point it back to my re record.
Exactly.
OK, so now my inbox is
actually much smaller.
And this actually supports
the workflow of an email app.
So my inbox, I click.
I go along and I click on the message,
that's when I need to go get the body,
because I'm going to
go to a different view.
So if you think about MVC type of
framework, model view controller.
>> The model contains the
data that the view needs
and the controller interacts with.
When I change the frame, when
I change the perspective,
it's OK to go back to the
server and repopulate the model,
because that's what the user expects.
When they change views, that's when
we can go back to the database.
So email, click.
I'm looking for the body.
Round trip.
Go get the body.
>> I read a lot less data.
I'm only reading the bodies that
David needs when he needs them.
And I'm not burn in 1600
RCU's just to show his inbox.
So now that-- this is the way
that LSI or GSI-- I'm sorry,
GSI, would work out.
We've got our hash on the recipient.
We've got the range key on the date.
And we've got the projected attributes
that we need only to support the view.
>> We rotate that for the outbox.
Hash on sender.
And in essence, we have
the very nice, clean view.
And it's basically-- we
have this nice messages
table that's being spread nicely because
it's hash only, hashed message ID.
And we have two indexes that
are rotating off of that table.
All right, so idea here is don't
keep the big data and this small data
together.
Partition vertically,
partition those tables.
Don't read data you don't have to.
All right, gaming.
We all like games.
At least I like games then.
So some of the things
that we deal with when
we're thinking about gaming, right?
Gaming these days, especially mobile
gaming, is all about thinking.
And I'm going to rotate here a
little bit away from DynamoDB.
I'm going to bring in
some of the discussion
around some of the
other AWS technologies.
>> But the idea about gaming is to think
about in terms of APIs, APIs that are,
generally speaking, HTTP and JSON.
It's how mobile games kind of
interact with their back ends.
They do JSON posting.
They get data, and it's all,
generally speaking, in nice JSON APIs.
>> Things like get friends, get
the leaderboard, exchange data,
user generated content,
push back up to the system,
these are types of things
that we're going to do.
Binary asset data, this data
might not sit in the database.
This might sit in an
object store, right?
But the database is going to
end up telling the system,
telling the application
where to go get it.
And inevitably, multiplayer
servers, back end infrastructure,
and designed for high
availability and scalability.
So these are things that we all want
in the gaming infrastructure today.
>> So let's take a look at
what that looks like.
Got a core back end,
very straightforward.
We've got a system here with
multiple availability zones.
We talked about AZs as being-- think
of them as separate data centers.
More than one data center
per AZ, but that's OK,
just think of them as separate data
centers that are geographically
and fault isolated.
>> We're going to have a
couple EC2 instances.
We're going to have
some back end server.
Maybe if you're a legacy
architecture, we're
using what we call RDS,
relational database services.
Could be MSSQL, MySQL,
or something like that.
This is way a lot applications
are designed today.
>> Well we might want to go with
this is when we scale out.
We'll go ahead and put
the S3 bucket up there.
And that S3 bucket, instead of serving
up those objects from our servers--
we could do that.
You put all your binary
objects on your servers
and you can use those server
instances to serve that data up.
But that's pretty expensive.
>> Better way to do is go ahead and
put those objects in an S3 bucket.
S3 is an object repositories.
It's built specifically for
serving up these types of things.
And let those clients request
directly from those object buckets,
offload the servers.
So we're starting to scale out here.
>> Now we got users all over the world.
I got users.
I need to have content locally
located close to these users, right?
I've created an S3 bucket
as my source repository.
And I'll front that with
the CloudFront distribution.
>> CloudFront is a CD and a
content delivery network.
Basically it takes data that you specify
and caches it all over the internet
so users everywhere can have
a very quick response when
they request those objects.
>> So you get an idea.
You're kind of leveraging all the
aspects of AWS here to get this done.
And eventually, we throw
in an auto scaling group.
So our AC2 instances
of our game servers,
as they start to get busier
and busier and busier,
they'll just spin another
instance, spin another instance,
spin another instance.
So the technology AWS has, it
allows you specify the parameters
around which your servers will grow.
So you can have n number of servers
out there at any given time.
And if your load goes away, they'll
shrink, the number will shrink.
And if the load comes back,
it'll grow back out, elastically.
>> So this looks great.
We've got a lot of EC2 instances.
We can put cache in
front of the databases,
try and accelerate the databases.
The next pressure point
typically people see
is they scale a game using a
relational database system.
Jeez, the database
performance is terrible.
How do we improve that?
Let's try putting
cache in front of that.
>> Well, cache doesn't work
so great in games, right?
For games, writing is painful.
Games are very write heavy.
Cache doesn't work when you're
write heavy because you've always
got to update the cache.
You update the cache, it's
irrelevant to be caching.
It's actually just extra work.
>> So where we go here?
You've got a big bottleneck
down there in the database.
And the place to go
obviously is partitioning.
Partitioning is not
easy to do when you're
dealing with relational databases.
With relational databases, you're
responsible for managing, effectively,
the key space.
You're saying users between A and M
go here, between N and Z go there.
And you're switching
across the application.
So you're dealing with
this partition data source.
You have transactional constraints
that don't span partitions.
You've got all kinds of
messiness that you're
dealing with down there trying
to deal with scaling out
and building a larger infrastructure.
It's just no fun.
>> AUDIENCE: So are you saying that
increasing source points speeds up
the process?
RICK HOULIHAN: Increasing?
AUDIENCE: Source points.
RICK HOULIHAN: Source points?
AUDIENCE: From the information,
where the information is coming from?
RICK HOULIHAN: No.
What I'm saying is increasing the
number of partitions in the data store
improves throughput.
So what's happening here is users
coming into the EC2 instance up here,
well, if I need a user
that's A to M, I'll go here.
From N to p, I'll go here.
From P to Z, I'll go here.
>> AUDIENCE: OK, those so those are
all stored in different nodes?
>> RICK HOULIHAN: Yes.
Think of these as
different silos of data.
So you're having to do this.
If you're trying to do
this, if you're trying
to scale on a relational platform,
this is what you're doing.
You're taking data and
you're cutting it down.
And you're partitioning it across
multiple instances of the database.
And you're managing all that
at the application tier.
It's no fun.
So what do we want to go?
We want to go DynamoDB, fully managed,
NoSQL data store, provision throughput.
We use secondary indexes.
It's basically HTTP API and
includes document support.
So you don't have to worry
about any of that partitioning.
We do it all for you.
So now, instead, you
just write to the table.
If the table needs to be partitioned,
that happens behind the scenes.
You're completely insulated
from that as a developer.
So let's talk about
some of the use cases
that we run into in gaming, common
gaming scenarios, leaderboard.
So you've got users coming in,
the BoardNames that they're
on, the scores for this user.
We might be hashing on the UserID,
and then we have range on the game.
So every user wants to see
all the game he's played
and all his top score
across all the game.
So that's his personal leaderboard.
>> Now I want to go in and I want to get--
so I get these personal leaderboards.
What I want to do is go get
the top score across all users.
So how do I do that?
When my record is hashed on
the UserID, ranged on the game,
well I'm going to go ahead
and restructure, create a GSI,
and I'm going to restructure that data.
>> Now I'm going to hash on the
BoardName, which is the game.
And I'm going to range on the top score.
And now I've created different buckets.
I'm using the same table,
the same item data.
But I'm creating a bucket that gives
me an aggregation of top score by game.
>> And I can query that table
to get that information.
So I've set that query pattern up to
be supported by a secondary index.
Now they can be sorted by BoardName
and sorted by TopScore, depending on.
So you can see, these are types
of use cases you get in gaming.
Another good use case we get in gaming
is awards and who's won the awards.
And this is a great use case
where we call sparse indexes.
Sparse indexes are the
ability to generate
an index that doesn't necessarily
contain every single item on the table.
And why not?
Because the attribute that's being
indexed doesn't exist on every item.
>> So in this particular
use case, I'm saying,
you know what, I'm going to
create an attribute called Award.
And I'm going to give every user
that has an award that attribute.
Users that don't have awards are
not going to have that attribute.
So when I create the
index, the only users
that are going to show
up in the index are
the ones that actually have won awards.
So that's a great way to be able
to create filtered indexes that
are very, very selective that don't
have to index the entire table.
>> So we're getting low on time here.
I'm going to go ahead and skip
out and skip this scenario.
Talk a little bit about--
>> AUDIENCE: Can I ask a quick question?
One is write heavy?
RICK HOULIHAN: What is?
AUDIENCE: Write heavy.
RICK HOULIHAN: Write heavy.
Let me see.
>> AUDIENCE: Or is that not
something you can just
voice to in a matter of seconds?
RICK HOULIHAN: We go
through the voting scenario.
It's not that bad.
Do you guys have a few minutes?
OK.
>> So we'll talk about voting.
So real time voting, we have
requirements for voting.
Requirements are that we allow
each person to vote only once.
We want nobody to be able
to change their vote.
We want real-time aggregation
and analytics for demographics
that we're going to be
showing to users on the site.
>> Think of this scenario.
We work a lot of reality
TV shows where they're
doing these exact type of things.
So you can think of the scenario,
we have millions and millions
of teenage girls there
with their cell phones
and voting, and voting, and
voting for whoever they are
find to be the most popular.
So these are some of the
requirements we run out.
>> And so the first take
in solving this problem
would be to build a
very simple application.
So I've got this app.
I have some voters out there.
They come in, they hit the voting app.
I've got some raw votes table
I'll just dump those votes into.
I'll have some aggregate
votes table that
will do my analytics and demographics,
and we'll put all this in there.
>> And this is great.
Life is good.
Life's good until we find out that
there's always only one or two
people that are popular in an election.
There's only one or two things
that people really care about.
And if you're voting at
scale, all of a sudden I'm
going to be hammering the hell out of
two candidates, one or two candidates.
A very limited number of items
people find to be popular.
>> This is not a good design pattern.
This is actually a
very bad design pattern
because it creates exactly what we
talked about which was hot keys.
Hot keys are something we don't like.
>> So how do we fix that?
And really, the way to fix this is
by taking those candidate buckets
and for each candidate we have,
we're going to append a random value,
something that we know, random
value between one and 100,
between 100 and 1,000,
or between one and 1,000,
however many random values you want to
append onto the end of that candidate.
>> And what have I really done then?
If I'm using the candidate ID as
the bucket to aggregate votes,
if I've added a random
number to the end of that,
I've created now 10 buckets, a
hundred buckets, a thousand buckets
that I'm aggregating votes across.
>> So I have millions, and millions,
and millions of records coming in
for these candidates, I am now spreading
those votes across Candidate A_1
through Candidate A_100, because
every time a vote comes in,
I'm generating a random
value between one and 100.
I'm tacking it onto the end of the
candidate that person's voting for.
I'm dumping it into that bucket.
>> Now on the backside, I know
that I got a hundred buckets.
So when I want to go ahead
and aggregate the votes,
I read from all those buckets.
So I go ahead and add.
And then I do the scatter gather
where I go out and say hey,
you know what, this candidate's key
spaces is over a hundred buckets.
I'm going to gather all the
votes from those hundred buckets.
I'm going to aggregate
them and I'm going to say,
Candidate A now has
total vote count of x.
>> Now both the write
query and the read query
are nicely distributed
because I'm writing across
and I'm reading across hundreds of keys.
I'm not writing and
reading across one key now.
So that's a great pattern.
>> This is actually probably one
of the most important design
patterns for scale in NoSQL.
You will see this type of
design pattern in every flavor.
MongoDB, DynamoDB, it doesn't
matter, we all have to do this.
Because when you're dealing
with those huge aggregations,
you have to figure out a way to
spread them out across buckets.
So this is the way you do that.
All right, so what
you're doing right now
is you're trading off read
cost for write scalability.
The cost of my read is
a little more complex
and I have to go read from a
hundred buckets instead of one.
But I'm able to write.
And my throughput, my write
throughput is incredible.
So it's usually a valuable
technique for scaling DynamoDB,
or any NoSQL database for that matter.
So we figured out how to scale it.
And we figured how to
eliminate our hot keys.
And this is fantastic.
And we got this nice system.
And it's given us very correct voting
because we have record vote de-dupe.
It's built into DynamoDB.
We talked about conditional rights.
>> When a voter comes in, puts
an insert on the table,
they insert with their voter ID,
if they try to insert another vote,
I do a conditional write.
Say only write this
if this doesn't exist.
So as soon as I see that
that vote's hit the table,
nobody else's going to be
able to put their vote in.
And that's fantastic.
And we're incrementing
our candidate counters.
And we're doing our
demographics and all that.
But what happens if my
application falls over?
Now all of a sudden votes
are coming in, and I
don't know if they're getting processed
into my analytics and demographics
anymore.
And when the application
comes back up, how
the hell do I know what votes have
been processed and where do I start?
>> So this is a real problem when you
start to look at this type of scenario.
And how do we solve that?
We solve it with what we
call DynamoDB Streams.
Streams is a time ordered and
partitioned change log of every access
to the table, every write
access to the table.
Any data that's written to the
table shows up on the stream.
>> It's basically a 24 hour queue.
Items hit the stream,
they live for 24 hours.
They can be read multiple times.
Guaranteed to be delivered
only once to the stream,
could be read n number of times.
So however many processes you want to
consume that data, you can consume it.
It will appear every update.
Every write will only
appear once on the stream.
So you don't have to worry
about processing it twice
from the same process.
>> It's strictly ordered per item.
When we say time
ordered and partitioned,
you'll see per partition on the stream.
You will see items, updates in order.
We are not guaranteeing
on the stream that you're
going to get every transaction
in the order across items.
>> So streams are idempotent.
Do we all know what idempotent means?
Idempotent means you can do it
over, and over, and over again.
The result's going to be the same.
>> Streams are idempotent,
but they have to be
played from the starting point,
wherever you choose, to the end,
or they will not result
in the same values.
>> Same thing with MongoDB.
MongoDB has a construct
they call the oplog.
It is the exact same construct.
Many NoSQL databases
have this construct.
They use it to do things
like replication, which
is exactly what we do with streams.
AUDIENCE: Maybe a
heretical question, but you
talk about apps doing down an so forth.
Are streams guaranteed to
never possibly go down?
RICK HOULIHAN: Yeah, streams
are guaranteed to never go down.
We manage the infrastructure
behind. streams automatically
deploy in their auto scaling group.
We'll go through a little
bit about what happens.
>> I shouldn't say they're not
guaranteed to never go down.
The elements are guaranteed
to appear in the stream.
And the stream will be accessible.
So what goes down or comes back
up, that happens underneath.
It covers-- it's OK.
All right, so you get different
view types off the screen.
The view types that are important to a
programmer typically are, what was it?
I get the old view.
When an update hits the table, it'll
push the old view to the stream
so data can archive, or change
control, change identification, change
management.
>> The new image, what it is now after
the update, that's another type of view
you can get.
You can get both the old and new images.
Maybe I want them both.
I want to see what it was.
I want to see what it changed to.
>> I have a compliance type
of process that runs.
It needs to verify that
when these things change,
that they're within certain limits
or within certain parameters.
>> And then maybe I only
need to know what changed.
I don't care what item changed.
I don't need to need to know
what attributes changed.
I just need to know that
the items are being touched.
So these are the types of views
that you get off the stream
and you can interact with.
>> The application that
consumes the stream,
this is kind of the way this works.
DynamoDB client ask to
push data to the tables.
Streams deploy on what we call shards.
Shards are scaled
independently of the table.
They don't line up completely
to the partitions of your table.
And the reason why is
because they line up
to the capacity, the current
capacity of the table.
>> They deploy in their
own auto scaling group,
and they start to spin out depending
on how many writes are coming in,
how many reads-- really it's writes.
There's no reads-- but how
many writes are coming in.
>> And then on the back
end, we have what we
call a KCL, or Kinesis Client Library.
Kinesis is a stream data
processing technology from Amazon.
And streams is built on that.
>> So you use a KCL enabled
application to read the stream.
The Kinesis Client Library actually
manages the workers for you.
And it also does some
interesting things.
It will create some tables up
in your DynamoDB tablespace
to track which items
have been processed.
So this way if it falls back, if
it falls over and comes and gets
stood back up, it can determine where
was it in processing the stream.
>> That's very important when
you're talking about replication.
I need to know what
data was been processed
and what data has yet to be processed.
So the KCL library for streams will
give you a lot of that functionality.
It takes care of all the housekeeping.
It stands up a worker for every shard.
It creates an administrative table
for every shard, for every worker.
And as those workers fire,
they maintain those tables
so you know this record
was read and processed.
And then that way if the process
dies and comes back online,
it can resume right where it took off.
>> So we use this for
cross-region replication.
A lot of customers have the need to
move data or parts of their data tables
around to different regions.
There are nine regions
all around the world.
So there might be a need-- I
might have users in Asia, users
in the East Coast of the United States.
They have different data that
needs to be locally distributed.
And maybe a user flies from
Asia over to the United States,
and I want to replicate
his data with him.
So when he gets off the plane, he has
a good experience using his mobile app.
>> You can use the cross-region
replication library to do this.
Basically we have
provided two technologies.
One's a console application you can
stand up on your own EC2 instance.
It runs pure replication.
And then we gave you the library.
The library you can use to build
your own application if you
want to do crazy things with that data--
filter, replicate only part of it,
rotate the data, move it into a
different table, so on and so forth.
So that's kind of what that looks like.
>> DynamoDB Streams can be
processed by what we call Lambda.
We mentioned a little bit about event
driven application architectures.
Lambda is a key component of that.
Lambda is code that fires on demand
in response to a particular event.
One of those events could be a
record appearing on the stream.
If a record appears on the stream,
we'll call this Java function.
Well, this is JavaScript, and Lambda
supports Node.js, Java, Python,
and will soon support
other languages as well.
And suffice to say, it's pure code.
write In Java, you define a class.
You push the JAR up into Lambda.
And then you specify which class
to call in response to which event.
And then the Lambda infrastructure
behind that will run that code.
>> That code can process
records off the stream.
It can do anything it wants with it.
In this particular example, all we're
really doing is logging the attributes.
But this is just code.
Code can do anything, right?
>> So you can rotate that data.
You can create a derivative view.
If it's a document structure,
you can flatten the structure.
You can create alternate indexes.
All kinds of things you can
do with the DynamoDB Streams.
>> And really, that's what that looks like.
So you get those updates coming in.
They're coming off the string.
They're read by the Lambda function.
They're rotating the data and
pushing it up in derivative tables,
notifying external systems of change,
and pushing data into ElastiCache.
>> We talked about how to put the cache
in front of the database for that sales
scenario.
Well what happens if I
update the item description?
Well, if I had a Lambda
function running on that table,
if I update the item description, it'll
pick up the record off the stream,
and it'll update the ElastiCache
instance with the new data.
So that's a lot of
what we do with Lambda.
It's glue code, connectors.
And it actually gives
the ability to launch
and to run very complex applications
without a dedicated server
infrastructure, which is really cool.
>> So let's go back to our
real-time voting architecture.
This is new and improved with our
streams and KCL enabled application.
Same as before, we can
handle any scale of election.
We like this.
We're doing out scatter gathers
across multiple buckets.
We've got optimistic locking going on.
We can keep our voters
from changing their votes.
They can only vote only once.
This is fantastic.
Real-time fault tolerance,
scalable aggregation now.
If the thing falls over, it
knows where to restart itself
when it comes back up because
we're using the KCL app.
And then we can also use that
KCL application to push data out
to Redshift for other
app analytics, or use
the Elastic MapReduce to run
real-time streaming aggregations off
of that data.
>> So these are things we
haven't talked about much.
But they're additional
technologies that come
to bear when you're looking
at these types of scenarios.
>> All right, so that's about
analytics with DynamoDB Streams.
You can collect de-dupe
data, do all kinds
of nice stuff, aggregate data in
memory, create those derivative tables.
That's a huge use case
that a lot of customers
are involved with, taking the nested
properties of those JSON documents
and creating additional indexes.
>> We're at the end.
Thank you for bearing with me.
So let's talk about
reference architecture.
DynamoDB sits in the middle of so
much of the AWS infrastructure.
Basically you can hook it
up to anything you want.
Applications built using Dynamo include
Lambda, ElastiCache, CloudSearch,
push the data out into Elastic
MapReduce, import export from DynamoDB
into S3, all kinds of workflows.
But probably the best
thing to talk about,
and this is what's really
interesting is when we
talk about event driven applications.
>> This is an example of
an internal project
that we have where we're actually
publishing to gather survey results.
So in an email link that
we send out, there'll
be a little link saying click
here to respond to the survey.
And when a person clicks
that link, what happens
is they pull down a secure
HTML survey form from S3.
There's no server.
This is just an S3 object.
>> That form comes up,
loads up in the browser.
It's got Backbone.
It's got complex JavaScript
that it's running.
So it's very rich application
running in the client's browser.
They don't know that they're not
interacting with a back end server.
At this point, it's all browser.
>> They publish the results to what
we call the Amazon API Gateway.
API Gateway is simply a web API
that you can define and hook up
to whatever you want.
In this particular case, we're
hooked up to a Lambda function.
>> So my POST operation is
happening with no server.
Basically that API Gateway sits there.
It costs me nothing until people
start POSTing to it, right?
The Lambda function just sits there.
And it costs me nothing until
people start hitting it.
So you can see, as the volume
increases, that's when the charges come.
I'm not running a server 7/24.
>> So I pull the form
down out of the bucket,
and I post through the API
Gateway into the Lambda function.
And then the Lambda
function says, you know
what, I've got some PIIs, some
personally identifiable information
in these responses.
I got comments coming from users.
I've got email addresses.
I've got usernames.
>> Let me split this off.
I'm going to generate some
metadata off this record.
And I'm going to push the
metadata into DynamoDB.
And I could encrypt all the data
and push it into DynamoDB if I want.
But it's easier for me, in this
use case, to go ahead an say,
I'm going to push the raw data
into an encrypted S3 bucket.
So I use built in S3 server side
encryption and Amazon's Key Management
Service so that I have a key that
can rotate on a regular interval,
and I can protect that PII data
as part of this whole workflow.
>> So what have I done?
I've just deployed a whole
application, and I have no server.
So is what event driven application
architecture does for you.
>> Now if you think about
the use case for this--
we have other customers I'm talking
to about this exact architecture who
run phenomenally large campaigns, who
are looking at this and going, oh my.
Because now, they can
basically push it out there,
let that campaign just sit
there until it launches, and not
have to worry a fig about
what kind of infrastructure
is going to be there to support it.
And then as soon as
that campaign is done,
it's like the infrastructure
just immediately goes away
because there really
is no infrastructure.
It's just code that sits on Lambda.
It's just data that sits in DynamoDB.
It is an amazing way
to build applications.
>> AUDIENCE: So is it more
ephemeral than it would be
if it was stored on an actual server?
>> RICK HOULIHAN: Absolutely.
Because that server instance
would have to be a 7/24.
It has to be available for
somebody to respond to.
Well guess what?
S3 is available 7/24.
S3 always responds.
And S3 is very, very good
at serving up objects.
Those objects can be HTML files, or
JavaScript files, or whatever you want.
You can run very rich web applications
out of S3 buckets, and people do.
>> And so that's the idea here
is to get away from the way
we used to think about it.
We all used to think in
terms of servers and hosts.
It's not about that anymore.
It's about infrastructure as code.
Deploy the code to the cloud and
let the cloud run it for you.
And that's what AWS is trying to do.
>> AUDIENCE: So your gold box in the middle
of the API Gateway is not server-like,
but instead is just--
>> RICK HOULIHAN: You can think
of it as server facade.
All it is is it'll take an HTTP
request and map it to another process.
That's all it does.
And in this case, we're mapping
it to a Lambda function.
All right, so that's all I got.
Thank you very much.
I appreciate it.
I know we want a little bit over time.
And hopefully you guys got
a little bit of information
that you can take away today.
And I apologize if I went
over some of your heads,
but there's a good lot of
fundamental foundational knowledge
that I think is very valuable for you.
So thank you for having me.
[APPLAUSE]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
is when you were saying
you had to go through the thing
from the beginning to the end
to get the right values
or the same values,
how would the values
change if [INAUDIBLE].
>> RICK HOULIHAN: Oh, idempotent?
How would the values change?
Well, because if I didn't run
it all the way to the end,
then I don't know what changes
were made in the last mile.
It's not going to be the
same data as what I saw.
AUDIENCE: Oh, so you just
haven't gotten the entire input.
RICK HOULIHAN: Right.
You have to go from beginning
to end, and then it's
going to be a consistent state.
Cool.
>> AUDIENCE: So you showed us DynamoDB
can do document or the key value.
And we spent a lot of time on the
key value with a hash and the ways
to flip it around.
When you looked at those tables, is that
leaving behind the document approach?
>> RICK HOULIHAN: I wouldn't
say leaving it behind.
>> AUDIENCE: They were separated from the--
>> RICK HOULIHAN: With the document
approach, the document type in DynamoDB
is just think of as another attribute.
It's an attribute that contains
a hierarchical data structure.
And then in the queries,
you can use the properties
of those objects using Object Notation.
So I can filter on a nested
property of the JSON document.
AUDIENCE: So any time I
do a document approach,
I can sort of arrive at the tabular--
AUDIENCE: Absolutely.
AUDIENCE: --indexes and
things you just talked about.
RICK HOULIHAN: Yeah, the
indexes and all that,
when you want to index the
properties of the JSON,
the way that we'd have to do that is if
you insert a JSON object or a document
into Dynamo, you would use streams.
Streams would read the input.
You'd get that JSON
object and you'd say OK,
what's the property I want to index?
>> You create a derivative table.
Now that's the way it works right now.
We don't allow you to index
directly those properties.
>> AUDIENCE: Tabularizing your documents.
>> RICK HOULIHAN: Exactly, flattening
it, tabularizing it, exactly.
That's what you do with it.
>> AUDIENCE: Thank you.
>> RICK HOULIHAN: Yep,
absolutely, thank you.
AUDIENCE: So it's kind of
Mongo meets Redis classifers.
>> RICK HOULIHAN: Yeah,
it's a lot like that.
That's a good description for it.
Cool.