>> NEEL MEHTA: So hello to
everyone who is watching here,
or watching online, or remotely.
My name is Neel, this is CS50.
And today's seminar is Responsive
Web Design with Bootstrap.
It's a subject that's
very close to my heart.
Hopefully, it will be
close to your heart
as well by the end of today's seminar.
So Bootstrap.
How many of you have done any
kind of web development before?
A good amount?
A little bit.
>> So Bootstrap is the world's most
popular, front-end framework.
It's used by-- I've chosen a
couple of random websites--
Lyft, Newsweek, and Vogue.
It's used by a number of websites.
It's a web design framework that
will let you make your websites
both beautiful and responsive.
And I'll go over these
two concepts here.
Beautiful.
So you have normal website on the
left, which is made by just HTML.
You've learned HTML in class
and in section at length.
Bootstrap is a way to make
your websites beautiful.
You can take what's on the
left side of your screen
and turn it into what's on the
right side of your screen with very,
very, very little code.
>> You get the nice blue button, you get
the fancy, rounded edges on the screen,
you get the list view, you get the
cards, and so on with very little code.
There's actually no CSS that
you have to write by yourself.
So Bootstrap allows you to
have these pre-built CSS
components you can put
inside of your web page
to make it look beautiful without
very much work on your own.
It's really a bootstrap,
a starting point,
for your web development adventures.
And so when you're just
mocking up a website,
it's a very good place to get started.
You can get a good looking website
with very, very little work.
And indeed, we're going
to do this ourselves
in the course of like five
minutes-- within 10 minutes.
So it's pretty easy to
make some great websites.
So that's the first part.
>> The second part-- responsive.
People, nowadays, don't just
access the web on their laptops.
Actually, as of 2014, more people
access the web through mobile devices,
like phones, or tablets, or
services, or so on than websites.
And websites have traditionally been
designed with laptops or desktops
in mind.
And so the websites are often not
very well suited to your phone.
If you ever visited
harvard.edu on your phone,
it's kind of an annoying
experience, right?
That's because it's not responsive.
We're trying to make
websites that are responsive,
that respond to people's screen sizes.
>> So if it's a phone, it's
going to go on phone.
If it's a tablet, it's
going to go on tablet.
It adjusts to match the
screen that is being used.
And so Bootstrap also provides some
very, very useful utilities for that.
And we're going to discuss that as well.
So again, there are two parts to
Bootstrap-- beautiful and responsible.
We're going to talk about those.
First, beautiful.
And then responsive.
>> So all the code that we're
going to talk about today--
we're going to have a lot of examples,
a lot of challenges, and so on-- it
all lives on this website here.
This slide is what we sent out.
So if you're here, you can feel
free to not have to write that down.
And if you're watching remotely, feel
free to pull this up on your computer
as well.
You'll probably need it during
the course of this seminar.
>> So we're going to use a
website called CodePen,
which is a collaborative coding
environment, during this seminar.
And CodePen-- and I'll
show you here real fast--
it allows you to write
HTML collaboratively.
I can write it, I can send it to
you guys, you guys can edit it.
Even if you're remote, you
can still access it that way.
You can type HTML code at the
top and it'll automatically
be converted into the
web page at the bottom.
So it's a way for you
to quickly try out code
without having to do any kind of stuff
on your IDE, or your own website,
or whatever.
>> So go ahead and pull up this
website, if you're remote
or if you are here,
especially if you're remote.
is.gd/cs50boostrap.
No caps, no underscores, no nothing.
So those of you who are
here, just give me a thumbs
up when you have pulled
up that web page.
Good?
>> AUDIENCE: Yes.
>> NEEL MEHTA: So we'll get
to that in just a second.
So first, we're going to get to, how
do you make your websites beautiful?
We're going to learn how to take boring,
old HTML, like I showed you before,
and turn that into
really nice components,
like nice widgets, nice, colored
buttons, and labels, and tables,
and all, using Bootstrap.
So if we could all go over to the
CodePen that you just pulled up.
It should look a little bit like this.
Does it look like this for everyone?
>> AUDIENCE: Yes.
>> NEEL MEHTA: If you're remote, it
should look like this as well.
If not, I will show you soon how
you can get it look like this
in a future part of the video.
So here we have written
a very basic HTML,
like the kind you've
been using in class.
It's pretty basic.
No frills.
And we have some stuff.
We've designed a very,
very basic start up
call Yalp! with which you can
find restaurants in the area,
and find reviews, and
directions on all of those.
It's a very good concept.
It's never been done before.
It's a very unique name, too.
>> So what we're going to try
to do is help the owner
of Yalp! make his website
look really, really cool.
So to begin with, the owner of
Yalp! has made a little search
box, and a little button,
and then maybe a little
highlighted area for a
highlighted restaurant, and then
a list of other restaurants
that are in the area.
So we can just go through
the HTML code real fast.
How comfortable are you guys with HTML?
We've done a little bit
section and also in class.
Decent?
>> So just as a recap,
HTML is all about having
tags or elements that tell the
computer how to lay out the web page.
So this h1 here-- start h1, Welcome
to Yalp!, end h1-- tells the computer,
draw a big header it
says, Welcome to Yalp!
inside there.
We also have forms.
We can inputs like this, text inputs,
which will render as text boxes
you write in.
You also have buttons.
You get a nice, clickable button.
It doesn't do anything right
now, but you get a button.
You can have divs, or dividers, to
break up your page into various groups.
>> You can have paragraphs,
you have buttons.
If you have paragraphs, then
you have unordered lists, ul,
and lists inside of that, li.
So these are the very basic
building blocks of a web page.
And indeed, pretty much
every website you see
is going to be built
using these same tools.
Of course, they don't all
look this bad because we're
going to spice it up a little bit.
So let's this boring old HTML and start
transforming it into the beautiful site
that we just saw a couple minutes ago.
>> So let's start off very simple.
So we have this button here.
In Bootstrap, as we saw, we can
have a nice, beautiful, blue button.
And that's done not by doing custom CSS.
There's no custom CSS here.
That's done by adding classes
to your HTML elements.
If you've tried classes, or hrefs, or
anchors, or type="text" for inputs--
HTML elements can have these attributes.
They can have extra information
that you might give them.
>> And so, in this case,
classes are the attribute.
So you'd write, button class=
something inside of strings.
And that attribute will tell the
computer, this is not any, old button.
It's a button that is in
this class of buttons.
And so Bootstrap, if you give it
a certain style on your element,
it will draw it a certain way.
So I write "btn btn-primary.
btn being a abbreviation for button.
You'll notice now that
my ugly button turned
into a nice, beautiful, blue button.
It looks very nice when we click it.
>> And so what happens is we have the
btn class and the btn-primary class
on our element.
And Bootstrap will go in and say, OK, I
know that there are these two classes.
Any element that has these two
classes should be drawn like this.
So that's the core of how you attach
styles to elements in Bootstrap.
You just attach classes to them and
it will weight it out as it sees fit.
So here's another example.
In the input, we can add
a class= "form-control".
And I'll show soon where you
can find out what classes
are available of each kind of element.
But the class that we just
added has nice, rounded corners,
it has nice padding, it has
a nice, blue glow to it.
>> We can also go into this form.
And class="form-inline", which will make
our form, as you might imagine, inline.
So it's looking a little bit more
like what we had before already.
So before we go on to style the rest of
the page, any questions about what we
did?
We just attached classes
to our various elements.
And I'll show you later how you can
figure out what classes are available.
We attached classes that
have certain styles.
And that tells the browser
how to layout the page using
Bootstrap's provided styles.
Any questions from the audience?
>> Good so far?
Cool.
A lot of the challenges
with Bootstrap is just
knowing what components are
available and how you use them.
And that is all learned
with experience and also
through reading the documentation,
which we'll talk about soon.
So we have this div.
It's just a boring, old thing.
We want to emphasize it somehow.
So in Bootstrap, there are a
lot of components available.
And this is getbootstrap.com.
It's a very useful reference.
It contains things like--
here's how you do a button.
And you can do nav bars, you can
labels, you can progress bars,
you can do list groups.
Basically, it's all kinds
of you might see a web page.
>> Here's one that we'll try right now.
It's called panel.
If you ever use Google
Now, they have cards.
Or any Android device has cards.
They have little white boxes
that have stuff inside of it.
And so we're going to try and do
that ourselves here using a thing
called a panel.
So if we attach class="panel
panel-default" to our outer div,
then we attach a div class=-- let's
just check this documentation.
div class="panel-heading" and
then div class="panels-body".
Again, don't worry about
memorizing this code.
It will be available online.
>> So we did this and now our boring, old
div turned into this nice, little card.
It has nice padding, it
has borders, it stands out
from the rest of the page,
which is pretty cool.
So let's go in and change this Get
directions button to look nice.
Who in the audience wants to tell
me what I can do to the button
to make it look nice using Bootstrap?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: We could add a class.
And we could do class="btn btn-primary".
NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
There's a bunch of other
colors available for buttons--
or for anything, for that matter.
We can do btn-danger and make it red.
There we go.
We can do btn-success to make it green.
We can do btn-info-- there's a bunch
of things that are available to you.
So I have little challenge for you now.
So there's one more thing
that I have left un-styled.
This Top Restaurants.
>> And we want to use a thing
called a list group to style it.
So my challenge to you is
go on to getbootstrap.com--
I'll pull it up here.
getboostrap.com.
Go to getbootstrap.com, find the
section where they go over list groups.
And you'll see here an
example and the right classes
that you can use to make your
lists into these nice list groups.
These are worked out examples
of code examples, what
code you use, what HTML code
you use, and what that outputs.
>> So my challenge to you--
go on getbootstrap.com,
whether you're here or at home, and
to try and add styles to this ul
to make it look nice.
And use a list group style.
You want to take a couple minutes,
and search the documentation,
try this yourselves?
Because as you're doing web development,
you'll realize a lot of your work
is going to be reading
this documentation.
So I think it's good to get familiar
with how to read documentation,
how to figure out what's where,
what code examples you can use,
what you can leverage.
>> So again, getbootstrap.com,
go to the Components tab,
and then scroll down to List Group.
And you'll see examples of code that
you can use to make your HTML fit that.
So take a couple of minutes and
try and explore it yourself,
whether you're here or at home.
If you're at home, pause the video,
perhaps, and try it out yourself.
If you're here, if you go to our
website-- if you refresh the page,
you'll see this on there.
This very same code is just
adding new styles right there.
So take a few minutes.
Let me know when you are feeling good
about it or when you're totally lost.
Sound good?
Cool.
Quick aside for those of you
at home, while we're waiting,
if you go on to the GitHub site
that I put up a couple slides ago,
towards the beginning of the video,
I have a GitHub repo, repository,
for this talk.
All these code examples that we'll be
talking about are stored right here.
So if you go to challenge-1.html, this
is all the code that we have right now
on our CodePen.
So you can just go ahead, and copy
this, and paste it in your own CodePen.
And that way, you can keep up
with what we're doing here.
So have this page open as well as we
go through the rest of the seminar.
Again, you want it to look like what you
see down at the bottom of your screen
there.
Feeling good?
Solid.
Let's wait for everyone else to
finish up with what they're doing.
>> Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Suppose that I wanted
to use Bootstrap at home--
NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
AUDIENCE: I see, on the website,
the Getting Started page.
They give me the options
Bootstrap, Source Code, or Sass.
Which of these do I want?
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
So the question is, how do you get
started using Bootstrap by ourselves?
It just happens to
magically work right here.
So if we have time at
the end of the seminar,
I'll show you how you can
get it on your own web page.
Like here, I've actually
put in some settings that
will have it automatically
loaded, but I'll
show you to do it from
scratch on your own web pages.
>> AUDIENCE: Thank you.
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
Good question.
Feeling good?
Cool.
So who wants to tell me how they made
this thing look nice and Boostrappy?
What's the first class we add to the ul?
AUDIENCE: class="list-group".
NEEL MEHTA: Yes. list-group.
And then what do we attach to the lis?
Someone else?
AUDIENCE: And then, after
that, class="list-group-item".
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: And it's the
same for the next one.
>> NEEL MEHTA: li class="list-group-item".
There you go.
We have our nice list group,
just like we had expected.
So there you go.
In 10 minutes, we have made
this boring, old Yalp! page
look nice and professional.
And that's just the beginning.
So now that you feel
good about that, let's
just go ahead and talk about
a couple more components that
might come in handy as you
go throughout your adventure.
>> Of course, there's a lot ones here.
And now that you've learned
how to do list groups,
you can pretty much teach
yourself how to do any of these.
But, of course, let's just try
and do a couple more ourselves,
just so you get a feel for
how you might use them.
I'm just going to go
to this example here.
Again, the code that I just pasted
in here is available right here.
So feel free to pull it up.
>> So we've already gone through
a couple of these examples.
So we have buttons, which we
have already seen how to do.
We can make buttons larger.
By button class-- it goes, btn btn-lg
and btn-default makes it white.
So this makes our button bigger
than it might otherwise be.
It might come in handy, if you have
big submit button or something.
We saw the list group example,
we saw the form example.
>> One very important one is icons.
And icons are a way for you to add
interesting things, like check check
marks, or pluses, or friend
icons, or restart icons,
or whatever to your web app.
So again, if we into here,
the components, glyphicons,
are the icons available for Bootstrap.
There's an exhaustive
list of all the ones here.
So just as an example,
let's try and add one.
>> So like Facebook, we're to trying
to have an Add Friend button.
Let's first add some style.
button class="btn btn-success".
And there we go.
Let's add an icon here.
What icon, do you think,
might make sense to put here?
You've probably seen on
some web pages or whatever,
but what's an example of an icon that
might go well inside this button?
Feel free to browse this view,
if you need any inspiration.
There's a lot of useful
ones available here.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Maybe the glyphicon user one?
NEEL MEHTA: OK.
This one.
That's pretty good.
Yes.
On Facebook, I think it
would look a bit like that.
So here's how we go about
adding icons to our pages.
We just have a span-- a span is a
neutral container for something.
A div is a container for something,
a span is another container.
divs have line breaks
around them, spans do not.
So there's different ways of
having generic containers.
Like it doesn't make sense to put it
inside of a paragraph or anything.
We've got to put it
inside something though,
so we just put inside of a span.
So span class=glyphicon
glyphicon-user" close span.
And we now have the
icon inside the button.
>> So it doesn't look entirely unlike
what you might see on facebook.com.
And so it's nice that these can
actually be placed anywhere you want.
In your header bars,
in your list groups.
Whatever.
It doesn't have to be
inside of a button.
So as an example, I can
put the same class here.
"glyphicon glyphicon-user".
And it appears just the same.
So these icons-- you can use the span
class="glyphicon glyphicon-whatever".
And that will let you add
icons wherever you want.
And icons are a very important
part of making a website look
professional and well done.
So don't overdo it, but it's
often a good thing to know.
>> Panels, again.
I'll just do this again as a recap
because they're kind of involved.
You'll notice that in
turning your normal HTML
site into a Bootstrap-afied
site, you'll have
to add extra structure to the website.
For example, we have extra
divs here just because those
are needed to make a panel.
So just keep that in mind that
you'll have to have extra structure.
So "panel panel-default".
Maybe it's panel-header.
I think it's panel-heading.
Yes.
There we go.
So, again, there is our panel.
>> One more thing that we
did not cover yet, tables.
Tables, by default look kind of ugly.
Like this.
But tables are, of course,
a very important part
of what you will do in web development.
In Pset7, for example, CS50
Finance, which will come out soon,
you'll use a lot of tables.
And a lot of web dev use a lot
of tables to display information,
like stocks, or scores, or whatever.
>> So styling tables is actually very easy.
You add the table class to your table.
And, I dare say, it looks pretty nice.
You can do extra things,
like "table table-striped".
And you'll see the results here.
You can do table-bordered.
There's a lot of options you can.
But basically, adding a
table, the table class,
will make your tables look pretty nice.
So that's a brief rundown of
some of the more important styles
and components you'll
need to use for Bootstrap.
So I think that wraps
up our beautiful part.
Any questions right now about how
to make your websites beautiful?
How you can use these
components to your advantage?
Feeling good?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Maybe this
is a silly question,
but can you use Bootstrap on Wikipedia?
If you're editing a Wikipedia page?
NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
So the question was, I'm
editing a Wikipedia page,
can I include Bootstrap styles in there?
>> AUDIENCE: Yes.
>> NEEL MEHTA: And so Bootstrap is
basically a big CSS style sheet.
A CSS style sheet just says, whenever
I have this class, attach these styles.
So the CSS style sheet for Bootstrap
is going to be something like .btn,
the button class, will get like a
rounded corner border or whatever.
So basically, Bootstrap it just a
bunch of classes and a bunch of styles
specified for those classes.
So as long as you have that CSS,
this list of rules in your page,
you will get the Bootstrap styling.
That is, of course, contingent on
having the Bootstrap styles in your page
to begin with.
>> And so in Wikipedia,
you probably could not
do that because Wikipedia
does not have Bootstrap in it.
But if it did have Bootstrap,
you could probably do that.
And if you wanted, you could
include it, but that might
break the existing layout of the page.
But very good question.
You can use Bootstrap
wherever it is included,
but it's not built in by default.
>> AUDIENCE: Thank you.
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
Any more questions?
Yes.
So whether you're here or at home,
just remember getboostrap.com-- again,
getboostrap.com-- is your friend.
Whenever you're using
Bootstrap, this will give you
instructions about how to get
started, how to use components.
There's some cool JavaScript
plug-ins that we won't go over here,
but they're worth checking out as well.
So this is your friend.
It's just important to get
used to how to use this.
>> So let's chat a bit about
making responsive websites.
So as I said before, people used
their laptops, they use their phones.
And as you might well imagine, this is
a very different screen size than that.
And so the same website
that looks good on my phone
is not going to look good,
necessarily, on a computer.
So what you have to do is
make your website adapt.
It has to adapt to the various
screen sizes that it's on.
>> It has to say, I know I'm on a
computer, a big laptop, I should expand.
I know I'm on a phone, I should shrink.
And so Bootstrap provides some
very, very useful tools to do this.
So Bootstrap let's you break
a website into 12 columns.
You can make rows and have 12 columns.
And you can partition
those however you want.
You can have one, big thing,
which is 12 columns wide.
You can have two things
that are six each.
You can do one thing that's four,
one that's two, or one that's six.
You can do three, three, three, three.
You can do whatever
breakdown that you want.
>> So maybe your web page needs to have a
left column that's one third the width.
So that would be four columns
wide and the rest of the page
would be eight columns wide.
So this is an example.
Let's pull up another example.
>> AUDIENCE: Does it always
have to be an even split?
Could it be a seven, five split?
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
It could be seven, five.
Yes.
As long as it adds to 12, it's fine.
So let's go back here.
Again, the code that is
here is also available here,
under responsive example.
So I just pulled up some
example responsive code here.
So you do this by using
a thing called row.
Row is just another class.
It's another style you add onto your
divs to make them their own components.
>> So you say, div
class="row" to make a row,
to give yourself 12 columns of space.
And then you put columns inside of that.
So here we col-xs-6.
Don't worry about the xs.
We'll talk about in a sec.
But basically, we have one
thing that is six wide.
We call it left.
And so that's the left box here.
We have one thing that is
six of the 12 columns wide.
And that one is on the right.
>> well just gives makes
your div fill it up gray.
So that's just so we can
see that they're distinct.
And so this the first example.
It's a very simple example of how you
would use your rows and columns here.
You define a row using class="row".
And then you do class="col-xs-6" do
half, "col-xs-6" to do the other half.
Here's a more complicated example.
Let's look at the Tiny,
Huge, The rest one.
>> We can make Tiny two columns wide,
we can make Huge six columns wide,
and The rest four columns wide.
That adds up to 12.
And so these end up spanning
the width of the page.
Again, we have a row outside.
Then we have div class="col-xs-2"
and then 6, and then 4.
And that will provide
the structure for us.
And so we can put whatever
the heck we want inside here.
Instead of Tiny, we can put a button.
button class="btn btn-primary".
And so notice that our button
doesn't take up all the width,
but at least it's restricted
to that much space.
>> So that's all well and good.
So we can now break up our web
page into chunks, width wise.
We can say we want to have a left
column, and a right column, and so on.
But we haven't gone over
how you make it responsive.
And so Bootstrap let's do that as well.
It has these things called breakpoints.
So it has a way of knowing whether
you're on a laptop, you're on a tablet,
you're on a phone horizontal,
or you're on a phone vertical.
It knows the screen size.
And breaks this into four categories--
large or lg, which is laptops, usually.
md or medium, which is tablets.
sm, small.
Or xs, extra small.
And so when you specify
a column, you say,
it should be six columns wide
on an extra small device.
That's why we did col-xs-6.
We're saying that it should
be six of the 12 columns wide
on an extra small device.
And if it's anything bigger, we'll just
default to using the extra small size.
If it's anything bigger than
extra small, it'll be six wide.
And so we can leverage
these to make of our columns
take up different amount of
columns based on the screen size.
Let's go to this responsive resizing.
So we have our columns.
And it says, "col-lg-6 col-xs-12".
So given what you know
so far, what do you
think is going to
happen on a big screen?
Well, it's kind of
given way, but what do
you think it will look
like on a big screen?
And why is that?
>> AUDIENCE: Is it that
on a big screen, it's
going to take only a
portion of the full space?
Like half of it, I guess?
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: And on smaller
screen, it's going
to take up the whole screen, the 12.
NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
Right.
So as an example, let's
just look down here.
Yes.
So on anything that is lg or
bigger-- so my computer happens
to be lg because it's
pretty wide-- it will make
it side by side because it's col-lg-6.
So because it's on large, it makes it
six columns wide and six columns wide.
Let's see what happens if I
make this into a smaller one.
I'm just going to un-full screen this.
And I'm going to shrink the screen.
I'm going to shrink the screen, so it
looks like I am on a smaller device.
So I'm going to shrink it like this.
>> And voila.
It is now stacked
because now we have gone
from large to-- this is probably
an extra small screen size.
And so now it says, OK, we're not
in large, we're in extra small land.
So we're going to use
the extra small size.
And we're going to xs-12, xs-12.
So it's going to be stacked.
And just notice that there's
a thing called a breakpoint.
A breakpoint is where
you made the transition
from extra small to small,
small to large, and so on.
>> So just notice that as I slide this
out, eventually, you'll get to the point
where they'll jump to be side by side.
There you go.
So there's the breakpoint right there.
So we can make it even more complicated.
Now we can say, these
things should be four wide.
That is, they should
take up about a third
of the speech on very large devices.
On a medium device, it should take
up half the screen because it's md-6.
On a very small device,
it should take up 12.
And so this looks pretty natural.
Let's just try this out for ourselves.
>> So on a big screen, they're four wide.
Shrink it a little bit.
And they are now six wide.
So this is six, six, six.
Shrink it even more and then
they will be totally stacked.
So this, for example, makes sense if
you're having cards, like news cards,
for example, where if
it's on a very big screen,
it's OK if you have several side by side
because they would all get enough room.
But they need to have enough room.
So on a smaller screen,
you'd want to give them
more room, proportionally, of the page.
>> So as a real world example,
let's say we have Twitter.
And we have text box, so
you can tweet on the side.
And we have a list of trending
topics on the right side.
So on a big screen, we should
have them be side by side,
so you can see them at a glass.
But on a smaller screen,
we should do 12 and 12,
so that the trending topics
are below the tweet area.
Because the tweet area is the
main thing and on a small screen,
the trending topics don't
matter quite as much.
And so we put them right below, so
that they can both get enough space.
Make sense so far?
>> AUDIENCE: Yes.
>> NEEL MEHTA: Solid.
So that's all the examples I have here.
Let's try and do a challenge.
So again, this is challenge-2.html for
those of you following along at home.
So my buddy, Mark Zuckerberg,
came to me the other day.
And he's like, Neel, I have
gotten pretty good at web design.
I can do the HTML.
I have made this little,
new edit to Facebook.
I have a new idea for how
we should style Facebook.
And here it is.
Right here.
Here's some example code.
So it's called Fancybook.
>> We have some status updates.
We have Nemo, Mike Kosowski,
Woody-- three status updates.
And then we have a list of
online friends right below it.
So he's done his homework.
He knows a little bit about
Bootstrap, he's made the list view,
he has done a little bit of HTML.
So he has the web page.
But he's like, Neel, I don't
understand responsive design at all.
Do you have any experts who
could help me with that?
And fortunately, you are now
experts in responsive design.
>> So what he told me was that he
wants Fancybook to look like this.
On a very small device,
like a phone, everything
should be stacked, like here.
So you have the timeline
upfront, up top, and then
you should have the
chat bar at the bottom.
But on a tablet or a medium
device, it should be half and half,
as in the timeline should be
half and the list of chat friends
should be on the other half.
>> Then on a laptop, the timeline
should take up three fourths
and then the chat hedge should
take up another one quarter.
And so he's like, Neel, I have this
code here, but it's not responsive.
It needs to behave like this.
So my challenge to you
is given this code here--
if you refresh your
CodePens, you'll see this.
Or if you just paste in the code
on challenge-2, you'll see this.
>> Here's this example code.
You'll see some xxxs.
I want you to change the xxxs, such that
the timeline and the list of friends
follows these specs here.
Don't worry about what's
inside the timeline for now.
We'll get that in the next step.
But for now, let's see if we get
these things to split it up like this.
So does that make sense?
So if you're at home,
pause the video and try
to make your web page
look responsive like this.
If you're here, take
like two, three minutes.
Feel free to chat with a neighbor,
and try, and fix Mr. Zuckerberg's
responsive design problem.
If you have any questions,
feel free to let me know.
Feeling good?
Done?
Nice.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
NEEL MEHTA: What?
>> AUDIENCE: I'm good.
>> NEEL MEHTA: Oh, good.
Nice.
AUDIENCE: The thing about
the 12, is it that Bootstrap
treats a given screen space as 12
units across and then divides that up?
How exactly does the
proportioning work for this?
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
So the question is, how
does the proportioning
work for Bootstrap, right?
>> AUDIENCE: Yes.
NEEL MEHTA: So whenever
you have a div class="row",
no matter how big the screen is,
Bootstrap will give you 12 units
of the same size to
take up that much size.
So in col 1, it's always 8.33%
of the size of the screen,
whether that's this wide
or that's this wide.
And so, of course, on a smaller
screen, each column is smaller.
You still have 12 columns
wide, it's a smaller.
So it's up to you to make sure
that things take up more column,
proportionally, to compensate
for that lack of space.
Does that make sense?
>> AUDIENCE: Yes.
Thank you.
NEEL MEHTA: Good question.
AUDIENCE: On a large
screen, can you have
the timeline take up three fourths?
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
NEEL MEHTA: How are guys feeling?
Good?
Cool.
So let's come back.
And let's try and fix this part
of Mr. Zuckerberg's website.
So the timelines is up here, at
the top, and the list of friends
is at the bottom.
And so we just need to assign
columns, with sizing proportional,
in each of these.
So this first xxx is for the timeline.
What classes do we put in here?
What did you guys put in here?
So remember, on a large screen, it needs
to take up three quarters of the width.
And so what style would give you that?
On a large screen, three
quarters of the width.
What class do we use there?
AUDIENCE: So we're just going to be
editing that first instance of class.
NEEL MEHTA: For now.
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: We're not editing each,
individual feature of the timeline?
NEEL MEHTA: Not now, at least.
So this whole thing is a block.
We're just changing the
designing of the block.
So here we do col-lg-9 because it's
nine out of the 12 wide on a big screen.
And then on a medium screen,
how many columns should I get?
AUDIENCE: It's supposed
to be half and half.
NEEL MEHTA: Right.
So how many is that?
>> AUDIENCE: So six.
NEEL MEHTA: Six.
And then extra small should be-- if it
takes up the entire width of the row,
how many should it be?
AUDIENCE: 12.
NEEL MEHTA: 12.
Yes.
And now we've got to
change this other ones,
so it takes up the rest of the space.
So col-lg--
AUDIENCE: It's going to
take up the whole screen?
NEEL MEHTA: It takes up a quarter
of the screen on a large device,
as we showed here.
>> AUDIENCE: Three.
>> NEEL MEHTA: Three.
And then col-md-6 to take
up the rest of the space.
col-xs-12.
So now we have the timeline
taking up three quarters
of the page in the big screen
and then one quarter on the side.
And then if size the screen down,
it should resize accordingly.
So it's stacked now,
on a very small screen.
And if we size it up a little bit,
they should be exactly half and half.
So we've done that so far.
Very cool.
And so we won't do the
other part of the challenge.
You can do that yourself.
But basically, you have to
try and make these responsive
as well-- make the timeline
items, themselves, responsive.
So now we've gone through
all you need to know
about the responsive side of Bootstrap.
Any questions about responsive
design with Bootstrap
and how you might go about doing that?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Is it similar if
we had an embedded video
and we wanted to control the
scale at which the video was--
the size of the video
going from laptop to phone.
NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
More or less.
You'd have to tell the video to
take up as much room as it's given,
which is a little annoying sometimes.
But the core idea is the same.
A video, like any other object in
the page, like a button or whatever,
as long as you use the
columns and the rows,
you can give it a
certain amount of space.
And so getting it to honor that is a
different question because like YouTube
embeds have a certain, preferred size.
But theoretically at
least, it would work.
Cool?
>> AUDIENCE: I suppose then,
for an image, do you actually
need to have different versions of
the same image in different sizes
for laptop versus iPhone?
Yeah The question is, do we need to
have images that are responsive as well.
And indeed, you can do that.
I think it's in CSS.
But Bootstrap allows
you to do that as well.
You can have responsive images.
You can have your images resize
according to the size of the page.
And there's a very new thing
HTML5, the newest version of HTML,
and CSS3, the newest
version of CSS, which
will let you request different images
based on the screen size you're at.
Usually, it's good enough to just
have your image just shrink or grow to
however big it needs to be.
But you can, if you want
to, have one 32 by 32
for very small screens, and
64 by 64 for a big screen,
and then serve those selectively.
You can do it.
It's done by some people.
It's still pretty cutting edge.
But short answer, responsive images--
Bootstrap can save the day there.
Cool?
>> AUDIENCE: Thank you.
>> NEEL MEHTA: So let's
talk real fast about how
to get this in your own web page.
Let's say you want make your
own website using Bootstrap.
And so let's just just
walk through it together.
Let's say you make just
a normal HTML page.
Feel free to follow along in
whatever your favorite editor is.
So we just have some HTML page.
We can do !doctype html.
This is also html, our page.
Nothing new.
We've done this before.
So here we have our HTML and
we can put stuff inside here.
We can have our button.
And as I said before, this
isn't necessarily going to work.
Why might this not work?
Why won't we get our
nice, colorful button?
>> AUDIENCE: Because we didn't link it
to the Bootstrap project or the file?
NEEL MEHTA: Yes.
Correct.
Because Bootstrap-- it's
just a fancy CSS file.
It's a series of styles that
are attached to your elements.
Here we've told it that we
want to use these styles.
I'll size that up a little bit.
We've told it we want use
these styles, but we never
told it what the styles are.
And that's what your
question from earlier was.
That's the answer to that.
We need to find a way to get the styles
and include them in our page somehow.
And so Bootstrap will
show us how to do that.
>> So if you go to the top
here, Getting Started.
There's different ways to download it.
This might not make sense necessarily.
Bootstrap-- this will let
you grab the CSS file itself.
And you included it in your own page.
Source Code is if you want
to hack on it by yourself.
You don't need this really.
Sass is a language
that compiles into CSS.
Think of it as a preprocessor.
Much like PHP is a preprocessor of
HTML, Sass is a preprocessor for CSS.
So if you want to do it
that way, you can do that.
>> The easiest way is using a CDN,
or content delivery network.
It's a website that just
serves up a copy of Bootstrap
very fast for you to
include in your own page.
So here's an example.
It'll give you this link element.
A link element tells your browser,
take whatever files are stored here
and include it in our web page.
And in this case, it's
the Bootstrap CSS file.
So we'll just copy that URL, or
that text, and we'll throw it inside
of our head.
>> And I won't start the page for this,
but you can trust that this works.
The link will get you the CSS.
Include it in your
page and then you'll be
able to use all of the Bootstrap
classes that you know and love.
If you want to keep it locally and
have it on your own file system
instead of having to go to
the internet to grab it,
like if you want to
use the site offline,
you can use the Download option.
But for the most part, using the
CDN is pretty fast because that way,
it's kept updated for you as well.
You have to manually update it either.
Make sense?
>> So a lot of tools will have this built
in by default. In your Pset7 and Pset8,
I believe Bootstrap is
automatically included.
And in CodePen, for
example, it's already
included because I
added add that setting.
So if you ever want to play around
with it, you can just go on CodePen,
or go on your ID, or whatever.
And you might be able to
access Bootstrap there,
but it's not always built
in, by default, to the web.
Make sense?
>> Yes.
just as a recap-- we have
like five minutes left.
But as a recap, in new web pages,
you can include Bootstrap like this.
And once you have it included,
you can do all the fun stuff here.
You can go on, and you can just peruse
the CSS, you can add some cool styles,
you can have components
like the buttons,
and the tables, and the list
items that we mentioned.
There's some cool JavaScript plugins,
which you might want to explore.
They add some cool
interactivity to the web page.
Like this one makes a modal dialogue.
>> So there's some fun stuff
you can do with Bootstrap.
So my advice to you is go ahead
and use it in your own projects,
follow the instructions we
just did as to how to get it,
and just read the Bootstrap because
you'll learn more about what to do.
And so we've gone
over, today, how to use
the documentation, what the building
blocks are, and how it is conceptually.
So now my challenge to you is
make a website using Bootstrap.
Go into the docs.
And use the tools that we've
learned so far to try and parse them
and understand them.
And use those styles and tools
you see there in your website.
And it's just a big,
experimental process.
>> Try out a certain style.
Does it work?
Does is not?
Try putting stuff together.
See what happens.
It's very much a self
guided, discovery process.
But today, we've learned the
very basics of what is Bootstrap?
Why does it work?
How does it work?
How do we start using
it, in the first place?
And so now that you're
over that hump, you
should be able to do it
pretty smoothly by yourself.
>> So once again, all the
code we did is here.
So if you ever want
to get a brush up on,
like, what's a quick cheat
sheet for all of the styles?
You can go into this sample here.
We have some example styles here.
If you want to try the
challenges again by yourself,
you can try them here and
check out the solutions.
So this link will be
included on the slides, which
will be sent out to you of course.
But it's also up here.
You can pause the video, if you want.
All the information you need is
going to be right here, on this site.
So if anyone has any questions, we can
take them for the next couple minutes.
Otherwise, thank you all
very much for watching.