ROSS RHEINGANS-YOO: Hi, I'm Ross.
And this is a CS50 seminar.
It will take you from programming
in C to programming in Python.
>> Python is a scripting language.
It's largely like C
in syntax, though some
of the technical details of
how that syntax gets executed
are slightly different.
It is less powerful than C in some ways.
It is less expressive for
where exactly in your computer
memory gets laid out,
how it gets laid out,
when it gets freedom, and
those sorts of things.
>> It's more useful than C in some ways,
because it's easier to program in.
The language is, to some
people, more intuitive.
And really, the goal is for
it to be faster to program
and potentially slower to execute.
>> Now if you think about
the amount of time
you spent on your last
problem set writing
your code against the
amount of time you spend
on your last problem
set executing your code,
you'd imagine that the language
which was twice as fast to write,
and twice as slow to execute, might
be an improvement over C in some ways.
Certainly when you're trying to write
small programs to do little things,
Python is a useful language of choice.
>> And at the end of this
seminar, I hope you'll
be able to make the
choice in future projects
about which language is
correct to use, not the idea
that one language is more
correct all the time.
A few things about what the seminar is.
This seminar is not intended to
teach you Python from scratch.
Python is very similar
to C, and I'm assuming
that you're a CS50 student, or someone
with a similar familiarity with C.
>> If you're CS50 student
around problem set 6,
so you've see a lot of
things in C, I'll give you
the major differences,
and some of the things
that make Python different
and special and useful,
but I'm not going to go for
what a programming language is
and how to write programs.
However, this seminar will teach
you to write a Python programs
if you're one of those few groups.
Again we'll look at how
you would implement psets--
that should be 1-6 in
Python-- and provide pointers
to official documentation
for future reference.
The other thing that's important
about how this talk is assigned,
this video will be
online, courtesy of CS50,
so you shouldn't feel like
you need to take notes.
You can always go back and look
at it later as a reference.
Additionally the slides
are available right now
at this site, which should
take you do a Google doc.
It's a slightly abridged version
of what I'm showing on the screen.
>> One careful caveat before
we jump in, Python 3
is a different language from Python 2.
They look a lot the same; there are
very slight technical differences
that will cause programs
written in Python 2
not to be able to be executed
in the Python 3 environment.
>> The CS50 appliance comes with
Python, by default it uses Python 2.
You can check this by
typing in your command line
python --version, which should output
2.7.6 on the current appliance.
Try Python 3, which does
work in the appliance,
if Python defaults to 2.X.Y, either on
the appliance or on your own machines.
You should replace Python 3 anytime
in this talk that I write Python.
If your machine is
running 2 by default, type
Python 3 in order to be able to actually
follow along and execute these things.
>> Additionally, I'll point you
at official resources now.
docs.python.org/3-- careful
that that's a 3 and not a 2--
has useful references.
Tutorial will take you through
much of the same things
that I'm doing now, except in text form.
Reference is useful as a
reference for the language,
and the Standard Library gives
you some of the extensions
with additional functionality.
>> So a very first Python program.
On the left we have standard C,
on the right, we have Python.
You might have recognized
this problem, it's
one of the first problem
sets in CS50, and these
solve it using the same solution.
Now, the reason that we're
looking at these side by side
is so we can look at
syntactic differences.
One of the elephants in the room
that you might have noticed right
off the bat, is that Python has no
main function wrapping around the code.
So in C, you write a bunch of
files, you link them together,
and the program starts executing
at this thing called int main.
>> In Python, you write a
file you, execute the file,
the program starts executing
at the top of the file.
So it's going to start
at the top of file
go down until it find something else.
If it finds a function definition,
it won't actually execute that code,
it will simply define the function.
But here, when the first
program is n equals 10,
the first thing that this program
will do is take this value of 10
and set it into a variable called n.
>> Speaking of that line, one of
other things-- sorry-- this
means that C programs,
you'll write them,
you'll make them, which will
invoke some clang commands,
and then you'll run a
resulting executable.
Python programs, you run the
text file-- this mario.py might
be this file that I just showed
you-- you'll run that file
and you'll execute,
and the contents of it
will be executed by
the Python interpreter.
You can do this in your IDE.
>> So if I have a Hello file,
which simply has this contents.
This is actually Python
2, not Python 3, so don't
worry about the syntax for now.
But I'll run Python, on
hello.py, and it runs.
>> Another way that I can use Python that
I won't deal with so much in this talk,
is if I just type Python, it
drops me into an environment where
I can feed it Python line by line.
So here, if I type in
print space 'hello, world'.
Type enter.
It will spit me that back the results
that individual line immediately.
>> This is might be useful.
In this talk I'll do things on slides.
And so you'll be able to follow
along either in here, or by writing
actual files and then executing them.
>> But, going back to this
code, another thing
that you might have
noticed-- well, there's
two things that you might
notice about these blocks.
The first, rather more mundane, is that
the Python has no trailing semicolon.
>> Semicolons are optional everywhere
and harmless everywhere.
You can add them.
It might make people who write
Python for a living snicker at you
behind your back, because
they're not necessary.
They're often a sign of being held over
from C. The designers of the language
feel that it is more clear this way
and that it's not necessary to declare
every time you end a line.
>> Another strange thing about this n
is it doesn't have a type attached.
One of the magic pieces of Python--
and I'm going to call it magic,
but there are very
technical reasons why it
works-- one of the
magic pieces of Python
is that variables can expand or
shrink to contain whatever data
types you would want them to.
>> So this is a 10.
If later down I assigned to this
n 0.5, it would take that 0.5.
No matter that it's an int here and
float there, anything that uses this n
will, more or less, be able to chug
along if it gets either of those.
Unless there's some very real
reason why it can't use the data
type that n currently has,
at which point it'll get
wedged and throw an error,
and those sorts of things.
>> But here, Python
doesn't really care what
it is that I'm going to stick in this
sentence, like, you want this thing?
This thing in that?
Yeah, it's kind of a thing.
I'll stick it in the end.
It'll be a problem later on, if
somebody who wants to use that end
can't handle it.
This is one of the major
differences between Python and C
that makes it easy to
write very large C programs
and makes it easier to write
very small Python program.
>> The for syntax is not very
different in what it does.
It's slightly different
in how it's expressed.
So this is a very, what is called
Pythonic, way of writing it.
for row in range(n), this is the
range of numbers from 0 to n,
inclusive on the bottom
and exclusive on the top.
So it's from 0 to n-1, which is
exactly what the C code is doing,
except it's a lot easier
to look at perhaps.
>> The relevant block is
not set off by braces,
instead it's set off
by this indentation.
So all of these lines are
four spaces over to the right,
or like about an elephant width.
And those are the ones which are
going to be executed in this for.
If I mess up the
indentation on this and I
push that print back to
the original indentation,
that print will leave the for loop.
In contrast to C, where here I actually
need to move that closed brace around.
>> This means that you don't get errors
that jump out at you because you
put a brace in wrong place.
It does mean that you get errors
that jump out at you because you
indented a line wrong.
So it makes indentations super careful.
Hopefully you were being super
careful with your indentation anyway,
and so this isn't that
much more of a burden.
>> But a basic rule for Python,
and we'll have a couple of these
that we'll go through through
the course of the talk,
is try natural syntax
before looking anything up.
So this syntax, for
this number in range,
is very distinctive in terms of style.
Lots of things in Python
we'll see taking this form.
>> And so if you come up
with a new object that you
think you should be able to
iterate over this, in this format,
turns out it probably
supports that format.
We're not going to go super deep in
the technical reasons why that's true.
>> But it's a useful intuition to have
when you're approaching Python programs,
that this thing is just going to work.
Try it.
Boot up the Command Line
Interpreter, see if it works,
move on with things, before you
even need to open up Google and say,
what's the syntax for
this particular thing?
Lots of Python you could
discover just by trying.
>> This if is even more similar
to C then the fors are.
Note that there's no parentheses.
The parentheses are, again,
harmless but unnecessary.
There is a colon at the end
just like the for loops,
and again, the relative blocks are
indented rather than set off by braces.
This else is at the original
level of indentation,
and its relevant block indented again.
Those work exactly as they do in C.
>> This is actually very much the same.
Again, print loses one character
off of printf You pass some strings.
It turns out strings
can either be marked off
by single quotes or double quotes.
There's no difference,
except that inside
of single quotes you can use
double quotes with abandon,
rather than having to
escape all of them.
And inside of double quotes, you
can use single quotes with abandon
without having to escape them.
If you wanted to mix
them, you can certainly
look up online how to do that.
>> You'll notice that over here,
I've passed in end= this thing.
This is an example of an optional
argument, which is one of those things
that Python supports that
makes it quite useful.
So print actually has a lot of
arguments, which are usually
set to their default
value, but here I've
decided to override the one called end.
The reason that I have to
override it with an empty string
is that print in Python, by
default, prints out a new line
after the thing that you told it too.
>> So this hash is actually going to
print out a hash in a new line.
And if I don't want hash to print out
a new line after it, then I have to say
don't print one.
But, yet so, the one last thing that
this program is missing that one has is
an include at the top.
Print is baked into Python so basically
that there's no header or module
that you need to
include, though if wanted
to include other things
in a Python script,
I would do it in a very similar format--
the words are just slightly different.
>> I mentioned that we
don't need a main here,
because the Python starts
executing at the top.
If I wanted to wrap
this in a function, I
would do it like this-- I
would say def function name,
arguments might go in here and we'll
see some of those later, colon,
and then again, this
entire set off block
is what is the operational
block for that function.
So this is the definition
of the function.
And there's a declaration, then down
here, I can just call the function.
And again, the program
interpreter, starting at the top,
will see this is the definition.
It won't execute this until it
get here, and then it's like, oh
now you've called it, I
guess I should execute it.
>> A thing that's very common
to see in Python files,
especially Python files that
are released to the public
and developed by-- and developed and
maintained, is something of this form.
This is basically-- so because
Python, you start at the top
and then you execute down to the bottom,
I if I just had Mario called out here,
then any time I included this file in
another file, because I wanted to use
is Mario function, that other file would
also have this call to Mario in it.
And when I ran that file,
it would call Mario.
>> So it's possible that I only
want to run this if I've actually
executed this particular file.
And so I can wrap this in an
idiom like this, where I say,
if the name of this execution
environment is main,
then I want to do these things.
Otherwise somebody else can
use-- include my function--
my file, and just to get
access to these functions
without having to run the things
that I want to execute in this file.
This is, again, optional
but very common.
>> These things are entirely-- are
exactly the same between C and Python,
certainly in 3.
I think in 2, the division operator
sometimes gives you back floats when
you operated on ints, and either
you wanted that or you didn't.
But plus, minus, and times
work exactly like you'd expect,
except over slightly more types.
So you can multiply floats by
ints, and those sorts of things.
>> set works exactly the same.
You can use two equal signs.
inequals-- greater than, less
than, these sorts of things--
have the meanings that
you're familiar with them.
>> Where C uses these operators,
Python uses slightly more English
readable ones.
So instead of two, ampersands, you
literally type the word "and," "or,"
or "not."
Like in your if-- in your
conditional statements,
we saw earlier that this syntax in C
corresponds to this syntax in Python.
And there's not a lot different
there, except for a little bit
of punctuation around the sides.
Again, where C would else
if, Python uses elif,
but these are mostly
surface level changes.
>> Iteration like this is often
written in this idiom in Python.
You can manufacture this sort of
thing with a while loop on the outside
if you wanted, but you
certainly don't have to.
And again, if you wanted the
print out elements in of an array
you might do it this way.
One of the fun things
about Python though,
is that you don't need
to use this paradigm,
and you can use a
slightly more elegant one.
You say for a in ary.
>> So rather than going here
and running over the indices,
and then pulling out
individual elements,
you tell the for to actually just
run over the elements themselves.
And then whatever you're doing
inside can operate directly
on the elements, which is pretty fun.
And we'll see-- we'll use
that idiom again and again
as we walk through code.
>> This is, again, an example
of something that I'll
call Python magic, though there are
very technical reasons why it works.
And there are technical things that
need to be true about array in order
for this to work behind the scenes.
The thing is that most types
which you'd expect this to work
have had this implemented for
you in the built-in language.
>> Another thing that it would be nice
if this worked in every language,
but there are some reasons why it can't,
print this string times this number.
Turns out in Python, this does exactly
what you'd like, which is just fun,
and means that we can actually
reduce this program, again mario.c.
Rather than iterating a lot, we can
just say, I want some number of spaces,
I want the number of hashes,
and some hashes at the end.
And again, we use this format.
>> Here, we're passing in
a variable this way.
Again, we don't need to say
what type of variable it is,
and the only time we'll
get errors is at run time.
When somebody tries
to pass something in,
it'll come into the function just fine.
If we wedge here because this isn't the
thing that you can create ranges over,
I'll get a runtime error there,
and I'll have to debug it that way.
But in the meantime, I don't have
to be very careful about what
gets passed in, so long as in the actual
execution it all works very cleanly.
>> I could even make this
a little bit cleaner
using a particular built-in function
on strings, which is Right Justify.
This is just a useful function
lying around the library.
It's in the documentation
if you go and look for it.
And I say, well I'm going to have
this string, some number of hashes,
and I'd like to right justify it-- pad
it out with spaces to be this length.
>> Again, this is in the
documentation, which brings us--
I'll actually click through these--
which brings us to our second rule
for Python-- standard library
function methods are your friends.
And it's often worth your while
to go looking for I wonder
if there's a thing that just does this.
There probably is.
If you'd like to pad
out a string, if you'd
like to take the back
half of a string, if you'd
like to search through a string, if
you'd like to smash a couple of things
together with a string
with commas between them,
there are standard library
functions for doing this.
>> And it makes your life
easier if you use them
instead of rolling out
everything on your own
in five lines of code here,
five lines of code here.
That really starts at
add up to real time.
>> One of the interesting things
about how this gets called.
You'll notice that there's a dot thing.
I have some object on the left,
and then I called a dot a function.
This is one of the paradigms that Python
uses for attaching methods to objects.
We'll talk about what this
is very briefly at the end,
but know that we can both operate on
things by taking that thing saying dot
whatever, or by calling
a function that takes
that object and some other arguments.
>> So these are both ways that
things get done in Python.
And whether a particular
functionality is implemented
in this style or this
style is something that you
should look up until you get a hang
for which one it's likely to fall into.
There's a more or less cohesive
philosophy behind Python
that you absorb mostly
by writing a lot in it.
At some point, which one of these
something will be implemented as
becomes natural.
For now, it's just something
you learn as you figure out
each individual thing.
>> So standard library
functions are your friends,
and they let you write things that
take up this much space really shortly,
really elegantly.
And this is actually probably more
legible, I'd say, than the C program
over there.
Not to mention the fact that is so
short you can fit a whole elephant
in the space that we've saved.
>> Another thing, this is an implementation
of mario that's dot C, which I think
is the shortest you can get it.
It doesn't have the get int, but
it hard codes the value of 10
the same way that this one does.
Turns out that this one clocks in at
84 characters, whereas Python is 64.
And this is infinitely more
readable than this garbage here.
So Python is more efficient in space.
It's slightly less efficient
in time, but not by much.
>> Lists are an important thing in Python.
We haven't seen them, but they
operate much like arrays do in C.
So here, you can declare them,
you can pass them into a thing.
Now squares holds an
array of these things.
Again, we haven't declared as
type, but if we ever try to use it,
anything that you'd expect to
work on an array of integers
is going to work on
an array of integers.
>> This Is a thing which
you absolutely can't
do in C, because the
memory it is so hands on,
but is very easy to do in Python.
If I want my array to be larger, I can
append an element to it and it's fine.
>> What's going on behind the scenes?
The interpreter will go
out and get some memory,
and maybe it'll get a
little bit of extra memory,
so I don't so I don't have
to realloc every time.
But how much have more
memory does it need?
This aren't decisions
that you have to make,
these are decisions that the
interpreter is going to do.
>> Here we see range can
take two arguments,
but it's still going to be inclusive
of the top so we add 1 there.
This is an idiom, which is an even more
clever way to write things like this.
It's called list comprehension,
and here what we're saying
is I'd like to put in i squared
for every value of i in this range.
This thing on the right could be another
array, and this thing on the left
to be any particular function
that would take in i as a variable
and give me out some result.
>> What I'm going to do is,
I'm going to construct
an array that's all of these things
for each value in this range.
And this is super elegant, super short,
and it's very clear what it means.
This is one of the
things-- this is again,
one of-- very emblematic of the
reasons that people like Python.
If you like programming
like this, then Python
is a language you might like to learn.
>> And again, there are technical
reasons why this works.
But as far as we're concerned,
we more or less don't care.
>> So if you want to print out lists,
some of the same idioms are useful.
For i in this range, we could
index through all the things
and then print them all out.
And you'll see len here.
If you've ever wanted to get
the length of the array, that's
very easy in Python,
it's very hard in C.
This would print out exactly
what you'd expect it to.
We could also, as we've seen before,
iterate over the elements in array
directly, and then just talk about
them, rather than having the index
back into the array every time.
>> And this is a thing that you can do.
So in C, if you ask for something
like this, print would say,
that's an array of integers.
That's definitely not a
string, I can't print it.
Python more or less doesn't care.
It's like, is there a way that I
could turn this in to a string?
Yeah, I'll do that.
And so I'll just print that out.
This means that you can
do things like-- these
are most of the hard parts
of game of fifteen, written
very briefly in Python.
>> You'll see that there's
a little bit of-- here
I've cast an integer to a string,
and I have to do that manually.
And I'm going to add
it to another string,
or otherwise Python gets confused.
But whether when you're
adding a string to an integer,
am I suppose to get an
integer back or a string back?
But again, if you just
call str on a thing,
and it could in any possible
world be converted into a string,
it will probably be
converted into a string.
>> Here, we see use of
nested list comprehension
on the left, some indexing, which
is exactly as you'd be used to it,
and some printing out of things.
Again, we've defined some
functions and we'll call them down
in main when we actually get the file.
return works exactly like you'd
expect from working with C. Find,
we can set up things like
this-- here's list comprehension
there's an assignment to a variable,
and we can actually do it even easier.
We don't need to write search,
because built-in to the language
is if this thing is in this array.
Return true, else return false.
So that's the entirety of find.
>> The entirety of sort
involves calling sort,
which is-- there are implementations
of this built into certain C libraries.
If you'd like this
sort of backwards, you
can override this optional
argument in reverse with a true.
And if you'd like to sort over
strings, that's built-in as well.
>> So this is not to say these are
things that you need to do every day,
but the idea is that this
is the philosophy of Python,
that all these things which you'd
sort of want to do are built-in.
And most standard functions,
so sort, length, whatever,
support most logically sensible input.
You call len on an array the same
way you call len on a string.
You multiply-- you sort strings
the same way you sort arrays.
>> Most standard functions
that people build,
and most third-party
libraries that people
build, because they're emulating
the design of the standard library,
can be called on everything that you're
like, why doesn't this just work,
in C. More or less,
it will work in Python
because people work behind to figure
out what a thing is and then operate
appropriately on it.
So again, technical background, but it
makes our lives easier as programmers.
>> So here's file I/O. file I/O has lots of
little things that make it complicated,
and so there are resources
online, but in a nutshell,
you call open on a file
name with a particular type.
So that's read, read and
write, write or append.
You read a certain number of
characters out and you print those,
you'll get Hello!
I mean, like this file had Hello!
In it, call to read,
and what you'll get back
is a string which has all
of the rest of the array,
or all of the rest of the file.
If you call read again,
you're at the end of the file,
and so you don't get
anything and so you'll close.
Again, this is .close rather than
close file, as it would be in C.
This is more or less because f is a
thing, and you'd like for f to close.
But basic file I/O is not
particularly complicated.
Again, if you'd like to open a file, if
you'd like to read a particular line,
you can get out of particular
line-- there's built-ins for that.
If you'd like to write a
thing, you can write this.
If you'd like to write out individual
bites, you can write those.
And if you'd like to iterate
over the lines of a file
individually, as we did in a piece from
a few weeks ago, you can do that to.
Again, most objects that you'd
like to be able to iterate over
support iterating over them.
In Pythons, a file is maybe a thing that
I'd like to iterate over line by line.
If it was a dictionary
of words and I was
trying to get those individual
words out, then, within this loop,
line it's going to be
each word in turn and this
is going to be executed for every line
in the file until the end of the file.
And again, if I printed out each
line, the lines come with new lines,
so I'm setting the end
back to a thing like this.
Then I'd get the contents of my file.
>> The second thing which operates in
some ways like lists, and in some ways
as something substantially
more powerful,
are dictionaries, which are really
cool to use but are basically hash
tables in disguise.
You create one using exactly
two characters, which is awesome
if you tried to implement the
hash table for your problem set,
you know much pain that can be.
But people have done
it, and done it so well,
that you don't have to
worry about it anymore.
>> Then you can insert individual things.
Hash tables-- or dictionaries
don't particularly
care what you're storing in them.
So if some entries are numbers,
and some entries are lists,
if some entries are other dictionaries,
and some entries are strings,
Python doesn't much care.
>> Again, if you go into it expecting
a string and what you get back
is an array, that's your problem.
And maybe it's fault of whoever
thought it was putting things
in the dictionary, maybe that was you.
If that was someone
else, hopefully they were
well behaved about what
was going in the dictionary
and didn't leave any pitfalls
for you to fall into.
>> But the standard functions will
give you back well-behaved things.
So they say this returns
back a dictionary of strings,
then everything you're going
to get out of is a string.
If you do some of this and it trips
you up, well, that might be on you.
Python certainly gives you enough
rope to hang yourself, if you'd like.
Now we can print out individual
elements of this and this returns
exactly what you'd expect.
Exactly what you'd expect, I guess,
is a phrase that I'm using a lot,
but that's more or
less how Python works.
If you ask for a thing which isn't
it, Python will throw out an error
and it will quit you out of
whatever program you were in.
It'll actually print out
more information than that,
it'll point you-- it'll
add a line, and so.
>> And, again, maybe we want
to iterate over dictionaries
and find all the things in it.
Here we are iterating over
two things at the same time.
And so we'll do it with a key, value,
but then print out all of these.
>> And if we wanted to cast--
if we actually ran this,
we would have some trouble because
on-- when we went in with David,
it couldn't add-- if we didn't
cast it to a string first,
we couldn't add that array
of strings onto a string.
But if we cast it to a
string, we get something
like this, which is maybe
what we'd like to read.
>> And this is speller.
We just read in things.
So we can read in
individual words as lines.
We chop off the last
thing, so colon minus 1
chomps off the last thing that we--
the last character of a string.
We'll say.
OK, each one of those gets
inserted into this dictionary,
mapping to a value of 1.
We don't particularly
care about that one,
but it's just there to say, oh well,
this thing I'll put in the dictionary.
Because later what we're
going to do is we're
going to say, well, if it's
in the dictionary at all.
>> Again, this check for
membership is up operating
using a completely different
algorithm than it will in a list,
but we call it the same way, which
is some of that Python sugar coating
things so that they're easier to use.
And again, we've seen
things like this before.
This is basically find, or
it's exactly the same syntax
as find, but is operating over a
completely different structure.
And we don't particularly care.
So those are the things that you
were asked to implement for speller.
At this rate, we're going to get
more or less all of the psets done.
>> AUDIENCE: So that
basically just comes back
as incorrectly spelled if it doesn't
match something in the dictionary?
ROSS RHEINGANS-YOO: Yes, yes.
And so, this is an
adaptation of a problem set
which asks you to do exactly that.
>> AUDIENCE: Why is the line minus 1 there?
ROSS RHEINGANS-YOO: So
when you're iterating
over a file asking for
by lines, the lines
come with a new line character
at the end of it-- the minus 1
is just to shop those off.
And this is a particularly flexible
way of indexing into things.
So if you have a string,
and you'd like, well I'm
going to start at character three
and I'm going to go to the end.
3 colon will do that for you.
If you're like, I want to start at the
beginning and go to the last minus 1
character, colon minus 1.
And if you wanted to go from
the third to the minus first,
then you'd say 3 minus 1.
>> Additionally, if you want to index
into things counting from the back,
you just index in with minus numbers.
And because, where C
would explode or maybe
feed you other memory you didn't have
access to, hear you can say minus 1
means the last but 1
character in a string.
>> Modules are version-- are
analogs to libraries in C
and are useful for a lot of things.
A lot of things you'd
like to do in Python,
besides simple
manipulation of variables,
you want to hook into the
larger libraries with larger
interfaces and more
capabilities for interacting
with other parts of the world.
sys is one of those
with a bunch of tools
that are useful for interacting
with the system itself
and will import it like import sys.
>> There's more documentation from
that, which you could go here,
or you could find on Google
by googling Python sys.
You type in enter.
The first link is going to be
the documentation in Python 2,
the second link is going to
be the documentation Python 3.
>> And if we wrote out a file that looked
like this-- If in particular, we're
looking at operating on
command line arguments,
like we learned to do very
early on in this class.
This isn't difficult.
You can get out argv,
which is one of those things
which is implemented by sys.
It's not built-in to the
base package, but again, you
can extend it by importing
that functionality from sys.
You'll call it sys.
whatever.
Here there's argv.
There's actually no
argc in sys, because you
can get it so easily by calling len.
We then printed that out, then we
ran on our terminal echo-args.py.
We get back an array, which
is this first argument.
Again, this is argv 0, which is the
name of the thing that got called.
If we called it with additional
arguments, we'd get those back.
This is one way of getting
command line arguments.
If you want flags where you turn
particular things on or override
a particular default,
argparse is your friend.
And again you find that online
at python argparse at Google.
>> There are a couple of utility
modules that you find yourself using
and again, if you spend any time
of this language importing jsons
for reading in and out of json
files, not that complicated.
You open up a file, you called json.load
on that file and you get back a thing.
What is that thing?
It's a json object.
Where that json has array,
the Python has arrays.
Where that json has
associative arrays, Python's
dictionaries, strings,
and numbers, and so on.
You want to dump that out, you
open up a new file, you call dump,
and loads and dumps to
go in and out of strings.
>> Similarly, pickle gets called
in basically the same interface.
It's slightly more useful if
you're dumping Python objects.
So if you've ever wanted to save
a version of the current status
of a variable for a future
run of your program,
pickle is Python's
library for doing that.
>> If you have any sort of
variable that can be written out
in like words and characters and
bytes-- like this dictionary,
we could write down, we
could write it down as
like a json object, which was
literally these characters.
And then it would be very easy for
a human to open it up-- open up
and read it.
If we didn't particularly
care about humans reading it,
we could package even more efficiently
into forms that could later be unpacked
or that could later be inflated.
And this saves 80% of the
space that your objects might
take if you wrote them out longhand.
>> You call pickle very much
the same way-- dump, load,
and then you get your things back.
So if you are writing very
short Python programs that
want to save state, and then read
them back later, things like this
are your friends.
That you could very
easily dump them as json.
Most Python objects
can dump out the json
if there's any hope that structurally
they could be represented that way.
>> These are just the tip of the
iceberg on modules that are useful.
So sys, os, multiprocessing, are
sort of basic workhorses for things
we need to interact with
the file system os.,
like os.isfile, os.isdirectory,
os.makefile, these are your friends.
If you want to interact
with a particular file type,
json, pickle, csv.
If you want to interact with web
pages, the urllib for getting http
pages. bs4-- BeautifulSoup--
it's a wonderful parser for html.
You run it on an html and you
get this nested array object now,
which you can traverse over
lookin, with like just looking for
if, is, in, which is fantastic.
>> There's a bunch of
packages for running--
for doing particularly mathy things.
So if you want to multiply,
invert, transform matrices,
numpy is used by people all
over the world for that.
scipy is even more useful
tools in that direction.
sklearn-- machine learning,
natural language processing,
super useful stuff, gets
implemented in Python all the time.
>> And again, takes slightly
longer to write-- sorry,
takes slightly longer to run, but
the reason that real engineers tend
use Python is because you tend to be
blocked on you writing the code, rather
than your computer running the code.
So if you're going to write a
program, which lots of other people
are going to use
forever, like Linux, you
might write it in C. If you were
going to write a computation engine,
you might write in Python if you needed
to change it every couple months.
Some people would write it in
C because they're like that.
>> So we've seen import sys
as a way of getting things
of getting module into your program.
You can also import it as
a nickname, if you'd like.
Again multiprocessing is a pain to
type out every time, so import as mp
and then anytime you
use it in the program,
you'll say mp.process, or what have you.
If you'd like import
only a single thing,
so urllib has a thing called
request, so you can just import that.
Later on, you won't invoke it as
urllib.request, but just as request
by itself.
>> And you can import everything
from a module if you'd like.
This is occasionally not a good idea--
this usually not a good idea, actually.
Because you very-- because if anything
in that module has a name that you
wanted to use somewhere else
in your program, you can't.
>> And it is not always obvious
that that's the case.
In order to make sure that
what you were doing was safe,
you need to open up
the module and see all
of the names that end up in
there-- all of the functions,
all of the variables
that live in that module,
because you're bringing all of
them into your local namespace.
>> So people do this.
It is generally recommended
that you don't do this.
But people do this all
the time because they're
lazy and don't want to type out mp.
anything, ever.
>> All this talk about modules
bring me around to a short talk
on how you design programs in Python.
The first step is to check to see if
anyone else has already done the thing,
or done 90% of the thing.
Chances are they probably have, and you
should go get their thing and run that.
Or write a wrapper around it
to adapt it to your purpose.
It's only after that has
failed that you'd then
go on and write-- begin thinking about
how you would put this thing together.
There's lots of stuff
out there, and that's
one of the most useful
things about Python.
Like the language is
elegant, the language
is easy to use, but also because
it's so elegant and easy to use,
people have been using it for a
long time and there's a lot of stuff
out there that you can
harness for your own use.
>> So last rule of Python is, somebody
else has already probably written
a module for that,
somebody else has already
probably written a library for that.
Before you try to do a thing, look
to see if it's been implemented.
It's not that hard.
All of the modules that I put up
before, with perhaps one exception,
come pre-installed in every
standard Python installation.
And so with a call to
import whatever, you
have all of that functionality
at your fingertips.
>> Beginning to wrap up this
talk, there are a few things
that I've left as black boxes
and sort of glossed over,
and there's a few white lies that I've
told that for the sake of honesty,
I'll at least point at
here, even if I won't
go super deep into all of them
and their technical explanations.
>> A lot of the things
that I've called magic
is what other people would call
object oriented programming.
So there are lots of things--
so variables are very often not
simple bytes sitting in,
memory, but are very complicated
objects that have internal
state about functions and lots
of hidden variables, lots of
hidden functionality, which
lets you turn them into strings,
which lets you iterate over them.
And if you're writing--
and the reason that they
have all of this rich functionality
is because the people--
the architects of the
language-- have gone
through and for every standard
object, put in the functionality
to say this is how this is
how this is going to operate
if someone wants to iterate over it.
>> So everything that somebody might
possibly want to iterate over,
has logic written in
manually on how you're
supposed to iterate over that object.
Everything that you might possibly want
dumped into a string has logic written.
This is the function that you call if
you want to dump this out to a string.
This is why you can
call len on things, this
is why you can call for in, this is
why you can call if in on everything
that you'd want to, because
those all are carrying with them,
the technical know-how to do that.
>> This is something that I'm
super not going to go into.
But for thing in list is subtly
different from C style for loops,
and you can read all about that on
the internet if you're interested.
There is a dark side to all
of this, that I mentioned,
so there's two things.
The first is that this object oriented
programming adds a lot of overhead
to random things, so you end
up using a lot more memory;
you end up using a little more
time than you would otherwise.
The other-- but the more
insidious dark side to this
is, if things just act
like you want them to
without you having to think super hard
about whether this should be an int
or whether there should be a
float, it might be that over here
you produce an int but over here you
think but they'll always-- sorry,
it might be that here
you produce a float,
but when you get to the second part
of your program, you're thinking,
oh well, but they'll
always pass me an int.
And if they don't, it's possible
that you wedged somewhere,
if you try to use that to index
into an array, or what have you.
>> So one of the real
useful things about C is
it forces you to think really
hard before you make any--
before you bring any variable
into existence, like what
is the type of this variable.
And it's going to have
that type for all time.
>> This is not true
Python, and in fact, you
can-- if you're just
sort of going by ear,
and you make some decisions
one way in one place,
and some decisions one
way in the other place
without putting enough stuff behind
the scenes in the other place
to catch things properly, you
can get some very strange errors.
And the program can keep running
for a very long time, because it's
doing a lot of work to say, well
this thing could operate this way,
so I'm going to run that way.
>> And in fact, the fact that it pushes
forward through a lot of small errors
means that, often when
an error is actually bad
and you do actually want to fix it,
it ends up miles away-- the program
ends up stopping miles away
from when you had your error.
And so one thing that we would like
programs to do, sometimes-- one thing
that we would like programs
to do when we're debugging
is fail loudly and fail very
quickly when something goes wrong.
>> Python is very bad at that.
Python is very good at not
failing and rolling forward
through unexpected things.
So this is useful for when
you're writing small programs.
When you get complicated
bugs it sometimes
takes a long time to tease them out.
>> So there's a dark side to all
of this, like it just works.
It just works like you'd expect it to.
Except that when it doesn't, you end
up in a completely different place
and trying to figure out where
it was that you went wrong.
>> Garbage collection is-- so
one thing that you will notice
is that any of these things that
I've brought into existence--
these arrays, these dictionaries, these
objects, these files-- never get freed.
There was no call to
free in any of this talk.
And that was on the C-side, because
we never got into those things.
>> But in Python-side, there isn't a free.
Things get automatically
freed when Python
thinks you're not looking at them.
It's really good not freeing things that
you might still possibly be looking at,
but this means that if you were
going to allocate this big thing,
and you're like, oh
I'm done with it now,
it's difficult to tell Python
that you're done with it now.
>> You can sometimes set
that variable to be none,
and then hope that eventually
the garbage collector
comes through and cleans it out.
But again, you don't
have control over that.
And one of the reasons that people use C
for really performance critical things,
is this ability to really
know when memory is allocated
and when it's freed, and have
a lot of control over saying,
I'm using no more memory than I need.
Which is something that
Python is not that great at.
AUDIENCE: Can I ask you a question?
What did you mean by fail loudly?
>> ROSS RHEINGANS-YOO: So if
something's going wrong
and you're in debugging
mode, you would very often
want your program to tell you
where exactly it's gone wrong,
and not just quietly stop running.
But you'd actually it to print
out all sorts of information about
like, here was this.
This thing happened If you're printing
a wen-- if you're running a web server--
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> ROSS RHEINGANS-YOO: Yeah, if
you're running a web server,
it's sometimes bad if you're
always discarding errors,
and you're saying,
well that didn't work.
I'm going to stop.
I'm just going to ignore
it and keep going on.
Because then you can get in hundreds
of these errors and not see them.
>> It would certainly be useful
for debugging purposes
if every time your web server made an
error, you had durable records of that.
Maybe you even want the program
to stop, so that those records
don't get buried under things.
But again, that's in debugging mode.
>> Often in production mode, the
world is a little different.
And in tiny scripts that I'm running,
where the thing that I said to do
might be only a little bit off
from what I would like it to do,
then sort of pushing through
errors is something you might want.
And in those cases, certainly
Python really earns its starts.
>> The last thing that I didn't talk
in this-- that I didn't talk about
but can be really infuriating the first
time you have one of these errors,
and the second and third and fourth
time you have one these errors.
Python, I mentioned
that it uses white space
to tell you what level of indentation
and what functional block you're in,
it treats tabs and spaces differently.
So if you tab over four, and then
the next line has four spaces,
even if they show up as the
same amount in your editor,
Python doesn't treat them the same.
>> In fact, Python treats tabs
and spaces like oil and water.
They are just different things.
There is no particular
length that a tab is,
so it's not like a tab equals 8
spaces, and so you would get around it
that way.
Like, when it says, what
level of white space I'm at,
it is actually looking for a
pattern of spaces and tabs.
And so, the best way to deal with this
is to always use spaces all the time.
>> And in fact, in the Cloud9
IDE and the CS50 IDE,
your Tab key inserts
four spaces in instead
of a tab, which is super useful.
Though again, if you wrote a Python
program with tabs that would be fine,
it's just if somebody
went in and tried to add
a single line to your program that
had four spaces for every tab,
it would break.
And it would break in a way
that really isn't visible.
Though the actual error
message that it throws
has to do with new
indent not expected here,
or-- if it's talking about indents
and it looks like it's wrong,
it's probably because
there's a tab-space problem.
They're still infuriating to debug.
The biggest whole in
this talk, which I didn't
get to because it's really
a complicated, subtle topic,
and wasn't necessary to do any
of the things we've done so far,
are a concept called tuples.
They are there much like the
arrays that you can't modify.
They get used all over the place because
they are useful for lots of things
that arrays are not useful for.
>> But if you'd like to make an array, and
then promise the interpreter that you
are never going to want to modify that
thing-- in fact, if you want to modify,
you'll make a new one with the new
values in it-- those are tuples.
Rather than producing
them with square brackets,
you produce them with round brackets.
Why you would use these things,
is a little bit of a question. .
The only thing that I'll
say about that is you
can use tuples as
indices for dictionaries.
You can't use arrays as
And why is, again, technical and
I'm not going to run into it.
>> The pset that I haven't touched
on in this talk is pset6.
So here's how you 'd
implement a-- here's
how you would implement pset6 in Python.
Keeping in mind the Python
design cycle, the first thing
that you do when you're
writing programs is check
to see if somebody's done it already.
>> In fact, if you want
to serve-- Apache 50
does approximately this,
except it doesn't come
standard installed on Linux machines.
Python does, and the Python
simple http server does as well.
If you're ever on a Linux machine,
or the Cloud9 IDE outside of CS50
and you'd like to serve this current
directory to a particular port,
python-m SimpleHTTPServer
port serves that.
You can also import
the simple http server
and it's got a lot of functionality if
you want to customize it, or change it,
or are run it-- harness it to
run your own server services.
>> So that's Python in a nutshell.
And this has been CS50.
Thank you.