>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
Thank you so much for coming.
This is CS50 seminar on Docker, a
technology that we ourselves and CS50
have started using for some time now.
So my name is David Malan, I
teach Harvard's Introduction
to Computer Science.
For quite some years,
we've been giving students
downloadable client-side
virtual machines
on which they do their problems sets.
That we have now transitioned
to a Cloud environment
that actually uses this technology
called Docker, such that all the CS50
students now have their
own Docker containers
that you'll soon hear all about.
>> Moreover, on CS50's server
side cluster, for many years
we were using Amazon's Cloud server.
We were running individual
virtual machines.
That too, we've begun to transition to
these things called Docker containers
so that all of our applications are now
perfectly isolated from one another.
So for that and more, allow me to
introduce our friends, Nico and Mano,
from Docker itself.
NICOLA KABAR: Thanks, David.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Nico and this is Mano.
We're from Docker.
We're going to be talking about--
giving you guys an intro to Docker,
and hopefully, towards the end
of this talk you can realize
how much you can use doctor to
oxalate your application development
and deployment.
>> So, we're going to start off real
quick with some background information.
Describe what Docker is all about.
How does it work?
How is it architected?
I'll be doing some demos.
And Mano is going to be
describing how can you use Docker
and giving you specific steps
how you can get started.
>> I would appreciate if you guys can hold
off for your questions towards the end.
That way, I might be addressing those
questions throughout the presentation.
So we'll leave some time
towards the end for questions.
>> So just real quick, who has
actually ever worked on Docker,
like played with it?
Awesome.
Cool.
Great.
So, I'm going to start
with some history.
So back in the '90s and
early 2000s, basically
as web developers, app developers,
when they went to deploy an application
it was tied to bare metal.
It was one server.
It was one application.
>> Traditionally, an example
would be like a LAMP stack,
where you actually had to
bring up the pool of resources.
CPU, memory, disk, network, installing
operating system on top of that.
If you're serving something, if
you're actually having web server,
you need something like
Apache to serve it.
>> If your application
needs database, backhand,
you would install something
like MySQL, and so on.
And if you need the run time, PHPs
and PHP Python work were there.
And so we actually had to
take those steps in order
to get your application up and running.
>> If you needed more compute power, you
basically had to call your Ops guy
or gal to go and rack up a new
piece of hardware, connect it,
and you have to repeat those
processes again and again.
So this process was
relatively expensive.
Was definitely very slow.
>> It was inefficient.
And in a lot of cases, your
hardware was underutilized.
So, in the late '90s and early 2000s,
hardware virtualization came across.
And as you can see here in the
picture, basically what they did
is abstracted the pool of
free hardware resources
and kind of served those
to the upper layers,
in this case, a guest operating system.
>> And the whole idea of
virtual machines came across
and that truly helped Cloud
computing as we know it today.
So what that meant is you
can run multiple VMs, which
meant multiple stacks, multiple
application on a same physical machine.
>> This definitely helped with the
speed of application deployment.
Definitely with expenses.
You don't have to go and spend
energy, time, and resources to rack
more servers to get to more compute.
And the speed of actually bringing
those resources up is much faster.
Great.
>> So we solved world hunger, right?
No, not really.
So, virtualization as much as it's
actually helped, address the problem,
it actually introduced
a lot of challenges.
The hypervisor definitely
introduced a lot of complexity,
handling those underlying
pool of resources.
>> It's heavier in the sense that before
you had a single operating system which
is like three, four gigs on disk.
Now, if you have 10 machines
on a single hardware
you have to multiply that
by the number of machines.
It's definitely more
expensive in a sense you still
have to get licensing for
the virtualization technology
if it's not open source.
>> But, let's not take all the
credit from virtualization.
Because what happened is there's a
lot of stacks and lots of software
technologies that were enabled
by how fast you were able to get
to resources with the Cloud boom.
>> So, today a single app or service can
be using any of the following runtimes
or databases.
PHP, Python, MySQL, Redis, whatnot.
So there's a lot of complexity on this
number of stacks to actually bring up
a single service.
And along with that, you had a lot of
underlying resources or infrastructure
types to test deploy and basically
take to production those applications
that you're developing.
>> Especially as your teams have
grown working on those apps,
there's a lot of
complexity and challenges
that were brought to ensure that
the cycle-- basically application
development cycle, is
actually successful.
So, the fact that your application
is working locally on your local VM
does not guarantee that your colleague
is going to expect the same results.
>> And when the operations team is
involved in taking what you have
and deploying it in production
scale, also there's no guarantee
that that's actually going to happen.
So this leaves us with a really
big-- a lot of question marks,
a lot of challenges actually
faced similarly back in the days.
And that reminded us of
the shipping industry.
>> So the shipping industry
had a lot of goods,
as you can see on the left hand side.
And on the right hand side,
there's a lot of, basically,
ways to ship those goods.
And what happens as a couple
folks came together and said,
we need to standardize how
we actually ship those goods.
And boom, you have the
intermodal shipping container.
>> So they agreed on the most
common sizes for the container.
How to handle them.
What exact method you need
to load them and unload them.
And therefore, that truly
helped the shipping industry.
Now more than 90% focus transported
globally are using those containers.
And that definitely decreases
the expenses as well as
the damages due to shipping.
>> So we take the same model and we
apply the two app development software
architecture, in the sense
that containerization
took the virtualization up one level.
So instead of doing that
at the hardware level,
it became more of an operating
system level virtualization.
>> And we do that by providing each
application in its own lightweight,
isolated, runnable, and
portable, most importantly,
a way to actually package
everything that it needs to run.
Anywhere it can be run.
So, regardless if you're running it on
local dev environment, your production
environment, your staging or testing.
No matter what underlying
infrastructure is there,
you had a functional working app.
>> So that's exactly what basically
containers do to this problem.
They address it by
packaging it in such way
that it can guarantee that it's deployed
successfully no matter where it lives.
So if you're going
like, Bob it's still OK.
If you're confused with what I'm saying,
I'm going to be elaborating on that.
>> So how does Docker itself
fit in this picture?
So Docker is an open platform
to easily, emphasize easily,
to build ship, run,
lightweight portable self
sufficient app containers anywhere.
So if you take something from this
talk, please take the following.
>> If you have your app running
locally and you developed it
in using the Docker platform, expect
it to be successfully deployed.
No matter what is the
underlying infrastructure.
So if you have a Docker
container and it's working, then
as long as there's a Docker
engine on the other side--
if your operation infrastructure
is using any Cloud, whether it
is AWS, or Google's, or Microsoft,
or any of the public Clouds,
or your own Cloud, or your open stack
Cloud, or your local environment.
>> If you have an engine
running, that means
it's going to be
successfully deployed there.
It's going to be running
exactly the same behavior
as you architected it to be.
So if we look at-- I'm going
to go through what actually
are in the main components of Docker.
>> So Engine is at the core of Docker.
It is the brain's.
It orchestrates building, shipping,
and deploying and managing
the containers themselves.
I'll dig into what Engine does
in more details in a second.
Basically, because Doctor was built
around the client server architectures,
so in order to interact with the
Engine you need some sort of a client.
>> Images are the templates in
which containers are built from.
So images are basically
just static files.
Templates and containers
is actually what's
is running at runtime that
is serving your application
or doing something with the data.
>> Registry is addressed as a problem of
how you actually distribute images.
So if you need to share an image
that you worked on to your colleague
or to the ops team, you
use it using Registry.
You can download an open source
version of it that Docker worked on
and open sourced.
>> Or you can use Docker help,
which is the Cloud version
to push and pull images out there.
That's a huge thing.
Because there's a huge
ecosystem around Docker and it's
really heavily utilizing the hub.
>> So to summarize here, this is how the
minimalist Docker workflow client.
You interact with the host, in
this case it's the Docker daemons.
It's the same thing as Engine.
You do commands like
Docker build, pull, run.
And the Engine itself goes
and does those things.
>> So either it interacts with
Registry to pull those images
and the layers of the images.
Whether if you want to deploy, run
containers, kill them, throw them down,
whatnot.
So this summarizes the workflow
of all of these components.
>> So if you take every
component by itself.
So Engine, it's just a daemon.
It'll kind of play it to support
it on Linux because it does
require certain Linux kernel features.
But Windows is working
on doing the same thing.
It's supposed to be supported
by Windows Server 2016.
>> So, again, the responsibilities with the
engine is to, or are to, build images.
Pull images from the Docker
Hub or your own Registry.
If you're done with those images
or you create a new images,
you can push those back to registry
to distribute them to other teams.
>> And trying to contain it locally
and manage the containers life cycle
locally.
It is built around HTTP REST API.
So technically you can
write your own client
as long as it uses HTTP, which is a very
standard mechanism to talk to Engine
and a lot of other services.
And you can see from
here that regardless
of what the infrastructure
is, as long as you can-- all
you need is an operating
system, Linux specifically.
>> And you can install Docker Engine
on top of that and have it running
and it orchestrates, basically,
all these app one, two,
and three are actual containers.
So that's Engine.
As I mentioned earlier because
you need to interact with Engine,
there's the client.
>> But actually when you install
Docker, it ships with it.
So it gets installed,
so it's a single binary.
And you can do local calls
to your Docker Engine.
Or remote calls to remote Engines.
It does use HTTP, as
I mentioned earlier.
There's a GUI client called
Kitematic from Docker.
And there are definitely
a lot of other folks
who are building a lot of
GUIs that basically implement
some HTTP calls to talk to Engine.
>> Just some sample commands.
If you do Docker version, it would
show you the client version as well as
the server version.
If you do Docker info it will
tell you all the information
about how many containers are running
or created, how many images you have,
and so on and so on.
>> Here I have, in the next to
last box, I have Doctor run.
So that's how I'm actually
creating container.
And I'm giving it to echo Hello World
and sleep for a second and whatnot.
And you can see the
result. So it's ongoing.
And similar to Linux ps, you can see
all the processes and, in this case,
all the running containers.
This one's referring back to
the container I just created.
>> So, this is really important because,
like, it can be a bit confusing.
So images are the read-only
collection of files, right?
They are what our container is based on.
But they're only read-only.
So you start off with a base image.
It tends to mimic OS-like, so
Ubuntu, CentOS, whatnot base image.
And then you start building on top of
that, certain layers, that will make up
your end image, the end result here.
>> And each of those layers
should have a parent image
that it references when it
actually wants to create.
They are immutable, in the sense
that because they're read-only,
you cannot actually
make changes to them.
You can use them to create a
container from an image, which
will call all the subsequent
required images underneath it.
>> You can make changes
to a different layer,
it's a rewrite layer I'll
talk about in a second.
But each of those layers
are never changed.
Basically images use something
called Union File System, UFS.
And there are different storage
backends that utilize this technology.
And what that means is that it
brings together distinct file systems
to make them look like one.
>> So you can actually, from
an application perspective,
you have a top of a view that shows
all the different file system needed
for that application to run.
But they're actually, on this,
they're actually in separate places
and being utilized by
other containers as well.
>> So as you can see in here that
if we start with daemon image
as a base image, and then
we go in and add [? emacs ?]
and then that's another layer.
And then add Apache.
That's another layer.
And then we spend the
container from that.
Each of those images,
each of those layers,
is distinct and can be
reused by other containers.
>> If you look at containers themselves,
they're somehow like VM-like,
but not treated the same time.
So, they do not have, technically, the
full operating system underneath them.
They use the single kernel
of the host operating system.
And they build on top of that.
They mimic in how they look.
They mimic their root file
system of the operating system.
But they actually are not replicating.
>> So, instead of having immutable layers,
the last layer, which is the container
itself, it's a read-write layer.
That also runs the processes
of your application.
And it depends on the underlying layers.
Every container is
created from an image.
And that image can be a single
layer or multilayer image.
>> And I want to note here
that Docker heavily uses,
or is based on Copy-On-Write mechanism.
So that, actually, if you are not
making changes to the container,
it's not going to take extra space.
So that's basically how you
summarize a Copy-On-Write.
It's going to definitely speed up
the boot time for the container.
Because if you're not making
changes to the container,
it's utilizing what's already there.
>> So, how it actually works.
Part of it's like, right now, it
utilizes at least two key kernel
features.
And that is basically what
created that level of isolation
for the containers themselves.
Those features are
namespaces and cgroups.
So namespaces are a way to
create isolated resources,
so that within the container itself,
only you can see certain resources.
Such as the networking interface
or the certain users or whatnot.
>> And those are only visible and only
accessible within the container.
Cgroup on the other side limits
how you use those resources.
CPU, memory, and disk.
When you can go in, I
mean those are actually
features that were developed by--
they're part of the Linux kernel.
So they were not reinvented
by or recreated by Docker.
Docker uses them.
>> What Doctor really did
here is actually it
orchestrated creating
namespaces for each container
and creating the cgroups so that it's
ridiculously easy to create containers
using those features.
Of course, as I described earlier, Union
File Systems and Copy-On-Write truly
help the speed and the disk
utilization of containers.
>> And once you get your
hands around Docker,
you're going to see how fast it is to
actually spin up containers and tear
them down.
So, if you might ask, how can
you actually build images?
We build images by a process of creating
containers and making changes, altering
them, and committing them
into becoming an image.
>> So it's a chicken and
egg reference here,
because all containers come
from images and images come
from committed containers,
for the most part.
There are three options
to create images.
I'm going to describe
the first and last.
You can either manually
go and run the container
and make those changes,
like you would do on any VM
or any operating system, such
as installing new binaries,
adding file systems, and whatnot.
>> And then you exit, as
you can see up there.
I am exiting my container.
And then I'm doing Docker commit.
And I'm committing that.
You can see that the number here
is just a UUID, or the first 12
bits of the UUID.
Or bytes of the UUID.
And then I'm calling it my image.
So now Docker takes care of
recording everything I did it
and creating the new
image based on that.
>> I'm not going to talk about tarball,
but there's a way you can get a single,
create a single, or make a single
layer image using tarballs.
What I'm going to talk about this
and what's mostly used today,
is Dockerfile.
Which is technically the first
step automated by Docker itself.
So Dockerfiles are things that you're
going to see in a lot of GitHub repos
today.
It's basically just a
text file describing
exactly how to build an image.
>> And for every line, it actually creates
the container, executes that line,
commits that container into a
new image, and you, basically,
use it for all subsequent operations
until you get to the last image.
Which is basically the
end goal here, the end.
And after you exec-- after you
write your Dockerfile, which
is purely in text, you do a Docker
build and the name of the image.
>> And you point at that that is
where the Dockerfile is at.
And you can expect to see my image
as an image that you have locally.
So that's just a visual
example of what goes on.
You start with a base image.
You run that into a container that
doesn't alter the base image itself.
But instead creates a
rewrite layer on top of it
where you make the changes,
in which you commit
and you repeat the process until
you get to your final image.
>> And by doing so, every other build
process can use the same layers
and the same-- basically
Docker caches those layers.
So that if I'm doing the same exact
process, but instead of installing PHP,
I'm installing Python.
It's going to use Apache and Ubuntu.
So that way you're utilizing your disk.
It's utilizing the cache
and available images there.
>> The final piece is Registry, which
is how you distribute your images.
And, as I mentioned earlier,
there's a Cloud version of it,
which is Docker Hub.
You can go and explore
a lot of, basically
it's a public SAS product that
you can still have private images,
but there's a lot of public images.
It's actually unlimited, you can
push unlimited public images there.
And this is how you can
collaborate with your team.
>> You can just point them at you repo
and they can download it or your image
and they can download it.
So enough with the talk.
Who wants to see some demos real quick?
All right.
So here I have.
Ca you guys see my screen?
All right.
>> So I have Docker running here, so I
can check it's-- This is the version
of Docker that's running.
Can do Docker info.
Check all the information about how many
images they have, and so on and so on.
Docker PS, there's nothing running.
Concatenated those.
>> So the first thing I want to do is show
you how you can easily run a container.
So the beauty about
Doctor run, if it actually
does not find an image locally,
by default it talks to Doctor Hub
and tries to find it there
and downloads it for you.
So it includes a Docker
pull command, naturally.
>> So if I do a Docker run, hello-world.
So, first it's going
to try to locate it.
Otherwise, as you can see here,
it could not find it locally.
Right now it just pulled two layers
that made that image and I ran it.
The hello-world is just basically
outputs, what you have done.
So this is the easiest,
one the easiest examples.
So actually I just ran and
terminated the container real quick.
>> If I want to run-- and by the way, if
I want to time that, just so you know,
this is how long it takes to
actually spin up and contain it.
We're measuring it in milliseconds.
So you can see how much this can
actually help you not only in testing,
but also even deployment.
So that's a quick note on that.
The next thing I'm
going to do is actually
run an image I've already prepared.
So docker run.
-d is just a flag to tell
it to run in the background.
And -p assigns certain ports.
Because by default, the
containers are isolated,
so you have to specify exactly
how it can access them.
And in this case, I'm telling Docker
to map a random port on the host
to a specified port within
the container itself.
And that's basically where the image--
hopefully this is the right one.
>> So it does parallel downloads each
of those layers as you can see here.
Those are of the layers making
the end image that I built.
It's going to take a second.
And voila.
>> So now if I do a docker ps, I should
see something that is running.
I should see the ID, the image
that this it was based off,
and the command that was executed.
And how to access it is
basically you go to that port.
So I'm going to go to-- this
is I'm running it on AWS.
I'm going to go to 32769.
Oops.
And here we go.
>> So this is actually just
a web service that shows
which container it's being served from.
So you can see that it
is from container a9f.
And here this is the
name of the container.
So you guys can see how quickly it
was to actually not only pull but also
deploy this container.
>> Now the next step is to
look into Dockerfiles
and how we can actually
build new images.
I'm just going to go get clone, a
sample Dockerfile based on the earlier
diagram, the one to Apache and PHP.
Hopefully I remember my repo.
>> So I have my repository right now.
And you're going to see
this a lot actually.
I did not install tree.
>> So basically you're going to see how
your source code documentation around
it, and then a Dockerfile on
how to actually package it.
So it's just a sample PHP
that echoes hello CS50.
>> So if I want to run it,
I'll do docker build.
I have to build it first.
I'm going to name it demo_cs50.
And you need a tag to it too.
So let's call it v1 dot.
So as I described earlier,
what I'm doing today
is I'm telling Docker to go use
that-- actually, sorry, my bad.
We did not take a look
at the Dockerfile itself.
So the only things in here are
index.php as well as the readme file
and a Dockerfile.
>> So if you take a look at
the Dockerfile, so it's
very similar to what
I described earlier.
It's just a bunch of
steps that Docker executes
by creating and tearing down containers
and [? counting ?] them into an image.
>> And basically you can
see-- [INAUDIBLE] it here--
but this is from the local repo.
It's going to go and grab index.php.
So that's the only source code that
are actually part of your application.
All this are basically
operating system plumbing,
getting the right packages and
Apache, and PHP, and whatnot.
But this is actually taking index.php
and committing it into the container,
into the image.
>> So if you go ahead and run the
command by doing the following,
it's going-- actually,
this might take a bit.
Hopefully it doesn't take too long.
So you can see the steps.
And I encourage you to go
back home today and try it.
And Mano will describe
how exactly you do that.
But it's really great to see exactly
what's happening behind the scenes.
But it's ridiculously easy to build
images and deploy them using Docker.
>> It's taking a bit
longer than I expected.
>> Let's see what happens when you-- cool.
So as you can see, each of those steps
represent lines in the Dockerfile.
And it shows here that it
successfully built this image.
>> So if I do docker images, I'm going to
see all the images that I have locally.
And one of them is called my
username, and the name of the image,
and the tag representing--
mainly it's a version tag.
>> So now if I want to run
it, I do docker run.
And I just want to do a -d -P. Do v1.
So I can see now that I have two
containers running, the one that I just
created and the hello
Docker one that I got last.
>> And you can see here that it
assigned it a different port.
So if I go to the same IP but assign it
a different port-- hopefully I did not.
So now this is application
that I just deployed.
>> If I want to make changes, I
can quickly edit the source code
and do the following.
Let's do hello Harvard.
So now what's going
to happen is that I'm
going to tag it with a
different version-- oh,
not this guy-- tag it
with a different version.
And you're going to
see-- do you guys expect
it to take the same amount of time
to build it a second time or not?
All right, and anyone knows why?
Speak up.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> NICOLA KABAR: It's basically we
only change one of the later steps.
And therefore it's going to use the
cache and use each of those layers.
And that's truly some of the
killer features of Docker
is how it actually utilizes
and reuses taking over
your disk for the same
exact pieces of information.
>> So if we do the same thing,
it took just a couple seconds.
If we want to redeploy-- so now
I should have three containers.
But this one is being
served on the-- seven one.
So now it's the third container.
Everyone understand
what I just did here?
>> So now if you want to share this
container real quick with your friends,
you can just do docker push the
name of the container, hopefully.
So now it's going to push it
to-- I'm not signed in here.
Sorry about that.
But I'm not going troubleshoot this now.
But basically that one command
is just going up push it.
And you're going to be able to
see it if you go to Docker Hub
And you log in, you're
going to be able to see it.
And then you can just
point whoever is going
to use that image to go and pull it.
And they can use it.
>> With that, hopefully
I kind of demonstrated
how easy it is to work with Docker.
And I'm just going to
give it back to Mano.
And he's going take it from here.
>> MANO MARKS: All right
thanks, thanks Nico.
So what?
So one of the things I
wanted to do is put together
why this is an important--
why Docker and why
containers are such an
important new development,
a new way of actually doing software.
>> And before I do, I'm going to
just introduce a few stats.
I'm not going to read all of these.
But this shows you a lot about how
popular this is in the community.
The core Docker technologies
are open source.
So that's Docker Engine, Compose,
Swarm, a bunch of other stuff
is all open source.
And we have, what did I
say, 1,300 contributors.
You're seeing now, if you look at the
number of job openings, the last time
we looked, it was about 43,000 job
openings specifically mentioning
familiarity with Docker.
Hundreds of millions of images have
been downloaded from Docker Hub.
And, well, much more large stats.
>> For those who are curious, it
was originally written in Python
and then rewritten into Go.
And it's only been
open source-- it's only
been released for about 2 and 1/2 years,
which means that in 2 and 1/2 years,
we've seen a tremendous amount
of growth and importance
of this in the community.
And so I want to talk
a little bit about why.
>> So just to reiterate some of
Nico's key points, Docker is fast.
It is portable.
It is reproducible.
And it sets up a standard environment.
>> And what-- this is my crappy
stamp out monoliths slide-- what
it's helping people do, which
a lot of the software industry
started doing in the
early 2000s, is moving
from these monolithic
single applications
where every dependency had to be
tested before the entire app had
to be deployed, which
could mean a website
only got deployed once
every three months, or more,
to a much more service
oriented architecture
or componentized different type
of application architecture.
And so allowing these
kind of architectures
that take advantage of
Docker to run in these three
principal areas of development, which
is development writing your actual code,
testing your code, and deploying it.
>> So why is this important?
If you're a-- let me give an example.
If you are a website
device developer, you're
developing a website that's based on the
database that David produced over here.
Sorry David, I'm calling you out.
If you wanted to deploy
the whole thing, you'd
have to wait under a traditional
monolithic software development
environment, you'd have to wait
until he was done with the database
before you could actually make
any changes to your website.
You'd have to redeploy the
entire application to do so.
>> And what Docker helps you do is each
person work on different components
and update them as they go, just making
sure that the interfaces stay the same.
So what it has done
is it's shifted people
from doing these massive monolithic
architected software that
deployed every month to a continuous
integration and continuous development
environment.
>> Now this isn't unique to Docker,
but Docker makes it so much easier,
which means you're basically
constantly deploying.
We talk to enterprises that are
deploying public facing applications
thousands of times a day because
they see the value in just making
small changes, and as long
as it runs through the tests,
letting it go out into production.
Nico was always telling me
earlier that in many environments,
the standard life cycle of a
container is measured in seconds,
whereas a virtual machine
might be measured in months.
>> I wanted to take a slight
turn here because I'm
at an educational institution.
I wanted to give an example of how
this works in an educational research
situation.
So there's an organization
called bioboxes.
Bioboxes does DNA
analysis for researchers.
>> Now what they found was that when
a researcher-- and this is not
the fault of any particular
researcher-- but when
a researcher deployed
an algorithm to analyze,
In a particular way, a DNA sample,
they would write the software,
publish that, maybe to
GitHub or somewhere else,
and then they were done.
>> Well the problem was that it
wasn't necessarily reproducible.
Because in order to
understand the software,
they would be set up for the
exact development environment
that that researcher used, usually
their laptop, or a server, or a data
center that they were using.
And consequently, it was very difficult
to reproduce research results when
analyzing DNA samples to look
at things like incidence--
compare incidence of heart attacks
based on certain genes being present,
for instance, or cancer risk, or
any of the other kinds of things.
>> So what they did instead was
they started creating containers.
And you can go to bioboxes.org,
it's a great organization.
And what they do is they produce
containers based on research.
And then whenever somebody sends
in their sample, they can run it.
And it has all the environment
needed to run that algorithm
and produce the results.
And they're finding that they're
much more likely and much
more quickly able to
return results to people.
>> And in fact, what people are doing
are running their own analysis on DNA,
sending that in to bioboxes, and
then biobox just takes the data,
runs it against the variety
of different containers
to see different results
based on different research.
So it's a very powerful
way in which researchers
can make a single instance that allows
other people to try and reproduce
the results.
>> So how do you get started?
We are well supported on Linux.
So if you want to install
anything on Linux,
you use your standard
package manager to install.
If you're using a Debian, it's apt get.
CentOS is yum.
Fedora Red Hat is
rpm-- I don't remember.
Anyway, it's all there.
We support a large variety
of Linux distributions.
You can check those out.
>> We also have options so you
could run on Mac or Windows.
Now Nico mentioned earlier that
it was only supported on Linux.
That's true because it
needs a Linux kernel.
But, you can run in a virtual machine.
And what the Docker Toolbox
does, which you can download,
it gives you that virtual machine.
>> So just a quick 48
second, I think, download.
You just search on Docker
Toolbox, download it to the Mac,
and this part is of
course sped up because who
wants to watch a download signal?
Standard Mac installation,
and then you're
going to see Jerome put in his password.
That's very exciting.
And then it installs a
whole bunch of tools.
And particularly it will
install a command line.
And then you could see
Jerome testing his images.
>> And then based on this,
you can see that YouTube
thinks that Nico is interested in
Star Wars, The Jimmy Kimmel show,
and I think Ellen.
I think that last one is
a clip from an Ellen show.
>> So Docker Toolbox though comes
with more than just Docker Machine.
So Docker Machine is
the thing that helps
you set up a virtual
machine on your Windows
or Mac-- your Windows box or your Mac
box-- and helps you do provisioning,
>> But it also comes with
Swarm and Compose,
which are designed to help you do large
scale deployments of your application.
So if you want to manage
clusters of nodes,
clusters of containers, Compose and
Swarm are the way to go about that.
>> And of course it comes with
Docker Engine and Kitematic,
which is this desktop GUI.
I should also mention Docker Registry,
which is not included in Toolbox,
but it is a way for you to run your own
registries of Docker Images like Docker
Hub, but you can also just use
Docker Hub as a way to do that.
>> And, plot twist, you're seeing
it running in a container.
And that's how we're
distributing our slides.
This whole presentation is
actually an HTML slide deck.
And it is running in a
container, which you can get by--
>> NICOLA KABAR: Yes, so it's
running full time on my Max.
And I'm presenting from it.
And you just do Docker after
you install your Toolbox.
You can just do a docker run
and get it, and use the slides.
>> MANO MARKS: And that's it.
So we thank you all for coming.
And we're happy to answer questions.
I should mention before anybody
leaves there is T-shirts over there.
Sorry anybody who is watching
this on Livestream or video,
but we have Docker T-shirts over there.
And we know Docker students,
and in my experience,
professors too, like free clothing.
>> So thank you all for coming out.
And follow us on Twitter
if you want, or don't.
I don't care.
Also follow Docker on Twitter.
That's also interesting.
And then that's it.
Docker.com.
Thank you.
>> [APPLAUSE]