CONNOR HARRIS: Hi.
I'm Connor Harris.
I'm a CS50 CA at Harvard.
STEPHEN KREWSON: I'm Stephen Krewson.
I'm a TF for CS50 at Yale.
CONNOR HARRIS: And we're going to talk
about some technologies that you might
want to use if you're interested
in doing a final project or really
anything with music.
We're going to be focusing on first a
programming language called Haskell.
It's a functional
language, so the paradigm
is very different from C or PHP
or other imperative languages
that you've used already, and especially
on a library written in Haskell
called Euterpea, which can help people
with writing music functionally,
basically.
And Stephen will walk you
through a great example of that.
>> After this, I'll introduce you to
something called LillyPond, which
is a technology for typesetting music.
It's sort of like LaTeX
for music if any of you
have used LaTeX for math classes or
other P set classes or what have you.
And so I'll give you, again,
some simple examples of that
and point you in the general
direction of some better resources.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: In
addition, we thought it
would be cool to set up
a little bit of hints
toward a pipeline between
Euterpea-generated MIDI files
in LillyPond, so we provide
some instruction on scripts
to do that that are
provided with LillyPond
just to keep it open source
and get a pipeline going.
CONNOR HARRIS: Again,
we should emphasize,
these two technologies, you
don't have to use them together.
They're not designed to work
together, though they do very nicely.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: Right.
And totally free.
CONNOR HARRIS: So
acknowledgements, just read that.
STEPHEN KREWSON: Duly noted.
Thanks to those folks.
This I'll linger on just for a moment.
The installation process
is a little bit tricky.
We have a read me on the GitHub
that you can take a look at.
Just email me if you have any questions.
But we'll run this under the assumption
that this is working for everybody.
CONNOR HARRIS: And if you can't
get LillyPond to work, no big deal.
There's no live compilation that
will be involved, at least on my end.
STEPHEN KREWSON: Haskell and
LillyPond should both have installers.
Euterpea is downloaded as a
package, so on and so forth.
So we're talking about computer music.
And this is just a
very 50,000-foot view.
There's a few different aspects of it.
And this is rough and is
going to obscure some detail.
But we could think of something
like algorithmic composition,
using algorithms,
using code, to generate
some type of-- maybe a self-similar
sequence of notes, or maybe notes
under some constraint.
And then those could be
performed or interpreted
with analog instruments
or anything like that.
But the composition was
done algorithmically.
>> But of course, maybe the area of
computer music or digital music
we're more familiar with is digital
sound synthesis or digital sampling
and digital recording.
A lot of digital instruments are
done through digital sampling.
In fact, we'll be using one of those in
the form of a sound font library later.
>> But there's also something called
digital synthesis that came out
of the late '70s and into the '80s with
Yamaha and John Chowning at Stanford
doing FM synthesis or
Frequency Modulation synthesis,
where you had a carrier
signal and a modulating signal
both in the audio spectrum.
But what we're focused on
today is something called MIDI,
and of course, algorithmic composition.
>> We're not going to make instruments, but
we're instead going to make some music,
and then that will get interpreted
by some instruments that
are conformant to the
general MIDI standard.
So what's MIDI?
I'm not going to get too deep into it,
but MIDI is data transfer protocol.
It's a kind of a guide across
different companies and industries
for organizing sounds or patches.
So we'll see that
there's a MIDI standard
for all the different percussion
sounds and MIDI recommendations
for all the different types of synth or
different types of all the instrument
groups in an orchestra, say.
>> You're probably familiar with
0 through 127 MIDI messages.
A MIDI signal is typically
one bit indicating
whether it's a data or a
status packet, and then there's
seven bits of a signal.
And these can control
everything from volume
to the action or pressure
on a particular key
if you're performing with a MIDI
controller as well as, of course,
notes.
And of course, MIDI has
been extremely useful,
because it's a way to wire
together or daisy chain
a bunch of MIDI hardware devices.
I have seven or eight back at my house.
It gets really complicated,
but it's really powerful.
And it's really old.
It's from the early '80s, and
it's really nice and small.
CONNOR HARRIS: Yeah.
All the classic Nintendo
video games would probably
have MIDI files for music, for example.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: Here's an
example of general MIDI,
showing MIDI as a kind
of general protocol.
And I think we can think of the
difference between the specification
that there should be something like
these instrument sounds and the actual
realization of those instruments sounds
in a sound font or a particular MIDI
synthesizer as being the difference
between maybe a typeface-- which says,
in general, this is the design of
this particular way to represent
characters-- and a particular font
that has a specific size and timbre,
and there's realization of the--
>> CONNOR HARRIS: Maybe a
better comparison would
be the Unicode standard says-- it gives
a number to every character, and really
every language in the world, or
a vast set of scripts of language
in the world, and then those are
rendered into something graphical
by various font packages.
And obviously, you can think of
MIDI as the Unicode of sound.
And it's just a list of-- a big stream
of events and instruments and whatnot,
and you have to have a separate
program, like a typeface,
to render that into
something that's audible.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: So why Haskell?
Haskell is a functional programming
language, very advanced,
very different from C,
very different from PHP.
And we're going to see that there's an
ease of function composition in Haskell
that will allow us to breeze through
composing or typing up, transcribing,
something like Frere Jacques,
this simple song that
has a lot of parts in it that
are self-similar or repeating.
So this will be some of
the motivation for why
we're using Haskell, in which
functions are first class citizens.
>> And I wanted to extend
this a little bit.
It's a little bit easy to
notate Frere Jacques in Haskell.
But what if we wanted to
add a drum part to it?
What if we wanted to try to make
something like a Roland 808 or 909 drum
machine where you have
about 16 different steps?
Usually these are
thought of as 16th notes.
And you can control the global
tempo, and you can pick out
a bunch of different percussion parts
of bass drum, a clap, different snares,
open and closed high hats
on these sort of channels,
and then you can EQ or
adjust their volume.
>> And we'll see a nice way in
Haskell of representing this step
sequencer with all the
various cool things in Haskell
we can do with generating
lists and filtering over lists,
mapping over lists, mapping
functions over lists.
And a quick apology.
This is a very cursory
and overly quick sketch
of some of the aspects
of Haskell and Euterpea,
which is a domain-specific
embedded language written
in Haskell for musical types.
So please do check out the code online.
Fire up GHCI, which is the Glasgow
Haskell Compiler Interpreter.
And I'll be doing some
of this in a little bit
so you can see how it's done.
>> And this allows you to load in with
the-- the syntax is colon and then
the command.
You can load in files.
You can use browse on those files
to see all the functions that
exist in a particular module.
And then as we'll see, types and type
classes are so important in Haskell,
so you can always check-- especially
if you're working in a new DSCL
like this, what is a music type?
I know about the way numeric
types work in Haskell,
but I don't know much about music.
But you can explore the way they're
defined by using this t or type command
and then calling in a particular
function or a data object.
CONNOR HARRIS: Yeah.
If you thought C and Clang
was hardass about types,
you have no idea about Haskell.
The good thing about Haskell is that
if you can get your code to compile
and if Haskell type checks,
it's probably right,
because the type system is so strict.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: Yeah.
So I just want to go
through-- and again,
this is not doing it justice-- a few of
the features of Haskell that, at least
to its creators-- and it was created
in the late 1980s by a bunch of people,
a committee of about 20
people-- thought were important.
And the first thing they
listed in a paper that
described the genesis of Haskell
over the first 20 years or so
was that it was lazy.
So what does this mean?
>> Well, it means when we have some kind
of expression, we need to evaluate it.
And Haskell does this in a call
by need way or a non-strict way.
That is, if we have a bunch of
components of our expression,
we try to delay the evaluation
of those subcomponents
until the absolute last minute--
that is until we actually need them.
>> So this means-- which is
really cool, especially
if we're thinking about the abstraction
of a musical step sequencer.
You turn it on, and you start
running a step sequence--
if you ever worked with a drum
machine-- and it just goes forever.
So it would be really nice if we
could emulate that in Haskell.
And we can do it with infinite
values, in particular infinite lists.
It's very easy to type an
infinite list in Haskell.
You could just use the syntax down
here, where you see 1 through 3,
remove the 3 1 dot dot, and
that is an infinite list
of all the natural numbers extending
on as far as you can imagine.
>> I want to introduce a
concept of folds right away.
And again, the purpose
of this seminar is not
to learn about folds in Haskell
or higher order functions.
But I just want to introduce it to
give an accurate sense of how weird
Haskell is and how powerful it is.
And in particular, we're going to be--
when we do our different drum parts,
we're going to be manipulating lists of
numbers, folding them onto each other.
And to do that, we'll
be using maps and folds.
>> There's a right associative
fold, which is this one right
here-- 1 minus the quantity, 2
minus the quantity, 3 minus 0.
And the syntax for a
fold, you give a fold
a base value and then an operation--
in this case, addition or subtraction.
I've shown both cases.
And then there's an accumulator that
accumulates over the entire list,
applying that operator plus or
minus, and then accumulating it.
So this will be the-- if it was called
with fold r plus of 0, starting with 0,
we would then sum all
the numbers in that list.
And that's a list from 1 to 3.
CONNOR HARRIS: So to put it another
way, fold r takes three arguments.
There's a function that
itself takes two arguments,
then there's a starter value,
and there's a list of values.
And what you do is you take
starter value, first value,
put them into the function.
What do you get out,
take that, feed that
into the function of the
second value, what you get out,
take that, feed that into the
function of the third value.
And then if you go down
this whole list this way,
you're going to get eventually
some singular value that's
of the same type of what you started
out with and of the same type
as things in the list, and then
that's the return result of fold R.
STEPHEN KREWSON: So in particular,
these are higher order functions,
because they're taking another
function as one of the arguments.
>> CONNOR HARRIS: Yeah.
If you've used certain other
languages-- I know R, [INAUDIBLE]
language has this, called Reduce.
You might have similar functions
in other languages, just called
different things.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: And
what's nice about fold R
in this instance is that fold
R can work with infinite lists.
So in this bottom, this P5
is generating the notes that
are turned on in the step sequencer for
some drum part, the fifth drum part,
and maybe it's a conga
drum or something.
And this is a deliberately
obtuse way of writing this,
but it's fun, because
it demonstrates a lot
of things about Haskell and Euterpea.
>> So fold R of this colon-- colon is
just an operator that pushes things
together on a list-- called on an empty
list, which is just the empty brackets.
And I'm calling that
on this infinite list.
This is actually two lists
added together down here.
The list 1 comma 6 dot
dot is 1, 6, 11, 16.
So Haskell-- in just
a few characters, you
can generate the entire
sequence of numbers
that are five numbers apart
stretching on into infinity.
And I prepend to that
this shorter little list--
3, 8, 21-- just to show you
how you can concatenate lists.
>> And then I've folded on itself.
And this ends up just being a kind of
identity operation, but it's infinite.
And fold R can do that, because it
lazily evaluates, as in the above.
If we have a 1 and a 2 and 3, we can
just bracket off the entire rest of it.
That won't work for
minus or plus, but it
will work for this colon
identity operation on the list.
>> So how do we practically use that if we
have an infinitely long list of things?
Well, Haskell provides
a lot of functions--
and look more into these in
your own time-- such as take
which says, OK, we're
generating this infinite list,
but we're just going to take some
number of it And in this case--
we'll see this later in
our drum machine code--
GM is just some kind of global
variable for the number of steps
in the sequencer.
On the roll-in machines I
showed you, that's typically 16,
but I have implemented it with 32.
It doesn't really matter.
>> Haskell is also pure, so it has strong
static typing that Connor alluded to.
So functions are
mathematical in the sense--
they're more mathematical
that they're guaranteed
to not access or change any kind of
variable or perform input or output.
So if you have a function,
it's deterministic.
It will always return the same
value in the state of the program
or remain the same.
There are, of course, monadic exceptions
to this, but that's beyond our scope.
>> CONNOR HARRIS: Yeah.
What this means, though, is there
are a few important [INAUDIBLE]
consequences of this.
One is that it's very easy to
parallelize Haskell programs.
Because if you have,
say, a function of that
needs to operate on a million values, if
you know that the function will always
give out the same value if
you feed at a certain value--
if you're [INAUDIBLE] f of 1, f of
2, then f of 3 or whatnot-- f of 1
is not going to write out
to a file or do something
that will alter the value of f2.
You can just split up this function to a
million different machines or a million
different threads or whatever,
get all the responses back,
get all the return values
back, and then that's it.
So very easy to parallelize things.
>> The downside is that input
and output especially
fit into the type system
in very complicated ways.
We won't go into that right now, but I
encourage you to look at some resources
online if you want to learn about that.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: So
type classes-- and this
was-- classes of types
were invented to solve
a problem of operator overloading.
So we wanted to have equality
between different types of things.
Of course, we could think of--
equality between numeric types
is very easy to think about, but
what about equality between lists?
What about equality between
tree leg data structures?
And this is all possible in
Haskell because of type classes.
>> So if you define a certain data type--
and here, these are musical pitches.
We're finally getting
to some computer music.
So we have C, C sharp,
and so on and so forth.
They belong to a bunch of
different type classes.
EQ-- they belong to the EQ type class.
That means they support
equality operations.
So you can evaluate whether one
sequence of musical primitives
is the same as a different one.
>> They belong to the ordinal class.
That means there's an ordering to these.
D comes after C. C sharp
comes after C as well.
They belong to the class
show, which means they can
be printed to a console or terminal.
They belong to the
class enumerated, which
means that even though
these are characters,
they have an underlying numeric
representation starting at 0
and going off through however
many things are here, 20 or so,
or 30 or 40, maybe.
>> CONNOR HARRIS: And when
we have a data type
that derives-- with that keyword
"deriving--" a certain type class,
it means that the compiler will try
to construct something automatically.
So maybe you'll want to
define a quality differently.
You'll want to define C sharp
as equal to D flat, for example.
With this construction
here, I don't think C sharp
and D flat will be equal, because
the compiler will automatically
say every different possible value
is distinct from every other.
>> So it is possible to override
the default implementations
of these types of classes.
Again, look at the reference if
you want to learn about that.
STEPHEN KREWSON: And
here, actually, this'll
be helpful for when we code later.
We see some of the infix operators
for sequential composition,
parallel composition, and so
forth, these pluses and equal signs
surrounded by colons.
That means we can play these different
musical primitives one after the other.
That's sequential composition.
>> Or we can play them in
parallel at the same time.
So I can have a musical value,
and then this equals and colons,
infix parallel composition operator,
and play them as a kind of chord.
And we're going to use
this when we combine
our drum part with our
little Frere Jacques song
to play these two sequences of
musical values at the same time.
>> Currying is-- Curry was last
name of Haskell Curry, who
the Haskell image is named after.
And this allows us a
nice elegance when we're
writing all these different
functions or filters that we're
going to be mapping over our lists.
A function of two
arguments-- f of x and y--
can be represented as
f of x applied to y.
So it's a function of
one argument that returns
another function of one argument.
So this means we can map a
function f of x over list of y's.
CONNOR HARRIS: Want to
give an example of this?
STEPHEN KREWSON: Yeah.
I have an example right here from
some of the things we will write.
So replicate 2-- well,
replicate will take
one value, which is how many
times to replicate something,
and then it will take a value--
usually a list or something.
So here, we're mapping
replicate 2 over another list.
>> So if we map replicate 2,
if we replicate 2 apply
to the first element of this list-- and
these are lists of musical phrases--
will produce two of "you sleeping--"
so are you sleeping, are you sleeping.
So now we have two.
But replicate takes two
arguments, but because we're
currying and then mapping,
we can represent replicate 2
as having been returned as a function of
one argument-- just replicating twice.
And then we're applying that to each
element of this list of phrases.
>> And concat is a Haskell
operation for flattening a list.
Because replicate 2 will
produce a list of lists.
And this is this intermediate form here.
And so then we can concat
or flatten that out twice.
CONNOR HARRIS: A simpler
example of currying,
if you'd like-- imagine f is just a
multiplication function that takes two
arguments and returns their product.
So if you have an f 4 5, it's 20.
But you can think of this as
also-- you have a function f 4
that takes an argument and returns
four times this argument-- just
partial application which
just one argument 4.
And if you feed f of 4
5, that will give you 20.
And that's a simpler
example of currying.
It's usually one of the textbook ones.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: Lambda
expressions or anonymous functions
are another Haskell hallmark.
So if we need to whip up a
little function life replicate,
but say it's not in
the standard library,
we can use a syntax
similar to the following.
And we'll breeze over this.
One thing you'll see a lot of in the
drum machine is we're making calls
to something called
filter, which like before,
is a mapping of a function
over a list, but it's
a mapping of a Boolean function.
>> So we have here an example
of a an anonymously
defined Boolean function that
just takes a couple values.
This is not strictly speaking
an anonymous function.
But it's define with
that syntax for brevity,
and this just takes x module n--
CONNOR HARRIS: Yeah.
So f is a function of
two arguments n and p
that returns a function that is itself
a function of one argument, namely x.
STEPHEN KREWSON: I
mentioned infix operators.
What are infix operators?
Well, infix operators are the
normal way we represent operations,
say, in mathematics-- 2 plus
2 instead of the operator plus
and then two arguments 2 and 2.
CONNOR HARRIS: It's called
reverse polish notation, which is
a term I doubt any of you would know.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: Right.
Reverse polish or prefix notation.
But Haskell decided to
use infix operators.
So these are some of
the custom ones that
are defined for the
Euterpea DSCL in Haskell.
So this was sequential composition.
This was parallel composition, and this
was truncating parallel composition.
And we'll need that
with our drum machine,
because we'll use the last
operator in that little tuple there
to play the drum machine along
with our Frere Jacques song.
And our drum machine is
going to be infinite.
It just plays forever.
But the Frere Jacques song is not.
It's not that long.
It's only a few bars.
So we need to stop the drum machine as
soon as the shorter musical value comes
to an end.
And that infixed operator
is super helpful with that.
>> And infix notation like
this is kind of nice,
because say you have a function like
quote, which gives the integer division
of x by something else--
sorry, that should be a and b.
You could write it as a quote of b.
So if you put-- element is
another example of this.
x element in some list, if you put
it in Backticks, you can use it.
Even though it's not a symbol
like plus or minus or times,
you can use the name of a
function like that in Backticks
as infix operator, which is pretty cool.
CONNOR HARRIS: Again, this is
all just syntactic sugar, really.
It doesn't affect the core of language.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: So we see here for the
last phrase of our Frere Jacques song,
I played some little chords or
thirds using the parallel composition
operator.
This is another way of saying some
of what we've just been saying.
So you can map functions
of one argument over lists.
CONNOR HARRIS: Again, references
for Haskell-- introductory textbooks
will have all of this in it.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: So here's a pretty
key line of the step sequencer
we'll take a look at using
a list comprehension.
And we see here is that element
in fixed operator in back quotes.
So if x is an element of the list of
x's, then we'll call up perc functions.
So perc is just a percussion function.
It takes some value p that's
part of the bounded set of all
the different percussion sounds
that we saw in a previous slide,
and then it gives that
duration of a quarter note.
Else it gives it a QNR, and QNR
is just a quarter note rest.
>> So this is building up something nice.
We have a list of elements, and
we'll loop over some list from one
to the max value of our step sequencer.
And when we're at a particular i in
that list of one to the max value,
if that i is a member of this
set created in this function,
well, then we turn it
into a percussion note.
Otherwise, we just play a rest, which
is to say, we just remain silent.
And we can see here that in
this list comprehension syntax,
x is populated by this
list constructed one
to the global size of the sequencer.
CONNOR HARRIS: Yeah.
The basic syntax for
list comprehensions is
bracket, value involving
some variables, bar,
possible values of the variables
themselves, closed bracket.
And if you've done set builder notation
in any sort of mathematics class,
you might have set 2n such
that n is in or n is in z.
Similar thing-- this notation
is meant to be suggestive
of that mathematical notation.
STEPHEN KREWSON: And you can
apply multiple predicates
and multiple filters in a list
comprehension, which is quite nice.
Algebraic types-- we
won't linger long here.
There's not a good notion in
Haskell or a good, obvious notion
of how to take, say, a default
parameter to a function or something.
In Python, this is quite easy.
You can just say with equals on
the declaration of the function,
a default value in
case none is supplied.
>> In Haskell, you could maybe
use maybe the maybe type,
which takes either nothing
or a value of type just a.
So we exploit this in the drum machine
to allow us to give optional volume
parameters to each of the drum parts.
So that gives us a way of having EQ
or a volume on a particular channel.
>> CONNOR HARRIS: In
other Haskell examples,
you might see maybe used for
functions that might fail.
This is a common one.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: And you can supply
some sort of error message as a default.
And that's particularly handy when
you're doing the I/O in Haskell.
That can be tricks.
CONNOR HARRIS: Or for a
similar example, think
of a function that involves division
of a parameter that might be 0.
And that function could
return maybe whatever.
So if there's no division by 0,
it will return just whatever.
And if there is division by
0, it will return nothing
as a way of signaling the error.
Because one consequence of
Haskell's very strict typing
is that there's no real--
exceptions are awkward, basically,
error handling is awkward.
And this is one very
common way of doing it.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: So now we get
to another mind-bending thing
about Haskell, which is pattern
matching and function definitions.
I showed you in the last slide the
declaration of the step sequence
function, which took a maybe value,
then an int, then a list of ints,
then returns a sequence of
music values there annotated
with both pitch and volume.
>> So those three arguments can be
pattern matched in the following way.
And we always want to be sure to
do a base case or exit case first.
And these underscores
can just be interpreted
to mean any value that's there.
So if we get a call to step sequence
with some value, some other value,
and then the empty list, what we want
to return is just silence, a rest 0.
>> And instead of that
being an empty list or 0,
it's a rest 0, because we're
dealing with the music type,
and the empty list of the music
type is just a rest of no duration.
It's no music.
And then we see if we get a step
sequence with a v for volume argument,
p for precaution instrument
argument, and then a list of x's.
>> Then we do some stuff.
In particular, we apply
this list comprehension,
and we perform some
operations on the maybe value
to turn it into a numeric value so that
it could be then enumerated and used
to select the instrument.
Again, this is a little
bit deliberately inconcise
just to show all the weird things
you can do in Haskell as you
take a look at it on your own time.
>> All right.
So we're finally getting to
do what we set out to do,
which is make some computer music.
So we're going to try to
make the Frere Jacques song.
So there are how many
phrases in Frere Jacques?
Four.
Great.
And what's nice is that
they're all repeated
the same amount of times, which is two.
>> So we have four phrases
each repeated two times.
And in particular, they're in a round.
And there are many,
many ways to implement
a round that could be fun to do.
I've done it in a
pretty simple way here,
which is just to construct-- the line
function takes a list of music values
and turns it into sequential composition
by applying that sequential composition
operator.
>> And then I delay the different parts
by making them begin with a rest.
So I start with a rest of two measures,
and then a rest of four measures,
and then a rest of six
measures, and then the round
works, as we all know this song.
We see two annotations or
modifications of the music values
that are contained in this sequential
arrangement of music elements.
We have an add volume.
This is a function to annotate
music with a particular volume.
This is a good example
of a MIDI signal running
from 0 to 127, the seven bits of
information that can be carried.
>> And then-- we saw it very
briefly, but the general MIDI
list of all the different instruments.
And there's not a whole lot of them.
If you use a digital audio workstation,
like Ableton Live or Pro Tools,
there's an incredibly wider range
of synthesizers and VST instruments.
But the MIDI standard only
has a few, or several dozen.
And some of them are funny.
I thought it would be fun if we played
the instrument the MIDI instrument
helicopter, and then the
next way through the round,
we did a pad synth, and then of
this corny lead square wave synth,
and then voice ooze, which are a
little bit indistinct on my bad MIDI
synthesizer, but they OK.
>> And then we see this let
and in syntax from Haskell,
and then we're playing
all these parts together
with the parallel composition operator.
And we could probably show some of this.
Here's the code.
And you can see in C, there'd be a
lot of throat clearing and setting
the table code before you
could make music like this.
Or any other programming
language, you'd probably
have to interact with some sort of
library or API and set everything up,
and then you'd have to clean up.
But here in Haskell is, I think, once
you get the hang of it, incredibly
readable and very expressive.
So there is the implementation
of Frere Jacques.
All right.
Now we want to add percussion,
and this is a little bit messier.
So let's take a look at the slides.
So the big idea is to make
a bunch of lists or parts.
On those roll-in machines, there
were typically about maybe eight
to 10 rhythm or percussion parts.
And then use a bunch of techniques.
And we've talked about these-- using
folds, filters, lambda functions,
mapped over lists to generate values
in some range 1 to r, r is 16,
or 32 steps in the sequencer.
>> And then if there's a value in that list
as we're running through the sequencer,
running through it over and
over, it turns on that note,
and that sample gets triggered.
Here are all the different weird ways
I came up with to generate notes.
Try it on your own semi sum.
It'll sound cool.
Time permitting, we'll go through this.
But for right now, I guess
we should demo what we have.
Let's hope this goes OK.
>> So this is GHCI.
And we'll load a file
I have called song.lhs,
which is the file I just showed you.
OK, great.
As Connor said earlier, it
compiled, it type checked,
so I can breathe a lot easier.
It's not going to blow up on me.
>> I did want to show you something useful.
You can see that a
module loaded called 50.
You can browse that module.
And this is so nice
about doing-- maybe what
you're doing in Haskell is not
called software development,
but you can do a lot of
fun stuff on your own.
And the workflow is really nice as
compared to a lot of other languages,
because you can see in a really
readable way what's going on.
So we see that we have
all these phrases, which
are lists of music pitches, and then we
build these up into something larger,
which is a music song.
It's a musical unit.
And then we can play this all
with a function called play music.
You can see that down here.
Which is just play.
>> I should say-- I didn't talk about
this dollar sign that's everywhere.
Dollar sign is another infix operator.
But it has the lowest precedence
of any operator, which effectively
means that everything on
the left of the dollar sign
and the right of the dollar sign,
we're going to get evaluated before it.
So it's sort of like another
way of adding parenthesis.
>> CONNOR HARRIS: It's basically
function composition.
And it ensures that you don't have-- if
you have functions either side or infix
operators on either side, they won't
associate across it and give you
unexpected results.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: So we can--
using that, we can call.
First, we'll play it without the drums.
That's the helicopter,
the MIDI helicopter.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
There's the square wave.
The voice ooze.
And you can really go wild with this.
I picked a pretty simple one,
because I knew I shouldn't bite off
more than I could chew.
Just keep it pretty simple
to show the main ideas.
But then I was like, we've
got to add some drums to this.
Just because this is a
little bit impenetrable,
and I didn't use the
name of the drum parts,
I mapped them-- because they're
part of that enumerated class,
I mapped them to ints.
One is like a bass drum.
Zero is as well.
Seven is a high hat.
And down in here where the
functions get a little more random,
these are like conga drums.
>> So if you think about-- maybe a
fun way to implement a drum machine
is to use very orderly
patterns on your bass drum.
So for instance, on filtering over the
list with everything that gives back
a 1 when it's taken module 04.
So I get 1, 5, 9, 13, 17-- so this
is the first beat of every measure.
>> And then this is the same
thing shifted over two steps.
So that's the offbeat.
So this would be
something like a high hat.
And then again, down here,
it's a little random,
because we're doing conga drums.
And I have some maracas down here, too.
>> So I could call play drum machine,
but it would go on forever,
and it might start grabbing up
all the memory in my system.
So I'll call this function
play music, which as we'll see,
use the truncating parallel composition
to play our little Frere Jacques song
along with this weird drum machine.
So let's take a look.
And please do improve on my
arrangement of all the drum parts.
Not my specialty, but I
had a lot of fun doing it.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> So of course, this is all
a little bit not as fun
if we can't convert it
to a score so maybe it
could be interpreted
by a human performer.
So I won't run it here.
I've already generated the files.
You can see that there's a
dot LilyPond file-- and this
will be my segue over to
Connor-- and a dot MIDI file,
and a dot PDF file, which is what
LilyPond will ultimately generate.
>> But these are those scripts, and I'll
just run them with their help options.
If you get these up and running with
Euterpea, you can generate a MIDI file.
And then from the MIDI file
with this MIDI 2LY program,
you can generate a Lily
Pond file, and then you
can generate a PDF of the score.
And we should take a look at this.
So Connor will probably show
you how to annotate this better,
but this is Frere Jacques as
generated by me in Euterpea.
It's just in C. I should have figured
out what the hack it's actually in.
But that is the pipeline for
how you do that with that.
Let's talk more about LilyPond.
>> CONNOR HARRIS: OK Let's see.
Did you mention Learn You Haskell?
STEPHEN KREWSON: Oh yeah.
Check out Learn You Haskell.
It's in the resources.
That's how I started
learning, and it's great.
Not dumb learning.
>> CONNOR HARRIS: So it's online.
So a guy named [INAUDIBLE]
learnyouahaskell.com, no spaces.
Grammar is sick.
STEPHEN KREWSON: It's illustrated, too.
CONNOR HARRIS: So what is LilyPond?
It's a declarative programming
language for music typesetting.
So declarative-- you can
think of things like HTML,
where you're not saying-- HTML
doesn't say how web browsers should
render pages step by step.
It's just saying this
is a textual description
of what you want the page to look like.
>> And then it's also a program
that compiles this language,
or it read its in and then actually
does the typesetting for you,
and it spits out these
wonderful looking PDF scores.
You can also get PNG format or whatever.
A good way to think
of this is by analogy
is that LaTeX is sort of like LillyPond,
but for just ordinary typesetting.
So instead of-- it's not
WYSIWYG, What You See
Is What You Get, like, say
Finale is, or Sibelius,
or Microsoft Word, where you can type in
real time and draft things in real time
and see changes instantaneously.
>> It is text based.
You have to compile your
scores using a separate program
and get out PDFs later.
This is a bit less
convenient for use if you're
trying to write directly
into a score and you're
trying to compose on the computer.
But there are a lot
of advantages for it.
One, it does look a lot nicer,
because LillyPond can actually
take the time to do
layout decisions properly,
unlike Sibelius or Finale, which have
to make compromised algorithms so
that they can display
things in real time.
>> So why is LilyPond--
computer graphics is hard.
If you're doing anything with music
and you want to write out scores,
you don't want to write
out everything by yourself
starting with how to draw
staffs and how to draw notepads.
It's very difficult.
It's been done before.
You're fine.
>> If you want to use Finale or Sibelius,
the file formats for those things
are very complicated, and you can't
really use them programmatically.
You can open up Sibelius with Finale
and go to File, Export as PDF yourself,
but you can't really
call that from a script.
LillyPond, you can call
from those scripts.
You could easily iterate
LillyPond with LaTeX.
I won't have that much time to go
into these technologies right now,
but they exist.
If you want to look
into a LillyPond book,
it's a program that comes with
your LillyPond distribution,
and it's for iterating
LillyPond fragments into LaTeX
if you want to do something
like a big musicology document
with examples, for example.
And it's a good skill for
life if you're doing anything
with music, not just CS50.
I've used LillyPond for all
of my composition projects
since I was basically a
senior in high school.
>> So here are some simple examples.
This is basically representative
of the level of difficulty
that most people would
face it they were trying
to use LilyPond for simple projects.
This first one is the beginning
to a chorale prelude by Bach.
This bottom one is an excerpt
from one of my own works,
and it's just there to show
you things like [INAUDIBLE]
putting multiple lines in the same
staff, how lyric undersetting works.
Lyric underlays are a thing that's very
easy to use LilyPond for choral music.
>> And so then there's some more
complicated examples here.
All these are done in
LilyPond and they're feasible.
This first excerpt is from
[INAUDIBLE] by [INAUDIBLE].
And this [INAUDIBLE] from
a piece for solo bass
flute by [INAUDIBLE],
who is a longtime-- who
was a longtime member of the
music department here, I think.
I'm not sure where he's gone off to.
But he was the adviser of the Harvard
Composers Association for a long time.
Wonderful man.
And he writes some music that has very
complicated notation that LillyPond
can nonetheless handle very nicely.
>> So just to give you a sense of what
this thing's capabilities are-- so
the internals of LillyPond
are very complicated.
And you can use it for
a long time, including
for some pretty complicated
things, without really
having to know a lot about them.
But the basic idea is that on the
lowest level, the atoms of LillyPonds
are the notes.
The notes contain a
context called voices.
So the voice context
basically corresponds
to a single line of polyphony.
And then context can be
contained hierarchically
in higher level ones that
represent staffs on the score
or larger groupings like
piano staffs or choir staffs,
and then eventually
entire score contexts.
And you can actually encompass
multiple scores in a book.
>> And every context has a
number of attached engravers.
If you look through the
contents of a context
and print a certain symbol or a
certain class of symbols as necessary.
So to every voice context,
there's [INAUDIBLE] notes
engraver that is basically a function or
an object that writes out all the note
heads on the right parts of a page.
Then there's a cleft engraver, which
writes out clefts on the staff.
Then there's a metronome
mark engraver that
writes out metronome marks in a score.
And all these fit pretty
well into the hierarchy.
And it's very, very, very
customizable, which you need
if you want to get things like that.
>> So all the contexts have a
lot of different attributes
that you can modify for everything
from the spacing to various font
selection to sizes of things.
If you want to do even
more complicated things,
there's an embedded scripting language.
They use scheme, which
is dialect of LISP.
These probably don't
mean anything to you.
But basically, a scheme
another functional
programming language, more or less.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: The tie-in.
>> CONNOR HARRIS: Yeah.
It's a good tie-in, I suppose.
And it's used as a teaching language,
actually, down Mass Ave. At MIT.
And it's very handy for LillyPond
for various technical reasons.
>> And so if you want to make simple
tweaks dependent on conditionals,
for example-- there's certain
condition of a score that's met,
make alterations to the
layout or whatnot-- then
those facilities are there.
They're complicated.
So here's a pretty simple code sample.
It's five lines.
Basically, I'm defining two staffs.
It's in 3/4.
The first staff has an
attached tempo mark,
but that's actually going
to go on to the whole score,
because tempo marks
are on the score level.
The metronome mark engraver
is attached to score context.
There are different keys,
because the [INAUDIBLE] engraver
is attached the staffs.
You can actually do is.
The sample I wrote is
actually in C major,
but it's just to
demonstrate you can have
different keys in different staffs.
And the basic syntax is you write
note names with E, F, G, whatever.
If you want to do accidentals,
you suffix IS or ES.
This is from Dutch
musicological conventions.
>> And to do octave leaps, you have to use
these tick marks, comma or apostrophe.
The relative just means
whatever you have a note,
it will automatically be plaec in the
octave closest to the previous one.
And if you want to jump more than
a fifth-- say a fifth or more--
then you have to use the [INAUDIBLE].
But otherwise, you don't have to
specify the octave of every single note.
>> And relative C, prime, and
C, you just specify middle C
and base C, especially first notes.
Then you have these staffs that organize
these two voices or samples of music,
and you have a score.
And that looks like this.
>> If you want to take the time to
copy that sample of LillyPond
code on the previous
slide down here, and you
can write it for LillyPond yourself.
I know we've got something
that looks a lot like this.
So there's another technology
called Music XML maintained
by completely different people.
XML is a textual data structure-- I
shouldn't say data structure-- say
metaphor map sort of.
And it's designed to hold
hierarchical data very well.
HTML, for example, is a type of XML.
And you can tell XML because they
had all the angle brackets and angle
bracket slash marks
that show data fields.
>> I don't have a code
example from Music XML.
You can find it yourself.
Basically, the reason you might want
to use XML as the intermediate stage
is, first of all, it's
an interchange format
for basically every-- I shouldn't say
every, but a lot of different score
writers.
So if you write in Music
XML, not only can LillyPond
read it with the help of this auxilary
program called Music XML to LY,
but also Finale can read
it, Sibelius can read it.
Depending on how your internal object
hierarchy works for representing music,
it might be easier to write out
to Music XML than to LillyPond
and just rely on Music XML
to LY to do the conversion.
>> I don't think [INAUDIBLE] has Music XML.
STEPHEN KREWSON: It does not.
Someone is working on it, though.
>> CONNOR HARRIS: OK.
Euterpea does not have a
Music XML output function yet.
If you want a final project idea,
maybe get in touch with guys
that Stephen knows, and
they could use your help.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: I would love that.
CONNOR HARRIS: Also, basically,
every programming languages
that's worth its salt
already has an XML library,
so you can internally convert all
of your music into some object
that the XML library can write
out that would require fewer
alterations to your internal structure
for whatever music objects you
want to write than writing it
directly in LillyPond would.
Then just print it out with XML with
the XML libraries in your language,
which will guarantee that it's
syntactically correct and everything,
and then convert it to LillyPond.
So technology you might want to
look into if you're doing something
like this.
>> [INAUDIBLE], another
auxilarry technology.
This is basically Tech Works
or Tech Studio for LillyPond.
So it offers help with
syntax, with templates
for various common
combinations of instruments.
It allows split screen viewing so
you can have your code in one window
and PDF in another window and
click on places in the PDF
to jump to the relevant
spots in your source code.
This is more useful if you're actually
writing LillyPond files yourself
than if you're generating
them programmatically.
But again, it's
something useful to have.
>> Great.
Another resources-- I'll just
go through this very quickly.
LillyPond manuals-- LillyPond has
excellent documentation on its website.
They have a tutorial.
They have a syntax reference.
They have hundreds of snippets
for various small things
yo might need do to demonstrate
various capabilities.
If you want to use
the scripting language
or make more extensive
customizations, then there's
internals reference at that URL.
If you want to use Music XML, there's
that URL, musicxml.com/tutorial.
>> And then if you need to learn scheme
because you actually want to use
the scripting facilities in LillyPond,
then there's a [INAUDIBLE] called
Structured Interpretation
of Computer Programs,
which is not only the second
greatest CS textbook ever written--
find me afterwards if you want to know
what I think the greatest one is--
but it's also a very good
introduction to the language proper .
You won't need more than
the first few sections.
>> And that's it.
Any questions?
>> STUDENT: Where can I download
your generated Frere Jacques
so I can put it on my iPod?
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: Well, you can write
out to some wav file in Euterpea.
And you have the code.
It's on GitHub.
Make your own variations of
Frere Jacques by CS50 hive mind.
It would be great.
CONNOR HARRIS: Anyone else?
STEPHEN KREWSON: We need
a better bass drum, too.
It's really bad.
>> STUDENT: Euterpea has not only
the composition side, but signal--
STEPHEN KREWSON: Yes.
In fact, the work I
did in Euterpea when I
took this-- there's a
graduate course at Yale that
uses it-- was on sound synthesis.
So there's a really
nice way using arrows
and some of the notation we saw of
composing together signal functions.
In particular, the bass for most
of them is just a simple sine wave.
But if you start composing those
in weird programmatic ways,
you can get crazy sound
effects, like weird cascades.
You can create very gritty
sounds with a lot of modulation.
>> I did a project on granular
synthesis, which is
somewhere in between FM and sampling.
You take very small,
little samples, and then
combine them with some sort of
modulator and build up a richer sound.
We also did physical modeling, so
trying to think about the physics
and psychoacoustics of something like
a trumpet, and thinking about the way
the sound is bouncing off
the bell of the trumpet
and the acoustics of
the room and modeling
that with the basic oscillators.
CONNOR HARRIS: Thanks so much.
Thanks for coming.
And I'm always willing to
take questions by email--
connorharris@college.harvard.edu.
>> STEPHEN KREWSON: Yeah.
stephen.krewson@yale.edu.
Cool.