ZACK CHAUVIN: Awesome.
So we'll get started.
Thanks a bunch for coming and to the
hordes of people watching online,
thanks as well for tuning in.
So my name's Zack.
And today we'll be talking about
how to create iPhone apps using
a language called Objective-C.
>> So my hope is that
after today, you'll feel
empowered to take on tutorials that
will help you guide you on your way
to starting iPhone applications.
So hopefully, if you
came today, then you're
a little bit interested
in this technology.
But just in case, I'll try
and motivate a little bit
why program for the iPhone
and then more specifically,
why we program for Objective-C.
>> So first of all, why iPhone?
So people will tell you
all sorts of reasons.
For me, iPhone's really exciting,
because it's what people around you
are using.
As you can see from this chart, iPhones
have the plurality of use in America.
Especially at Harvard,
they're really well-used.
And so creating iPhone
apps is really exciting,
because your friends will be using them.
>> As well, in case you're
motivated by other things,
you can see that even if
Androids have a higher
share of the market
in terms of downloads,
iPhone consistently comes
up on top in terms of sales.
So that's another great reason in case
you're interested in a job in tech
later.
Cool.
So now you're sold on
programming for iPhones.
But you still have choice.
As you've probably heard, there's
a newer language called Swift.
And both of those are great options.
Personally, my background
is in Objective-C.
And that's why I'll try and
sell you on Objective-C.
But Swift's another great option.
>> So why use Objective-C over Swift?
The first reason is that Objective-C
has been around for a really long time.
I believe it's like around 20 years.
It's been around for a long time.
And so because of that, there's a wealth
of resources that are available to you.
>> And so I'll give you some examples of
tutorials at the end of this seminar.
But you just type anything in, like
how to do this in Objective-C. It's
everywhere, tutorials.
There's a huge community
surrounding Objective-C
because it's the commonplace thing.
>> Similar to that, it's a
very established language.
You guys have been
studying C this semester.
And as you can see by the name,
it has a strong resemblance to C.
We'll look at some Objective-C later.
But certainly in its
origins, it came from C.
And you'll see how that
presents itself in a language.
Finally, it dominates the industry.
So even though Swift is like
this new, fancy technology,
you see, if you go to iPhone,
like if you go to app companies,
you'll see that a lot of
them still use Objective-C.
And that's either because
their code base was originally
made in Objective-C or
for these other reasons
that I've told you, namely that
there's a wealth of resources.
They know that if they're
going to use a library,
then it's been heavily tested
by other apps and such,
whereas Swift code is
less heavily tested.
So definitely reasons for both.
But that's why personally I would
go with Objective-C right now.
Cool.
So you guys have been working
in the CS50 IDE this semester.
And it turns out that in order
to program anything for iPhone,
you have to use Xcode, which is the
native IDE for Objective-C and Swift.
And so the caveat to that is that if
you want to develop for iPhone, then
you have to have a Mac, because
this is only available for Mac.
Of course there are workarounds, but
the best way to develop for an iPhone
is on your Mac with Xcode.
>> So that being said, let's
poke around in Xcode
to see what this looks like and some
of the tools that we might use in here.
So this is Xcode.
There's a lot going on.
It's a little bit more complex than
the IDE that you're used to from CS50.
But the good news is that it's
been developed over time to really
have all sorts of tools
that are really awesome.
And I'll do my best to
show you some of these.
>> In the center, we have your normal
text editor that you know and love.
This is where you'll be
typing Objective-C. There
are some examples of Objective-C
that we'll walk through later.
On the left, we have our file directory,
exactly the same as the CS50 IDE.
On the right, you have something
that helps you more closely examine
the thing that you're looking at.
For example, let's say we are going
to click on something like this.
Here, let's do an easier example.
>> So if we look at this
file, say we're trying
to manipulate this thing right here.
On the right, we get a panel in which
you can specify different things
about that panel.
Obviously you don't know what this
is yet, but just it for granted
that this side is to make
little adjustments on the thing
that you're working on right now.
So in that way, it's nice to
have this IDE, because you
don't have to do everything in code.
Instead there's an option to
use the user interface to change
little things about your application.
>> Probably the best thing about Xcode
is the presence of the simulator.
So today we'll be looking
at this application.
OK.
So I've been telling you little things.
I'm just typing out my little examples.
So I have to remove
them before I compile.
>> Perfect.
So it'll come up.
We get this little simulator.
And then the right away
you can see exactly how
it would appear just like you have
the iPhone in front of you, which
is really sweet.
We're going to play around with this.
It works just like your normal iPhone.
>> And you can even do things like press
the Home button or shake it, rotate it,
all sorts of awesome stuff that means
that your development process can
be really quick.
Instead of having to port it
out to your phone every time,
you can just use the simulator.
And we'll see how we can use that
to our advantage in a little bit.
>> So that's Xcode for you.
Super powerful IDE.
Definitely if you're going to invest
some time developing in Objective-C,
It's important to get to know and
love Xcode, because using this tool
well will make it so much easier
for you to program in Objective-C.
>> So that being said, this is
the first step to programming
Objective-C is acquiring this Xcode.
And that can be done through
the app store on your Mac.
And that's pretty much the only
setup, in fact, is downloading this.
Once you have this,
you're set up to develop
for the iPhone, which is pretty sweet.
Any questions, just let me know.
>> STUDENT: What does NS
stand for in NSObject?
>> ZACK CHAUVIN: Yeah.
So we'll get a little
bit more into that.
But you see NS everywhere
in the language Objective-C.
And so it turns out that they've created
a whole bunch of objects for you,
a whole bunch of things that you
can use that are super helpful.
>> So in this example, this is an
object that represents any object.
Or here we have a NSString,
which represents a string.
It's sort of like how CS50
defined a string for you.
The people that created Objective-C
defined a NSString for you.
And NS is just the prefix
that they use to save it
as something they created for you.
It stands for next steps.
>> And if you're interested, it has to
do with the history of Objective-C.
And I think one of the first companies
to work with this was called NeXTSTEP.
And we'll talk about objects
and all that good stuff later.
But basically it just means
this is an object for you
to use that we've created.
So there might be like NSNumber,
NSString, all that good stuff.
Awesome.
Yeah.
And if any of you have
questions, just let me know.
>> Cool.
OK.
So that was a little bit about the IDE.
Let's dive in and take a
look at what Objective-C is
and how we use it to create apps.
So the first thing is that you'll
notice on the left we have primarily two
different types of files, .h's and .m's.
And it's kind of like how in C,
we have two files, .h's and .c's.
>> So just like before, the
.h is the header file.
So we'll look at one of these.
But the header file is something
that just basically warns
the compiler of what's coming.
Like hey, I have this object.
And it has these methods
and these properties.
That might not make too
much sense to you right now.
But basically it's similar to how you
say like hey, I have these structs,
or I have these functions in your .h.
It's just declaring
ahead of time the sorts
of things that you're going
to be using in your file.
>> On the other hand, we have the .m's.
And m is for implementation.
So in a .m file, you actually
specify the logic of those functions.
So whereas .h might say, I have
a function called my function,
.m might say I have a
function called my function.
And it does x, y, and zed by
manipulating these variables and such.
That's the difference in .h and .m.
And you'll notice that they appear
in pairs because every .m needs a .h
to describe to the compiler what
sorts of things it will contain.
>> Yeah.
Perfect.
So the language is called
Objective-C. What's
the deal with this objective part?
It turns out that C doesn't support
a very well-known part of programming
in general, which is called
object-oriented programming.
And object-oriented programming was
a revolution in computer science
that started moving programmers to
thinking about programming the way we
think about the world.
And the way we think about the world is
that all around us are objects, right?
I have a laptop.
I have a table.
Let's see if we can
program in that way where
we describe all of the
objects that are interacting
in our system in our application.
And then describe the
types of things, the types
of information that they store and
the types of things that they can do.
>> So in Objective-C, those two things
are their properties and their methods.
So in this example, I have a car.
In real life, this is
the object, the car.
What does a car look like if you were
to describe it in code as an object?
So first of all, you
say, hey, I'm going to be
describing this thing that's a car.
And this car is a more
specific type of NSObject.
>> So first of all, there
are some properties.
There's some information
that the car has.
It has a brand which is a string.
We talked about NS before.
And that just means it's like the
normal string that they gave to us.
It also has a make.
So that might be like this is
if you have a Honda Odyssey,
the Odyssey would be the make.
And finally, it has
the speed which keeps
track of how fast is
this car going right now.
So those are all the
properties, the information
that we need to know about the car.
But cars aren't just
packets of information.
They also do things.
So these are methods or functions
that can act on this car.
So for instance, we could say, hey car.
I want you to start
driving at this speed.
And so this is a function
that doesn't return anything.
It just goes off and does something.
But in order to start
driving at a certain speed,
it has to know what speed you
want it to start driving at.
>> So we pass in a float, the same
float that you guys are used to,
which is called speed.
And note that this is
an example in a .h file.
And so you'll see that
all of this is just
telling the methods that will exist.
But it hasn't given the implementation.
In the .m file, you could
go in and be like, OK,
now I'm going to set my speed to this.
And start the engine up, whatever.
Then there could be another
method to stop driving.
So those are the two
things that cars can do.
They can start.
And they can stop.
And you can see how by defining
all sorts of these objects,
we can represent super,
super complex things
in a way that makes sense to people.
That's good news, because
people are the one programming.
So object-oriented programming is a
way to make very complex things much
simpler by encapsulating
the method or the actions
and information about an
object all in one file.
>> So it's a great part of Objective-C. If
we tried to program for iPhones in C,
it would be a nightmare, because
this sort of stuff is very hard in C.
And that's why they created
a new language called
Objective-C to accomplish
this sort of stuff.
>> OK.
So I said that, first of all, let's just
look a little bit more detail into what
methods look like.
So the first thing is
we have this minus.
And then we see the return type.
In my other example, that
return type was void,
because it didn't return anything.
Then we have the name of the method.
>> And we have a whole bunch
of these pairs that say,
this is the type of the
thing getting passed in.
This is the name of the
So from now on, I'll be able
to refer to it as stringVar.
And then you can have as many
of these pairs as you want,
which say a little bit
of text and then the type
and then the name of the variable, the
name that the variable will end up as.
>> So if you wanted to look at
how this might be called,
you would say if you have an actual
instance of the object, which
means that so the car class is like
this high level idea of what a car is.
It might be like the
blueprints of that car.
It's just if we define
the class, then we
say it is possible that a car
exists, whereas if we create a car,
we create an instance of a car,
that's like a real physical car.
It's like this car has this
make, this brand, and whatever.
>> So if we go back to this
example, this is the class.
But an instance is an actual
car that we've initialized
and now we've given data to.
Is that distinction clear?
So you can have the class, which
is like the high-level blueprints.
And then an instance, which is an actual
car that has all this stuff filled out.
>> So in this example, we're saying,
I want you initialize this class.
And now what all of this
returns is an actual instance.
So instance is like an example
of a particular car with a make
and a brand and all that good stuff.
And so if you have an instance, you
can call an instance method on it.
>> So it says, this is how we
call functions in Objective-C
with the square brackets.
So the thing that you're calling
the method on and then the method
that you want to call.
So the method is called
myMethodTakesAString.
And then you give it the
string and then the rest
of the name and the second parameter.
So that's kind of confusing.
That's new to you guys.
You're used to writing the entire
method function name and then
all the arguments.
It's a design decision that they
decided to make in Objective-C that you
actually intersperse the name
of the method with the things
that you're passing in.
>> So it's like a little bit of a name,
and then the thing you're passing in,
more of the name of the
thing you're passing in.
And so now stringVar will be Hello.
And floatVar will be 1.5 as you go
in to actually implement this method.
>> I'll contrast that with a class method.
So whereas an instance method, you call
on a particular instance of that car,
it would only make sense to tell
a particular car to start or stop.
But maybe there are methods that you
want to call on the entire class.
For instance, class, tell
me what your name is.
What is the name of this class?
>> For that, it wouldn't make sense
to ask an individual car that.
Instead we want to ask the blueprints.
Blueprints, what's the
name of your class?
And that would give us back.
So basically, the plus
defines a class method.
And so that means you call
it on the entire class,
whereas a minus defines
an instance which
you will call on a particular instance.
This might be a little bit of a jump.
And so this will probably
something that will get teased out
as you start your tutorials.
So don't get scared away by this.
It's just like a little distinction
and a little better example
of how we use methods in Objective-C.
>> Cool.
Another very important thing is your
favorite concept from this week's pset,
Model-View-Controller.
So it turns out that
Model-View-Controller
isn't something that's specific
to CS50 Finance or to PHP.
It's an idea in app creation.
You guys are applying
it to web applications.
But it turns out that in
most types of frameworks,
they actually use MVC in
order to clarify the roles
and responsibilities of each file.
>> So just like you guys
have learned, there
are three parts to an application,
a model, a controller, and a view.
And hopefully you got a little
bit of an understanding of this
from this week's pset.
But I just want to
make this super clear,
because in Objective-C
it becomes especially
important to understand this concept.
And hopefully this will help
you with your pset as well.
>> So we have these three parts with the
controller being like the middleman.
He's the guy in the middle
that does most of the thinking.
So he is responsible
for taking, basically
acting upon the request
that's made by the user.
And so some things that he might
do are update or ask questions
about the model.
And then once he's done some thinking
about what he got back from the model,
he'll update the view.
>> So basically he's the guy in the middle
talking to both the model and the view.
But note that there are
no connections here.
The view never talks to
the model, because the view
doesn't do any thinking.
It's just like controller,
give me some information.
And I'll display it.
That's all I'm responsible for.
I don't even know
anything about the model.
I just know that I receive a
little bit of information on it.
And I display it.
>> And this is super important
to keep this distinction,
because it simplifies our files a lot.
Technically, you could implement
all of the MVC in one file.
But that would lead to
super confusing code that
doesn't run as fast as code like this.
>> So an analogy, of course.
So here we go.
You walk up to Walmart or
to your favorite store.
And there's lots of stuff going on.
There is this guy who's greeting you.
There is some mannequins
in the front window.
And there's a guy with
a clipboard who knows
everything there is to know about
what Walmart buys and sells.
So this is really what
you're interested in.
You don't want to see
this guy or this guy.
You came here to look at mannequins and
try and decide what you want to buy.
>> But if they only had one sort of
mannequin, that'd be crappy, right?
So you could create a static website
that just had the same thing always.
But you need these two in
order to make a dynamic.
>> So the first thing you do is
walk up to the controller.
And you say like hey, I am interested
in buying this sort of clothing.
This is my size.
And I'm specifically interested
in ordering a jacket.
So he's like OK.
I don't, I'm allowed to think a bunch.
But I don't actually know
what we have in stock.
So I'm going to go ask my friend the
model, who's going to give me back all,
everything that he
knows about our jackets.
>> So the model guy checks his clipboard.
He sees that we have three jackets.
And he tells the controller back,
here are the jackets we have on store.
The controller isn't allowed
to show you anything.
That's not his job.
His job is to be the middleman
between the model and the view.
So he doesn't directly show you them.
He hands it over to the mannequin
guy or the mannequins themselves.
Puts it on the mannequins.
And the mannequins are the ones
that show you the final product.
>> So he takes the jackets.
He's the controller,
gives them to the views.
They get all done up.
And at the end of the day,
you see what you want to see.
Similar to a website how this
guy takes what you have inputted,
asks the model for them.
And then eventually,
gives it to the view
in order to be displayed on the screen.
Hopefully that makes it a little bit
clearer for the pset and Objective-C,
because for both of
them, it's very important
that you know which files are which.
>> You say is this file a controller?
Am I putting view code in my controller?
Or am I doing too much
thinking in my view?
All of these will potentially
even lead to bugs,
because Objective-C very
stringently enforces this principle.
So basically, don't break MVC.
It'll make your code
sad and possibly buggy.
>> Sweet.
So that's a little bit about MVC.
With that being said, let's
check out a code example.
And so I don't want to get into
too much detail, because really,
in order to learn this stuff, you
have to learn it from the ground up.
And that's done by
checking out tutorials.
But hopefully just by
looking at some examples,
we can at least get a sense of what
the structure of these things are.
>> So, I'll come over here.
We have lots of different
types of files in here.
But luckily they line up pretty
nicely with the three parts of MVC
that we talked about before.
So one of them is the model.
That's really nicely shown up.
Those are like the two
different models that we have.
They're the two different, you can think
of them as the two different databases
that we have.
>> So in your pset this week, you have a
users database, a portfolios database,
and a history database, those
would be like your three models.
There's three different
dudes with checkboards.
And they know everything
there is to know
about those three different things.
Similarly here we have these files.
And if we click into one, so
here we have ScaryBugData.
So this is my class.
This is my class.
You can see here that I've
defined it as an RWTScaryBugData.
>> And so like I said before, all classes
have things that they contain in them,
as well things that they can do.
Those are the two different
things that are in a bug data.
What's some info that's in bug data?
Well first, what's
the title of this bug?
I guess I should explain
what this app does.
It's the app that you
saw before which just
is a list of all types of scary bugs.
>> So here we're going to end up displaying
the bugs with their pictures and stuff.
So this class is going to encapsulate
just the text of this bug.
So that includes what its name is, as
well as a rating of how scary it is.
And one of the things that this data can
do, well, the one thing that it can do
is it will get initialized with a
title and as well with a rating.
>> So if we have an instance, an
empty instance of this data,
we might want to
initialize it with data.
And so we could pass in the
title and the rating in this way.
So one way that this would get called
is so if I say RWTScaryBugData.
And then I do alloc.
That just means give me an
empty instance of this class.
So now we have an empty
instance of ScaryBugData.
And we're ready to
start feeding it stuff.
>> Well luckily we have a method on
this class that does exactly that.
So we can say initWithTitle and string.
What's the title that
we want to give it?
We want to say that
it's a spooky spider.
And its rating is going to be a
9.5 out of 10 on the spooky scale.
So that example of how
we might use the init
function in order to
actually pass in the data
to initialize an instance
of the spooky spider.
>> And so now we have an actual
instance of the class bug data, which
represents something to do with a bug.
Cool.
For those of you curious,
this little at is just
a quirk of Objective-C that means that I
want to create an instance of a string.
So it's like a super
quick way of creating
an actual object which is a string.
Basically just remember
put at before your strings.
>> Cool So I told you that
the .h is the header.
And the .m is the implementation.
So if we went into here, we'd expect to
see a little bit more of implementation
as to what this stuff is.
So you'll learn about this
stuff in tutorials hopefully.
There's just something that you
have to remember to cut/paste.
But what we do see is that
this function, this method,
actually gets implemented.
It says when somebody
calls this function, what
do you want to have happen?
>> And it turns out this is
what you want to have happen.
In a init function,
it's fairly formulaic.
But if you created your own function
that had your own custom behavior,
the logic for what would
go in that function
would be very similar to what you're
doing in C. It's exactly the same.
You create a function.
You want that function to do something.
So in here you write
the Objective-C that
would make it do that thing, which
will hopefully be clearer to you
once you know Objective-C.
>> Sweet.
So these are examples of our models.
What about controllers?
What do controllers look like?
So we have four files here
that say ViewController.
And that's normally the suffix that
will go on any sort of controller.
In Objective-C they're
called view controllers,
which just kind of helps you to make
that connection between the view
and the view controller.
>> So let's check one out.
So we have this guy called
MasterViewController.
And his job is to be this big,
basically this entire view,
the MasterViewController is the
thing that controls that view.
So it's the one that does all the
thinking for that entire page.
>> The other guy says DetailViewController.
And he's the one that does
the thinking for this,
because this is the
detail view, similarly
to how you guys have a quote
controller for your quote page
and a by controller for your by page.
Each one gets a pair of
ViewController and View.
>> So this guy does lots of stuff.
One method that you'll see over
and over again is the viewDidLoad.
And this is sort of like
your int main function
in Objective-C, which says
that the view did load, which
means that I'm ready to start thinking.
Basically I have this
empty view which I want
you to start doing the thinking
for, start initializing stuff
where it needs to be.
And so it's sending you that
message that the view did load.
And now you're ready
to do some thinking.
>> So what does this guy
do when his view loads?
He sets up the navigation bar,
which is this thing at the top.
He adds a button to the navigation
bar, which is this little plus.
And then he sets his
title to be Scary Bugs.
>> So without getting too nitty gritty,
there are a bunch of other methods
that happen in this master
view controller that are
fairly specific to this application.
But what else can I
call your attention to?
Another thing this view does is similar
to how your view or your controller,
sorry, handles the user's responses.
This is the function
that will respond when
somebody clicks on a particular row.
>> And in Objective-C,
that's called a segue.
You're segueing from
one screen to another.
So this says given
that somebody is trying
to go from here to here,
what do you want me to do?
So how can I prepare in order to go
from this stage to the next stage?
So that's an example of a controller.
It's the one that does the thinking.
>> And then finally, what
does the view look like?
One really awesome
part about Objective-C
is that views actually look like views.
They're not code.
In most cases, they're not code.
They're actually pictures of how
you want to lay out your view.
>> And so this is an example of what
the view looks like in this case.
And they're actually called
storyboards, because it kind of tells
a story of how somebody
goes through your app.
So for very simple apps,
this works very well.
So for example, here you can
see the table view, which
is the list of all the different bugs.
It has this little arrow that says
that when somebody clicks on a cell,
I want you to transition
to the detail view.
>> So this is what your views look like.
They're normally storyboards.
There are other programmatic
ways to declare views as well.
But if you're working
with a really simple app,
a storyboard is the way to go.
And support for this has gotten
really, really good in the last couple
versions of Objective-C iOS.
So that's an example of a view.
Are there any questions about, is there
anything that you guys want to look at?
Or any questions about
what's going on in, yeah?
>> STUDENT: Can you change the view there?
Or does it have to be within your file?
ZACK CHAUVIN: Yeah.
So the question is can
you change the view?
So you can do all sorts
of stuff to this view.
For instance, down here I have
a list of all sorts of stuff
that I can add to the view.
So say I want to always have a label in
the middle of this guy that says CS50.
If we were to re-run it, then
CS50 would show up right there.
So it's like a drag and drop type
deal where you lay everything out.
>> And it also has this sweet
thing called auto layout,
which means that as
you rotate your phone,
it will automatically readjust to that.
And that's the sort of stuff that would
be a nightmare to type out in code,
but when you're just showing it on a
screen like this isn't so bad to do.
And so it's basically like you
never have to write CSS again,
which if you've written any CSS for this
pset, you should be really happy about.
>> Cool.
OK.
So that's one way.
And then another way is
there are programmatic ways
to add things to views as well.
So in you might have another
folder that's called views.
And you can declare a
view just by writing out,
I don't have any examples here.
But there are ways in code to also
define what's going on here basically.
So you might say add label to my
table view controller, something
like that, table view.
>> Sweet.
OK.
So there is a little
example of the code.
Next up very simple, just
talking about some tips.
And then we'll be done.
So my biggest tip is
that if you try and jump
right into making your final project
when you're learning a new technology,
it very rarely works
out well, because as you
may have seen with some of
your psets, the first time
that you attempt anything, it
ends up being a little messy.
>> And that's not so bad when the course of
what you're working on is just a week.
But if you're trying to develop
this for your final project
or beyond your final
project, it's important
that you start your
project after you have
a fair bit of knowledge of other thing.
So it doesn't have to be huge.
You don't have create
two final projects.
But maybe find a tutorial
from one of the resources
that I'll list at the end of
the thing that says create
an example of a Twitter application.
>> Or create an example,
even the scary bugs thing.
If you implemented all
the scary bugs, that
would be a great start so that when
you actually go to create your own,
you aren't making the little mistakes or
ending up with all sorts of random code
in your final project.
Make a small app before you
jump into the final project.
>> Next up we have use git to collaborate
with partners and save work.
So git isn't something we've
talked a lot about in CS50.
>> STUDENT: Is it like GitHub?
>> ZACK CHAUVIN: It's sort of like GitHub.
So what are git and GitHub?
What's the difference?
What do they do?
So git is a way of saving
multiple versions of your files
a whole bunch of times.
So say you're working on an essay.
The thing is you only ever
have one version of that essay.
So if you type a whole bunch of stuff.
And then you're like, oh,
I have this great idea.
I'm going to add this whole paragraph.
And I'm going to cut this
out and blah blah blah.
And then you get to the end of it.
And you're like, oh.
I actually think I like my version
before better than this one.
So then you just type
undo a million times.
>> Basically what git does is it has
you save versions of your file,
of your entire project, as you go along.
So you might implement the
first part of your project.
And then save a snapshot of
what your project is like then.
So you can say, I just finished this.
And all of this is working.
And then a day later, come back.
And you spend an entire
day working on it.
And it turns out that
you broke some stuff.
>> You don't know what's going on.
If only you could go back to your
previous version or even just
look at what your previous version was
to see what you're doing differently.
Git will allow you to do all of that.
>> And you mentioned GitHub.
Git is also the way that you
collaborate with other people.
So GitHub is this online thing that
requires that you're using git.
And if you're using git
locally on your own laptop,
then you can use GitHub,
which is like a cloud,
like a storage space in
the cloud, so that you
can push your stuff from your local
version of git onto the cloud.
And then somebody else who also has
git can take what's on the cloud
onto their machine, their local machine.
>> So GitHub makes collaboration
via git possible.
And so git has the two advantages
that it will prevent you
from getting super
frustrated about not be
able to go back to previous work,
which happens surprisingly often.
And also it allow you to craft
collaborate with partners.
Literally we see people like draw boxing
stuff back and forth to each other,
which will make you very sad quickly.
>> Git is the way to do it.
It's specially created for programmers.
And it has also awesome tools.
There's probably a CS50 seminar on it.
If not there's all sorts of
great resources online about git.
OK.
My final tip is to run your
code often to catch bugs early.
This is really like a tip for any
sort of programming that you're doing.
But it's especially important when
you're taking on a new technology,
because if you make 10 minutes worth
of changes, and then you run it,
and it's broken, you have much less idea
of what's broken if you were constantly
running your programs.
>> And even as somebody that's been
programming in Objective-C for a while,
I find that if I wait too
long before running my code,
it's not really clear where
the bug is coming from.
So run your code often.
And that will prevent frustrating
experiences later in the line.
>> So what are some resources for you?
This first and last one are great
resources online, raywenderlich
as well as rypress.
The example of scary bugs
came from raywenderlich.
I'll be sending out
these slides as well.
But you're welcome to
take them down now.
So those are available online.
And then the Stanford iOS course
is available through iTunes U.
>> And that's actually
the course that I did.
I worked in an iOS job this summer.
And then I showed up.
And I realized I knew nothing about iOS.
And so I took this course
for like a couple days.
And then I was ready to
jump into iOS development.
>> So if you're dedicated to
using iOS for your project,
then your best bet for sure is
to do one of these tutorials
before you try anything else, because
it can be super frustrating to just poke
around in Objective-C without really
knowing some of the fundamentals.
>> So all of these are great resources.
And I would probably recommend
the Stanford course the most,
just because it's a professor.
He's taught a lot about
this sort of stuff.
And so it's a great resource.
That's all I have to say
about Objective-C. Do
you guys have any final questions?
Or like we can also
talk about your ideas?
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: What other languages out
there for coding on app development?
What are the benefits of Objective-C
over others or others over Objective-C?
>> ZACK CHAUVIN: For sure.
Is that specific to iPhone or?
STUDENT: Yes.
ZACK CHAUVIN: Sweet.
So the question is what languages
are there for developing on a iPhone?
So pretty much the only two
are Objective-C and Swift.
And so my background is in Objective-C.
And so that's what I would push for.
>> I talked a little bit about this.
But it's basically just like
the more established language.
It's been around for many years.
Because of that, many people use it.
And there's way more resources for
it, because it's been around longer.
And it's also much more
similar to C than Swift.
Swift is probably more like JavaScript.
And it's much more common.
>> Objective-C is much more common
in the industry than Swift
for most the reasons that I said before.
It's kind of like the legacy
language that people started using,
as well that it's much more
better supported by resources.
Swift's great as well.
There are other tutorials.
There are other CS50 tutorials on Swift.
You're welcome to check those out.
And make the decision for yourself.
It's definitely where it's going.
I'm not going to pretend
that Objective-C's
going to be around forever.
But it's a question of when
that switch will happen.
But most people use Swift.
Cool.
Any other questions?
Sweet.
OK.
So that's all I have.
I'll stick around for a bit in case
you guys want to talk about your ideas
or how feasible they are.
But thanks a bunch for coming.
And good luck with your projects.