>> SPEAKER 1: All right, let's take a
look at how the staff solution actually
operates, so that you
get a sense, first off
how the web server's supposed
to run, and how you can actually
get it running on your own computer.
So picture it here.
I've already installed in CS50 ID
pset6 dot zip, per the specification.
I've unzipped it, and I've
CDed into my pset6 directory.
One of the first things you're
going to want to do, especially
if you've been using a CS50 IDE to play
along with recent lectures, wherein
we've been using PHP in
CS50 IDE, specifically,
using that web server called Apache,
whereby you can start and stop it
with that command, Apache 50.
First, go ahead and
type "Apache 50 stop"
just to make sure that if you were
following along in recent days,
and you turned on Apache, you're
turning it off in this way
by stopping the server.
Now, what I'm going to do is exactly
what the spec tells me to do.
I'm going to go to tilda CS50 slash
pset6 slash server, and just hit Enter.
You'll notice that I'm yelled at
with some usage information, whereby
I should be running
the program as server
with an optional dash p and then a
port number, which you can actually
leave blank because by
default, per the spec,
the web server is going to
assume that you want port 8080.
Meanwhile, you might recall that
port 8080 is not really standard,
rather port 80 is the
number we've talked
about being the default for HTTP.
Well, turns out that CS50 IDE
is simply configured in a way,
such that when you with a browser try
to visit port 80 from the outside world,
it's going to sort of magically
port forward, or redirect itself,
to port 8080 inside
of your server itself.
>> So the last thing here is the command
line argument, the path to route.
And by that I just
mean, what folder do I
want to tell the server
to use to serve up files?
In other words, if the user visits
slash, what should he or she see?
Well, let's go ahead and
run exactly that again,
this time specifying that I
want the root of my web server
to be the public directory, that comes
with problem set six distribution code.
When I hit Enter, you'll see
in yellow here, a reminder
as to what folder I'm actually using.
In this case, it's a long string,
"home ubuntu workspace pset6 public."
And that last word is what's key.
And then lastly, apparently, my
server's now listening on port 8080.
>> What I'm next going to do is recall that
in CS50 ID in the top right hand corner
of your screen, you're going to see
a URL that is ide50-username.cs50.io.
And indeed, if you click
that, you'll be whisked away
to another browser tab,
that, in this case,
is going to show me the contents
of my web servers roots.
In other words, the files you see here,
cat dot HTML, cat dot JPEG, favicon dot
ico, hello dot HTML,
hello dot php, and test,
are all of the same
contents that you would see
with LS inside of my public directory.
And what's nice is that if I go
ahead and click now on cat dot HTML,
I see cat dot HTML.
And if I click on cat dot
JPEG, or hello dot HTML,
or even type in my name David,
and then click "say hello,"
you'll see that all of the
files work because the staff
solution, of course, installed
in CS50 ID is fully functional.
So it works exactly as your own
solution should ultimately work.
>> Meanwhile, if we go back to my terminal
window, where I ran the server command,
notice what the console has been saying.
I see here that the first request that
I received was literally get slash cat
dot HTML, HTTP version 1.1.
And then, in green what
the staff solution has done
is it's showing me the
first line of output
that the web server is responding with.
In other words, we've
already written the code
that opens up that virtual envelope,
containing that get request.
And then we respond to the
user but, simultaneously,
print to the output screen
here HTTP 1.1, 200 OK
to confirm what we're putting in
the return envelope, so to speak,
that we're sending back to the user.
>> And so what's going on here is
that in the terminal window,
we're running the web
server, and, therefore, it's
listening for HTTP
requests on TCP port 8080.
Meanwhile, in my web browser,
as I click through each
of those files, or even input my
name David, and then click Submit,
that is my browser
talking to the web server.
And what the web server's doing,
then, in that terminal window
is showing me exactly
the first line that's
been received in a virtual
envelope and exactly
the first line that's being
responded with to that web client.