>> SAM GREEN: Hi, everyone.
Welcome to our seminar.
My name is Sam.
HUGH ZABRISKIE: I'm Hugh.
SAM GREEN: And we're going to talk today
about JavaScript and the Web Audio API.
Just to start out, this is an outline
of our agenda for the seminar.
We're going to start by talking about
why you should be interested in the Web
Audio API, why is JavaScript
the language you need for it,
and then talk about JavaScript
essentials-- so like,
walk you through some
basics of the language,
and then talk about the
audio API at a high level.
Then, Hugh will talk about some
of the stages of audio production
and then demo this awesome sequencer
project he built and show you the code.
And then, we'll have time for
questions at the end for people
who are here live.
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: Cool.
>> SAM GREEN: Cool.
I will back up.
>> SAM GREEN: So, first things first.
So one of the great things
about the Web Audio API
is that there's no set up required.
It comes built-in to
most modern browsers,
including Chrome, Edge, a whole
bunch of others-- all the ones
that large portions of
people are using today.
So there's no set up,
aside from just getting
a web server going, for
you to get started working
on your project, which is great.
>> We recommend pretty
heavily that you consider
using Chrome for
JavaScript web development,
just because its developer
tools are really strong.
As an example of just what we mean
by saying open up your JavaScript
console-- if you go into Chrome
and you look at any web page,
and you left click
Inspect Element, and then
you go to this little drop-down
right here and you click on Console,
you'll see what opens up looks a
lot like a command prompt that you
might see on your Mac, or on the ID.
And just like that, we can
type commands here, like Clear,
and other commands like that.
We can create variables, as
we'll see later in JavaScript.
And so anything we can do in
JavaScript, we can do with the console,
and that's a super handy way to
start playing around with APIs
and getting comfortable with
JavaScript right off the bat.
No set up required,
which is really nice.
Cool.
Awesome.
>> So just one more thing to add.
If you have any questions-- there are
many of you who are not here live,
feel free to email us-- these
are our email addresses.
If you have questions
you don't want to ask us,
like, oh I have a bug
in my code, or something
that's a little more specific,
maybe Google it first.
There are a lot of great resources
about the Web Audio API out there.
It's really well
documented and it's being
used by a ton of people in
industry, and people who are just
building fun stuff for themselves.
So there should be a lot
of resources out there.
Awesome.
>> Cool, so why the Web Audio API?
This diagram is a little bit
of an evolution of the way
sound on the web has grown over time.
Bgsound was like the original HTML tag
that Internet Explorer used to support.
It only allowed for pretty basic sounds,
the functionality wasn't very robust,
and you couldn't do
complicated sequencing,
or control when sound started
and stopped very robustly.
So, it wasn't particularly
well developed.
Then after that, Flash
came along-- which,
I'm sure that you guys are all familiar
with Flash-- maybe not how it works,
but you've certainly seen it.
You've got to update your Flash
Plug-in, all that kind of stuff,
and that certainly extended the range
of functionality that was available.
But making the user install
a plug-in is definitely
a drawback to including Flash
in your application, right?
Because then you're dependent on the
user going and finding this plug-in,
and probably being turned
off by this extra step
they have to take to use your app.
And then there could be an update
that'll break your whole application,
and it ends up being a nightmare
for the developer, too.
So that was a barricade.
>> And then after that came along,
the HTML audio tag, which
is a feature of more modern HTML-- which
certainly allowed for a lot more stuff,
but even the things you could do
there were a little bit limited just
as a result of the things
that HTML was capable of.
So when the JavaScript
API, the Web Audio API,
became a standard
practice across browsers,
that really broadened the set
of opportunities for developers
to really get into building
cool stuff for the web.
For a long time there had
been really robust tools
for native audio applications,
like-- everyone knows GarageBand,
and then obviously there are more
professional audio mixing applications,
and that kind of stuff.
But there wasn't a
really good Cloud-- not
Cloud, yeah, I guess
Cloud-- web-based platform
that would allow developers to
build applications for people
to do audio mixing.
And as he will show you
later, the Web Audio API
allows for really powerful
stuff to happen really simply,
which is pretty cool.
So that's the instruction to why you
should watch the rest of the seminar,
basically.
>> And now, I'm going to talk about
some JavaScript-- just basic elements
of the language, so that
we can be on the same page
when we talk about the
API a little bit later.
Cool.
>> So, this is a summary.
I forgot this was here.
Yeah.
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: There's two slides here.
>> SAM GREEN: This is the summary
of some of the limitations
of the other binding, old methods.
And then now, we have these things.
Cool.
Awesome.
>> So, JavaScript essentials.
First things first, there's a
pretty significant difference
in JavaScript versus in a
language like C, in the way
that variables are created.
So in C, we're used to having
to type our variables, right?
And I don't mean type like
type them in, I mean type
like assign them a type-- meaning
like, an int, a float, a char.
In C, we were really used to
having to create a variable
and then stick to that type for the
entire time that we use that variable.
And that isn't necessarily worse,
but it's probably harder to use.
One of the cool features
of JavaScript is
that variables are what's called
"dynamically typed," which
means that I can create a
variable with that syntax,
varX equals 5, for example.
That originally creates
an integer variable--
right underneath the
hood somewhere-- but I
can change that variable
to refer to a string
without doing anything like
creating a new variable.
I don't need to worry
about the type changing.
JavaScript knows that the type's
changed, and that happens dynamically.
>> So, there are benefits
and drawbacks to that,
as anyone who's worked in
JavaScript for a while might know.
There are times when
you might accidentally
change the type of a variable and
not handle that type changing,
and then your JavaScript
can crash-- or an exception
be thrown, because you'll have the
wrong type when you expect one type.
Cool.
>> So, scoping-- which is like, if we
remember the early weeks in the course,
refers to how visible a variable
is and in what area of the code.
All of that looks very similar
to the way it looks in C.
So variables are scoped generally
within curly braces within a function,
and then there are also
globally-scoped variables that
are-- if you write a variable
outside of a function,
it will be visible in the entire text.
>> One difference between
JavaScript and C in particular,
is that if you declare a global
variable anywhere in a text file
it's visible in any function
within that text file.
That's correct, right?
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: Yep.
>> SAM GREEN: So that's also a little
bit funky in comparison to C,
where we always had to have our
variable definitions above the places
they were used.
That's not a rule that's enforced
anymore, so, a little bit different.
And again just to reemphasize,
global versus local variables--
very similar to C. You could have
two variables with the same name,
and have one of their names be shadowed
by a local variable if one of them
was global.
So, similar kind of
problems that some of you
may have run into in some
of your problem sets so far.
Cool, so that's variables.
>> Control flow, meaning like,
if-else-- logical stuff-- and loops.
So to start with, this is what if-else
statements look like in JavaScript.
The placement of the various things
on the lines isn't important.
This is just one of the conventions
for the way we structure code.
Just like in C, we have an
"if," a parenthesis statement.
That's not what I meant to do.
I did it again.
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: Trying to exit?
SAM GREEN: No, I'm
just trying to zoom in.
It doesn't matter.
>> So, we have an "if" statement and
we have a condition inside of it
that evaluates to true or false,
and that determines whether or not
we enter that block of code.
And likewise, we have an else-if, and
an else, just like we're used to in C.
>> You also should be pretty comfortable
right off the bat with loops,
because they also look
a lot like C looks.
But you'll notice again that we
have, instead of int initializations,
we have var initializations.
And I guess you have
to be careful to make
sure you don't change the value
of I from an int to a string,
for example, because that's going to
cause weird behavior you might not
expect.
But this should look
pretty familiar, as well.
>> So this is where things start to
get a little bit crazy in JavaScript
for someone who is going from a
background of C. There are functions
in JavaScript, and there's one way
to declare a function that looks
sort of similar to C, and
then there's another one that
looks kind of different.
>> The first version,
which we can see here,
is kind of C-like, where
we say, this is a function,
give it a name, give
the number of arguments,
and then the contents of the function
go inside those curly braces.
We'll see an example of
arguments in just a second.
>> Whereas on the next line, we see, oh,
here's a variable called "myFunction,"
and we equal it to this
generic thing-- function-- that
doesn't seem to have anything going on.
The reason that's different
than C is that JavaScript
is what's called a functional language,
or has functional elements, which means
that functions are actually values.
And that means that we can set
a variable to equal a function
and then move that function
around, pass it as an argument,
do all kinds of stuff
like that with functions.
>> One other thing to note--
functions are written
with a certain number of arguments.
We'll see an example of a function
with an argument on the next slide.
But JavaScript won't
yell at you if you try
to use a function with the
wrong number of arguments.
It'll just do its best to make
do, meaning that if you pass,
you call a function that expects an
argument with no argument, all that
will happen is it'll do its best
to try and execute that code,
and if it eventually runs
into an exception or an error,
it'll throw that exception and just keep
going-- which is just one of the ways
that JavaScript works.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: What happens if
there's too many arguments?
SAM GREEN: So the
question was, what happens
if there are too many arguments?
And the answer is that
JavaScript will just
ignore the ones that are
after the ones it expects.
It'll try to execute the function
call as if it was just the first two.
Right?
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: That's right, yeah.
Similarly, if there
are too few arguments,
it just kind of gives null to all the
arguments it doesn't have any values
for.
>> SAM GREEN: Which can
actually be handy, if you
want to write a function that
takes a variable number arguments.
You can set default values in
the definition of the function,
and it can ignore the fact
that the input's not there.
So I want to talk a little bit
more about this last bullet
point, which is functions are values.
This is an example that is
a little bit mind-blowing
if you just read it, and don't think
about what's going on for a second.
So, let's look just at
the first line here.
We have this variable, f1, that we say
is a function that does this thing.
And the contents of the function
are console.log('hello').
You can think of console.log as the
JavaScript equivalent of printf.
So what will happen is, if we
run this code in our browser,
it'll print out a string.
I can demonstrate that.
AUDIENCE: By log, though, does that
mean it's being recorded somewhere?
SAM GREEN: Yeah.
So I'll show you what's going to happen.
So the question was, what does log mean?
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: So console.log
is like printf for C.
SAM GREEN: So console.log
is like printf,
so if I have this console.log('hello'),
and I call that, the string "hello"
gets printed out to the console.
This is the console.
It's just like printf, where
it prints to standard out.
And we'll see in a minute,
but this is actually
referring to the console object,
and calling a method on that object.
That'll make more sense
in a minute when we
get to talking about
objects in JavaScript,
but I thought I would just mention that.
HUGH ZABRISKIE: We're
used to in C, right--
we usually write a big program
in main to do anything.
But what's cool in JavaScript is you
have this kind of interpreter that
runs in real time, so it
takes just line by line,
it can just interpret that on the spot.
And it keeps track of
things that have run before,
so it's a pretty useful tool to
use console.log, or the console,
generally, for just playing
around with JavaScript.
>> SAM GREEN: So going back to this
example-- the second line of code
here is pretty mind-boggling in my head.
The first time I read this,
it was like, what's going on?
So what's happening is, this
function declaration says,
I have a function called f2
that's expecting one argument, f,
and then it calls that
function, f, which
was passed to it as an argument
with no arguments itself.
So, that might have been confusing.
If we understand this as f2 takes f1
as an argument, and then inside of f2,
f gets called-- which means
that this line of code,
after these two lines of
code, results in "hello"
being printed to the console.
>> The fact that we can pass
functions around as values
ends up being one of the most
powerful features of JavaScript
as a programming language.
Outside of all of the
awesome things it can do,
just as a feature of the
language in terms of the way
that it makes things easy
to program and allows
for things that aren't particularly
well-suited to the web,
functional programming and functional
programming aspects of JavaScript
is one of the most
powerful concepts that
exists in JavaScript-- if you ask me.
Cool.
>> So, next thing.
In addition to being functional,
there are also elements of JavaScript
that are object-oriented,
which is one of the very
popular buzz words in computer science.
Object-oriented programming
is a really popular thing.
JavaScript has a version of that,
where I believe every value is also
an object, which means that every object
wraps together some number of values.
So for values that are simple, like
an integer, like varX equals 5,
that object just wraps that one value.
>> But we can also imagine a situation
where-- we can think of situations in C
where we wanted to do
something with structs,
for example, that wraps several
values together and makes
it really easy to pass things around.
That's when an object is in JavaScript.
>> It's important to remember
when I say that objects wrapped
some number of values together,
that functions are also
values, which means that functions can
also be inside of a JavaScript object.
And the reason that's important
is that, whereas we often
think of calling a method
on an object that's
of a popular term from other
popular object-oriented languages,
one of the differences here is that
all that a method is in JavaScript
is a value stored inside of an object
that performs some action-- possibly
using the other values that are inside
of that object, but not necessarily.
So you can imagine a situation, I
guess in a little bit of a crazy way,
where you called a method of one
object on another object, for example.
So, it's a little bit funky in that way.
>> And you can also change the methods
that are associated with an object
by assigning that method a
new function, which is also
pretty different from other
object-oriented languages, where
once we declare an object
and instantiate it,
we can't change the methods that are
associated with that object anymore.
So that's pretty different.
Cool.
>> So here's an example, first,
of an object in action.
This is what's called
a generic object, which
means that it doesn't have any
particular name, doesn't have a class,
it's just some wrapping of values.
And the way that looks is, we have
this outer pair of curly braces here
that indicate to JavaScript
and say, this is an object.
The values inside of it
are each values inside
of the object that should
be wrapped together.
And inside of that object,
we then have key value pairs,
where the key refers to the name
of the value inside of the object,
and the other side--
opposite the colon here--
is the actual value
that should be stored.
>> So you see here that we have a
key called fn with value sam,
followed by a comma,
saying onto the next entry.
Then a key called ln,
with a value of green,
followed by a comma,
followed by "print,"
which is going to have a function value
that is going to do this line of code.
Let's take a step back and
unpack what's going on here.
So this is a little bit complicated,
and we're seeing something new
for the first time.
The "this" keyword is the new thing
we're seeing here, and what this does
is, refers to the current
object in scope, right?
So when we say, this
points all the way back
to this entire object--
when we do this.fn,
we're going to go all the way back
to this object, go to the fn value
and get sam, pull it all the way
back, stick it here, and then move on.
>> AUDIENCE: So with the retrieval, is
that done because of the parameter
definition?
SAM GREEN: So the question was, is the
retrieval done because of the parameter
definition?
Yeah, absolutely.
What's going to happen here is,
this dot says to the JavaScript,
OK, I'm getting some value
from this object from myself.
And then it'll look for an entry
called fn, and if it finds it,
it'll return that value-- so, it's sam.
But I could also have typed
something that was not defined here,
and then it would just
return undefined-- which
is a thing that JavaScript can
do, which can have benefits,
but it's also-- if you make a typo,
it can result in weird errors.
So it'll just try to find
whatever you tell it to find
and it's not going to
complain if doesn't find it.
It'll just say, I didn't
find it, and then move on.
So it would be undefined,
plus blank, plus last name.
Yeah.
And then we can see that if we
could then go down and access--
and we call tf.print() with parentheses.
It's going to call that print
function with no arguments, right?
But if we just said tf.print()
semicolon, without the parentheses,
all that would have done is pull
out the function from the value,
but not actually called it.
Cool.
HUGH ZABRISKIE: Should
we make an object?
SAM GREEN: Sure, let's do that.
So I can move this
example to the console.
We can imagine that I have an object.
So this is a simple object.
This is an object that contains two
values with two keys, two key value
pairs.
So I can then access the value stored
inside of this object by doing x.x1,
for example, and I get 1 back.
Likewise, x.x2, get that value back.
>> And now the really cool thing is, I can
actually add something to this object
after I've created it.
So you can imagine, let's
say I have a function.
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: You
have to do Shift-Enter.
>> SAM GREEN: Oh, that's annoying.
What did it not like?
Oh.
Here we go.
Cool.
>> So I've just created
this function, f, that
is going to go to the current
object and print this.x1.
So if I just call f by
itself, nothing's going
to happen, right, because there is no x1
field in the object it's referring to.
But, if I say, x.f = f, and then I
call x.f(), I'm going to get back 1.
That f function is now
associated with the object x,
which has a key called x1
associated with the value 1,
so when we call this.x1, it's
going to find what it's looking for
and be able to print a value out.
So that's just one example
of kind of the crazy things
you can do with objects in JavaScript.
>> So that version was the
generic version, meaning
that we've created an object using this
parentheses notation-- brace notation,
rather-- and that's
handy if we just want
one instance of a particular object, but
what if we want to have more than one
of the same kind?
And the answer to that
question is, there are things
called classes in JavaScript as well.
We can create a function that
does some sort of initialization
for a foreign object,
and we'd say, like,
my class-- so the name
of the reusable object--
equals function that sets it up.
So what this would be equivalent
to is creating an object that
would be just like,
curly brace, str, colon,
this is a string,
semicolon, curly brace.
That would be the generic
object we initialize,
with the one difference being on the
next lines we create a prototype, which
means it's a default key that
we add to our object that
has the value listed here.
Meaning that, when I create a new
instance of this MyClass object,
it's going to have pre-built inside of
it a value called str and another value
called myPrint, which is
going to be a function.
Awesome.
>> Great.
So the last thing to
say about JavaScript
is that it's really useful for what
are called asynchronous operations.
Asynchronous means is that we
can wait for some operation
to complete before we move
on, but move on while we wait
and then have something happen later on.
And what I mean by that is, you
can imagine a situation where
you send a request to
some web server somewhere,
and it's going to to send you back
some big chunk of data, right?
And your user could wait in the
meantime for that to happen,
and nothing could be
going on at that time.
But that's not a great design, right?
You don't want the web page to freeze.
What if the user wants to
click on a drop-down menu?
It's not a great design pattern.
Instead, basically what
JavaScript does is says,
OK, do this operation asynchronously.
So like, wait in the background,
and then when the operation is done,
call the callback function--
call some function,
do some action-- to signal that the
operation we were waiting for to end
is over.
And the reason that's super powerful is,
we can do something, pass an argument,
do something, and then wait
for something to happen.
Then, once that something
completes, we can call a callback.
That's really handy because it lets
us do things with Web Audio API,
for example, like load an
audio file from a remote server
without having to wait for the
entire audio file to be loaded,
which would be really
bad for user experience.
Cool.
>> Last couple notes about
debugging, since this
is a thing you're going to have to do
as part of your project, guaranteed.
I mentioned the JavaScript console.
It's a super useful feature
of all modern browsers,
And we really encourage you to get
comfortable using your console,
if you want to get good at JavaScript.
It's super handy for
debugging, but it's also
really useful for figuring
out how to use an API.
It allows for really
easy experimentation
without having to type some
code, and then compile it.
You don't have to do all those steps.
You can just write
some code into a line,
and then get immediate feedback on
whether or not that line of code
worked-- very handy.
>> And also, just one technical note--
the JavaScript console is an example
of a REPL-- so that's R-E-P-L, REPL,
which stands for read, evaluate,
print loop.
You're going to type some stuff
in, it'll read what you typed in,
it'll evaluate it, and it'll print the
output, and then it'll start again.
That allows you to rapidly go in
circles iterating, which is really cool.
>> I guess real last note-- this
is the actual last note, yes.
How do we actually use JavaScript?
So first, we can import
it using a script tag
at the top or bottom of an HTML file--
anywhere inside of an HTML file,
really.
And within a script tag, there are
two sub-ways of importing JavaScript.
The first is by having a
separate JavaScript file
that we import in its entirety, or
by having an area of code like script
to start, and then
backslash script to end.
And then we just write
JavaScript inside the HTML file.
Those are the two ways.
You can't have it inside of HTML.
AUDIENCE: Is one better than the other?
SAM GREEN: The question was,
is one better than the other.
So, yes, as a coding style practice,
and also it's like a design practice.
There are two reasons
why it might be better.
The first is, it makes your code a
lot more readable if all of your HTML
is in one place, all of your CSS is in
another place, all of your JavaScript
is in a third place.
Right?
I think we should have already talked
about it in sections-- like CSS-- what
that is-- and it goes
often in another file.
So, similar kind of concept here.
You can also imagine that JavaScript
would be reused on more than one
HTML page, or perhaps a
great many HTML pages,
and having that JavaScript
refactored into one
file that you can import
into more than one place
allows the code to be
way more maintainable.
You can imagine making one
change to the JavaScript
and having to change it
in 100 different files.
And instead we can just change it
in one, which is way more powerful.
Did I answer your question?
Cool.
>> We can also type into the console,
as we've mentioned before.
And again, one last note--
Web Audio is built in,
you don't need to load anything.
Cool.
Are there any questions, do you have
any more questions about JavaScript,
before we move on?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SAM GREEN: All right, cool.
So now he's going to talk about the API.
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: Cool.
Thanks, Sam.
>> SAM GREEN: Sure.
HUGH ZABRISKIE: Awesome, so
we'll move on from JavaScript.
So we've talked about some of
the essentials of JavaScript,
and those are the variables, functions,
objects, functions as variables,
asynchronous loading.
These are all things that you'll
see as you use the Web Audio.
So we're just going to talk
about it first at a high level.
>> It's an API, so it's something
that's built, as Sam said,
right into the JavaScript
that you use in the console.
And it's actually just like C++ code
that is really built into Chrome
and Firefox, and all of these browsers.
So the main idea with Web
Audio is that you have
this kind of pipeline of audio, right?
So your audio data
comes in in some form.
>> There are kind of three main forms--
you have the oscillator, which
creates a sine wave, cosine wave,
we're going to see how that works.
Another very common one,
of course, is an MP3.
So maybe you start with
a song, and then you
want to do some filtering
to that and output
that-- that could be a possible source.
And then a really cool
one is the microphone.
So you can use some very
basic calls in JavaScript
to get access to the
microphone, and so if you
wanted to make an app
like a pitch detector,
for example, that takes in
your voice and figures out
the pitch-- very easy way to that.
You can just kind of read it
in, figure out the frequency,
and then output a number.
So we'll see how that works, as well.
>> The destination is basically
where the audio data is output.
So generally, that's like
your laptop speakers.
Other options are like
a ScriptProcessorNode--
we'll get to nodes in a
second-- but basically,
either you're putting sound out
through your computer through speakers,
or you're kind of recording it, so
you're storing it as audio data.
So maybe if someone creates
music in your app and then
you want to record that and maybe like
export it to SoundCloud, for example--
that would be one way to do that.
All the fun stuff,
which we'll talk about,
happens between these two points,
where we load in the music
and then output it.
>> So I'm going to talk about the five
stages of audio production in a second.
We have this thing called
an AudioContext, which
is this little wrapper we see here.
Basically what AudioContext is-- if we
go to the JavaScript console right now,
we can create one right now.
Just an example of REPL, right?
We're reading,
evaluating, and it prints.
>> AudioContext is a global state.
It's a struct, it's an object
here, and it keeps information
about things that are going on
on the screen related to audio.
One example is the current time.
This tells you the number
of seconds, very precisely,
since the web page loaded.
So this is a really useful
little property that you can use.
It's read only-- I think actually
you can try to set it a value.
It'll tell you set it,
and then if you print it
again-- it didn't actually quite work.
So there are read-only
properties in JavaScript.
This is really useful if
you're kind of syncing
a lot of different
information, when you're
kind of playing different sounds.
>> Another really useful one
is the context destination.
Definitely, if you're interested, be
trying this at your own console right
now.
So this is an AudioDestinationNode.
Basically what this says is,
where is the output going?
So there are two real options here.
Usually the default
is just your speakers,
so AudioDestinationNode
basically just says
there are zero outputs to the sound
coming in, sent to the speaker.
So generally, you don't
have to play with that.
If you're interested in actually using
the ScriptProcessorNode for recording,
definitely shoot me an
email later because that's
a little more complicated.
But generally, you're just kind
of outputting sound in some form.
So cool, we'll jump back here.
AUDIENCE: I'm sorry.
HUGH ZABRISKIE: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: I know you said to talk
to you later about recording.
Can you interface that with Pro Tools?
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: With Pro Tools?
Let's see.
I don't think so.
So going between the client,
which is the JavaScript
console, and your actual
computer, is generally
something that's kind
of off limits, if you
will, kind by the nature of the--
it's kind of a design thing,
but you try to keep the browser separate
from the user's actual computer.
Generally, the only thing you're able to
access is the microphone or the camera.
You're not able to, I
don't think, use Pro Tools.
However, if you created
a track in Pro Tools,
exported that, you could load that
in here, filter it, for example,
process that, and record that into an
Audio Destination-- or, no-- a Sphere
Processor Node.
And then from there, you could
export that to SoundCloud, you
could send it in an email, or
whatever you like from there.
>> But there is kind of a slight barrier
between making music on your computer
and making music online.
>> SAM GREEN: And that's
not unique to this API.
It's a security feature of Chrome, and
I think every other modern browser.
The browser is self-contained.
So for example, a web page can't
use JavaScript to turn the sound
on on your speakers, for example.
Or it can't turn your computer off.
And there is no intermediate point
between those two things, right,
so either you have a
complete abstraction,
or you open up the
security flaw of letting
a programmer with bad intentions do
whatever they want with your laptop.
And that's why Chrome is self-contained.
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: Yeah.
Does that make sense?
Cool, cool.
I was just going to
show an example of one.
This is pretty much as
far as you get, in terms
of accessing the user's computer.
If you have a USB keyboard plugged in,
you can use something called the Web
MIDI API, which we won't
really talk about here,
but this is another API that's
built into at least Chrome-- again,
this is why we love Chrome--
I think Firefox or Safari,
this is an easy thing to
google-- different browsers have
different support for which
APIs they have implemented.
But if you wanted to plug in a keyboard
and work with that information,
kind of send the keyboard
information over to the computer
and then use that online, this API
is where you'd be working that.
>> Cool.
OK.
So, quickly moving on here.
How are we doing on time?
>> SPEAKER 1: About 15.
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: 15 minutes left?
OK, cool.
So we'll race ahead here.
>> So basically, the main point of
thinking of this as a pipeline
is that each step in the pipeline
is a series of audio nodes.
Our source, let's say, is an oscillator.
We need to create an oscillator node.
And that is just kind
of the little function--
and they're all based out
of the audio context here.
>> AUDIENCE: When it said
oscillator, does that mean
it's actually literally going from
two different poles back and forth?
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: No, it's like
a digital representation.
It's actually implemented in C++.
I actually don't know the specs
of how it's actually implemented,
but all this is working as binary data.
Actually, yeah.
That would be saying, I could
actually, if you're interested,
I could send you a little more
information about how waveforms
are kept having a digital format.
OK, cool.
>> So we're generating a tone like a sine
wave or something like that, maybe
440 Hertz.
We create an oscillator.
If we want to set the volume, we
connect anything to a GainNode,
which we could do with .creategain.
That sets your volume.
You can pass that onto any
of the other options-- well,
so an audio buffer source
node is where you might
store an MP3 that you've loaded in.
>> Biquad filter is for filtering if
you want to take all the base out
of a song, or something like that.
God forbid you want to take
the base out of a song.
And AudioDestination node is, again,
like where our finalization is.
If you're ever interested in seeing
all the different possible options,
just go to the tab and let
the auto-complete come up.
And if you do create, you'll see all the
different things that you can create.
You can create dynamic
script processors,
I don't even know what that
is, for mixing channel mergers
and channel splitters and all that.
Cool.
>> So this is just an
example of a pipeline.
So we have three sources coming in.
Maybe these are waveforms,
maybe these are MP3s.
One's going through a
filter, another one's
getting distorted another
one's panning left and right.
You can do all sorts of things and
they all get mixed around together,
and then out comes the audio
at the end, as destination.
This is an example of what more
complicated Web Audio code looks like.
You're creating all these
different objects right here--
I'm not sure of this.
No, it doesn't zoom in.
OK.
>> SAM GREEN: You do Control, Scroll-Up.
HUGH ZABRISKIE: Control Scroll--
SAM GREEN: No, no.
Control--
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: Oh, Control, Scroll?
Oh, gotcha.
Yeah.
Wow, nope, nope.
OK.
I will not do that.
>> So yeah, in this first
section here, you see
we're creating all these different
nodes out of the context.
We're just piecing them
together in the second part
by this function called Connect.
That's a really key
function in Web Audio.
It just means once you've done
something with the sound in one node,
pass it on to the next node.
So we have the source, it
connects to the analyzer,
the analyzer does something with it,
it goes to distortion, and so on,
and to the destination
at the bottom right here.
Cool.
OK, so we'll keep moving on.
>> The pipeline-- again, these
are the most common pipelines,
so we talk about all these things like
distortion, panning, all this stuff.
If you're really interested
in using things Pro Tools,
those probably interest you.
If not, maybe you just
want to play the sound,
or maybe you just want to
set the volume on the sound.
Those are the two most common sort
of pipelines in audio production.
>> Again, the ways you can take it
in as an oscillator-- so, let's
do a the demo of that right here.
So we're going to create a
simple audio context here,
and from that we're going
to create our oscillator.
So that is, again, we're just
going to call Create Oscillator.
We're going to set a frequency on
that, 440 Hertz, everyone's favorite.
Then we connect that to the destination
point-- which is the speaker, so
the context destination.
Finally, we just say, start zero
seconds from now, and do we have sound?
>> [RINGING]
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: Here we go.
It's just a sine wave.
OK, cool.
And then we'll stop that.
>> AUDIENCE: Where did
that feedback come from?
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: The feedback?
Oh, probably our microphones.
So yeah, that's how you do it.
And actually, if I had
kept it running, you
could have the frequency
value as it's running,
so that's a fun thing to play around.
Cool.
That's always a lovely one to present.
>> SAM GREEN: We didn't
think about that, did we?
HUGH ZABRISKIE: Yeah,
that's a nasty one.
So, buffer loading-- I'll show an
example of that at the very end.
That's loading an MP3.
And microphone, you use just a function
called Navigator.getUserMedia()
to request access to the user's
microphone for that information.
>> Here's filtering, I'll
just keep moving from this.
This is pretty high level,
but filters just allow you to
>> [BEEPING]
Filtering also allows you
to create things like pink
noise, brown noise, white noise.
If you want to create pure noise, which
some people love to mess around with,
you can use Web Audio
filtering to do that.
>> Audio Panning-- so imagine
if you're writing a game
and you want the sound to
sound like it's coming, like,
shooting across the screen, you
can use the panning of the audio
to create this kind of cone,
which like-- it's pretty mathy,
but it's actually really
cool if you get it work,
and there's some good
tutorials on it I can send you.
Basically, you can kind
of create the sound
of something going by in a 3D way.
And if you have a DJ interest, you can
start mixing and cross fading songs.
>> This is just some very basic
code, basically what I did before.
This sets the volume of the
oscillator, so we create our oscillator
which creates the waveform.
We create our GainNode,
set our frequency,
and then connect the oscillator to the
GainNode, which then basically changes
how much signal is allowed through.
But really, it's a digital
thing, so it's more just-- yeah.
That's not what's actually happening,
but that's what happens in real life
with a gain.
>> AUDIENCE: --quantization
of the volume parameter?
HUGH ZABRISKIE: Sorry?
AUDIENCE: Is it a
quantized volume parameter?
HUGH ZABRISKIE: Yeah.
And this is one thing I'm really
deficient on in my knowledge,
how gain works on a digital level.
I know with actual
signals, it's basically
controlling how much you're
amplifying the signal.
So, yeah.
I'll send you more information about
that, because I'd be curious actually
to know more about that.
But basically the parameters
are, one is the fold--
the louder signal-- and zero is no
signal, or you won't hear any sound.
We'll skip demo time for that because
it's basically what I did before.
And again, the Context.Destination
is the audio destination node.
Awesome, OK.
>> So I'm going to do a quick two demos.
How are we doing on time?
>> SPEAKER 1: About 10 minutes.
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: 10 minutes?
Great!
Awesome.
>> So the first one I'm going to
do, it's called My Favorite Song.
So this is just a
little HTML JavaScript.
We're going to have two buttons
on the page play my favorite song
and stop my favorite song.
I'll change this.
>> AUDIENCE: Cover your microphone.
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: Yeah.
And I've loaded in here
a script that basically--
and this is really useful
for loading an MP3,
so this just makes
loading MP3s way faster.
It's basically just a wrapper.
It just makes the process of
loading in MP3s much faster,
otherwise you're using HTTP request,
kind of like what we were doing
on the current piece set with Server.
It's really ugly, you
don't want to do it.
>> So this guy, Boris Smus, wrote a really
useful little tool called BufferLoader.
All you do is simply pass it the
context, you pass it a list--
or, yeah, is it a list in JavaScript?
SAM GREEN: An array.
HUGH ZABRISKIE: Oh, it is
an array, that's right.
It's an array of paths
to different files.
And then you pass it a function.
This is the callback we were talking
about with asynchronous loading.
That will be called
once the files loaded.
And that function that is called when
the file's loaded takes as a perimeter
an array of loaded buffers.
So that occurs here.
Basically, BufferList is
going to be one value--
or it's going to be an array of
length one, that has in it in index
zero the entire loaded file of the MP3.
So what I do when I finish
loading is, I simply
create a buffer source, which
is an audio buffer source node.
The next step is I load in the
source.buffer as the full loaded buffer
from the BufferList--
it's a lot of buffers--
and then you connect that audio
buffer to the destination.
So what it's going to do
is just simply put the MP3
straight through to the output,
and start it immediately
upon getting this call.
>> Cool, so let's see
this happen in action.
My [INAUDIBLE] here, let's see.
So I'm just going to
start a basic server.
That's something that
you need to do if you're
making requests for loading files.
I'm going to start a basic server.
This is basically your entire
PSET right now in one line,
but it's just starting
a server on port 80/80.
So we go over here, we
going to load 80/80,
we're going to go to My Favorite Song.
So if I hit "Play my
favorite song" right now,
it's going to load my
favorite song and play it--
[MUSIC - THE EAGLES, "LIFE IN THE FAST
LANE"]
--which happens to be "Life in
the Fast Lane" by The Eagles.
Now, I could hit "Stop my
favorite song" and replay it.
>> [MUSIC - THE EAGLES, "LIFE IN THE FAST
LANE"]
>> And if I go over to console, because
I used a global variable over here
to keep track of this value, it actually
will now be recognized in the console.
So it auto-creates for me.
So that's what's playing right now,
and I can simply call source.stop()
on that.
Well, you know what?
Just so you guys have heard this
song-- you might recognize this song.
>> [MUSIC - RICK ASTLEY, "NEVER GONNA GIVE
YOU UP"]
[MUSIC - THE EAGLES, "LIFE IN THE FAST
LANE"]
We've now all been Rickrolled.
OK, great, moving on.
Cool.
So this is basically an example of
just how you could load an MP3 file--
[MUSIC - THE EAGLES, "LIFE IN THE FAST
LANE"]
--and play it, and stop and start it.
I could have done a lot more [INAUDIBLE]
>> The last one I'll do is,
I'll show you a [INAUDIBLE].
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> It's like, ogg.wave.mp3.
I think, if I remember correctly,
I've run into some issues with .m4a,
but I'm not sure about that.
I think mp3.wave--
>> [MUSIC - RICK ASTLEY, "NEVER GONNA GIVE
YOU UP"]
>> OK, great.
I shouldn't have said that.
Anyway, hello.
So we have this open.
So now all I do is, I basically created
a basic syntax for creating music.
So if I do something like, add g4
on 1 2, what that means is that,
add the piano note, G4,
which is the fourth G
up on the piano from the bottom.
So this is kind of MIDI speak,
so for those who are music based,
this is just MIDI notes.
>> AUDIENCE: That's the G
of the Middle C, right?
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: This is the G
above Middle C, that's right.
>> AUDIENCE: Above Middle C.
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: Yeah.
Actually, yes.
I think I actually made
it one [INAUDIBLE],
so this might be an octave above that.
So let's see.
If I hit Play--
[REPETITIVE PIANO NOTE]
--we're going to hear that.
The idea is that it operates
just like a command line would,
so if I go up and down
on my keyboard, you
can go back to previous
commands, which is pretty useful.
And below is my list of tracks,
which are all running on loop.
>> AUDIENCE: You were assuming the
88-key keyboard on that, right?
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: The question was,
am I assuming an 88-key keyboard,
and yes, I am.
What I did is I
basically took 88 samples
of the piano, one for each note.
And so every time you
hear a note from now on,
that is actually a loop that looks
like-- this is getting played on loop,
so for every note, this is running.
What happens is, I
create a buffer again,
I create a gain node to set the volume.
This just a really
complicated way of saying I
store the buffer in a source.buffer.
I give it the gain, I
connect it to the gain,
the gain is connected to the
output, and then I play it.
So that is kind of the process
of taking in a buffer source.
>> AUDIENCE: Can you actually take that
dry sound and make it wet [INAUDIBLE]?
>> HUGH ZABRISKIE: You can, yeah.
There's re-verb, there's
delay, distortion.
You can basically put anything in
between in that sandwich of-- well,
pipeline is a better metaphor,
but you can add anything in that.
Cool.
>> So I'll finish the demo
here to give you a sense
of just the sheer number of times you
can run that function all at once.
So I'm going to remove this.
I'm going to create a generator that--
basically what does-- this is really
kind of a complicated syntax-- but it's
going to generate notes on the fly,
and just start playing
them as it evaluates them.
[INTERPOSING PIANO]
>> So we can just make a little music here.
>> So what this command
does, for example, is
it takes those three notes for the
piano and then puts them on B3.
This syntax might make
a little more sense
to those who have a
music background here.
>> I can add a kick drum.
I can--
>> [INTERPOSING INSTRUMENTS]
>> --just play around with that.
>> So you can make--
[INTERPOSING INSTRUMENTS]
That one's a little more annoying.
>> So that randomly adds a dry cymbal
on every 16th note, with a 16%
[INAUDIBLE].
>> [INTERPOSING INSTRUMENTS]
>> Yeah, so the way this
works-- it's always in 4:4.
[INTERPOSING INSTRUMENTS]
>> Yeah, so the four quarters, and 16/8.
>> So on average, you get 60%
of hits on the 16th notes.
>> Anyways, this was just
kind of to show off
some of the things you could
build with the Web Audio API.
It's really powerful, it's really fast,
and you can make a lot of cool things
with it.
So again, any questions you have,
email myself-- Hugh-- or Sam,
and honestly, Google has
a ton of good resources.
Any last questions?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: So you can access
the built-in microphone.
What if you wanted to
use a better microphone?
HUGH ZABRISKIE: If you wanted
to use better microphone?
So again, this is part of the
abstraction between Chrome
and the rest of your computer.
Unless it's available through
an API, like Web MIDI API,
you could probably find some hacks,
but generally not as feasible.
>> SAM GREEN: You can also--
all the Chrome knows
is what your default microphone
is, and it accesses that.
So if you had a microphone you could
set as computer's default microphone,
you could access it that way
and it would probably work.
HUGH ZABRISKIE: That's a good point.
I've never tried that, but
you might be able to kind
of-- if you redirect the input speaker,
you might be able to do that, yeah.
>> Any last questions?
Cool.
Well thank you guys
so much for watching.
I'm Hugh.
SAM GREEN: I'm Sam.
HUGH ZABRISKIE: And this is CS50.