>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> SPEAKER 1: All right, this is CS50,
and this is the start of week four,
and as you may have heard or
read, the world has been ending.
Going all around the internet
has been knowledge and awareness
of a bug in a program, a
programming language called Bash.
This has been wonderfully branded
as Shellshock, or the Bash door,
but articles like these
have not been uncommon.
And in fact, many of them bring
back memories of Heartbleed,
which you may have noticed in the
press back this past spring, which
was similarly fairly dramatic.
Now of those of you here
today, how many of you have,
even if you don't understand what
it's all about, heard of Shellshock?
All right, and how many of you
have computers that are vulnerable?
OK, there should be far, far more hands
up right now, for reasons we shall see.
>> Let's take a look at what's
been going on in the media
and then explain it a bit
here for us technically.
>> SPEAKER 2: Security experts have
warned that a serious flaw could
be about to affect hundreds of
millions of the world's web users.
So what exactly is the bug that's been
dubbed Shellshock, and what does it do?
Well, Shellshock is also known as the
Bash bug, the software it exploits.
Hackers use the virus to scan vulnerable
systems running Linux and Unix
operating systems and then infect them.
Bash is a command line shell.
This lets users issue commands to launch
programs and features within software
by typing in text.
It's typically used by programmers, and
shouldn't be open to the wider world,
though Shellshock changes that.
>> Well, worringly, some analysts
warn it could be a bigger threat,
because Shellshock allows complete
control of an infected machine,
whereas Heartbleed only allowed
hackers to spy on computers.
It's so serious, it's
been rated a 10 out of 10
for severity by the National
Vulnerability Database.
2/3 of all web servers are at
risk, including some Mac computers.
Well, make sure you
patch your systems now.
Anyone hosting a website running
the affected operating systems
should take action as soon as possible.
Anyone who can afford it should look
to their monitoring and web application
firewalls to look out for any attacks.
SPEAKER 3: Worst thing
that could happen is
that somebody would write code that
would automatically go and scan
the internet and would affect
all of these computers.
And once they do that, well,
the worst thing they could do
is just delete everything,
or shut the sites down.
So we could see damage
from that point of view,
where we would have malicious people
who just decide to cause havoc
by bringing systems down or deleting
files, and things like that.
SPEAKER 2: Some say this is one
of the most difficult to measure
bugs in years, and it
may take weeks or even
months to determine its ultimate impact.
>> SPEAKER 1: So all of that is true,
but the funny thing is, almost all
of the imagery you just saw,
except for maybe the keyboard,
has nothing to do with
the bug whatsoever.
Servers and wires and so forth,
it's sort of tangentially related,
but at the core it's actually pretty
familiar what's going on here.
In fact, let me go into
our CS50 appliance.
Let me go ahead and maximize
the terminal window here.
And you guys have been using this,
or the embedded version thereof,
in gedit in order to write programs,
type commands, and so forth,
and this is actually, and has
been for weeks, Bash, B-A-S-H.
This is the Bourne-again shell,
which is just a fancy way of saying,
this is a program that has a
blinking prompt, effectively,
that sits there waiting
for input for you.
And it's the command
line interface via which
you guys have been running commands and
ultimately compiling and then running
programs.
>> But Bash is also a programming
language in the following sense.
You know that there are commands like
cd and ls and also clang and others,
but you can define your own commands
by implementing them in Bash.
Now we're not going to
go into great detail
as to Bash the programming language, but
know, for instance, that at the moment,
there's no command called "hello."
So it can be found in
one of these packages.
It's not installed on my computer.
Ask your administrator.
But if I want there to be a program
called "hello" in Bash or at my prompt,
I can actually use syntax that's
quite like C. It's not quite the same,
but it looks pretty similar to a
function, albeit missing some details.
Nothing seems to happen,
but now if I type "hello,"
you can actually write a
program, not in C, not in Java,
not in another programming
language, but in Bash itself.
>> Now the key here is that I wrote the
name I wanted to give this new command,
and the parentheses are also
symbolic of this being a function.
As an aside, you can also do fun
things, and in fact, even on Mac OS,
this is a program called Terminal.
It comes built into anyone's
computer that has a Mac in this room,
and you can do similar things in Mac
OS, but you can go more beyond that.
And this is a little tangential,
but it's kind of fun.
I was reminded this morning,
when thinking this through,
of a little game I used to play
with one of CS50's former TFs
whereby any time he would walk away from
his keyboard with his screen unlocked,
I would execute a command
like this-- "say hello."
And now any time he came back to his
keyboard after I cleared the screen
and he would sit down,
try to do some work,
list the contents of his directory--
>> [AUDIO PLAYBACK]
>> -Hello.
Hello.
>> SPEAKER 1: So, in fairness,
it wasn't actually "hello."
It was usually something
more akin to that--
[AUDIO PLAYBACK]
-Beep.
SPEAKER 1: --that I would--
so his computer would
swear at him any time he actually
sat down at his keyboard.
And very quickly he figured out
not to leave his screen unlocked.
But this suggests the sort
of stupid fun that you
can have with something like Bash.
But it's a little more
serious, to be sure, than that.
And in fact, this is one of the
most dangerous and long-lasting bugs
that has really hit the world globally.
This bug has been around
for some 20 years,
and you'll be struck in just a
moment by its relative simplicity.
>> So this is a representative
command that if you
own a Mac, literally right now
when you have your lid open,
you can try typing into that
program called Terminal.
Terminal is under
Applications Utilities--
for once, Windows users don't have to
worry about this particular threat--
but those of you with Macs can type
this into a window like I'll do here,
and if you do type
that into this program
called Terminal, like I'll do now,
if you see the word "vulnerable,"
your computer is
vulnerable to exploitation.
>> Now what does that actually mean?
And this is admittedly
some pretty crazy syntax,
but let's at least draw out
some of the interesting aspects.
So there's some syntax that looks
a little familiar, at least from C
and programming more generally.
I see some parentheses,
semicolons, curly braces, and such,
but it turns out that this
stupid thing here in yellow
is essentially a function
that does nothing.
The colon means do nothing, and the
semicolon means stop doing nothing.
So inside of these
curly braces, the fact
that I have an equal
sign to the left, this
is essentially creating
a command, or a variable,
called x, and assigning it
that yellow bit of code there.
That could be something like "echo
hello" or "say beep" or something
akin to that.
But notice if your eyes
wander further to the right,
there's more to this line than
just the end of that semicolon.
"Echo vulnerable," and then
beyond that there's even more.
Another semicolon, bash -c:.
>> So long story short,
this line of code is
sufficient for compelling
a computer that's
vulnerable to doing something
that you want it to do,
because there's a bug in Bash whereby
even though Bash was supposed to stop
reading lines of command right
there after the yellow text,
for a 20-plus year old bug,
Bash has actually been reading
beyond that semicolon and pretty
much doing what it is told.
>> So what's the implication
of that ultimately?
I just said "echo hello"
or "echo vulnerable,"
but what if you did something
actually malicious, like rm -rf *,
which you might not
have ever typed before,
and frankly you probably
shouldn't too soon,
because you can do a
lot of damage with it.
Why?
rm does what, of course?
Removes.
* means what?
All.
So it's a so-called
wild card, so it means
delete everything in
the current directory.
-r happens to mean recursive,
which means if what you're deleting
is a directory, and inside of there
is other files and other directories,
recursively dive into there
and delete all of that.
And -f is the worst of them all.
Anyone know what -f means here?
Force.
So force means, even
if this is a bad idea,
do it without prompting me
for further confirmation.
So, you know, we laugh at
this, but frankly, I probably
type this multiple times
a day, because the reality
is it's the fastest way to
delete a whole bunch of stuff.
But even I have done some damage.
>> But if you were to trick a computer
into defining some stupid variable
or function called x, but then
tricking the computer into executing
beyond the boundaries of that
function, beyond that semicolon,
you could indeed trick a computer
into executing something like rm -rf
or the Email command
or the Copy command.
Anything literally you can do with the
computer, whether it's deleting files,
creating files, spamming someone,
attacking some server remotely,
if you can express it
with a command, you
can trick a computer into doing that.
>> Now what's an example of
how you might do this?
Well, there's a lot of computers
on the internet running Bash.
All of us Mac users are among them.
A lot of Linux servers are among
them as well, and Unix servers.
Windows again gets
relatively off the hook
unless you've installed
special software.
Now a lot of servers, for
instance, run web servers,
and in fact Linux is perhaps the
most popular operating system
to run on computers on the internet
that are serving up web pages.
Now as we'll see later
in the semester, when
you send a request from
your browser-- Chrome,
Internet Explorer, whatever--
to a remote server,
it turns out that even though
you just typed www.example.com,
your browser is sending a message
that's a little more arcane, like this.
>> But notice a little something strange.
The first two lines
I've never seen before,
but they don't look
particularly threatening.
But notice what I've stolen
for the third line here.
If a bad guy were to send a message
like this from his or her computer
to a vulnerable Mac or a
vulnerable Linux server,
the funny thing is that Bash,
that simple little command prompt,
is omnipresent and is often
used to essentially execute
the contents of a
message that it receives.
And by that logic, you can
trick a web server, therefore,
by sending something like
User-Agent, which usually
is supposed to say the
name of your browser.
User-Agent Chrome, User-Agent Internet
Explorer, User-Agent Firefox, this
is just your browser's
way of identifying itself.
But if a bad guy very
cleverly says, mm-mm, I'm
not going to tell you
what my browser is,
I'm instead going to send you this
cryptic-looking thing with an rm -rf
* in it, you can literally trick a
vulnerable web server on the internet
into executing exactly that in
there for deleting all of the files.
And frankly, that's not
even the worst of it.
You can do anything.
You could start a distributed
denial of service attack
if you sent this message to
whole bunches of web servers
and then had them all descend, for
instance, on Harvard.edu servers,
and you can sort of bang
the heck out of them
by a network traffic that was
otherwise triggered by this bad guy.
>> So, long story short, almost
everyone in this room who owns a Mac
is vulnerable to this.
The silver lining is that unless you're
running a web server on your laptop,
and unless you've actually configured
it to allow something like SSH into it,
you're actually safe.
It's vulnerable, but there's no
one trying to get into your laptop,
so you can sort of rest assured.
However, Apple will soon
be updating a fix for this.
The world of Linux has already released
a number of fixes for Fedora and Ubuntu
and other versions of Linux, and indeed
if you run update 50 in the appliance,
even that too will be
updated and corrected.
But that too has not
really been vulnerable,
because unless you've
tinkered with the appliance
and made your laptop publicly
accessible on the internet, which is not
by default, you've
actually been fine because
of firewalling and other techniques.
>> But it's an extreme example of a bug
that we've lived for for literally 20
years, and who knows if someone
all this time has known about it?
And in fact, this is one of
the fundamental challenges
that we'll see later in the
semester about security,
is that just like in the real world,
the good guys are at the disadvantage.
To keep the bad guys out, we have to
make sure that every door is locked,
that every window is secure, that
every point of entry into a home
is secure to keep the bad guys out.
But what does the bad guy have to
do to actually compromise your home
and steal from you?
He or she just has to find one unlocked
door, one broken window, or something
along those lines, and it's the
same thing in computer security.
We can write millions of
lines of programming code
and spend hundreds or thousands
of hours trying to get it correct,
but if you make just one
mistake in correctness,
you can put the entire system and
indeed in this case, the entire internet
and world at risk.
>> So if you'd like to learn more
about this, go to this URL here.
There's no need for action
tonight unless you're
among those more comfortable that
have been running your own web
server, in which case you should,
in fact, update your software.
>> And this too is the title of
a speech, and now a paper,
that we've linked on the
course's website for today.
It was by a fellow
named Ken Thompson, who
was accepting a very famous
award in computer science,
and he gave this speech some years
ago, essentially on this same topic.
Asking folks the question,
should you really
trust, ultimately, the
software you've been given?
For instance, we all have
been writing programs,
and we've been compiling
them with Clang.
And to your knowledge, have you written
any programs for CS50 where there's
a back door of sorts, there's a way
that a bad guy, if running your program,
could take over your computer?
Probably not, right?
Mario, and Greedy, and Credit.
These are all pretty small programs.
You'd have to be pretty
bad if you actually
made your whole computer vulnerable
after writing 10 or 20 lines of code,
or at least unaware of some
of the security implications.
Now I say that facetiously,
but we're going to see today
and this week it's actually
really, really easy
to be bad and make even
short programs vulnerable.
>> But for now, at least, realize
that the question being asked here
is about Clang in a compiler.
Why have we been trusting Clang
for the past two or three weeks?
Who's to say that whoever wrote Clang
didn't have an "if" condition in there
that essentially injected some zeros
and ones into every program it compiles
that would let him or her access
your computer when you're asleep
and your laptop lid is open
and your computer is running?
Right?
We have this sort of honor system right
now where we trust that Clang is legit.
You trust that the appliance is legit.
You trust that literally every program
on your Mac or PC is trustworthy.
And as this simple bug suggests,
even if it's not malicious,
that's absolutely not
likely to be the case.
>> So you should be scared as hell.
Frankly, there's no simple
solution to this other
than a sort of societal awareness
of the increasing complexity
that we're building on top
of our computer systems,
and how increasingly vulnerable
we might very well be.
>> Now with that said, Breakout.
So Breakout is problem set three, and
Breakout is a game from yesteryear
that you might recall, but
for us in problem set three,
it allows us to take
things back up a notch
so that when we are writing programs,
even in a Terminal window like this,
we can actually run, ultimately,
graphical programs not
unlike those we had
access to in Scratch.
So this is the staff's
implementation of Breakout,
which is just this brick-breaking
game, that you move your paddle back
and forth, and you hit the ball
against those colored bricks up top.
So this is bringing us
sort of back to where
we were able to be very quickly
with Scratch, and now with C,
implementing our own
graphical user interfaces.
>> But more than that, this
problem set represents the first
in which we're giving
you a bunch of code.
And in fact, I bring explicit
attention to this, because especially
for those less comfortable, this
problem set, at least at first glance,
is going to feel like
we've taken it up a notch.
Because we've given you,
for some of the search
and sorting problems in the pset,
a bunch of code that we wrote,
and a couple of comments
that say "to do,"
where you have to fill in the blanks.
So not too scary, but
it's the first time
we're handing you code that you need to
first read, understand, and then add to
and complete it.
>> And then with Breakout,
we're going to do the same,
giving you a few dozen more lines
of code that, frankly, give you
a lot of the framework for
the game but stop short
of implementing the bricks
and the ball and the paddle,
but we do implement some other features.
And even that at first glance, again,
especially if less comfortable,
might seem particularly daunting and
you think there's so many new functions
you need to wrap your mind
around, and that's true.
But keep in mind, it's
quite like Scratch.
Odds are you didn't use all of
the puzzle pieces in Scratch.
Odds are you didn't care to wrap
your mind around all of them
because all it took was a
quick glance to understand, oh,
that's what I can do
with that puzzle piece.
And indeed, in problem set
3 spec, we'll point you
at the documentation that will
introduce you to some new functions,
and ultimately the programming
constructs you use.
Conditions, loops,
variables, and functions
will be identical to
what we've seen thus far.
>> So indeed, what we'll give
you is some sample code that
lets you create a window
that looks not unlike this,
and ultimately turn it into
something quite like this.
So take advantage of CS50,
discuss office hours and more,
and take comfort in the fact that
the amount of code you have to write
is actually not all that much.
The first challenge is just to acclimate
yourself to some code we've written.
>> Any questions on pset3,
Shellshock, or otherwise?
>> AUDIENCE: It seemed like
going through with Breakout
that the code is almost
an object-oriented style,
but I thought C was an
object-oriented program.
SPEAKER 1: An excellent question.
So in looking through the
distribution code, the code
we wrote for pset3,
for those familiar, it
looks like it's a
little object-oriented.
Short answer is, it is.
It's an approximation of how you
might do object-oriented code using
a language like C, but it is
still ultimately procedural.
There are no methods inside of
the variables, as you'll see.
But it is reminiscent of that.
And we'll see that feature again
when we get to PHP and JavaScript
toward the end the semester.
But for now, think of it as
a hint of what's to come.
Good question.
All right.
So merge sort was how we
left things last time.
And merge sort was cool in the
sense that it was so much faster,
at least based on the cursory tests
we did last week, than, say, bubble
sort, selection sort, insertion sort.
And what was neat too is just
how succinctly and cleanly
you can express it.
And what did we say it was an upper
bound on the running time of merge
sort?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: n log n?
>> SPEAKER 1: n log n, right. n log n.
And we'll come back to what that
really means or where that comes from,
but this was better
than what running time
that we saw for bubble
selection and insertion sort?
So n squared. n squared
is bigger than this,
and even if it's not quite obvious,
know that log n is smaller than n,
so if you do n times
something smaller than n,
it's going to be less than n squared.
It's a bit of intuition there.
But we paid a price for this.
It was faster, but a theme that started
to emerge last week was this tradeoff.
I got better performance
time wise, but what
did I have to spend on the other
hand, in order to achieve that?
>> AUDIENCE: Memory.
SPEAKER 1: Say again?
AUDIENCE: Memory.
SPEAKER 1: Memory, or
space more generally.
And it wasn't super
obvious with our humans,
but recall that our volunteers
were stepping forward and stepping
back as though there's an array
here, and as though there's
a second array here that
they could use, because we
needed someplace to merge those folks.
We couldn't just swap them in place.
So merge sort leverage
is more space, which
we didn't need with
the other algorithms,
but the upside is that it's much faster.
And frankly, in the real world space
these days-- RAM, hard disk space--
is relatively cheap, and so that's
not necessarily a bad thing.
>> So let's take a quick look, a little
more methodically, at what we did
and why we said it was n log n.
So here are the eight numbers and the
eight volunteers we had last time.
And the first thing that Merge
Sort told us to do was what?
AUDIENCE: Divide in two.
SPEAKER 1: Say again?
SPEAKER 1: Divide in two, right.
This is very reminiscent of
the phone book, of divide
and conquer more generally.
So we looked at the left half.
And then once we said, sort
the left half of the elements,
what did we next say?
Sort the left half of the left
half, which allowed us to,
after dividing in two,
focus on four and two.
>> How do you sort a list now, in
yellow, of size two, using Merge Sort?
Well divide it in half,
and sort the left half.
And this was where things
got a little stupid briefly.
How do you sort a list that's of
size one, like this number four here?
It's sorted.
You're done.
>> But then how do you sort a list of
size one when it's the number two?
Well, same thing, but now what was the
third and the key step in Merge Sort?
You had to merge the left
half and the right half.
And once we did that, we looked
at four, we looked at two.
We decided all right,
obviously two comes first,
so we put two in its
place, followed by four.
And now you have to kind of rewind,
and this is sort of characteristic
of an algorithm like Merge
Sort, rewind in memory.
What was the next line of the story?
What should I be focusing on next?
The right half of the left
half, Which is six and eight.
>> So let me just step through this
without belaboring the point too much.
Six and eight, then six is
sorted, eight is sorted.
Merge them together like that,
and now the next big step
is, of course, sort the right half from
the very first step of this algorithm.
So we focus on one, three, seven, five.
We then focus on the left half.
The left half of that, the right half of
that, and then merge in one and three.
Then the right half, then left half
of it, then the right half of it.
Merge it in, and now what step remains?
Merge the big left half and the big
right half, so one goes down there,
then two, then three, then four, then
five, then six, then seven, then eight.
>> So now why is this ultimately revealing,
especially if n and logarithms more
generally rather escape you,
at least in recent memory?
Well, notice the height of this thing.
We had eight elements, and we
divided it by two, by two, by two.
So log base two of eight gives us three.
And trust me on that if
a little hazy on that.
But log base two of eight is three,
so we've done three layers of merging.
And when we merged
elements, how many elements
did we look at on each of those rows?
A total of n, right?
Because to merge the top row,
even though we did it piecemeal,
we ultimately touched every number once.
And in the second row, to
merge those lists of size two,
we had to touch each element once.
And then here really
clearly in the last row,
we had to touch each of those
elements once, but only once,
so herein lies, then, our n log n.
>> And now just to make things a little
more formal for just a moment, if you
were to now analyze this
at a sort of higher level
and try to decide, well how
might you go about expressing
the running time of this algorithm
just by looking at it and not
by using a contrived example?
Well, how much time would you say a
step like this in yellow would take,
if n<2 return?
That's a big O of what?
So I'm seeing one, so one step,
maybe two steps because it's if
and then return, but it's
constant time, right?
So we said O(1), and that's
how I'll express this.
T, just be running time.
n is the size of the input,
so T(n), just a fancy way
of saying the running
time given input of size n
is going to be on the order
of constant time, in O(1).
>> But otherwise, what about this?
How would you express the
running time of this yellow line?
T of what?
You can kind of cheat here and
answer my question cyclically.
So if the running time in
general we just say is T(n).
And now you're kind of punting here and
saying, well, just sort the left half,
and then sort the right half.
How might we symbolically represent
the running time of this yellow line?
T of what?
What's the size of the input?
n over two.
Why don't I just say that?
And then this is another T(n/2) and then
again, if I merge two sorted halves,
how many elements am I going
to have to touch total?
n.
So I can express this,
just to be kind of fancy,
as the running time in general.
T(n) is just the running time of T(n/2),
plus T(n/2), left half and right half,
plus O(n), which is probably n steps,
but maybe, if I'm using two fingers,
it's twice as many
steps, but it's linear.
It's some number of steps
that's a factor of n,
so we might express this as this.
And this is where now we'll punt to the
back of our high school math textbook
we're that recurrence ultimately
ends up equaling this, n times log n,
if you actually do out
the math more formally.
>> So that's just two perspectives.
One numerically with a
hard-coded representative example
using eight numbers, and a more
general look at how we got there.
But what's really interesting here
is, again, this notion of cycling.
I'm not using for loops.
I'm kind of defining
something in terms of itself,
not only with this
mathematical function,
but also in terms of this pseudo code.
This pseudo code is recursive
in that two of its lines
is essentially telling it to go
use itself to solve a smaller
problem of smaller size,
and then again and again
and again until we whittle it
down to this so-called base case.
>> So let's actually draw a more compelling
take-away from this as follows.
Let me go into gedit and take a
look at some of today's source code,
in particular this example here.
Sigma 0, which apparently adds
the numbers one through n.
So let's see what's familiar
and unfamiliar here.
First we have a couple of
includes, so nothing new there.
Prototype.
I'm a little hazy on
this after few days,
but what did we say a
prototype of a function is?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: What's that?
AUDIENCE: We announce it.
SPEAKER 1: We announce it.
So you are teaching Clang, hey,
not actually implementing this yet,
but somewhere in this file, presumably,
is going to be a function called what?
Sigma.
And this is just a promise that
it's going to look like this.
It's going to take an integer as
input-- and I can be more explicit
and say int n --and it's
going to return an int,
but semicolon means, mm, I'll get around
to implementing this a little later.
Again, Clang is dumb.
It's only going to know what
you tell it top to bottom,
so we need to at least give
it a hint of what's to come.
>> Now let's look at main here.
Let's scroll down here and
see what main is doing.
It's not that long of a function, and
in fact the construct here is familiar.
I declare a variable n, and then
I pester the user again and again
for a positive integer using getInt,
and only exit out of this loop
once the user has complied.
Do While, we've used to
pester the user in that way.
Now this is interesting.
I declare an int called "answer."
I assign it the return value
of a function called "sigma."
I don't know what that does yet, but
I remember declaring it a moment ago.
And then I'm passing in the
value that the user typed in, n,
and then I report the answer.
Well let's scroll back
for just a moment.
Let's go ahead into this directory, make
sigma 0, and actually run this program
and see what happens.
So if I go ahead and run
this program, ./sigma-0,
and I type in a positive
integer like two, Sigma,
as the Greek symbol implies, is just
going to add up all the numbers from
zero on up to two.
So 0 plus 1 plus 2.
So this should hopefully give me 3.
That's all it's doing.
And similarly, if I run this again
and I give it the number three,
that's 3 plus 2, so that's
5, plus 1 should give me 6.
And then if I get really crazy and
start typing in bigger numbers,
it should give me
bigger and bigger sums.
So that's all.
>> So what does sigma look like?
Well, it's pretty straightforward.
It's how we might have implemented
this for the past couple of weeks.
"int" is going to be the return type.
Sigma is the name, and it takes
a variable m instead of n.
I'll change that up top.
Then this is just a sanity check.
We'll see why in a moment.
Now I declare another variable,
sum, initialize it to zero.
Then I have this For loop
iterating, apparently for clarity,
from i=1 on up to an =m, which is
whatever the user typed in, and then I
increment the sum like this.
And then return the sum.
>> So a couple of questions.
One, I claim in my comment that this
avoids risk of an infinite loop.
Why would passing in a negative number
induce, potentially, an infinite loop?
>> AUDIENCE: You'll never reach m.
>> SPEAKER 1: Never reach m.
But m is passed in, so let's
consider a simple example.
If m is passed in by the
user as negative one.
Irrespective of main.
Main protects us from
this too, so I'm just
being really anal with
sigma to also make sure
that the input can't be negative.
So if m is negative,
something like negative one.
What's going to happen?
Well, i is going to
get initialized to one,
and then i is going to be
less than or equal to m?
>> Stand by.
That was-- let's not,
let's nix this story.
I didn't ask that question, because
the risk that I am alluding to
is not going to happen because i is
always going be greater than-- OK,
I retract that question.
OK.
Let's focus only on this part here.
Why did I declare some
outside of the loop?
Notice on line 49 I've
declared i inside of the loop,
but online 48 I've
declared some outside.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: Sure.
So first and foremost I certainly don't
want to declare and initialize sum
to zero inside of the
loop on every iteration,
because this would clearly defeat the
purpose of summing up the numbers.
I would keep changing
the value back to zero.
And also, what's another more arcane
reason for that same design decision?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: Exactly.
I want to access it outside
of the loop too on what line?
On 53.
And based on our rule of thumb
from a couple of lectures ago,
variables are scoped, really, to the
curly braces that encompass them.
So if I don't declare sum inside
of these outer curly braces,
I can't use it in line 53.
Put another way, if I declared
sum in here, or even within the
For loop, I could not access it in 53.
The variable would effectively be gone.
So a couple of reasons there.
But now let's go back
and see what happens.
So sigma gets called.
It adds up 1 plus 2, or 1 plus 2
plus 3, and then returns the value,
stores it in answer, and printf here
is why I'm seeing on the screen.
So this is what we'll call an iterative
approach, where iteration just
means using a loop.
A For loop, a While loop, a Do While
loop, just doing something again
and again and again.
>> But sigma is kind of a neat function in
that I could implement it differently.
What about this, which
just to be kind of cool,
let me really get rid
of a lot of distraction
because this function
is really quite simple.
Let's whittle it down just
to its four core lines
and get rid of all the
comments and curly braces.
This is kind of a mind-blowing
alternative implementation.
All right, maybe not mind-blowing,
but it's kind of sexier, all right,
to look at this so much more succinctly.
With just four lines of code,
I first have this sanity check.
If m is less than or equal to
zero, sigma makes no sense.
It's only supposed to be in
this case for positive numbers,
so I'm just going to
return zero arbitrarily
so that we at least have
some so-called base case.
>> But here's the beauty.
The entirety of this idea, adding the
numbers from 1 to n, or m in this case,
can be done by kind of passing the buck.
Well, what is the sum of 1 to m?
Well, you know what?
It's the same as the sum of m
plus the sum of 1 to m minus 1.
Well you know what?
What's sigma of m minus 1?
Well, if you kind of follow this
logically, it's the same as m minus 1
plus sigma of m minus 2.
So you can kind of just--
this is like, if you're just
trying to annoy a friend
and they ask you a question,
you kind of respond with a question,
you can kind of keep passing the buck.
But what's key is that if you keep
making the question smaller and smaller
and smaller, you're
not asking what's sigma
of n, what's sigma of
n, what's sigma of n?
You're asking what's
sigma of n, what's sigma
of n minus 1, what's sigma of n minus 2?
Eventually your question
is going to become what?
What is sigma of one or
zero, some very small value,
and as soon as you
get that, your friend,
you are not going to ask
the same question again,
you're just going to say, oh it's zero.
We're done playing this sort
of stupid cyclical game.
>> So recursion is the act in programming
of a function calling itself.
This program, when compiled and run, is
going to behave exactly the same way,
but what's key is that inside
of a function called sigma,
there is a line of code wherein
we're calling ourselves,
which would normally be bad.
For instance, what if I first
compiled this, so make sigma--
make sigma 1 ./sigma-1.
Positive integer, please, 50 1275.
So what the function seems to
be, based on one test, correct.
But what if I get a little dangerous
and delete the so-called base case,
and just say, well I'm just making
this more complicated than it is.
Let's just compute the sigma
by taking m and then adding
in sigma of m minus one?
Well, what's going to happen here?
Let's zoom out.
Let's recompile the program,
save it, recompile the program,
and then ready ./sigma-1 zooming in,
enter positive integer please, 50.
How many of you are willing
to fess up to seeing that?
>> OK.
So this can happen for
a number of reasons,
and frankly this week we're
about to give you more of them.
But in this case, try
to reason backwards
what might have happened here?
Segmentation fault, we said last
time, refers to a segment of memory.
Something bad happened.
But what was it
mechanically that went awry
here because of my removal
of that so-called base case,
where I returned a hard-coded value?
What do you think went wrong?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: Ah.
Good question.
So the size of the number
that I was summing up
got so big that it exceeded
the size of the memory space.
Good idea, but not fundamentally
going to cause a crash.
That might cause integer overflow,
where the bits just flip over
and then we mistake a really big
number for like a negative number,
but that itself won't cause a crash.
Because at the end of the
day an int is still 32 bits.
You're not going to
accidentally steal a 33rd bit.
But a good thought.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: The method
never stops running,
and indeed it calls itself again
and again and again and again
and again, and none of
those functions ever
finish because their sole line of
code calls themself again and again
and again.
And what's really
happening here, and now we
can kind of draw this pictorially.
Let me go over to a
picture for just a moment.
This is a picture, that
will eventually flesh out
in more detail, of what's going on
inside of your computer's memory.
And it turns out that on
the bottom of this picture
is something called the stack.
This is a chunk of
memory, a chunk of RAM,
that's just used any time
a function is called.
Any time you, a programmer,
call a function,
the operating system, like
Mac OS, Windows, or Linux,
grabs a bunch of bytes, maybe a
few kilobytes, maybe few megabytes
of memory, hands them
to you, and then lets
you run your function using
whatever variables you need.
And if you then call another
function and another function,
you get another slice of memory
and another slice of memory.
>> And indeed, if these green trays
from Annenberg represent that memory,
here's what happens the first
time you call function sigma.
It's like putting a tray like this
on what's initially an empty stack.
But then if that tray
calls itself, so to speak,
calling another instance
of sigma, that's
like asking the operating system,
ooh, need a little more memory,
give me that.
And then it gets piled on on top.
But what's key here is that
the first tray is still there,
because he invoked this second tray.
Now meanwhile, sigma call sigma,
that's like asking for more memory.
Gets piled on over here.
sigma call sigma, that's another
tray that gets piled on here.
And if you keep doing this,
eventually, kind of map this visual
to that chart, what's going to
happen with the stack of trays?
It is going to exceed the amount
of memory your computer has.
And as soon as this green tray
exceeds the horizontal line
above stack and above that word heap,
which we'll come back to in the future,
that is a bad thing.
The heap is a different
segment of memory,
and if you let these
trays pile and pile on,
you're going to exceed
your own segment of memory,
and a program is indeed going to crash.
>> Now as an aside, this idea
of recursion, therefore,
can clearly lead to problems, but
it's not necessarily a bad thing.
Because consider, after
all, how-- and maybe
this takes some getting used
to --how elegant or how simple
that implementation of sigma was.
And we're not going to use
recursion all that much in CS50,
but in CS51, and really any class
where you manipulate data structures
like trees, or family trees,
that have some hierarchy,
it's super, super useful.
Now, as an aside, so that you
as aspiring computer scientists
are familiar with some of Google's
inside jokes, if you go to Google
and you look up what is the
definition of, say, recursion, enter.
Uh-huh.
As an aside, I pulled up a few.
This was like 10 minutes of
procrastination this morning.
If you also Google "askew," notice
by tilting your head slightly--
and then this one is perhaps
most atrocious of all
since someone spent like
their day implementing this
some years ago-- come on.
Oh, wait-- that's a bug.
>> So running on one of the
world's biggest websites
are these stupid little Easter eggs.
They probably consume a
nontrivial number of lines of code
just so that we can have
little fun things like that.
But at least now you get
some of those inside jokes.
>> Now let's take a look at some of the
white lies we've been telling of late,
and start to peel back
some layers technically
so that you really understand
what's been going on
and you can understand
some of the threats,
like Shellshock, that
have now started to become
on the forefront of everyone's
attention, at least in the media.
So here is a very simple function
that returns nothing, void.
Its name is swap.
It takes in two variables
and it returns nothing.
Takes in a and b .
So a quick demonstration.
We brought these up.
We might as well take a little
break here for just a moment
and have a little something to drink.
If someone wouldn't mind joining
me up here for just a moment.
How about you in the maroon shirt?
Come on up.
Just the one today.
Thank you, though.
All right, and we have
coming up who here?
What's your name?
>> SPEAKER 4: Laura.
>> SPEAKER 1: Laura.
Come on up.
So Laura, very simple challenge today.
Nice to meet yo.
All right.
So we have some milk over here and
we have some orange juice over here
and some cups that we
borrowed from Annenberg today.
>> SPEAKER 4: Borrowed.
SPEAKER 1: And going to go ahead
and give you half a glass of this.
All right.
And we'll give you half
a glass of the milk.
Oh, and just so that you can
remember what this was like,
I remembered to bring
this up and on today.
Okay.
If you wouldn't mind, let's see, we
can put them over your own glasses
if you want.
This'll be the world from Laura's eyes.
All right.
So your goal, given two cups of
liquid here, milk and orange juice,
is swap the two contents so that the
orange juice goes into the milk cup
and the milk goes into
the orange juice cup.
>> SPEAKER 4: Do I get another cup?
SPEAKER 1: I'm so glad you asked, though
it would have been much better footage
if you hadn't asked.
But yes, we can offer you a third
cup that's empty, of course.
All right.
So swap the contents there.
Very nice.
Very good.
You're doing this remarkably carefully.
And step three.
All right.
Excellent.
A big round of applause
would be good for Laura.
All right.
We have a little parting gift
for you, but let me take these.
Thank you so much.
So a simple example, though,
to demonstrate that if you do
want to swap the contents
of two containers,
or let's call them variables,
you need some temporary storage
to stage one of the contents in so
that you can actually do the swap.
So indeed, this source code up here in
C is representative of exactly that.
If the orange juice was a and the milk
was b, and we wanted to swap the two,
you could try something creative
by pouring one into the other,
but that probably wouldn't
end particularly well.
And so we use a third cup, call
it tmp, T-M-P by convention,
and put the contents of the
OJ in that, then swap one cup,
then put the OJ into the
original cup, thereby
achieving, exactly as
Laura did, the swap.
>> So let's do exactly that.
Let me go ahead and open
up an example that's
actually called "no
swap," because this is not
as simply done as you might think.
So in this program, notice that
I'm using stdio.h, our old friend.
I have the prototype
for swap up there, which
means its implementation's
probably down below,
and let's see what this main
program's going to do for me.
I first declare int x gets
one, and int y gets two.
So think of those as OJ
and milk, respectively.
And then I just have a
printf saying x is this
and y is this, just so I can
visually see what's going on.
Then I have printf claiming
that I'm swapping the two,
and then I print out a
claim that they're swapped,
and I print out x and y again.
So down here in swap is
exactly what Laura did,
and exactly what we saw on
the screen a moment ago.
>> So let's go ahead and
be sorely disappointed.
Make no swap, and run no swap,
zooming in on the output here.
Enter x is 1, y is 2, swapping swapped.
x is still 1, and y is still 2.
So even though, frankly, this looks
exactly like, albeit more technically,
what Laura did, didn't seem to work.
So why is that?
Well, it turns out that when
we write a program like this
that has both main, highlighted here,
and then another function, like swap,
highlighted here, which
it calls, the world
looks a little something like
these trays a moment ago.
When main first gets called,
that's like asking operating system
for a bit of memory for any local
variables like x and y that main has,
and they end up right there.
But if main calls swap, and main
passes to swap two arguments, a and b,
orange juice and milk, it's not like
handing the orange juice and the milk
to Laura.
What a computer does, is it
passes copies of the orange juice
and copies of the milk to Laura, so that
what's ultimately inside of this tray
is the value one and two, or OJ
and milk, but copies thereof,
so that at this point
in the story, there
is OJ and milk in each of these trays.
There's a one and a two
in each of these trays,
and the swap function is indeed working.
It's swapping them inside
of the second topmost tray,
but that swapping has no impact.
And based on just some
basic principle we've
talked about before, and indeed
just a few minutes ago, what
might explain why changing
a and b inside of swap
has no effect on x and y, even though
I passed x and y to the swap function.
What's the key word here that
might simplistically explain?
I think I heard it here?
AUDIENCE: Return.
SPEAKER 1: Return?
Not return.
Let's go with one other.
What's that?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: OK, so return-- we could
make return work in the story,
but there's an even simpler explanation.
AUDIENCE: Scope.
SPEAKER 1: Scope.
I'll take scope.
So scope, remember where
our x and y declared.
They're declared inside
of main right up here.
a and b, meanwhile, are
effectively declared
inside of swap, not quite in
the curly braces but still
in the general area of swap.
And so indeed, a and b
only exist within this tray
from Annenberg, this
second chunk of code.
So we're indeed changing the copy, but
that's not really all that helpful.
>> So let's take a look at
this a little lower level.
I'm going to go back into
the Source Directory,
and I'm going to first
zoom in here, and just
to confirm that I'm in this
bigger terminal window,
the program's still behaving like that.
Suppose now that this
is not intentional.
Clearly I wanted swap to
work, so it feels like a bug.
Now I could start adding a
lot of printf's to my code,
printing out x over here, y over
here, a over here, b over here.
But frankly, that's probably what
you've been doing for a couple of weeks
now, in office hours
and at home when working
on psets trying to find some bugs.
But you'll see, if you haven't already,
that problem set three introduces you
to a command called GDB,
where GDB, GNU debugger,
has itself a whole bunch of
features that can actually
let us understand situations
like this, but more compellingly,
solve problems and find bugs.
So I'm going to do this.
Instead of ./noswap, I'm instead
going to run GDB ./noswap.
In other words, I'm going to run my
program not in Bash, our new friend
today.
I'm going to run my
program noswap inside
of this other program called
GDB, which is a debugger, which
is a program that's designed to help
you humans find and remove bugs.
So if I hit Run here, there's
an atrocious amount of text
that you really never have to read.
It's essentially a distraction
from the prompt, which
I'm going to hit Control-L
to get up at the top there.
This is the GDB prompt.
If I want to run this program now,
as this little cheat sheet on today's
slide suggests, Run is the first
commands that we meant to introduce.
And I'm just going to type
run up here inside of GDB,
and indeed it ran my program.
Now there's some additional
outputs of the screen like this,
but that's GDB just being anal
and telling us what's going on.
You don't really have to worry
about these details right now.
But what's really cool about
GDB, if I do this again--
Control-L clears the screen-- let me go
ahead and type "break main," thereby,
when I hit Enter, setting what's
called a break point at noswap.c,
line 16, which is where GDB
figured out my program actually
is, my function actually is.
This we'll ignore for now
but that's the address
in memory specifically of this function.
So now when I type run,
notice what's cool here.
My program breaks at the line I
told GDB to pause execution at.
So I don't have to now change my code,
add some printf's, recompile it, rerun
it, change, add some printf's,
save it, recompile it, run it.
I can just walk through my program
step by step by step at human speed,
not at Intel-inside kind of speed.
>> So now notice this line
appears here, and if I go back
to my program in gedit,
notice that that is actually
the very first line of code.
There's line 16 in gedit.
There's line 16 within GDB, and even
though this black and white interface
isn't nearly as user
friendly, this means
that line 16 hasn't been executed
yet, but it's about to be.
So indeed if I type print
x, not printf, just print x,
I get some bogus value there of zero,
because x hasn't been initialized yet.
So I'm going to type next, or, if you
want to be fancy, just n for next.
But when I type next enter, now
notice it moves on to line 17.
So logically, if I've executed
line 16 and I now type print x,
what should I see?
One.
>> And now this is admittedly confusing.
$2 is just a fancy way of, if you
want to refer to that value later,
you can say "dollar sign two."
It's like a back reference.
But for now, just ignore it.
What's interesting is what's
on the right of the equal sign.
And now if I type next again
and print y, I should see 2.
I can also now print
x again, and frankly,
if I'm getting a little confused as to
where I am, I can type list for list
and just see some context around
the point I'm actually at.
And now I can type
next, and there x is 1.
Now I type next.
Oh, y is 2.
And again, it is confusing,
because GDB's output
is being commingled with my own output.
But if you keep in mind, by
glancing back and forth at your code
or laying it out side
by side perhaps, you'll
see that really I'm just
stepping through my program.
>> But notice what happens next, literally.
Here's line 22.
Let me go over it, thereby moving on
to 23, and if I print x now, still one.
And if I print y now, still one.
So this is not a useful exercise.
So let's redo this.
Let me go back up to the
top and type run again.
And it's saying the program
that's being debugged
has started already,
started from the beginning.
Yes, let's do this again.
And this time let's do next,
next, next, next, next,
but now things get interesting.
Now I want to step into
swap, so I don't type next.
I type step, and now notice it
has jumped me to noswap.c line 33.
If I go back to gedit, what's line 33?
That's the first actual
line of code inside of swap.
Which is nice, because now I can
kind of poke around and get curious
as to what's going on truly in there.
Let me print tmp.
Whoa.
Why does tmp have some
crazy, bogus garbage value?
AUDIENCE: It hasn't been initialized.
SPEAKER 1: It hasn't been initialized.
And indeed, when you run a program,
you're given a whole bunch of memory
by the operating system, but you
haven't initialized any values,
so whatever bits you're
seeing here, even though it's
this crazy big negative
number, just means
that those are the remnants from
some previous usage of that RAM,
even though I haven't
myself needed it yet.
So now I'm going to go ahead and type
next, and if I now type print tmp,
what should I see?
Whatever the value of a was,
a is the first argument, just
like x was the first
thing being passed in,
so a and x should be the same,
so print tmp should print me one.
>> So what you'll see in problem set
three is a tutorial of sorts on GDB,
but realize that this is the beginning
of a look at a tool that will actually
help you solve problems
so much more effectively.
What we're ultimately
going to do on Wednesday
is start to peel back a few layers
and remove some training wheels.
That thing called string that
we've used for some time,
we're going to slowly take that away
from you and start talking about
something more esoterically
known as char*,
but we're going to do this nice and
gently at first, even though pointers,
as they're called, can do some
very bad things if abused,
by looking at a little claymation from
our friend Nick Parlante from Stanford
University, a professor in computer
science who put together this preview
of what's to come this Wednesday.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-Hey, Binky.
Wake up.
It's time for pointer fun.
>> -What's that?
Learn about pointers?
Oh, goody!
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
SPEAKER 1: That awaits you on Wednesday.
We'll see you then.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-And now, Deep Thoughts,
by Daven Farnham.
>> -Why are we learning C?
Why not A+?
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> [END VIDEO PLAYBACK]