>> DAVID J. MALAN: So this is CS50.
And this was CS50's own Colton Ogden,
for more of who's music you can
download at soundcloud.com/cs50.
>> So today we focus all the more
on the art of programming.
And we take where we left
off last week, focusing
on Scratch, which was this
graphical programming language.
And take things down to a lower level,
using a more traditional programming
language known as C. But
along the way, realizing
that the same ideas we
talked about last Friday
will recur not only in this
language C, but in most every other
that we look at this semester.
>> So we called this thing
here what last time?
This is representative of a statement.
So we called this a statement.
And it does something.
It's an instruction that a
computer or Scratch might execute.
And henceforth, let's also start
calling something like this a function,
for reasons we shall soon see.
>> Meanwhile, we saw things like this.
And these are generally
known as what construct?
>> AUDIENCE: Loop.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So a loop.
So pretty straightforward.
It literally does what it says.
And in Scratch, if you want to
cram more puzzle pieces in there,
the piece will grow to fit it.
And we'll see in C that
we can do the same thing.
>> Another type of loop, though,
in Scratch might be forever,
or there's any number
of other approaches.
But let's take a more
generalist look, with a face
that's likely quite familiar,
at loops more generally.
MARK ZUCKERBERG: One
thing that computers
are really good at is
repeating commands.
As a person, you'd get
really bored if you
had to do the same thing
lots of times in a row.
But a computer can do the same thing
millions or even billions of times,
and not get bored, and be able
to carry that out really well.
>> So for example, if I
wanted to wish everyone
on Facebook a happy birthday
by sending them an email,
it might take me more than a
century to actually write out
all of those emails to everyone.
But with just a few lines of code, I can
have a system send an email to everyone
on Facebook wishing
them a happy birthday.
So that's what loops are and why
they're valuable and something
that computers can do very well.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So if
you've been the recipient
of some of CS50's and
Dropbox's space of late,
that's actually precisely what we
do, using code quite like that.
We essentially have a big
spreadsheet into which
folks have been inputting their
names and email addresses.
And we wrote a tiny bit of code that
can iterate over those addresses
and spit out unique addresses in
case anyone submitted multiple times.
And thereafter, we send an
automated email from CS50's bot,
including the coupon code.
>> Now we also looked at
this construct last time.
And this is a particular
example of what?
So, yeah, a Boolean expression.
And the shape is meant
to capture that as well.
All such questions of the
form true or false in Scratch
will look a little something like this.
And we call this a Boolean expression.
That's indeed true or false, yes or no.
It's a way of answering a question.
>> And Meanwhile you can use these Boolean
expressions inside of constructs
like these, which of
course are conditions
or branches, proverbial
forks in the road.
And they can look not only
like this, but they can also
have elses associated with them.
And you can actually have a three way
fork in the road or a four way fork
in the road, simply by
nesting these things,
as you'll see in Scratch
if you haven't already.
And as you can do in C as well.
>> Let's take another generalist
look at an alumnist, as well, who
might present a different approach
to these things called conditions.
>> BILL GATES: People make
decisions every day.
For example, before you go outside you
kind of have an if statement that says,
if it's raining then I
need to get my jacket.
And computers are amazing once you
decide those kinds of statements,
that they can reliably execute
those things at unbelievable speed.
And so a computer program really
is a little bit of math and some
if statements where
the decision gets made.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So as
you may know, it was
folks like Bill Gates,
Paul Allen, and others
that truly kicked off the
so-called personal computer
revolution some years ago.
I thought, before we dive
into some administrivia,
we'd relate a tale from the Albuquerque,
New Mexico museum of Natural History
and science where some of Bill Gates'
and Paul Allen's earliest stories
are recounted how we have now
today's PCs and Macs and more.
For this, though, we need two volunteers
who have very good narration voices
to read a script aloud.
>> All right, how about in back there.
Come on up.
And how about in front here.
Come on down.
Take your places here.
As you guys come up, a couple
of administrative announcements.
sectioning, the process
of choosing a section,
will start this
Wednesday through Friday.
More on that this coming
Wednesday in lecture.
>> Super sections, meanwhile, are
something that we offer next week
whereby the entire class is invited
to participate in fairly large scale
sections, one more comfy,
one less comfortable.
And we will announce the particulars
of that, as well, later this week.
>> Meanwhile sections,
themselves, will start
in week three of the course, zero index,
which means those are a couple of weeks
out.
So not to worry.
You have not yet missed
anything along those lines.
Meanwhile in the meantime, if you
have any questions administratively,
email myself and Devon and Gabe
and Rob at this address here.
>> Lastly, problem set
0 is, of course, out.
You may have noticed it
on the course's website.
It should provide you with
all answers to questions
you might have along the way for
getting started with the problem set.
But if you find yourself
in need of a helping hand,
by all means attend office hours,
Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday
of this week in the evening
in four dining halls.
See that URL there for the particulars
of where office hours shall be.
>> Now Let's meet our
two guests here today.
What's your name?
>> JAY PAUL: Jay Paul.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Jay
Paul, nice to meet you.
>> HIKARI: Hikari.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Hikari?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Hikari.
Nice to meet you as well.
Jay Paul and Hikari have in
front of them on these music
stands two scripts that I printed
out this morning from the New Mexico
museum of Natural History and Science.
And what I thought
I'd do on the overhead
is accompany your recitation
of the script and this history
with some visual images, no surprises.
>> And what I've done in advance
is prehighlight on your script
what you should read,
and what you should read.
And we'll essentially
just alternate paragraphs.
So it's much like you might
have done in English class.
That's really compel the audience
to believe in your tale here.
Shall we?
So the story here is, we have a
BASIC, and it begins in Cambridge.
>> JAY PAUL: It was winter, 1974,
in Cambridge, Massachusetts
where winters can be cold.
A bearded, long haired
college dropout named
Paul Allen was drudging across Harvard
Square, absorbed in his thoughts.
His main preoccupation in those days
was how to get his friend, Bill Gates,
to quit school and go
into business with him.
HIKARI: The two had already gone
through a number of business ventures
together, beginning at Lakeside
school in Seattle where
they were paid in free computer time to
test a PDP-10 computer at a local time
sharing company.
The most recent plan had been to quit
school and form a software company.
Allen had left Washington
State University.
But at the last minute, Gates
decided to stick with Harvard.
>> JAY PAUL: That day, crossing Harvard
Square, Allen spotted the January,
1975 issue of Popular Electronics
with the earth stopping headline,
World's First Minicomputer Kit
to Rival Commercial Models.
Beneath the headline was
a picture of a small box
adorned with lights and switches.
It was called the MITS Altair 8800.
And Allen knew this was what
he had been looking for.
>> HIKARI: Days of discussion followed.
Allen and Gates understood the
significance of the Altair.
They had talked often
about microprocessors
and were waiting to see what
would be done with them.
Now there was a minicomputer kit on
the cover of Popular Electronics.
It apparently had no software yet.
They imagined a nation of
programmers descending on MITS.
And so they called Ed Roberts,
the head of the company,
claiming to have a version of the
BASIC programming language almost ready
for the Altair.
They didn't.
And Roberts must have known they didn't.
He was getting 10 calls a day from
people who had a BASIC almost ready.
And his stock response
was, "The first person
who shows up with a working
BASIC gets the contract."
>> JAY PAUL: Gates and Allen
had never seen an Altair.
They had never even seen the
Intel 8080 microprocessor
at the heart of the Altair.
But a couple of years earlier
Allen had written a program
on a mainframe computer that emulated
the operation of a previous Intel
microprocessor.
And this time around they
would do the same thing.
>> HIKARI: With an Intel
8080 manual at his side,
Allen sat down at a
Harvard PDP-10 computer
and wrote the emulator and software
tools necessary to do the programming.
Meanwhile Gates stopped going
to classes and devoted himself
to designing the BASIC,
using every trick
he knew to get the size
down below 4 kilobytes.
>> JAY PAUL: Out in Albuquerque,
Ed Roberts got a call from Gates
asking for details about how the
Altair handled specific routines.
No one had ever asked that before.
And Roberts began to get interested.
>> HIKARI: With the development
tools and the design ready,
Gates and Allen wrote
the code on the PDP-10,
enlisting another Harvard student,
Monte Davidoff, to write math routines.
After a final night of
programming, Allen got on a plane
to deliver their BASIC to MITS.
He spent the plane ride out worrying.
And back in Cambridge
Gates was worrying.
They had tested their BASIC and
it had worked on the emulator.
But what if the emulator was wrong?
JAY PAUL: As the plane
approached Albuquerque,
Allen realized that their
BASIC, now neatly contained
on a small roll of
punched paper tape, would
be useless without a separate
program, called a loader, that
would tell the Altair how
to read the paper tape being
fed into the teletype machine.
He took out his notebook and quickly
scribbled down a loader program
in Assembly language, then manually
translated that into the 1s and 0s
the Altair would understand.
>> HIKARI: Allen was expecting a
clean, little, high tech company
run by men in business suits.
So he was surprised when Roberts met
him at the airport looking like a ranch
hand.
Roberts was also surprised.
When he dropped the Harvard
programmer at an expensive hotel,
Allen had to confess that
he couldn't afford the room.
>> JAY PAUL: MITS, itself, was
located in a dusty strip mall.
Inside on a cluttered
workbench was an Altair
loaded up with 5 kilobytes of
memory and connected by a cable
to a teletype machine.
Roberts and Chief Engineer,
Bill Yates, waited expectantly
as Allen toggled his loader
program into the Altair.
The teletype began chugging as it pulled
the paper tape through the tape reader.
It took perhaps 15 minutes
to load the program.
Then the teletype abruptly printed a
memory prompt, then a ready prompt,
and Allen began typing
a few test commands.
To everyone's amazement,
the software worked.
There were bugs, of course.
But the main thing was it worked.
>> HIKARI: Later, on their way to a
$3.00 lunch at Pancho's, a wasp flew
in the window of the pickup
truck and stung Allen on the arm.
But at that point nothing
could spoil the mood.
The Altair now had its BASIC, the
first commercial software for a home
computer, made by Paul Allen and Bill
Gates, doing business as Microsoft.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Many
thanks to our two readers.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Now
you have your choice,
before you leave, of a sparkly
or a glow in the dark-- oh,
wait one sec, wait-- sparkly
and a glow in the dark elephant
from CS50's own Cheng Gong.
HIKARI: Aw, thank you.
DAVID J. MALAN: All
right, thank you so much.
[APPLAUSE]
DAVID J. MALAN: So true story.
This is to say that all of these
machines and the ease with which we
use them now and take
for granted, really
started here, just a few paces
from this actual theater.
And now today, if you've not been,
this is Maxwell Dworkin, the computer
sciences building,
also around the corner.
And on the second floor of this
building does hang three pages
from the original source code that
Bill Gates and Paul Allen wrote.
In fact, if use you zoom
in you can see not only
their names in the
original type, but also
their signatures that they adorned a
few years back when they last visited.
>> But what was particularly compelling
about this is what they set out to do
was to write a program that would
enable other people to write
their own programs.
At the time all there was with
this Altair machine made by MITS.
And all they needed was some way of
making it easy for hobbyists and people
like us in this room to actually program
that without necessarily understanding
Assembly code, or machine
code, or God forbid, 0s and 1s.
We programmers, like
those in this room, we
want to be able to express
ourselves much more like pseudo code
even if it's a bit more nit
picky than we talked last week.
We don't want to write code like this,
which Paul Allen and Bill Gates did.
We, instead, want to write code that
looks a little more user friendly.
>> Now this is a language known as BASIC.
And the line numbers there are what you
use to simply number the lines of code
that you're writing.
We don't even have to
do that these days.
But you can see here
how PRINT "hello, world"
would indeed presumably print just that.
And so what Bill and Paul did was
empower people to write code like this
instead of-- if you take a look at the
computer science wall-- code like this.
>> In fact, CS50 recently
had an opportunity
to sit down with Professor Harry Lewis
in the Computer Science department, who
actually taught Bill
Gates some years ago,
and is standing here before
those three pages of excerpts.
Let's take a look.
>> HARRY LEWIS: What you have here is a
listing of an early piece of software
written by Bill Gates and Paul
Allen, the founders of Microsoft.
So the code is interesting
for two reasons.
First of all, it became
Microsoft's first product,
which was an interpreter for
the BASIC programming language.
And secondly, this was
one of the first attempts
to create an interpreter so ordinary
people could use personal computers.
>> So Bill Gates was an
undergraduate at Harvard.
I started teaching at Harvard in 1974.
This was done in 1975.
So it was early in his career
and early in my career.
I actually taught Bill in
a course around this time.
Paul Allen was not a
Harvard student, but he
had been a high school
classmate of Bill Gates.
If you come and look
at the listing, you'll
actually find a third
name, Monte Davidoff,
who was Gates's classmate
here at Harvard.
>> OK, so here's an
interesting comment up here.
It says "In 4K can delete square root
but for loops should still work."
OK, so what that means is that there
were two ways to compile this program.
One was to run on a version
of this Altair computer
that only had 4K words of
memory, 4,096 words of memory.
But the big version had 8K.
And so what this says is
that in the 4K version
you had to delete some
code to make it fit.
And one of the things
that would be deleted
would be the square root routine.
But apparently the
for loops should still
work even when you're compiling down
for just the 4K version of the computer.
DAVID J. MALAN: So one of the themes,
as we'll see in computer science,
is this notion of
layering and abstraction,
and really standing on the shoulders
of folks who have come before us, not
unlike some of the Bill Gates
and Paul Allen narrative here.
And what this means is
that today we can take for
granted that things are actually
easier for us to write code.
Indeed code, as we said on Friday, is
more technically known as source code.
And it's this English like syntax
that's more proper and more well defined
than something like pseudo code, for
which there is no formal definition.
>> And today what we're going
to focus on is source code
that looks like this, which
admittedly at first glance
looks completely cryptic.
And frankly, it's way more aesthetically
complex than the underlying program is.
All this program does,
recall, is what did we say?
It just prints "hello world."
And yet look at all of the stuff we need
to wrap around that very simple phrase.
But before long all of
these lines and more
will make much better sense to you.
>> And the flow is as follows.
What we need at our disposal
is to take code, like source
code that we just saw.
And we need a new program
to run it through.
We need algorithms that can
convert source code, like this,
into object code, 0s and 1s.
In other words, what
we're going to learn today
is how to do this, write
source code up top,
pass it as input to a special
program known as a compiler,
and we're going to produce object code.
Which is just a fancy way of
saying we will take something
that looks like this, pass it
into a program called a compiler,
producing object code
that looks like this.
>> So these are literally
the patterns of 0s and 1s
that are understood by an
Intel computer these days,
that if interpreted by the CPU,
the brains inside of a computer,
will literally print out,
quite simply, "hello world."
Now there's way more 0s and 1s than you
would hope might be necessary for that.
But that's because we're building
on a good deal of complexity
that we can henceforth take for granted.
In other words, a lot of smart people
have given us a lot of cool tools
and powerful software with which we
can now make projects of our own.
>> So let's get started.
Whereas last Friday, and
for Problem Set 0 this week,
you'll be playing in a
world that looks like this.
Starting today and for Problem
Set 1 next week, the code
is going to look a little more
cryptic, but functionally is
going to be the same.
So notice, top is Scratch,
bottom is C. Frankly Scratch
is a lot more user
friendly and accessible.
But if you now compare visually top to
bottom, there's kind of a one to one
correspondence between the
puzzle pieces and the language
we're about to play with.
In particular, say, the
blue puzzle piece up top,
is apparently equivalent to what keyword
or special phrase in this language
called C?
AUDIENCE: Printf.
DAVID J. MALAN: Printf.
That means formatted printing.
And that's just a fancy
way of saying printf in C
is going to be a statement or a function
that prints something to the screen.
What does it print to the screen?
Whatever you tell it to inside
of quotes, inside of parentheses.
So again, admittedly,
there's a lot of stuff
that you have to keep in mind,
parentheses, quotes, semicolons,
and all of this.
But all of that is sort
of beside the point.
The interesting takeaway for now
is that the say block in Scratch
is pretty much equivalent to
the printf statement in C.
>> Meanwhile, the yellow puzzle piece
up top, when green flag clicked,
is probably equivalent
to what keyword here?
AUDIENCE: Main.
DAVID J. MALAN: So main.
Maybe int, maybe void.
But main kind of sounds like
it's important, and indeed it is.
So when green flag clicked
is, again, the puzzle piece
that kicks off an
entire Scratch program.
But we are going to now start calling
that main, this function known as main.
>> Now meanwhile we'll
generalize this as follows.
We might call say a function.
And it might look
specifically like this.
Well, what about loops?
If we want to start converting or
translating more in Scratch to C,
this thing here apparently just
says "hello world" forever.
So if you associate these
scripts with a cat in Scratch,
it's just going to keep saying
in some kind of cartoon bubble,
"hello world, hello world, hello
world," ad nauseum, forever.
If we want to do something similar in
C, it's going to look a little cryptic.
But we can achieve the same
results, as we'll eventually
find out, with syntax like this.
I'm going to use printf again,
because at the end of the day
I want to print "hello world."
And I'm apparently using a
keyword that isn't forever.
It's instead the word while.
But just semantically in
English, while kind of
suggests some kind of loop or cycle.
>> So that happens to be
the keyword that C uses.
And while true, why does while
true effectively mean forever?
Well, while, as we'll soon
appreciate all the more,
has this parenthetical next to it
where you can put a Boolean expression.
And so long as that
expression is true, this code,
as denoted between these two
curly braces as we'll call them,
will just keep running again and again.
>> So true is true.
So while true means
just do this forever.
It's almost a stupid
construct to express yourself.
But there was no forever
keyword in C. There was while.
And there was a very simple
Boolean expression like true.
And so this, we'll see,
achieves the same result.
>> How else might you implement a loop?
Well, in Scratch you might
hard code a specific number
of iterations in the loop here.
And so that's exactly what we
might do in this version of C,
whereby we have a so-called for loop.
And the for loop here is going
to iterate, somewhat cryptically,
from the value 0 on up
to but less than 10.
>> Now variables in Scratch.
You might not have had
occasion to use these.
But what's the point, in general,
of a variable did we say last week?
What's that?
>> AUDIENCE: Points.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: To point?
Oh, points.
OK, keeping track of points,
for instance, in a game.
Or more generally doing
what with the variable?
What's the utility of them?
>> AUDIENCE: Memory.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so memory.
It's for storing something.
And the sort of silly visual I used
last time was like this glass bowl.
And if we wanted to store
something inside of a variable,
for instance right now the
value is six because there
are six ping pong balls in here.
It's just some kind of storage
container that underneath the hood
is implemented with bits, 0s and 1s,
however a computer happens to do that.
>> So in Scratch, if we
want to have a variable,
we can use an orange block like this.
We'll call that counter
in this particular case.
I initialized it to 0.
And what it I then do?
Forever, say counter, which if
you play with that in Scratch,
you'll just see Scratch.
The cat or whatever costume you put on
him will speak the number in question.
>> Change counter by 1 is
like incrementing by 1.
And so this is going to
count from what so what?
From 0 til infinity, or
until Scratch breaks,
or until you sort of
lose interest in watching
how high he can actually count.
>> So how might we convert this to C?
It's going to look a little cryptic.
But again, if you look at each
of these lines individually
they kind of lineup generally.
So apparently int is going to
have some special meaning in C.
We'll see that again.
As an aside it means integer.
So it just means number.
So that's the type of
glass bowl I want, one
that can store numbers,
not ping pong balls.
And I'm going to use the equal sign
there to assign it a value of 0.
So that's quite like set
counter to 0, but in C.
>> Meanwhile, while true, that was
equivalent, of course, to forever,
even though it's a little cryptic,
and then inside of the curly braces.
And you can think of these curly braces,
which you can type on your keyboard,
as really being like the curvature in
these yellow loop blocks in Scratch.
It embraces multiple lines of code.
>> Printf is getting a
little scary now because I
see not only quotes in parentheses.
But what else is new
syntactically in this example?
There's a percent d.
And then backslash n is there.
We did see that before, even
though I didn't mention it.
Then there's a comma.
And then there's a counter.
>> But we'll see in just a
moment that this is just
a standard way of saying print a
"decimal number," quote, unquote,
some decimal number.
But I'm going to tell you later
what that decimal number is.
So the fact that there's a comma
in this line saying printf,
means go ahead and print
some decimal number.
Oh, and by the way, the number is
whatever the value of this variable is.
And so to make this more
clear, we'll see an example
before long involving exactly printf
in the context of real C programs.
>> Now just to wrap up some
of these constructs.
Boolean expressions, you might not have
occasion to use these in your program
but you might very well,
especially if using conditions.
And so these two examples from
Scratch mean if x is less than y,
or if x is less than y and y is less
than z, how might we translate that?
>> Well, in C it's just
going to look like this.
A little cryptic, more parentheses,
some weird ampersands, but fundamentally
the ideas are as simple as they
are in the puzzle piece world.
We're simply checking if something
is less than something else.
>> How about conditions?
In a nutshell in English, what does this
chunk of Scratch code do would you say?
>> AUDIENCE: Compares two numbers.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Compares two
numbers, and if x is less than y
it says as much.
If x is greater than y
it says as much, else
if x is equal to y it says as much.
Now where did x and y come from?
Who knows.
This chunk of Scratch
code is out of context.
But what we want to do now is translate
this for just a moment to see.
>> So as you get comfortable
this week in Problem Set
0 playing in this world
on the left, realize
that the ideas aren't changing
this week or next or beyond.
We're simply going to
start writing things
in a different way with our
keyboard instead of our mouse.
>> So if x is less than y, and
there's some parentheses there,
then there's some curly braces
again to kind of encapsulate it
just like the yellow puzzle pieces do.
And I'm going to printf x
is less than y and so forth.
>> What is nice about C,
as you can see here,
is that you don't get this nesting,
nesting, nesting that's necessarily
going to push your code to the right.
You can instead have everything
lineup neatly like this.
But that's just an aesthetic
detail we'll see again before long.
>> All right.
So that brings us back to
this cryptic looking program.
Let's actually write some code.
Now how do you go about writing code?
All these years that you've owned
a Mac or PC, desktop or laptop,
you've actually had the capability
to start writing programming code.
But you're probably missing
a special type of program.
You can certainly write code.
But you can't necessarily,
out of the box,
convert that source code
into object code, 0s and 1s
without what on your computer?
AUDIENCE: Compiler.
DAVID J. MALAN: So a compiler, right.
Now most of you probably
don't own a compiler,
have never downloaded a compiler.
But you'll see you can download it
like most any other piece of software.
In the world of Mac OS, you might
download or have downloaded already
something called Xcode or GCC or Clang.
If you come from the
Windows world you might
have downloaded Visual Studio,
Visual Basic, environments like that.
There's dozens of compilers
these days that you might use.
But the short of it here
is that it would be a pain
and, frankly, a technological
nightmare for hundreds
of people with different
computer configurations to all
configure their machines
in exactly the same way
so that we can all be on the same page.
>> So what we, instead, do
in CS50 is we give you
a standard environment, a
Linux environment that's
going to look a little
something like this.
You'll see more of this in the
Problem Set 1 specification which
will go online this Friday night.
>> And what this means
is that you henceforth
are going to be able to
download and install a program
called the CS50 Appliance.
And you're going to download and
install another program called
a hypervisor, which is just a
fancy way of achieving this.
Whether you own a Mac or PC or a
Linux computer or a Solaris computer,
or whatever crazy operating
system you're running,
you're going to download a program
called the hypervisor that's
going to run the CS50
Appliance on your computer
no matter what your operating system is.
A hypervisor in other words converts
our stuff to whatever language,
whatever instructions your
own computer understands.
>> So this is a layering.
And again, this is kind
of thematic in computer
science, the building on top of things.
You might have Windows.
You might have Mac OS.
But starting next week you're
going to have downloaded
a free piece of software
called the hypervisor.
You're going to have downloaded a piece
of software called the CS50 Appliance.
>> That's going to run in the hypervisor,
which is going to run on your computer.
And the end result is
that all of us will
have a simple window like
this on your Mac or PC
that gives us the illusion of all
running the same operating system,
without any other
impact on your computer.
And you can full screen
it and essentially behave
as though you are running an
operating system called Linux,
which is what the CS50
Appliance is based on.
>> So let's actually use this
now to write a program.
You can write a program
using Microsoft Word.
using TextEdit, or Notepad,
or WordPad, or pretty much any word
processing program you've ever used.
But the reality is you shouldn't
use really any of those programs.
You certainly shouldn't use
something like Microsoft Word, which
has bold facing and italics, and
bigger fonts and smaller fonts,
because the computer doesn't
care about any of that.
All the computer is
going to care about is
English like instructions written in C.
>> So what we'll do inside
of the CS50 Appliance
is use a program freely
available, and it's
pre-installed in this
appliance, called Gedit.
And Gedit is just a super simple
text editor like Mac OS's TextEdit,
like Windows Notepad that's going to
look a little something like this.
>> So let's actually not
look at slides of this.
But let's actually go into
the environment itself.
I'm going to go ahead and
log in, in this other window,
to my CS50 Appliance, which I've
pre-installed on my laptop here.
>> Notice that, like Windows and
Mac OS, it's got some menus.
Like Windows it puts
it down there instead
of Mac OS, which puts it down there.
But the reality is it's
all kind of the same.
And in here is a whole
bunch of software.
There's Dropbox.
There's a whole bunch of accessories,
graphical programs that we'll
use later in the term for problem sets.
There's a web browser built in so
that this is a full fledged computer
inside of a computer.
>> But I'm going to click this
leftmost white icon here,
which is the icon for Gedit.
And it's going to open a window
that has three panels to it,
a left one, a top one, and a bottom one.
>> Now it's in this top right one that
I'm going to actually write some code.
So let's do this,.
I'm going to go to File, Save.
And you might not ever have seen
this particular window before.
But this is like Mac OS or Windows.
It's just a window
with all of the folders
that I have inside of this computer.
>> And I'm going to save
the file as hello.c.
And I'm going to go
ahead and click Save.
And now notice I have a tab
at top left called hello.c.
So probably pretty
familiar even if you've not
used this particular program before.
>> And now I'm going to type in those
fairly cryptic sequence of commands
that we saw a moment ago.
Include, standard I/O.h.
More on that soon.
Int main void, open curly
brace, closed curly brace.
And then inside of there I think is
where we had "hello world," semicolon.
And now save.
>> So this is a program written in C,
written, therefore, in source code.
But I can't just run this program.
I kind of want to double
click on an icon somewhere,
but no icon exists other
than the source code file.
What, again, is the process now that
I need to run this file through?
AUDIENCE: Compiler.
DAVID J. MALAN: So a compiler.
So in different computers you
do this in different ways.
But what we've done here in
the CS50 Appliance that's
representative of how you might
do this on many different systems,
is I'm simply going to
run a command called make.
And make is literally going to do that.
Make me a program.
>> So make is going to
run a compiler for me.
And the name of the program
I want to make is hello.
Now make is a program.
And make is smart enough to
realize that if I say make hello,
it's going to look automatically
for a file called hello.c
just because that's the
way it's configured.
>> So when I now hit Enter here, this
crazy cryptic line just got executed.
And trust me, before
long, within just days,
you'll understand what all
of that nonsense means.
But for now, just know that make
triggered execution of a compiler.
In other words, it found
a compiler on my computer
that's pre-installed
on the CS50 Appliance
that we'll hand to you in Problem Set 1.
And it then took hello.c as
input, and produced apparently
0s and 1s as output.
>> And by default what it does is it saves
those 0s and 1s in a file called hello.
And though this syntax too might
be new to you, simply by saying dot
slash hello is going to be the
means by which I run this program.
>> For now and for at least a couple
of weeks, almost all of the programs
we write are going to be in
black and white text windows.
No mice, no clicking,
no windows, no icons.
We're going to keep it simple
and focus on the underlying ideas
initially before we get to something
higher level, for instance,
like the break out game that we talked
about in the first lecture last week.
>> So when I hit Enter here, it's
equivalent in a text only environment
to double clicking an icon called hello.
What do you expect will
happen when I hit Enter then?
>> AUDIENCE: It'll print "hello world."
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Hopefully
it will print "hello world."
And indeed it did.
Now there's been some
cryptic syntax here.
Let's rewind for just
a moment and see if we
can't start inferring just by
tinkering, trying and failing,
as to what's going on here.
What if I get rid of the backslash n?
Now some of you who've
programmed before probably
know instantly what that means.
But for those of you who've
never programmed before,
at least think to yourself what is going
to change when I rerun this program?
So I'm going to go back down to my
little black and white window, which
is the window in which
I can compile this.
I'm going to recompile hello.
We're going to see the same
cryptic sequence of commands.
And I'm going to do dot slash hello.
And now someone, if you would,
who's never programmed before,
what might be different this time?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: It won't stop
printing "hello world."
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It's going to-- sorry?
>> AUDIENCE: It won't stop printing it?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It won't
stop printing "hello world."
So not a bad idea.
Other ideas?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Error message?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Error
message, OK, could be.
What else?
AUDIENCE: It might print the
bracket with the semicolon as well?
DAVID J. MALAN: Might print the
bracket with the semicolon as well.
So maybe that backslash then is some
kind of terminous that's important.
Any other thoughts?
>> So all good ideas.
And in fact, it's going
to be an error message.
That's probably most likely
to be the answer in general
for the next few weeks
as we learn to code here.
>> But for now remember that computers
only do what you tell them to do.
Much like the ridiculous peanut
butter and jelly example.
Our human computers were only supposed
to do what you told them to do.
So in this case, if you
don't tell the computer
to move that blinking cursor to the
next line, it's not going to do it.
So when I run this program
now, notice the difference.
>> Looks like a bug.
It's an aesthetic bug, perhaps.
But what is different about this
output versus the last one obviously?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: It didn't do a new line.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It didn't do a new line.
Now those of you who
have maybe made web pages
before, you might know of the
BR tag or the paragraph tag,
very similar in spirit.
A web browser will ignore you until
you tell it exactly what to do.
Similarly, is a language like C only
going to do what you tell it to do.
>> So the reason that
all of these examples,
thus far, have kind of
casually had this backslash
in there, that's the means
by which you express yourself
as a new line character, so to speak.
And you can kind of appreciate, perhaps,
that this would look kind of stupid
if nothing else.
If I wanted a new line, just
hitting Enter and then kind
of butchering the code like that
shouldn't really rub you the right way.
And even if you don't
really care at this point,
you will realize that
this is not a particularly
good looking piece of code.
>> And so what the world
decided years ago is
that when you want to put the
cursor onto a new line explicitly,
you must explicitly say
new line, backslash n.
And there's some other
symbols like that.
But for now we'll just
focus on backslash n.
>> Now let's make the program
a little more interesting.
I'm going to go ahead and
this time open up a new file.
I'm going to save this as hello-1.c.
And just for kicks, I'm going to
go put it into my Dropbox folder.
>> As you'll see in the CS50
documentation for the appliance,
later this week for Problem
Set 1, we'll encourage
you to use Dropbox or
some equivalent service,
because then all of your code's
going to be backed up automatically.
And so that's why I've
gone into this folder here.
>> And now I'm going to write a
slightly different program.
Include, standard I/O.h, int main void.
And then in here printf, hello world,
which is exactly the same as before.
>> But now I want to print something
that's a little different.
I want to print out,
say, "Hello, David."
All right, so obviously,
it should hopefully
be the case that if I recompile
this program, rerun it,
it's going to say "hello, David."
>> But what if I want to introduce
this sort of variable,
the notion of a container that's going
to store D-a-v-i-d and not hard code it
into my program.
Well what if I start
doing something like this?
>> String s, so this is a variable.
If you want a string,
a.k.a. a word or a phrase.
A sequence of characters is what
we in programming call a string.
We're just going to generically call
it s, because it's a nice simple name.
But I could call it anything.
>> I'm going to say string s equals
quote unquote, "David," semicolon.
And now I want to insert
D-a-v-i-d into what I'm printing.
And before we saw a teaser on
the screen of some special syntax
that allowed us to
substitute in a value.
What was the special
symbol a few slides ago?
>> So percent.
At the time it was percent
d for decimal number.
That doesn't really seem relevant here.
Turns out there's
another percent symbol,
which is percent s, which stands
for a placeholder for a string.
>> So now, very simply, I'm
going to go make hello-1,
because this file's called
hello-1.c, and hit Enter.
And I screwed up.
What's going on?
Well, here's where we have to begin to
appreciate that we're in this command
line environment, this
text only environment.
There's no clicking on icons
like folders right now.
And think back a moment ago.
In what folder did I say
I was saving my code?
So the Dropbox folder.
Could have been called anything.
But it happens to be called Dropbox.
So I somehow need to double click on
that Dropbox folder in order to get
into it and get at my
code called hello-1.c.
In fact, let me go ahead and minimize
this window for just a moment.
Just like Windows and Mac OS,
there are folders in Linux.
There are folders in the CS50 Appliance.
It's just right now we're confining
ourselves to this text environment.
>> But if I double click
on Dropbox, notice there
is the file that I want to compile.
But I need this black and white
terminal window, so to speak.
But I need, therefore, to move
into that folder or directory.
So slightly arcane, but
you'll get used to this too.
>> In the world of Linux,
which again is the operating
system we're running inside of the CS50
Appliance, there's a command called CD.
Which means I can do CD, space, Dropbox.
CD, change directory.
Right.
Back in the day when people were
inventing computers and operating
systems like this, they wanted to
type the fewest keystrokes possible.
So the easiest way to say
change directory was CD.
>> So if I hit CD, space Dropbox,
notice what has changed here.
Inside of parentheses
the appliance is kind
of humoring me and
reminding me where I am.
So the open folder is Dropbox.
If I now type ls for
list, again succinct,
because people didn't want to
type back in the day l-i-s-t.
So they instead made it ls.
>> Enter.
Notice I see two things, hello-1.c,
and then this cryptic thing, source 1m.
That's just my way of saying
source code for week 1 Monday.
That's a folder I downloaded from
CS50's website that I made earlier today
and just put it into the
appliance in advance.
>> But for now the only thing we
care about is making this program.
So when I type make hello-1, Enter.
Damn it.
Something went wrong.
So let's tease this apart.
And unfortunately this is where things
get a little stressful at first,
at least if you've
never programmed before.
>> My god.
I wrote a two line program and
I have four lines of errors.
So what's going on here.
First and foremost always scroll back
up and find the first error message,
because oftentimes compilers just
get confused by what you and I do.
Compilers are pretty dumb.
They'll only do what
you tell them to do.
And if you confuse them, they're just
going to kind of throw up their hands
and maybe throw more error messages
than are actually relevant.
>> So let's look at the first.
Super cryptic at first.
But notice, here's the name of the
file in which I screwed up apparently.
Colon 5, colon 5 just means on
line 5 at the fifth character.
So fifth column of characters,
if you will, error.
Use of undeclared identifier string.
Did you mean standard n?
>> No, I meant string.
And then it's kind of
copying and pasting
what I typed to really draw my
attention to where I screwed up.
So for some reason C,
or at least the compiler
does not understand the word string.
And that's because we made it up.
So string does not exist
in C. What CS50 does,
for the first few weeks
only of the class,
is we provide some training
wheels, so to speak.
And we put these training wheels
inside of a special file called CS50.h.
>> So this is the second of two file
names that apparently end in dot h.
Let's rewind.
Printf is a statement or function
that apparently prints something
to the screen.
But you didn't see me
implement printf, right.
Someone years ago implemented printf.
In what file would you wager he
or she put the implementation
for printf, the code for printf?
>> In a file called standard I/O.h.
In fact, it's probably in
two files, standard I/O.h,
which stands for header
file, and standard I/O.c,
which stands for C source code.
So he or she some years ago plopped
the code that they wrote into that file
so that people like us
years later can include it,
so to speak, in our own programs.
>> And indeed, that's what the pound sign
followed by the word include does.
It looks on the local hard drive,
finds the file called standard I/O.h,
and then effectively copies and
pastes it inside of my own file.
So now my program knows
how to print to the screen.
>> So by that logic, where
is string defined?
>> AUDIENCE: CS50.h.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: CS50.h.
And indeed, that's what we,
the core staff, have done.
We've invented a few data types,
so to speak, like a string,
in addition to ones you
get for free, like an int.
And we'll see others like a char
for a character and a few more.
Inside of CS50.h apparently is
at least some mention of string.
>> So now let me go ahead
and rerun make hello-1.
I'll zoom in again and cross my fingers.
Now by having made one
change I fixed most things.
But damn it.
More percents than data arguments.
What did I do wrong this time?
>> So it's still pretty cryptic.
But this error is on
line 7 and character 21.
So let's go look up here.
It's a little subtle.
But if you think about what
the fundamental ideas here are,
perhaps we can tease this apart.
>> So printf is the name of the function.
Parentheses, thus far, is
just like what we put around
the stuff we're passing
as inputs to a function.
All right, just an
arbitrary human convention.
Use parentheses.
Inside of those parentheses
we've been putting double quotes,
and then a string like "hello world."
>> But in that earlier example very
briefly did we look at with Scratch.
And we had the percent d, what else
was inside of those parentheses
that I called out verbally?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: So it's what you're taking
[INAUDIBLE] from within [INAUDIBLE]
what these [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
So we had the percent d.
But then we had close
quote, comma, counter.
Right.
We specified what we want
to do as the placeholder.
So what I'm going to do here is
comma, what do you want me to put?
AUDIENCE: S.
DAVID J. MALAN: S,
because s in this case
is the name of the storage container.
It's the name of that glass bowl.
Whereas before it was counter in that
simple Scratch example we looked at.
So now having made two
changes, let me zoom in
and try once more to
compile this program.
>> Now I see that cryptic line.
But that's actually the
name of the compiler.
Clang is the name of the compiler.
Make is just saving me
the headache of ever
typing that long crazy command out.
So now if I do dot slash hello-1,
I should see "hello, David."
>> Pretty underwhelming, though, right?
We could have done
this a lot more simply
without talking about variables
and CS50.h and all of that.
So let's make it a
little more interesting.
>> In addition to CS50.h,
having things like string
declared, the CS50 library
also has a few functions.
So just like years ago, someone wrote
printf and put it in standard I/O.h
and some other file.
>> We, the CS50 staff, wrote a function
called GetChar, GetDouble, GetFloat,
GetInt, GetLongLong, GetString,
and we put those inside a file
called CS50.h and CS50.c.
And we put them inside
of the CS50 Appliance.
And people can also
download them online if they
want to put them on their
own computers as well.
Which is to say that we have created
functions that get input from the user.
I don't know what all
of these data types are.
GetInt is kind of straightforward, like
get an integer somehow from the user.
And GetString is probably like get
a word or a sentence from the user.
>> So let's focus on that.
And I'm going to go back into the
appliance and I'm going to go ahead
and save this file as, let's call
it hello-2.c as my second version.
And let's make a couple of changes.
>> This time instead of
hard coding David, which
makes an incredibly consistent
but underwhelming program,
what if I instead do GetString?
Now notice GetString
has an open parenthesis,
closed parenthesis, because
it doesn't need any input.
It's just going to go get
a string from the user.
>> And now a word on other syntax.
Semicolons just end a line of code.
You don't need them everywhere.
But that just means I'm
done with this line of code.
Let me move onto another
statement or function.
String declares a variable.
String is like saying
give me a bowl, please.
And let me put a string in it.
>> And now the equal sign.
What is the equal sign
essentially equivalent to?
>> AUDIENCE: Assign.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, assigning a value.
So if I, for instance, call
this function GetString,
and we'll see in a moment that's
going to prompt the user for a string.
This is like letting me then write
D-a-v-i-d on a piece of paper.
And when I say string
s equals GetString,
equal doesn't really mean
equal in C programming.
It means assign from the right
hand side to the left hand side.
>> So I've gotten a string.
And the equal sign means put it
in the storage container called s.
And Then pass this off to
printf to actually do its thing.
>> So the end result then is going
to look a little different.
Let's do make hello-2.
Either could work.
You're following along.
Make hello-2 worked.
Dot slash hello-2, Enter.
>> I seem to have an infinite
loop or something.
Nothing's happening.
Why?
>> AUDIENCE: It's making an infinite loop.
DAVID J. MALAN: It is an infinite loop.
It's kind of waiting for me to
actually provide it with some input.
So let me go ahead and type
in David, and hit Enter.
And now it says "hello, David."
If I run it again.
Let's type in Rob, "hello, Rob."
>> Now this is the worst
user interface ever.
The user's apparently
supposed to know what to do.
But no matter.
Using these same building
blocks just like in Scratch,
we can solve that problem and say
something like your name please, colon,
space, closed quote, close
parenthesis, semicolon.
So a lot of again
silliness with the syntax.
>> But notice I've just added a
puzzle piece above this one
and above this one.
So now if I rerun this, hello-2, Enter.
Wait a minute.
What's wrong?
It's not behaving any differently.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: You didn't run make again.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: I didn't
run make again, right.
So I've changed my source code.
But again, there's that flow.
Source code through the compiler gives
you new object code, or 0s and 1s.
So I need to actually
rerun make hello-2 Enter.
OK, something seems to have happened.
Dot slash hello-2.
Your name please.
And to be clear now, why is
the cursor on the same line?
Exactly.
I didn't put the backslash
n up here in my code.
So now I can write
something like Daven, Enter.
I can run it again and type
something like Gabe, Enter,
and we get a different program
again and again and again.
>> Now ultimately we're going to need
to use a few different capabilities.
We need to introduce ultimately some
conditions to do things conditionally.
Maybe loops so we can do
things again and again.
>> Maybe it would be nice if we
could implement our own functions,
like we could implement our own
printf or our own version of GetString
and GetFlow, because ultimately even
using this command line environment
can we do even the most
visually interesting of things.
>> Indeed in conclusion let me do this.
I'm going to go ahead
and close these windows
and open this icon here,
which is just a bigger
version of that embedded
terminal window.
So Gedit has not only
the place for my code,
but also a built in terminal window, the
black and white window where I can run
commands.
>> I just happened to open
a bigger version of this.
And now I'm going to go into
the folder that I've already
put in advance on the course's website.
And I'm going to go ahead and
open a file called thadgavin.c,
which was written by someone else.
>> And if we look at this,
this is not the kind of code
we'll be writing since
the goal of this code
was to write the prettiest
looking code that he or she could,
irrespective of whether or not
another human being could ever
understand this code.
>> Indeed, every year there's what's
called an obfuscated C contest, which
is for real geeks who write
code that no one else can read,
but that does something either
really simple or really amazing.
And we thought we'd
conclude with this look
at something that's pretty amazing
you might have seen once before.
But we'll end on this
note, dot slash, thadgavin.
This then is what awaits.
>> That's it for CS50.
We will see you on Wednesday.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]