>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J MALAN: All right, welcome back.
This is CS50.
This is the end of week seven.
And it's the end of that scavenger
hunt from problem set four
that you might recall.
After recovering all of
those JPEGs of staff,
you were challenged, if you'd like,
to photograph yourself with as many
of those folks as you can.
We got a whole bunch of submissions
over the past few weeks,
indeed, quite a few right before noon
today, some of which are those here,
caught here in-- looks like-- Annenberg
Hall at office hours, one here
in Lowell House with Nick.
Here's Ramon being caught on the phone.
This was at a CS50 lunch.
This was Jason Skyping with
a more creative classmate,
who phoned him this way.
We don't know what this was.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID J MALAN: But
that's worth a gigabyte.
Here is Chang, who
literally ran off the stage
to avoid being photographed one
day, but was eventually caught.
Here is Nick.
And here is Alison down by the fields.
And Zamyla even was found
at a ballroom competition.
So we will go through
these photos, figure out
who submitted the most
the earliest, and reward
one fabulous prize, as
promised in the spec.
And we'll also follow up about
the space that was involved.
>> A couple of announcements-- so lunch
is, again, this Friday at 1:15 PM.
If you'd like to join us,
RSVP at that URL here.
Jason appears again here from one
of the sections a couple of years
back, which happened
to fall on Halloween.
And indeed, he dressed as a
pumpkin that particular year.
If you watch this section
of his from 2011 section
eight, if you are curious,
at CS50.tv, I think
this was the year in which
his air pump was working.
>> If you then watch the
similar section in 2012,
you'll see this Jason much deflated,
since the suit no longer functioned,
which is only to say
this Friday, if you'd
like to carve a pumpkin with Daven
and Gabe and others, RSVP to the heads
at cs50.harvard.edu address.
It promises to be great fun.
Daven, we're told, has carved
pumpkins all of his life.
Gabriel from Brazil has never
carved a pumpkin for Halloween.
So be there with them as he learns.
>> Seminars, meanwhile--
so you'll learn soon
about what our expectations are for
the final project, which essentially
will boil down to
designing and implementing
most any project of interest to
you, albeit subject to the approval
and guidance from your teaching fellow.
Toward the end of the
semester, we introduce a number
of seminars, which are optional classes
led by the teaching fellows and Harvard
staff, friends of the course across
campus, on various topics that
are tangential to the
course's underlying syllabus
but nonetheless applicable, fun, and
different for potential final projects.
>> For instance, first, if you'd like
to register, head to that URL there.
And this is the lineup for
this year's seminars alone.
But realize we have dozens of
seminars from years past, all of which
are linked in the Seminars menu
option of the course's website.
So if you're thinking about
going beyond your comfort zone
or picking up some new skills,
for instance, programming iPhone
apps with Swift, a new language
from Apple or Objective-C
or Android apps or programming [? cue ?]
light bulbs, or any of the topics
up here and more, due check
out the registration page.
>> So we began and concluded on
Monday with looking at HTTP.
So quick refresher-- HTTP,
HyperText Transfer Protocol.
But what does that really mean?
What does that really mean?
Is that a hand?
I know you're just scratching your head.
But you want to propose what HTTP is?
>> AUDIENCE: How computers
communicate with [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J MALAN: I missed the last part.
How computers communicate with--
>> AUDIENCE: Internet servers.
DAVID J MALAN: Good-- with internet
servers, and specifically, web servers.
Because recall, there's a bunch of
services on the internet, some of which
you use probably daily between chat
and message, chat, and web, and email,
and the like.
And HTTP is just the
protocol that web browsers
speak when communicating with
web servers, and vice versa.
And the analog in the
human world might be,
I extend my hand to shake some
other human's and he or she
acknowledges by extending
his or her hand as well.
So that's just a protocol,
a set of conventions.
>> And what indeed are those conventions?
Well, it just boils down to
sending messages back and forth,
as we depicted here.
And there's a couple of ways in
which you can send these messages.
And perhaps the most
common is known as get.
And we'll see a contrast
to this before long.
>> But a get request from a browser
to server just looks like this.
It's a bunch of text that it puts
inside of a virtual envelope.
On the outside of that envelope
go a couple pieces of details.
What needs to go on the
envelope, so to speak,
in order to get a request like
this from me to a web server?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Your IP address.
>> DAVID J MALAN: My IP address
in the From field, so to speak,
and of course, the
recipient's IP address.
But in the case of a web packet,
we need a little more detail
It's not sufficient just to
send an envelope to a server,
because that server might be
listening for different types
of internet traffic.
So what else do we need
besides the recipient's IP?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Is it TCP?
DAVID J MALAN: Good.
TCP--
>> AUDIENCE: Address.
>> DAVID J MALAN: Address,
or port, as it's called.
Close, but a TCP port number.
And there's a bunch of these.
But surely the most
familiar should eventually
be 80, which is the default
one used for web traffic.
And another familiar
one soon will be 443,
which is used for secure web
traffic, URLs that start with https.
>> So this is what goes
inside of that envelope.
And get/ just means, give
me the default web page.
Give me the root of the hard
drive on that web server.
And hopefully, the web
server will respond with, OK
and the number 200, which is just
a convention saying, yes, all
is indeed OK.
Here's the page.
The type of the web page is going to
be text, but more specifically, HTML,
which we're about to dive back into.
And the dot dot dot just
means, here is the HTML.
And that's where we
pick up the story today,
actually writing HTML,
HyperText Markup Language, which
is the language in which
web pages are written.
It's not a programming language.
There's no functions
or loops or conditions.
It's a markup language,
as well again see today,
that allows you to specify
how to structure and stylize
aesthetically a web page.
>> So this was the one
and only page we really
looked at, if briefly, on Monday.
And notice a few
salient characteristics.
There's a lot of open angled
bracket and close angled bracket.
In between those angled
brackets are words.
And we're going to start
calling those words tags.
So open bracket head
and closed bracket head
are the open and closed tags,
or the start and end tags
respectively, of an HTML element,
as we'll call it, called head.
And the same jargon applies
to body in HTML and so forth.
>> And what's nice is
HTML-- and indeed, we'll
spend terribly little time on it,
because you'll mostly just figure out
what features it has when you
actually have a concrete problem
to solve-- you'll find that
a browser is pretty dumb.
It's just going to do-- not unlike
a computer-- what you tell it to do.
And so when you have open
bracket HTML at the very top
there, that essentially
just means, hey, browser,
here comes a web page written in HTML.
>> When it sees open bracket
head, that just means,
hey, browser, here comes the head, or
the topmost portion of my web page.
When it sees a closed bracket
head, that just means, hey,
that's it for the head.
Standby for something else.
And that something else is
apparently going to be the body.
And when you don't have a tag, like
you have just hello, comma, world,
that's just going to be raw text that
ultimately is displayed in the screen.
>> Now, you'll notice too
the indentation here.
You can probably infer
how we're stylizing it.
Every time I open a tag,
so to speak, I indent.
And every time I close
a tag, I un-indent,
similar in spirit to curly braces.
And beyond that, I'm kind
of using my judgment.
Notice that I didn't bother hitting
Enter inside of that title tag.
Why?
Well, I just decided it looked a
little cleaner to me, the human,
to just not bother doing that.
So again, there's some
judgment calls just
like there is in C or any language.
>> But notice too that this indentation
lends itself to a mental model,
not to over complicate it.
But a tree, right?
If you think of a web
page, apparently written
like this, as being
nicely indented that way,
you can almost think of the open bracket
HTML closed bracket tag is demarcating
the root of a node, a family tree
style node in the style of the trees
we looked at last Friday.
>> And indeed, we have on the right here
what we'll call a DOM, D-O-M, document
object model, a fancy way of saying
a tree that represents that HTML.
And notice that HTML has, we'll say,
like a family tree, two children.
On the left is head.
On the right is body.
>> And just as a mindless thought exercise,
head, of course, has how many children
according to this structure?
So just one, title--
and that's why we have
the arrow going from head to the title.
So it's as though that person in the
family tree had just one offspring.
And then title itself can
be said to have a child too.
>> Recall that the HTML had
hello, comma, world beneath it.
And I've simply drawn it within an
oval instead of a rectangle just
to convey semantically that even though
it's a node in the tree, so to speak,
it's sort of fundamentally different.
It's not a tag.
Or more properly, it's not an element.
It's just a text node, if you will.
But these are completely
arbitrary human conventions.
This is just now my way of
representing what I'll as an aggregate
call the document.
>> And as an aside, the thing at
the super top left hand corner,
open bracket exclamation point doc
type HTML, this looks like a tag,
but it's the stupid corner case where
that is just there, copied and pasted
to indicate the browsers
this is HTML version 5.
The world keeps changing what the
first line of code in a page should be.
This just means version 5.
So it doesn't quite
look like the others.
>> All right, so with that
said, you'll now appreciate
this fairly this stupid
tattoo someone got.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID J MALAN: All right,
and now let's actually dive
into doing something with this.
You'll recall that last time
I opened up the CS50 Appliance
and I did something as
simple as opening up gedit.
And I saved the file even on
my desktop-- nowhere special--
as hello.html.
>> So let me do that
again-- hello.html Enter.
And now in this file, I'm going to
go ahead and replicate what we just
saw-- doc type html Then I'm going to
do open bracket html closed bracket.
And then I'm going to preemptively
open and close the tag.
Why?
Just so I don't forget later.
It's just good practice, like opening
and closing curly braces all at once.
>> And then what came next?
You can think of the tattoo.
>> AUDIENCE: The head.
>> DAVID J MALAN: The head.
And then in here, I
had the title, I think.
And the title was arbitrarily,
hello, world close title.
And then down here, the body, of
course-- then we close the body tag.
And then just somewhat redundantly,
I had the same thing down here.
>> So I claim that this is a web page.
This is something that
could now live on the web,
even though of course, it's literally
living on my desktop right now.
But indeed, if I minimize gedit,
I'll see on my desktop its icon.
Even though this is the appliance,
you could do this on Mac OS
without TextEdit or
Windows with Notepad even.
>> And if I go ahead and double click
that even, and select-- well, let's
not select that because
Chrome's not opening.
Let's go ahead and open Chrome.
And then do Command-O for open
And navigate to my desktop
and open that file.
That is how a browser interprets
HTML, top to bottom, left to right.
Hey, browser here's HTML.
Here's the head.
Here's the title.
Here's the body.
And indeed, this is how
it renders that web page.
>> But notice the URL.
None of you could pull up this specific
page on your laptops right now,
even inside of your
appliance via that URL,
because file:// indicates it's actually
on my file system, my hard drive,
not yours.
So this isn't all that useful.
>> Let's now move toward
using an actual web server.
And it turns out the CS50 Appliance
is more than just an environment where
you can write C code and compile
and run it like you've been doing.
It also has been configured by the
staff to represent a typical web
server that's on the internet,
one that you might pay for
or one that's in the so-called cloud.
>> And it's running
standard free open source
software, for instance, something
called Apache, which is perhaps
still the most popular web
server software in the world
that thousands of websites use today.
And it also even has
software like MySQL,
which is a database server
that we'll eventually get to,
which is only to say
I can start treating
my appliance as a full fledged server
that I'm not paying for elsewhere.
It just lives on my own laptop for
development and convenience purposes.
>> So let's go ahead and
take advantage of this.
I'm going to go ahead and
open up a terminal window.
And I'm going to go ahead and
move-- actually, first I'm
going to navigate to my desktop.
If I do ls, there's hello.html.
And I'm going to go
ahead and start using
a new directory we've
not used before today.
>> hello.html-- I'm going to move
to ../vhosts for virtual hosts--
more on that in the future-- and then
into a directory called localhost,
which is the nickname given to almost
any computer, whether it's a Mac, PC,
or Linux computer, and then
specifically into a directory that we,
the staff already created for you when
you downloaded the appliance called
public.
And as its name suggests, anything
I put in this folder, in theory,
is going to now be
public, at least to people
who have a direct
connection to my computer.
>> So now let me go ahead and
do cd to that same directory
so I can see what's
going on and type ls.
And indeed, that's the
only thing in there.
I claim now that because I have put this
file hello.html inside of a directory
called public inside of a directory
called localhost inside of a directory
called vhosts, which
thanks to CS50 staff
has been pre-configured to be
the root of your web server,
I can now hopefully do this.
>> I'm going to open up a new tab.
And I'm going to go not to file://.
I'm going to use actual
http/localhost, which
again, is the nickname
for my own server.
And then I'm going to go to what
file name, just to be clear?
Where is this story probably going?
hello.html.
>> So in other words, I want to now this
is my own computer, my own appliance,
as though it's an actual server.
Its nickname is localhost.
But think of localhost as like
Facebook.com google.com, whatever.
It's just my local name.
And then the final I want is in the
root of the hard drive, so to speak,
or the root of the web server,
ergo the forward slash and then
the file name hello.html.
>> Let me zoom out and hit Enter.
And indeed, there is now my web page.
So it's slightly different.
And it's just as underwhelming.
This is the old version.
Let me shrink the font back.
This is the old.
This is the new.
But what's fundamentally happening
now is that HTTP is being used.
>> Let's make this a little more clear or,
if you will, a little more complicated.
Let me go to the bottom right
hand corner of my appliance.
And notice that all this
time, there's been a number.
That is the unique address
of your CS50 Appliance.
It's a private address,
as implied by the 172.16,
which just means only you physically
can access this web server.
Everything is firewalled and
nicely protected from the rest
of the world because of this addressing.
>> And now notice though if I go to
this address, not in my appliance,
but in Mac OS-- I'm going
to go back over here.
This is my Mac now.
And now I'm going to open up
this version of Chrome here.
And I'm going to go to http://172.16.25
/ and I forget the rest-- 133.
>> So I'm going to visit from my Mac
that IP address /hello.html Enter.
And now I see from my Mac
that my CS50 Appliance, who's
IP address is that
number, is indeed behaving
like a web server on the internet.
It doesn't have a nice easy to
remember name like Facebook.com,
but it's using HTTP
apparently, even though Chrome
is kind of simplifying the world
for us but not showing us HTTP.
But this is indeed exactly that.
Chrome is just saving some
keystrokes these days.
And that's what we now see.
>> So that's all fine and good.
But it's a pretty underwhelming page.
Let me go in and do something
a little different now.
So let me go back to gedit.
And instead of hello,
world, let's put an image.
And I claimed from before-- let me go
into my localhost directory public.
And let me go ahead and copy a
whole bunch of files from today
from my Dropbox folder into here.
>> Now if I type ls, look
at all these files
that I've distributed by the
course's website in advance of today,
one of which is still hello.html.
So there's that one.
And recall this silly one
from last time-- cat.jpg .
So let me try to embed
cat.jpg inside of my web page.
>> I'm going to go ahead
and do cat.jpg, save.
Let me go back to Chrome.
And let me zoom in the
font and now reload.
Oops, where I put this?
Standby-- I still have the old
version from my desktop open.
So let me go into my vhost, my
localhost, my public, and hello.html.
So now let me go ahead and
say cat.jpg inside of the body
where I want it to be
displayed and reload.
Of course, this is not correct.
>> So I need to tell the browser a little
more deliberately what I want it to do.
Simply typing the name is
obviously not sufficient.
So recall that there was another
tag, image, img for short.
That's just because humans
don't like the type full words.
And then we can do source="cat.jpg".
>> And now I'm going to do
one thing different here.
Even though all of
our tags thus far have
had this notion of a
start tag and an end tag,
that doesn't really make
sense for an image, right?
An image is either there or not there.
And so the humans have come
up with a simpler convention.
When you have a tag that can both
start and end at the same time--
it can be empty, so to speak-- just
put the forward slash inside of the tag
at the very end.
Now let me go back to my browser.
Hit Reload Damn, something's wrong.
You've probably seen this
occasionally on the web,
even if it's not been your fault.
It's the web server's fault.
What odes this seem to indicate?
It's broken.
That's where the image belongs.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: But it doesn't
have access to the image.
>> DAVID J MALAN: It doesn't
That, or even worse, maybe
it doesn't even exist.
Let's see if we can't diagnose that.
Recall from last time that if
in Chrome, in the appliance,
or even on your Mac or PC,
you go to the Developer menu
and go to the Developer Tools
option, which probably you've
not used much or ever.
And if I go to Network
and reload the page,
let's actually look at the HTTP
requests that are being made.
>> It looks like hello.html is
indeed OK, hence the 200.
But cat.jpg is a 403.
So it's not a 404.
File probably exists.
403 means forbidden.
So this is a little confusing.
I'm going to go back
to my terminal window.
Let me zoom in up here.
And let me do an ls.
There's those same files.
>> Now let me do a ls-l,
which you've probably
used before to look at file
sizes maybe or timestamps.
And we see a whole bunch of
overwhelming information.
But notice a few details.
Here's hello.html in this
row here and here's cat.jpg.
And it's just the appliance being
user friendly by highlighting JPEG's
in purple like this.
But what else is different beside
the file size and the file name?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J MALAN: Yeah, there's
two more R's over here.
Notice what hello.html has going on.
So it turns out that the name of
this directory public is important.
Anything in this directory
is meant to be public.
But it's not sufficient
just to drop files in there.
You also need to change
the mode of the files,
change the permissions of
the file to proactively not
be the default setting,
which is that only I can read
and write it, I being the owner.
I want the whole world everybody to
be able to read my file, so to speak.
Read just means view it.
>> And indeed, as you'll see in problem
set seven, that's what these R's mean.
These two R's mean let everyone
else in the world also read it,
especially now that
it's in this directory.
So the simplest way to fix this is to
go to my prompt and do chmod for change
mode and then do a+r, altogether,
everyone, all, plus r for read,
and then cat.jpg Enter.
Nothing seems to happen, which
usually means a good thing.
So ls-l again-- now
let's look at cat.jpg.
And this permission
seem to have changed.
As an aside, if you make a
mistake and you, for instance,
just made your-- I don't know-- essay
publicly accessible by accident,
you can do the opposite, chmod a-r.
Though frankly, it shouldn't
be in the public directory
anyway if that's the concern.
>> So now let's go back to
my browser and reload.
And I'm going to click
the little Ghostbusters
symbol to clear that part of the
screen so we can see new requests.
And indeed, here is
Grump Cat from before.
But more importantly,
technically, there is
the number 200, which
means we got it OK.
All right, so that's all fine and good.
But we're not making
the best of websites,
nor are we going to try too hard to
make the fanciest of websites today.
But let's at least do something
super familiar before rattling
off a few other tags.
So suppose I don't just want a cat here.
Suppose I actually want this
cat to link to something.
>> I might, for instance
do something like this.
a for anchor href for
hyper reference equals--
and let's just do something
like www.google.com close
quote close bracket.
And now search for cats.
Close anchor tag.
So this has only one sort
of fundamentally new detail.
The tag of course, is different.
It's the name a for anchor
href or hyper reference.
>> But more importantly, there's
this syntactical feature here.
This is what we'll start calling
not a tag, but an attribute.
And an attribute is something that
modifies the behavior of a tag.
And this attribute, href, means
modify the behavior of this anchor
so that when it's clicked,
it goes to this URL here.
And of course, that URL is Google.
>> Meanwhile, what is this
text here going to be?
Well, that's going to be
what the human actually
sees as the underlined
link, as simple as that.
So let's try this.
Let me save it.
I'm still in hello.html.
But in the versions online, you'll see
the actual file names we pre-prepared.
Let me go ahead and reload.
And now it's a very
underwhelming page still.
But if I hover over there--
and it's a little small,
but-- you can see in the bottom
left hand corner of your screen,
it's indeed going to google.com.
And if I click that, it will
whisk me way to the actual Google.
>> But notice here an opportunity for
exploitation, just as an aside.
And we'll come back to other
issues of security before long.
Because there's this dichotomy
between where you go and what you say,
you could do something like
this-- http://www.google.com.
OK, and now if I reload
after saving that page,
it looks like I'm going to go to Google.
But there's no reason I
have to go to Google, right?
I could actually go to something like
badguy.com, reload the page over here.
And notice, it still looks like Google.
And only if I'm sharp
enough to hover over here
do I see it's even going to
go to a different location.
>> So if you've ever gotten
an email, especially
one from Paypal, or
seemingly from Paypal
asking you to log in
to your account, this
is why you should never
ever click links in emails,
frankly, any links in emails.
If you know you have actual
money in Paypal or Bank
of America or Fidelity or any
website, manually type it in.
Because look how easy it is to
trick someone into presenting what
looks like a link.
But it actually could
go absolutely anywhere.
>> And there's far greater
threats than this.
In fact, this is a bit
of a tangent now, but one
of the best ones I ever saw
which has since been closed,
is someone led people
to-- so this might say,
click here to log into your
account, a bank account.
And this was Bank of the West.
>> So someone bought this.
And it's a little easier to see
it in a mono spaced font zoomed
in on a 30-foot projector.
But when it's small font in an
email that you're receiving,
this looks like bankofthewest.com,
not bankofthevvest.com,
which someone had paid $10 to buy.
And then this led them to the
equivalent of some bad website.
>> And you'll see too-- actually we can do
this-- if I go to the actual website,
bankofthewest.com, again,
recall from last time
that if this is their web page and
you're curious as to how it works,
you can certainly go to
Chrome's developer tools.
And you can see all of the
HTML nicely formatted there.
>> But more to the point,
you cam-- let's close
this-- you can go to View
Developer View Source.
Why don't I just copy
all of that And then I
can go into my little gedit window
here and make my own web page.
Save this in hello.html.
And probably this is going to break,
because it's not this easy usually.
But now if I reload my own page on
my own CS50 Appliance and hit reload,
OK, some stuff broke.
But I'm pretty close to having
my own banking website, right?
All of this HTML--
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID J MALAN: --I
didn't actually-- and you
know there's someone out there who
would actually click these links too.
So clearly, some stuff broke.
But that's going to lead
us into a discussion,
unnecessarily right now, as to what
CSS, cascading style sheets, are,
and how you actually
download the other HTML files
and JPEG files GIF files that
the website might be using.
But all of that is accomplishable.
But it really boils down to
these very simple heuristics.
>> So now let's just skim through a
couple of other examples of HTML
just to give you a sense
of what else you can do.
For instance, this is list.html.
Suppose I wanted to make a web page
with a list of houses in the quad.
I might use the ul tag for unordered
list and then the list item child
and then iterate over-- or list,
rather-- the houses in question.
>> And if I open this up, let's do this.
Let's go not to hello.html,
but to list.html.
Damn it.
How do I fix this?
It's the same issue as before, right?
So let me do chmod-- oops--
chmod a+r of list.html.
And now if I go back to my browser
and click Reload, there it is.
So if you've ever wanted to make
a bulleted list, you can do that.
If you want to be super fancy and make
an ordered list, not an unordered list,
change those to ol, reload the page, and
now the browser will number it for you.
>> What else can we do?
Well, a couple of others-- if
you've got long paragraphs of text--
for instance, some
Latin text like this--
and you want it in separate paragraphs,
open p, close p for the paragraph tag.
And do it again and again.
And if I now open up this file,
paragraphs.html, well, this
is getting annoying.
So now let's just go back to my
prompt, chmod a+r r star .html--
a nice little wild card so to speak.
It should fix all of
these problems for me.
Let's reload.
There's three paragraphs.
>> And now let's go ahead
and open up one other.
How about table?
You'll notice table looks
a little more complex.
But it's the same idea--
open tag, open tag,
open, open, open, close tag, open tag.
And these happen to stand for
table, whose border is apparently
going to be a thickness 1-- whatever
that means-- table row, table
data, which means a cell.
And if I go back to my browser
here and go to table.html,
you can see something
like this, hideous.
But we'll get to the point
where we can actually
make things prettier than that.
>> So let me stipulate for now.
There's bunches of more tags.
And HTML is wonderful to pick up
because, frankly, all you need to do
is look at existing web pages
with which you're familiar.
And you're like, oh, that's how
they did this aesthetically.
>> Or you can look up any online
resource as to how HTML works,
and you'll see that there's a
whole vocabulary of other tags.
But with the simple mental model
alone that almost any tag you open
has to be closed, it really
does suffice to teach oneself
HTML after understand
these basic ideas of tags
and attributes and the well-formedness
that we've talked about,
closing anything that we might open
so that we don't confuse a browser.
So let's now take this to
a more interesting level
by going to the actual.
And let's go to my Mac
here, to google.com.
And now notice-- let's do this.
I'm gong to go to
Settings, Search Settings.
I want to turn off this annoying instant
results thing where it immediately
starts responding to your typing.
Let's do this older school so
we actually see what's going on.
>> So I'm going to save my
Google settings here.
And now notice-- I'm going to
search for something like cats.
And it's still doing auto
complete here, but based on things
people have typed in the past.
But notice what's going to happen.
>> In the URL at the moment
is this, just google.com.
And technically, it's slash.
Google's just saving a character
and not showing us that.
They are showing us https, just
to be super reassuring that we're
at a secure or encrypted page.
>> So let me go ahead and search for cats.
Now this got really
overwhelming quickly.
Look at the length of this URL.
But it turns out that most of this stuff
in the URL is actually pretty useless.
I'm going to start deleting
things I don't understand.
I see cats.
I understand cats.
I don't know why cats are there again.
I really don't know
what this nonsense is.
So I'm just going to keep
highlighting and deleting stuff
that I don't understand,
distilling the URL into just this.
>> Now let me get enter again.
It looks like Google still works.
So for some reason, they're adding a
lot of stuff to their URL's by default.
But it's not strictly required.
So what is nice about this?
Well, let me go ahead and
open up Chrome's Inspector.
There's a little mouse shortcut for it.
>> Go to the Network tab.
And now let me reload
this page once more.
And I'm holding Shift.
As an aside, browsers
tend to cache or save
information just for efficiency's sake.
But usually, holding Shift and
reloading will force everything
to start over from the beginning.
And that's what I want to do here.
>> And notice all of these
rows that just appeared.
It turns out that in any given web
page, there might be just one file
involved-- hello.html-- or there
might be 52, as in this case.
When I visit google.com,
apparently, my browser
kicks off 52 separate HTTP requests.
Why is that?
>> Well, look at what's inside
of this web page up top.
There's not only text,
but there's actual images
of cats over to the right.
There's a colorful logo up here at left.
There's all of these icons
for a microphone and so forth.
There's a lot of pieces, building
blocks, scratch pieces, if you will,
to this web page.
And what the browser is doing upon
getting the very first file, which
is this row here, it is essentially
iterating over the HTML top
to bottom, left to right, looking for
things like image tags or other tags
that are mentioning other files and
when it sees them, goes and fetches them
via HTTP, viable whole
envelope metaphor,
and then displays them in the
appropriate location in the web page.
>> But notice here if I focus on
the first throw, search cats,
notice that, indeed it's using HTTP 1.1.
And unfortunately, Google
Chrome right now in version 39
is kind of dumbing things down and
not showing us the actual headers.
But what was indeed sent is a request
for not slash, but /search?q=cats.
>> Now, why is that important?
Well, I'm going to infer
from this that if you Google
supports queries of this form, why
don't I implement my own search
engine for CS50, but just the front
end, just the graphical user interface.
And we'll outsource the back end,
the actual search results to Google.
>> So how can I do this?
Well, let me go into gedit over here.
And let me go ahead and open
up, let's say, a new file.
And I'm going to save this
temporarily as search-0.html.
And then eventually, we'll fast
forward to the one I pre-prepared.
>> And I'm going to
quickly whip up doc type
html open bracket html
close bracket html.
Then I'm going to do head
close head open title CS50
Search instead of Google search.
Down here I'm going to have
the body, down here close body.
And now I need CS50 Search.
And actually, let's
build this incrementally.
I'm going to go ahead and close this and
actually put it in my public directory.
So give me just one moment.
search-0.html-- I'm going to
temporally call it search.html.
I'm going to chmod it a+r search.html.
And now I'm going to open it.
All right, so that was fast.
But the goal simply was
to get us to the point
of having this text
file called search.html.
So not much to look at yet.
Indeed, if I go to my browser, and
go to search.html, that's all it is.
But you know what?
I can be a little fancier.
I read in a book that there's
a heading tag called h1.
And I'm going to go ahead and
use that open h1 and close h1.
Reload the page.
And now it's bigger and bolder,
not all that interesting,
but at least it structurally
more interesting.
But now let me introduce another tag.
It turns out there's a form tag.
And let me close that tag.
And it turns out there's
an input tag that
has an attribute called type, which
is the data type of the field,
if you will.
And is going to be of type text.
And its value is going
to be CS50 Search.
Close tag.
And there's going to be no notion of
opening and closing with separate tags.
>> Let me go back over here and
see what's going on, reload.
Getting interesting.
It looks like it's a text field.
And actually, I didn't want
to put a value there yet.
Let me go back here and actually get
rid of this value to keep it simple.
Instead of a value, what I wanted
to give this thing was a name.
And I don't know what it is,
so I'll come back to that.
>> But below that, I want
to do input type=submit.
And this value will be CS50 Search.
And we'll see why I
moved the value to this.
When I reload, I seem to now have
the beginnings of my own search
engine, super hideous,
though frankly, it's
not a far throw from what
Google's default page looks like.
>> If I go here now, I can type in
cats and hopefully click Search.
But I'm not quite done yet,
because I haven't implemented,
obviously, a database.
I haven't crawled the
web for search results.
So I need to outsource that to Google.
So how do I do this?
>> Well, first of all I
need to add and action
attribute to my form tag that
is http://www.google.com/search.
And I know that only from having
inferred by looking closely
at their URL's.
And now take a guess.
What should this text field probably
be called, based on where we came
from before?
>> AUDIENCE: ?q.
>> DAVID J MALAN: ?q.
And we don't actually need question
mark it turns out, but q is indeed it,
q for query probably by
default, just because that's
what Larry and Sergey
came up with years ago.
So now let me reload this page.
It doesn't look all that different.
But now watch what happens.
>> If I type in cats and click
CS50 Search and let go,
notice I get whisked
away to actual Google.
Now, Google is being a little
annoying in that they're
appending an additional parameter,
if you will, to the URL.
That's all happening
automatically on Google side.
>> The important part is that I seem
to have generated this request here.
And indeed, that's what happens.
When you have HTML that
looks like this, this
is sort of web developers notation
for saying, go ahead and create a form
that when it's submitted,
it's going to go to this URL.
And when the URL has provided
values for things like q,
don't go just to this URL.
Actually, go to question
mark and then q=cats.
Append the parameter, the
HTTP parameter like that.
>> And just to be super precise,
what's being inferred here--
but I'll be more explicit-- is
that the method I want to use
is get, instead of something like
post, which we'll eventually see.
So in short, simply by understanding
HTML and using some fairly simple tags,
we can now begin to create
our own front end user
interface with a search
engine behind it.
>> But this of course, is pretty hideous.
So let me actually open up
a slightly better version.
This is the one I prepared in
advance that has some comments.
But you'll see that I
pretty much recreated it.
So this is already available online.
And I did happen to preemptively
go to https just to keep it simple.
>> And now let's open up a
next iteration of this.
Is version 1 instead of 0.
What jumps out at you as slightly
different in this example?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> Yeah, there's this text align center.
This is a little weird up here.
But this is indeed new.
And maybe guess what's going to happen.
If I go to my browser now
and visit search-1.html,
it's almost the same thing.
But it's a step closer to
being a little more pretty.
It's still ugly, but prettier in that
at least everything's now centered.
>> So it turns out that what I'm using
is another language altogether called
CSS, cascading style sheets.
And CSS, frankly, is kind
of, in my personal opinion,
an atrociously designed language.
It is very annoying to remember
all the various details.
But it is what stylizes the
entire worldwide web today.
I offended someone.
All right.
So let's go back here and see
how we're actually using this.
And it turns out, at least it's
actually a pretty simple language.
It's just key value pairs, properties
and values, properties and values.
Indeed, here is one
such property and value.
>> Simply by using the style
attribute on my body tag
and giving it a value of a
word colon and another word,
or a property and a value,
I can affect the aesthetics
of the web page, not
necessarily the structure yet,
but the aesthetics of it.
And just by Googling around, I realize
that CSS, cascading style sheets,
supports a property called
text-align, whose value can
be left, right, or center, for instance.
>> So now when I reload
this page, what I did get
was a centered page,
but still pretty ugly.
Let's go ahead and open
up version 2 of Search.
And now notice I've done a little more.
Notice that up here inside of the head
tag, there can be more than title.
In fact, there's a style tag.
And this is where it just gets a
little messy seeing CSS sometimes.
>> Notice that I seem to have something
that structurally looks very different.
But here is the name of
the tag I want to stylized.
Here are our old friends curly
braces and closed curly brace.
And then here is that
property and its value.
>> If I load this file, search2.html,
the end result is identical.
But it's a step toward better design.
By factoring out this CSS, I've
not commingled it with my HTML.
And indeed, as we'll see, I could
reuse these properties and values.
If I wanted to make bunches of
parts of my web page centered,
I don't have to type style=text-align
center all over the place.
I can put in one place
perhaps, like up at the top.
>> But even this isn't the best design.
In fact, one of the things you'll learn
as you spend more and more time with
web programming is that the more you can
modularize things and factor things out
like .h files let us factor stuff out,
like helpers.c let us factor things out
a few psets ago.
Similarly, might we
want to achieve this.
>> So notice in version
three of search.html I've
cleaned up the head of
the page and just put
in this, a link tag, which
contrary to the name,
does not give you a hyperlink.
It links to another file by way of
an href whose value in this case,
is search-3.css
So I realize we're going quickly.
But all I'm doing is kind
of moving things around.
Let me open search-3.css.
There it is, nothing really to it.
I just copied and pasted it into a new
file, much like we factored stuff out
into other files before.
And the result--
completely underwhelming--
is going to be exactly the same.
But we're moving toward-- no, it's not.
Oh, I know why.
>> So it seems to be a bug.
And it is in some sense.
But let me open up my Network tab.
Let me reload the page.
Ah, why is the CSS not being applied?
Well, the CSS file, similarly, has
to be world readable, so to speak.
And it too is currently forbidden.
So let me do a chmod a+r
of star dot CSS-- whoops--
we're dot CSS is just the
file extension for CSS files.
Now let me go back to
my browser and reload.
OK, a little better.
>> Now let me do one last thing.
In search-4.html.
I have a version that I just thought
was way cooler, albeit way more
complicated.
Let's look at the result first.
Close this to give us more room.
Change this to search-4, Enter.
>> And now a bunch of things are broken.
I'm going to go back
into my directory here.
And now I'm just going to do
a chmod of a+r on a file--
because I know it exists-- called
logo.gif, which is an image.
And now reload.
And wow-- so now I'm
pretty close, frankly,
to like the 1999 version of Google, and
frankly, the 2014 version of Google,
right?
>> So it's now going to their website,
ultimately, if I search for cats.
And indeed it is.
But what did I do differently
in this version 4?
So we won't dwell too much on it here.
You'll see this in problem
set seven eventually.
But notice I did a few things.
>> I introduced a div
tag, which is division,
similar in spirit to a paragraph tag.
But a division is just like, here's
a rectangular invisible region
of the screen.
Let's give it a unique
identifier, a footer, just
so that we can talk about
it in our HTML elsewhere.
Here is another div of the page
whose ID is going to be content.
It's the content of the page.
And up here is the header of the page.
>> In other words, I've
essentially in HTML am mentally
viewing this web page as
three components, a header
up here with this invisible rectangle,
the content in the middle, and then
the footer down below, even
though we don't see those things.
Because I want to in my head of
page here, or in a .css file,
I can use this syntax.
>> Header is not a tag.
It's an ID so it turns
out that by doing #header,
I can now apply one or more
properties to the header.
I can do the same content,
the same for content here.
>> So for instance, in the footer, notice
all of these properties I'm adding.
And I know they exist just by reading
up on the documentation for CSS.
Font size is going to be smaller--
so some relative font size.
The weight is going to be bold.
Margin-- how many pixels
around it-- is 20 pixels.
And it's going to be centered.
>> But right now, the page looks like this.
If I'm not pleased with
my copy right there,
I could do something like color red.
And then I can save this, reload,
and now I've stylized the footer.
So this is just hinting at the power
of what you can do in a web page
to change things around.
>> And even cooler than this, if you want
to poke around with actual websites,
you can't permanently change them.
But if I open up
Chrome's Inspector again
and I go not to the left hand side
here, which shows Facebook's HTML,
but shows on the right
hand side all of its CSS,
you can either and
change things on the fly.
So let me go ahead and do this.
>> Let me go ahead and control
click on this random word here,
sign, and click Inspect Element.
Chrome very conveniently jumps to
the h1 tag that Facebook is using.
And notice here Facebook
has kind of lazily
hard coded font size as a property here.
>> So the cool thing though is
that if I actually go in here
and say, oh, Facebook, I don't like that
64 pixels, we can now change Facebook.
Of course, we're only changing it
for me personally at the moment.
But this is just another
tool in our tool kit
that's going to allow us to tweak
and figure out and also diagnose
issues in our own web pages.
And we could similarly go over
here, which is the same thing.
If you really want to get fancy, I
mean, now you can really mutate the page
and do crazy things.
>> So why is this all useful?
Well, ultimately, we're
going to want to be
able to create web pages that
are driven by our own back ends,
not by just Google and
outsourcing the back end there.
We actually want the
value, for instance,
of our search engine's action
attribute to go not to someone else,
but to something like search.php,
where search.php is on our own server,
not on someone else's.
>> And so to get there, we actually
need to introduce a new language.
So we've already looked at one new
language here, or two really, HTML
and CSS.
But they really are just
structural and aesthetic languages.
They're not programming
languages per se.
And that's about as much formal
time as we'll spend on them.
Because we'll begin now
to transition to PHP.
>> So PHP is an actual
programming language.
It's a scripting language
in the sense that it's
meant to be lighter weight
than something like C.
And it's an interpreted language,
which means it's not compiled.
So in a nutshell, what did it mean
when we used a language like c
and we had to compile it?
What does it mean to
compile C source code?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J MALAN: Say it again?
DAVID J MALAN: Perfect.
It turns it into binary.
It turns it into zeroes and ones
from actual English-like source code.
And then we can actually
run those zeroes and ones
by passing them through the
CPU by double clicking an icon
or running a command.
>> PHP and Python and Ruby
and Perl and JavaScript
and bunches of other
languages are interpreted
languages, which is to say
you do not compile them.
Rather, you feed them as input to
a program called an interpreter.
And that interpreter,
which someone else wrote,
reads your source code top to bottom,
left to right and just interprets
those lines and does what you say.
>> So if you encounter a
line that says print,
it doesn't necessarily convert print
to the corresponding zeros and ones.
It just has this interpreter like
a big if condition that says,
if programmer's instruction is
print, then do the following.
So it interprets it just
by kind of reasoning
through what you're telling it to do.
>> And PHP is one of these languages.
And PHP years ago was designed
precisely for web programming.
And it was initially a
very sloppy messy language.
And indeed, there's a huge
amount of bad PHP code out there.
But the language itself
has matured over the years,
so much so that now it's
actually a wonderful next step
pedagogically from C because it's
so darned familiar to everything
you've just seen in the past few weeks.
>> The one initial difference we'll see
is there's no main function anymore.
When you start writing code, it's just
going to get executed no matter what,
as we'll see in a moment.
Meanwhile, here's what a
variable looks like in PHP.
It's a little different,
but only barely.
>> In PHP, there's not strong typing.
There's week typing,
which just means there
are data types like strings
and numbers and other things.
But you don't bother specifying
what they are anymore.
PHP figures it out for you.
The dollar sign is just a decision
that the PHP people made years
ago such that any variable in PHP
just starts with a dollar sign.
It's actually kind of useful in that
it jumps out at you a little more.
>> But after that, this
is a condition in PHP.
What's different versus C?
Trick question-- nothing,
which is actually really nice.
Boolean expressions in PHP-- the same.
Boolean expressions with and versus
or, switches, loops, loops, loops-- OK,
this one is different.
>> So it turns out there's a
couple of other features in PHP.
One of them is actually this,
which is wonderfully convenient.
If $numbers is an array that you've
declared previously in a program,
you have this fancy for each construct
that instead of doing all of that
annoying I equals 0, I is
less than this, [? I++ ?],
for each numbers as number, where each
of those dollar sign values is just
a variable, and the latter
you can think of as I.
You could call it anything you want.
I called it number.
This is going to iterate over
the array called numbers.
And on each iteration, it's
going to automatically update
for you the dollar sign number
variable so that you constantly
have access to the variable you want
without having to do any square bracket
notation or indexing into an array.
>> Beyond that, we even have things like
arrays, which look almost the same,
except it's very common, as we'll
see, both in PHP and JavaScript
to pre initialize an array
using square brackets.
C uses curly braces.
So it's slightly different, even though
we didn't really use that trick much.
>> But even more powerfully,
PHP has associative arrays,
which is a fancy way
of saying hash tables.
In fact, if you want to declare a hash
table in PHP, unlike in C-- how many
lines of code did it take to
actually implement a hash table in C?
Or how many lines of code is it
taking to implement a hash table in C?
So it's probably a lot, right?
It's a few dozen, maybe 100 or 200.
It's nontrivial.
Or it's about to be, as
you'll soon see, nontrivial
to implement a hash table
[INAUDIBLE] and also a try.
But in PHP-- and frankly, I
probably shouldn't tell you this
until Monday-- in PHP, if
you want a table, done.
That's a hash table-- so
with one line of code.
And
>> A lot of languages do that.
Have fun with pset five.
So a lot of languages do this.
They give you these abstractions
that other people, other programmers,
have created for you so that
you can stand on their shoulders
and start using ideas that are super
compelling, like hash tables and trees
and tries.
But you don't necessarily have to
implement those things yourself.
>> And so ultimately, what
we're going to use PHP for
is potentially writing programs
of the so-called command line.
We could recreate every program
we've written this semester thus far,
except maybe Breakout which uses SPL,
which is specific to C at the moment.
But every other problem set,
certainly Mario and Caesar
and Vigenere and
[? Crack ?] and onward, we
could re-implement in PHP, and
probably a little more easily.
>> But what we're ultimately going
to use PHP for is web programming.
And we're going to introduce next
week a mental model, a paradigm called
MVC, model view controller,
which if you've done programming
before in Python or
Ruby or elsewhere, you
might know of this team with
Rails and Django and the like.
But if you're new to
this too, you'll see
that this is actually a very natural
extension of the factorization
and the sort of design
of code that we've
been doing in C. We're going to now
apply some of those lessons to PHP
so that ultimately, we are
implementing our own websites.
And if you're sort of
mesmerized or amazed
that we're going to do
all of the so quickly,
realize that almost every
semester, nearly 90%
of students CS50, including those
who have never programmed before,
end up making final projects that
are based on web programming.
And so you will see that the returns
are high in the weeks to come.
So we will see you then on Monday.
>> SPEAKER 1: And now, Deep
Thoughts by Daven Farnham.
Hash tables.
>> [LAUGHTER]