>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
Welcome back.
This is CS50.
This is the end of week 8.
And as you know, we have pretty
regular office hours in a few
of the dining halls,
including Annenberg.
And some of the team kindly
took some photos lately.
And in honor of
Halloween, we thought we'd
share one that rather caught us by
surprise here in Annenberg Hall just
the other night.
Your classmate Jacob posed for
this photo, but was more amusing
was on Facebook, the ensuing
conversation that happened afterward.
>> His first post in response
to his photo was this.
A few minutes later, he decided
to one up himself with this.
It went on then to go to this,
and then, even more amusingly
is when his mom chimed in.
And then ultimately,
it seems this was just
a wonderful ruse for a
play that's going on.
>> So, if you would like
to see Jacob and others,
among them Cynthia Meng, who's
behind the scenes of CS50 zone staff,
head to this URL and this play here.
So without further ado, today we
continue this look at web programming,
and the actual creation of programs
that don't run at your command line,
but instead run inside of a browser.
>> Presumably now, or very
shortly, you're going
to be in the midst of implementing
your own web server, which
is different from web programming.
The web server in pset6 is all about
writing software that knows how to take
HTTP requests from a browser,
or even from you, a human,
with a program called Telnet, and
then respond to those requests either
by spitting out an HTML file, or a
jpeg, or a gif, or even a .php file.
>> But with a web server, it's not
supposed to just open a PHP file,
something ending in .php, and
then spit out the contents.
It's supposed to do
what to that file first?
So to speak.
Not compile it, we said on Monday,
but rather-- So, interpret it.
>> PHP's an interpreted language, and so
one of the key features in your web
server, albeit implemented by us,
is this ability for your web server
to notice, oh.
This is a file ending in .php.
Let me not just send it to the
user like it's static content,
but rather let me read it line by
line, left to right, and interpret it.
>> And to do, that you
guys will essentially
punt to a program in the appliance,
and on a lot of computer systems,
just called PHP.
That is the name of PHP the
language's own interpreter.
So, that piece we implement for
you, and what's left for you,
ultimately, is a number
of pieces, among which
is implementing support
for static content.
>> But now, and with
problem set seven, you're
going to start to transition to
actually writing the PHP code
that gets interpreted
in talking to a back end
database that stores information.
So let's better understand first
a couple of these superglobals
and just how much power you
get out of the box for free
with a language like PHP.
Things you don't have
to implement yourself.
>> So, we saw on Monday $_GET,
which is a superglobal,
which is just PHP speak for a global
variable you can access anywhere.
And what's inside of $_GET?
What's inside of this
superglobal that we see?
Surely statistically at
least one person knows.
What's inside of $_GET?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: It's the variables
you put in the query string.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
It's the variables you
put in the query string.
So, in our older example of
reimplementing Google when we had
a URL, and then question mark,
which demarcates the start of HTTP
parameters, then we had q equal
something, like q equals cats,
what would automatically go inside
of that $_GET super global for you,
because of PHP, is a key of Q,
and of value thereof of cats.
>> In other words, $_GET and all of
these things are associative arrays,
hash tables of sorts, that
store keys and values.
Now, back in pset5, the hash
table you might have implemented,
or the try you might
have implemented, really
was effectively an associative
array, a data structure
whereby you can associate
keys with values.
>> But in pset5, the values were trivial.
The value was essentially true or false.
Is the word in the dictionary?
So, when you hashed a word like apple
to see if apple is in the dictionary,
your check function presumably
returned true or false.
So, that's effectively the
value we're getting back.
>> But we saw on Monday
briefly, you can certainly
associate more interesting
values than just true or false
with keys, like apple.
You could actually return an
arbitrary string, and indeed,
that's what $_GET and these
other variables let you do.
>> So $_POST is similar in spirit,
but if you submit a form via post,
a different HTTP method that's
used for things like credit cards,
and private information, and even
binary information like photos,
those things end up inside of $_POST.
And actually for files
like jpegs and whatnot,
there's even another that's not
up here called $_FILES as well.
>> So, server we won't dwell on too
much, but it gives you access
to sort of lower level details about
the server itself that you're using.
Cookie and session, though,
we'll effectively see now.
The last is what we use to implement
the notion of a shopping cart.
A super simple one, but recall
that we had this example here,
counting how many times you
had visited this page before.
>> But today, rather than just look at
the effect of this, let's open up
Chrome's Inspector,
which you can usually
do by right clicking or Control
clicking anywhere on a web page,
and then choose inspect element.
Or you can go through the menus
that we describe in pset6's spec.
And I'm going to the Network tab
here, and let's watch for a moment
the HTTP traffic that's
going back and forth.
>> Let me first go ahead
and clear Chrome's cache.
So some of you might be familiar
with this technique already,
and we're going to use it
for debugging purposes here.
Now we as computer
scientists are going to start
doing this for debugging
purposes, whereby
we will clear the cache,
typically, so that we
can get rid of things called cookies.
So you're probably generally familiar
with what cookies are, or at least
that they exist, but what's
your understanding of them,
as just a user of
computers, what is a cookie?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: It's a bit of-- well, not
bit in a term of computer science.
It's a piece of data that a
website sends to you in order
to be able to record statistics on you.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, good.
So it's a piece of data that a
server, puts onto your computer,
and let's generalize it even
more, it's a key value-- well,
that's getting more precise.
It is a piece of
information, a piece of data,
that a server is able
to put on your computer
and very often, the server does
this so as to remember who you are.
So for instance, odds
are you're probably
logged into sites like Facebook,
or Gmail, or others before,
and you log in with your
username and password,
and then after that, for some number
of minutes or hours or even days,
the server remembers that
you are, in fact, logged in.
Now, how is that actually happening?
Because you're certainly not retyping
your username and password every time
you navigate to a
different page on Facebook.
So it turns out the
cookies are the answer.
>> A cookie you can think of as,
sort of like, a digital hand
stamp that you might get at an amusement
park or a club that essentially
indicates you have been here
before, and you've already
shown your ID to the bouncer, for
instance, and that the club or the park
should now assume that you
have authenticated already.
You have already been identified by it.
>> So with that in mind,
let's open up counter here.
Let me go ahead, I just did,
and clear all of my cookies.
And now what I'm going to do is
hold Shift, just for good measure,
and forcibly reload the page.
Shift just make sure
that nothing gets cached.
And here's the request
that went back and forth.
So over here we have a request, and let
me zoom in down here, and a lot of this
is sort of uninteresting details for
now that the browser has automatically
sent, but let's click View
Source to see the raw headers.
>> And if you've dived into pset6 already,
you'll certainly recognize things
like this, and maybe some
of these other lines here,
but what's more interesting for today
if I scroll down, not to the request
but to the so-called response,
this line probably looks familiar.
That's a good thing
when you see a 200 OK.
Apparently this is the
date and time on the server
and there's a bunch of stuff.
Oh, this is interesting.
>> Turns out whenever you use
PHP, at least in this server,
the server spits out what
version of PHP you're using.
Which, actually, for security
purposes, is not a good thing.
But, we'll come back to that
some other time perhaps.
But now this is the juicy line today,
and we saw briefly some of these,
I think with Facebook when we poked
around the Inspector at that time,
set cookie is what is planting
that little piece of information
onto your computer.
>> This is an HTTP header
that's effectively
telling your browser,
Chrome, IE, whatever,
hey browser store on the user's
hard drive, or in the user's RAM,
a key called PHPSESSID, which is a
shorthand notation for session ID,
and give it a value of
0vlk8t, dot, dot, dot.
A really long pseudo
random alphanumeric string.
It's just a really big number, but
it's encoded with letters and numbers
so that the size of it can be
even larger than numbers alone.
And then, by the way, Path=/, that
just means that this cookie should be
associated with the
entirety of the website,
not just a specific
page the whole thing.
So this is that virtual hand stamp.
It's as though the server, Facebook,
or in our case the appliance,
has literally written 0vlk8t
and so forth, on your hand.
Notice what the server's,
not doing is it's not
storing my username, certainly
not storing my password.
>> Instead, it appears to be
storing pseudo random information
so that no one can guess
what my hand stamp is.
On the server side,
meanwhile, the server
is going to remember, probably
in a database or something,
that the user, who in the future
presents a hand stamp of 0vlk8t, dot,
dot, dot, should be associated with this
particular shopping cart, so to speak.
In other words, if I now go
back here and reload this page,
how does the server know
that I visited one time?
>> Or if I do it again, how does the server
know that I've visited it two times?
Well if I go down to this
most recent request, which
is now the third that I've sent
in total, notice my request now.
There is still this
request up here, same
as before, there's still a whole bunch
of stuff that we've ignored as before,
but the very last header, this
time, because I've been here before,
is a presentation of
this virtual hand stamp.
>> Whereby this line here, not set cookie
but cookie colon PHPSESSI= 0vlk8t,
that's just my browser's automatic
presentation of this hand stamp so that
now the server, as soon as it realizes,
ooh, this is user 0vlk8t dot, dot, dot,
I can now remember who he or she is
and reassociate with that user whatever
information I want to, and all of
that information can be stored by you,
the programmer, in $_SESSION.
>> So to be clear, if I open up real quick
in gedit that actual file, counter.php,
in my local host public directory
as before, notice that, indeed,
I'm ultimately storing in
$_SESSION quote unquote "counter,"
the value of the previous counter which
I get from these lines up here that we
looked at last time plus one.
So underneath the hood,
that's all cookies are.
It's just the sort of digital
hand stamp going back and forth,
and frankly if you open Chrome's
Inspector on any website
you visit today, with
super high probability,
you're going to see maybe one,
maybe half a dozen cookies
being remembered by you.
>> And worse yet, if those
website you're visiting
all have advertisements, which
is certainly quite common today,
and if those advertisements are coming
from some central party, someone
like Google or AdWords as they
call one of their products
or other such vendors that
sell ads, what's interesting,
and frankly what's a little
worrisome, about how HTTP works,
is that if you have an ad embedded
in Facebook.com, and Google.com,
and Harvard.edu, any number
of websites, so it's such
that there's a middle man who is serving
up ads for all three of those websites,
it turns out that the
cookies are per domain.
>> So if you have an ad coming from the
same company on different websites,
that company can effectively track who
you are across all of those websites.
Harvard might not know
you're visiting Facebook.
Facebook might not know and
you're visiting Harvard.
But whatever ad service
they're using if that domain is
present in both Harvard.edu web
pages and Facebook.com webpages,
this middle man surely knows who you are
because of these cookies being shared
across, or rather to,
that so-called middleman.
>> So we'll come back to this in
security implications thereof,
but there's a lot of information
being stored about you any time you
visit most any web page on
the internet and it really
reduces to this very simple mechanism.
What happens, then, if
you're super paranoid
and you decide to go into Chrome or IE
or whatever and turn off your cookies?
What happens?
Yeah?
You really-- you've done this right?
OK.
No, go ahead.
>> AUDIENCE: Certain websites don't have
a function without it like Facebook.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah!
So certain websites
will just stop working.
And in most websites these days
that fundamentally rely on cookies,
especially if they have you log
in, they're just going to break.
Because consider the
alternative, if the website
has no way of remembering who you are,
and therefore your web browser is not
representing with every HTTP
request of this hand stamp,
effectively a website
like Facebook's going
to have to prompt you to
log in every darn time
you change pages, or click a link, which
is surely not a particularly good user
experience.
>> So that there, too, is
among the trade offs.
So without further ado, let's take
for granted that with web programming,
in languages like PHP, you can remember
information like that in problem set
seven when you implement your own
E*Trade-like website with which to buy
and sell stocks, you'll remember exactly
what the user has bought and sold
and who he or she is
by way of this session.
But we're going to need
a fancier way than email
to start keeping information around.
Right?
>> On Monday, we talked about Frosh IMs
and how in version one of that website,
years ago, all we did was
email the Proctor who's
in charge of the intramural sports
program, the name, and the gender,
and whether or not they're a captain,
and the dorm of someone who's
registering for an intramural sport.
So it's not bad, but he or she then
had to troll through their email,
make a spreadsheet or something like
that, to keep everything organized.
So surely we as programmers
can do this for that proctor.
And so enter in SQL,
Structured Query Language,
which is going to look pretty
different to both C and PHP,
and you'll dive in much more hands on
PHP and problem set seven but also SQL,
or SQL, this is a language that
you use to talk to a database.
>> But what's a database?
Well you think of a
database, at least for now,
as just being like an Excel file, or
if you're a Mac user a numbers file,
or if you're a Google Apps
user a Google spreadsheet,
it's effectively a database, or really
specifically a relational database.
A relational database is just
something that has rows and columns,
and you can store any kind of
information in these rows or columns.
>> But what's nice about SQL, and
about actual databases, not just
spreadsheets or Google spreadsheets,
is that you can use a language
to actually execute queries to
insert data, to remove data,
to look for data, even
most importantly, and you
don't have to use it fairly manually
as you might typically a Google
spreadsheet like this.
>> So in SQL, there's a bunch of
fundamental statements or pieces
of functionality built in.
There's many more than these,
but you can go a huge distance
just by knowing that
this language called
SQL has at least four
statements you can leverage.
>> Delete, for removing data,
Insert, for adding rows,
Update, for changing
rows, and Selecting,
for getting back rows and
that's indeed what SQL does.
It operates entirely on rows so
that when you insert, or remove,
or update, or select what you're
getting back as a so-called result set,
like an array of rows.
A bunch of rows from a table.
>> So back in the day,
and even to this day,
you can interact with the
database using a command line,
but it's not particularly fun to use
this black and white style window
and actually execute commands
and poke around your database.
A graphical user interface, or GUI,
is much more preferable, arguably,
and so the tool we recommend and
preinstalled for you on the appliance
is called phpMyAdmin.
It's a total coincidence that the
name of this thing has PHP in it,
it just means that the people
who wrote this program themselves
wrote it in PHP.
>> But it's ultimately about administering
a database server, like a MYSQL server
that you might have, as you
do, in the CS50 appliance.
So there's more detail here than
we need to care about today,
but what's key is that on the left
hand side is a list of the databases
that you have on your computer,
on your CS50 appliance,
or come final projects that you might
have on a third party, a company's
website or web server, that
you might be paying for space.
So on the left is the
databases, one of which
is pset7 which I borrowed from next
weeks pset, and then on the top
there notice there's a
bunch of tabs, one of which
is databases, SQL, status,
users, export and so forth.
So you can go a long
way just by realizing
that most of the user interface
is in the top left column
and across the top right up there.
So what can we actually do with this?
Well, let's start creating a
bit of information as follows.
>> Suppose the following is the case,
as will be in just a few days,
you want to implement a
website, called CS50 Finance,
and this website lets you buy
quote unquote and sell stocks.
And it's going to figure out
the price of those stocks,
ultimately as you'll see,
by talking to Yahoo Finance.
Which, wonderfully, has a free service
whereby you can pass in a stock ticker
like GOOG for Google, and it will
give you back Google's current stock
price within the past
few minutes at least.
>> So you'll use that, ultimately,
to pretend for the user
to buy and sell actual
stocks using virtual money,
but the very first thing
the user's going to see
is this login screen which asks them
for their username and password.
And so, one of the first
challenges for you in pset7
is going to be to implement the back end
database, the spreadsheet if you will,
that's going to store
users names and passwords
and ultimately what stocks they own, and
how many, and how much cash they have,
so a bunch of other things in
other tables, or spreadsheets.
>> So let's take a look at how this
might appear at first glance.
I'm going to go back to
the appliance and I'm
going to go to this URL here
phpMyAdmin localhost/phpmyadmin
and you'll see that it
takes me to an interface
exactly as we saw on the
screen shot, and here I
have an additional database
called lecture for today
and let me go ahead
first and click on pset7.
>> I seem to have a couple of options,
one for new , for creating a new table,
and a link to users, which
is a table I already created.
So what's a table?
So if you used Excel
before, and if you've
used numbers or Google
Spreadsheets, you open up a window
and you get a whole bunch
of rows and columns,
but then you usually have worksheets
along the bottom, or separate tabs.
You can think of each
worksheet as a table
so that database, ultimately, is a
combination of one or more tables, one
or more worksheets, in the
world of a normal spreadsheet.
So let me go ahead and
click on this worksheet
that I premade, called users, a.k.a.
Database table.
And if I scroll down here,
let me zoom out a bit,
this is what phpMyAdmin is telling
us is inside of this table right now.
It's a little confusing at first
glance because the UI is not
the prettiest thing in the world, but
what is interesting is this part here.
ID, username, and hash.
>> In advance, and you'll be handed
this in problem set seven,
we give you a file containing a super
small database table, borrowed actually
from the hacker edition
of problem set two,
inside of which there are six rows.
One for Belinda all the
way down to one for Zamyla,
and notice to the left of those
usernames are unique IDs like one,
two, three, four, five, six, integers,
and then to the right are hashes.
>> And if, odds are, you didn't do
the hacker edition problem set two,
but a hash is just like an encrypted
password with a few caveats.
And so, what you see here are
the encrypted versions of all six
of our passwords from problem
set two's hacker edition.
Now to the left is just some GUI stuff,
editing this row, copying this row,
deleting this row.
>> But what's interesting
now is the following.
I can actually start
experimenting with this table.
So if I go and click the SQL
tab, I get this big text box.
And this is not how we're going to
do it when actually writing code.
To be clear, phpMyAdmin
is just a tool that's
going to let us poke around the database
and let us experiment with queries.
>> So for instance, suppose
I execute exactly this.
Select, which is one of those
keywords I mentioned earlier, star,
which represents all
the columns in a table.
From what table?
Well, users.
And notice there's this
weird convention in SQL
where you actually use
back ticks, typically,
not single quotes and not double quotes
when you talk about tables names,
so the back quote is the thing on the
top left hand of your keyboard most
likely.
>> So let me go ahead now
and just leave that alone
and scroll down and click Go, and we're
actually going to see the same thing.
We have just executed a SQL query
saying select everything star
from table called users, and
what you get back is this.
Ultimately, we'll be able to
do that same thing in code,
but for now all I wanted to
do was see it in my browser.
Well let's do something
a little different.
Let me go back to the SQL tab,
and let's just say that what?
Zamyla has lost all of her
money, and therefore it's
time for us to delete her as a user.
She's no longer logging in.
>> So I'm going to say delete from--
well, maintain capitalization
for consistency, delete
from users where.
And so, we can have these
predicates, or these
qualifiers, at the end of my statement
where and how could I delete Zamyla?
By her name Zamyla, so the
column, one of the columns
was named, so where name = "Zamyla".
And here I use double
quotes or single quotes,
you only use the back ticks when
talking about the names, for instance,
of tables or fields.
And let me click Go here.
And now, the web page is
being a little uptight.
>> Or, do you really want to execute delete
from users where name equals Zamyla?
Yes.
So now, if we go back to my table
by clicking users, notice that Hm.
I goofed.
And in fact, I kind of
clicked away so fast
you didn't even see the
red error message, perhaps.
What did I do wrong?
AUDIENCE: You didn't need
to capitalize her name.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah I
capitalized her name,
but her username-- actually I
made a couple mistakes, right?
One, her username is
zamyla, lowercase Z,
and the column name is username,
not name, so let's do this again.
Let me go ahead and
delete from users where
username equals quote unquote "Zamyla".
All right?
So this looks a little better, let
me go scroll down and click Go.
It's still going to
yell at me to be sure.
I click Yes, and now we see,
frankly this happened, really
fast, less than one
second certainly, this
is exactly the query that got executed.
To confirm, let me click users
and indeed now Zamyla is gone.
Now let's do the opposite.
Suppose that Gabe wants to
register for the website.
What's the SQL query, what's the
command I could type to add Gabe?
Well it's pretty straightforward.
Insert into users, and now
it gets a little cryptic.
I need to specify, to the server,
what fields I want to assign.
I don't really care what Gabe's ID
number is, so I'm going to skip that.
I'm instead going to say
username, hash, and then
the values I want to put
there is going to be Gabe.
And then his hash, I don't know.
So for now, I'm going to
leave that as a big to do.
We'll come back to
that in the problem set
spec as to how you actually do that.
>> So notice, again, the syntax.
Insert into table name, then a
parenthesized list of the fields,
the columns you want to add
values to, and then just
the same exact ordering left to
right of the values you want to add,
and it's just wrapping because
the text is a little long.
So now let me click Go.
One row inserted.
And now if I go back to
users, what's interesting
is that not only is Gabe now in the
database, what is apparently his ID?
>> Well it's seven.
Why is it seven when I didn't add it?
So this, too, is one of the
features you get of the database.
A lot of built in functionality.
It turns out that when
created this table,
I preconfigured it's automatically
assign an ID in such a way
that it increments.
So if you've ever poked around,
and looked at what your Facebook ID
number is, these days it's not really
a thing to do, but Facebook as an API,
Application Programming Interface,
whereby you can get back
a whole bunch of data about
yourself, about your friends,
and your connections.
And what used to be kind
of cool, back in the day,
was to look up what your
Facebook ID number was.
Mark Zuckerberg's,
for instance, is three
since he was the author of the site.
And as the story goes, he created
two test accounts, users one and two,
which he then deleted.
And so, Zuck, as is his username
on Facebook, is ID number three,
and all of us have numbers much
larger than three these days.
In fact, at some point
Facebook moved away
from even using an int, which
is a 32-bit value, to using
the next step up,
essentially a long long so
that they could accommodate
even more users registering.
So a fun little historical fact.
>> So that's just the
basic syntax with which
we might execute a couple of
queries, but we can actually
do a bunch more things with SQL.
And you'll see, ultimately,
in the problem set seven
that you have to make a
number of design decisions,
among them is going to be
what data types to use.
So just like in C, there are data
types in a database, like MySQL,
and the data types you have to choose
from include these fields here.
Char, varchar, Int, big int, decimal
and date time, and many others.
So let's actually do this.
Let's pretend that we didn't
hand you this user's table
and let me go ahead and create, for
myself, in the lectures database--
actually let me go ahead and delete
the table I have in here already
so that we can actually create this.
Whoops.
I'm going to drop this
table, and now I'm
going to go again to the
lecture database over here,
I'm going to create a table
called users and let's
just do three columns
initially and click Go.
>> Now, for the most part,
again, this is just
using this graphical tool called
phpMyAdmin, and what we're doing now
is creating a table.
So this is like going File, New,
and creating a new Excel file.
So it's asking me a few
questions, from left to right,
what's the name of the first column,
and then the name of the second column,
and the name of the third.
So let's recreate this.
ID, and then username was one,
and then hash was another.
So what should the data type
be now for a field like ID?
>> Here is the whole list of data types
available to you in a database,
and for now let's just go with int.
32-bit value, I don't
think realistically I'm
going to have more than 4 billion
users in my account, in my service,
so I'm going to keep moving
on to the next question.
I'm not going to specify
a length or values,
it's not applicable
here for an int, per se.
And now I can specify,
apparently, a default
value, which I'm not going to specify.
A collation, I don't know what that is.
An attribute.
Now we actually do
have a design decision.
So there's a few fields here, not all
of which are applicable, but unsigned
just means what?
That the int must be?
Just non-negative.
So it has to be 0 on up.
No, I'm not going to check because
I want every user to have an ID,
it cannot be null.
And then, we get to some more
interesting design decisions like this.
We'll come back to this in a moment,
but what another feature of database
is, is that you can tell
the database server go ahead
and optimize yourself, your
RAM and your hard disk space,
so that selects, and inserts, and
deletes, and updates are really fast.
Contrast this with pset5.
>> If you wanted to look up something
in your hash table, which
you think of as a database,
who had to do all the
work for making your hash table fast.
It's like, obviously, you.
Right?
You had to put in all the time fine
tuning things, getting a hash function
right, figuring out how
many buckets to have.
>> But what's nice, again,
about a database is
you just punt all of
this to other people
who have thought this
through for you, and what
I'm going to say here under
index is that my ID field
is going to be the primary way of
identifying users in this database.
I'm not going to think
of Zamyla as Zamyla,
I'm going to think of
her as the number 6.
>> Why is it, perhaps, better
intuitively to think of and model
each of your individual rows using
a number instead of something
like a string, like the Zamyla
or Gabe or longer string still?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: An ID is unique?
DAVID J. MALAN: Say again?
AUDIENCE: An ID is unique?
DAVID J. MALAN: An ID
is unique, but suppose--
as the case in general
with usernames, suppose
I also said there can only be one
Zamyla in the world, and only one Gabe.
I could impose the uniqueness
constraint on strings, too, if I wanted.
So not a bad thought.
>> AUDIENCE: More secure.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: More secure, why?
AUDIENCE: You can't tell which
is which, as in the user.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, you
can't tell which user
is which so there's a
privacy aspect to it,
especially if the IDs maybe
appearing in the URLs.
So sure, that could kind of work, too.
Other thoughts?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: It's easier to
perform operations on an int.
DAVID J. MALAN: That's the real kicker.
It's just more efficient,
or easier for the computer,
to perform operations on an integer.
Right?
An int is guaranteed to
be 32-bit, whereas Zamyla
is a few characters long, Gabriel
is a few more characters long,
Davenport is really long, and so it's
not particularly efficient to use
strings to compare values and look
for fields, and update fields,
if you can get away
with just one integer.
Just 32 bits.
So usernames, too, this way,
don't have to be unique,
although they probably should
be, and even in this way too
a user could be allowed to
change his or her username.
>> So let's now leave this as the
primary means of identifying the user.
This is telling the database
go ahead and optimize yourself
so that look ups on ID are super fast.
AI, horribly named, just
means Auto Increment,
and this is the check
box we need to check
to specify that the ID field to
be automatically updated for me,
and then I'm going to
scroll to the right here
and frankly I'm not really interested
in any more of these fields.
Certainly not today.
>> So I'm going to go back here,
to the first column, where
I need to specify username
and hash, and let's
at least focus on the
second one for now.
Int is probably not the right call,
so what makes more sense perhaps?
>> AUDIENCE: Text.
DAVID J. MALAN: Say again?
AUDIENCE: Text.
DAVID J. MALAN: Text?
OK, I heard text.
What else?
We kind of have a bunch of choices
that are textual in nature.
So when, and why, do
you use some of these?
Well char, contrary to what you might
think, is not a single character.
It's a specific number of characters.
So if we know that all usernames
must be like eight characters,
as used to be common in older
computer systems, I could say char
and then I could say 8 here.
That's when the third column becomes
applicable when creating a table.
>> But that's kind of annoying
because some people might
want to have a longer username
than eight characters,
some people might want to
have a shorter username,
so why commit myself
to a specific number?
Why not have a variable
number of chars and just
say that the maximum length of a name
is, I don't know, like 64 characters.
I can't think of any friends who
have names longer than 64 characters,
and even if that's too short you could
certainly bump it up arbitrarily.
>> So varchar is a variable
number of chars.
Text is not a bad instinct, and
frankly that sort of does what it says,
but a text field can be
like 65,000 bytes at least.
That's probably overkill for a
field, and in fact, yup, 65,535.
name, so we'll stick, typically,
with varchars for textual
field and hash, too.
Hash, it turns out, we could do a
varchar as well or something like that,
but we won't focus today on the
cryptography there and the numbers
that we might actually
want to use for its length.
>> But let me scroll down to the right.
You can only have one
primary index for a table,
but do I want to apply any of these,
now, to username, would you say?
What should username be based on a vague
understanding of these four options?
Just by their names?
>> AUDIENCE: Unique.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So unique, right?
So it turns out that not only could
you tell a database, in advance,
this is the primary way
of identifying fields.
You can also say this is
going to be a unique field.
It's not going to be
the thing I rely on,
but I would like the database to
essentially have that if condition, so
that if I ever tried to register
two users with the same name,
the database flat out
is not going to let me.
I might have some additional code
in PHP that prevents as much,
but the database, too, can ensure
that that's never going to happen.
>> Now, as an aside, especially as
you think about final projects,
keep in mind it index and full
text are actually quite useful.
If you have a larger database, not with
dozens, but with hundreds or thousands
or even millions of fields, you can
also tell the database in advance
this is a field I'm going
to be searching on a lot.
Maybe its username,
maybe it's bio, if you're
making a Facebook-like website that
has paragraphs that the user's allowed
to save, and if you want to
tell the database in advance
I'm going to be searching on this field
a lot, but it's not necessarily unique,
you can specify create me an index.
Or, you can say also allow me to do
sort of arbitrary searches like Command
or Control F, like you
might in a Word Processor,
so you could look arbitrary strings
or substrings in this field.
In other words, we're getting
to the point in the semester
where you don't have to worry about
how to implement things efficiently.
You just need to know about what
design decisions to make so that you're
using the right tools for the
trade in order to leverage features
that other people have built for you.
So to recap, primary should only
have one, you can only have one,
and it's the thing you're committing to
using to identifying fields uniquely.
Unique is just similar in spirit, but
you might only occasionally use it,
but you want the database to impose it.
Index just means preemptively
speed things up in the future
so that I can search for
things in this field.
And then full text is generally for
paragraphs, or essays, or large bodies
of text where you
might also want to have
wild cards like the equivalent of star.
Right.
>> So that was kind of
a lot to all at once.
Let's see if we can't distill
a couple of these features
and then build something
fairly simple, but powerful.
So among the other
design decisions you're
ultimately going to have is along
the lines of storage engines.
And let me just make mention of this
in anticipation of final projects,
and anticipation of let's
say-- no let's do this.
Let's build this little
application first.
I'm going to go into my terminal
window, and in here is not
only counter.php, which we're now going
to get rid of as no longer germane,
but we have a whole bunch
of directories and this
is going to be very similar in spirit
to what you'll see in problem set seven.
>> So we have three directories
includes public and templates, which
is exactly where we left off on
Monday with our whole MVC paradigm.
And to recap, in public is going to go
any file that I want users to actually
v be able to visit in
their browser via URL.
Template.
What did we put in templates?
What kind of stuff?
There wasn't much but a couple
files at least on Monday.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Header and Footer?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Header and Footer.
So we have something similar today, too.
We've got a few more files but
Footer I see, Header I see,
and then a bunch of other files.
So this is the equivalent
of the V MVC view, which,
again, will be a bit more
clear in problem set seven,
but this is just a folder I'm
putting a lot of my aesthetics.
A lot of my HTML, a lot of my forms.
Meanwhile, includes, is another
directory that has these three files
and let's take a quick look at these.
>> I'm going to go ahead
and open up config.php.
As it turns out, much
like earlier in the term,
you sharp included
CS50 dot h with pset7.
In today's example, you're going
to do the equivalent of that
with a require statement
that effectively
includes these several lines.
So to be clear, this is
a file called config.php.
And notice what it's doing.
It's apparently doing something
cryptic, turning on error messages
so that you can see them in the browser.
It's, then, apparently
requiring two other files
so this is like #include in C,
and then this one we did see,
and we've relied on, this turns on
that shopping cart like functionality.
>> This means a cookie will
be sent back and forth.
So why is this interesting?
Well, if we go back to this
directory and open up, for instance,
constance.php.
Notice that PHP does support constants,
it's not quite like #define in C.
Instead, you literally
say defined, and notice
that I've stored in advance
four constants in this file.
One for today's database, for
my password, for my username,
and for the name of the server.
So these are actually going to be
pretty similar in problem set seven.
And lastly, and this is where I'm
going to get some nice functionality
from the staff, in functions.php
is a bunch of code we've written,
and I stole some of this
from problem set seven
for today, that does a bunch of things
and let's just look at one of them
in particular.
This function here,
query, is going to be
the PHP function we call
in order to execute SQL.
A moment ago we were using
phpMyAdmin, but that's just
for sort of learning purposes
and diagnostic purposes
and forgetting your database set.
When you actually use your
database, you, the human,
are obviously not going
to be pulling up a web
page every time someone registers.
You're going to write code that
inserts and deletes users on demand,
and we're going to do this
by way of the query function.
If I now scroll down, there's
going to be a few more features.
Redirect is going to
be a function we wrote
for you that allows you to
send the user to another URL,
and render is a function, quite like
we saw on Monday, that actually renders
a template, but more on these in the
form of pset7's own walk through.
For now, let's go ahead and do this.
>> Let me go into my lectures table and
see that there's currently nothing
here just yet, and let me also go
into my public directory, where
there's just one file, index.php.
This file appears to be super simple
at the moment, it looks just like this.
Very much like how we
left off on Monday.
I'm requiring this file,
config.php, which is in
an includes directory, which
is in dot dot, my parents,
and then it's just rendering this file.
So what is this file?
>> Let's open up in my templates
form.php, and we'll see this.
Super simple, apparently this form is
going to submit by a $_GET or $_POST.
Quick sanity check.
Literally visually search the file.
Method equals post.
So it's not going to use the URL, like
Google does, it's going to sort of hide
the information behind
the scenes and it's
going to submit to a
file called register.php,
and that's the file
we haven't yet written
but what this is going
to look like is this.
>> If I go to a separate page This is
what localhost/index.php looks like.
And again, the server's
just assuming index.php.
Enter.
So that's where we're
at, and what I want to do
is be able to type things
like David, and then
my phone number, which will say
617-555-1212 for now, register
and now register.php was not found.
So I need to implement this.
So let's quickly whip
something like this up.
Let me go into my public directory
and do gedit of register.php,
and now I'm going to go ahead and
start PHP mode, like we did on Monday,
and close PHP's tag, and
let's do a couple of things.
>> So one, I know, from
having written that form,
that I want to check for the following.
If it is empty, whatever the user
typed in to the name field, then
I'm going to say something
like apologize missing name.
Apologize, meanwhile, is
not a built in PHP thing,
it's a function we wrote
in functions.php for pset7
so that you have access to it.
Else if the other field
is empty, number, then I'm
going to apologize to the
user and say missing number.
Save this file.
>> Now let's go back to my browser,
go back to the forum try again.
Register.
OK.
Nothing happened, which is good.
I didn't get an error message.
But if instead, let's reload this
page, and not provide anything.
Damn it.
Do that.
Register.
What did I do wrong?
If empty, $_POST name.
Say again?
>> Oh, of course.
I forgot the most important part, which
is require("../includes/config.php.").
I need to have access to the
apologize function, which
is why nothing was happening.
The function doesn't actually exist.
So let's try this again.
Let's reload the page, click Register.
OK.
There it is.
So, the output we're
seeing here is the result
of calling an apologize
function, super simple,
and it just prints out whatever
I give it as an argument.
>> All right, so let's cooperate.
Let's provide my name
like David, register,
missing number OK let's
provide that, too.
617-555-1212.
Register.
OK.
So all is well now, just nothing
interesting is happening.
So now let's make something more
interesting happen like this.
Let me go into phpMyAdmin, and let's
actually create a table called users,
I'm going to give it three
columns, and I'll quickly
create ID, and then
name, and then number,
and the ID field I'm
going to leave as an int.
The name field I'm going
to leave as a varchar,
and we'll say 64, somewhat arbitrarily.
The number I'm going
to make, you know what?
We're going into
support US numbers here,
so I'm going to do something
like char and then 10 characters
max for an area code
and then seven digits.
And then over here, I'm going to
specify auto increment this field,
make this a primary key, and
I'm going to go ahead and not
check any of these other boxes.
>> So when I now finally click Save,
and I go back to my users table,
this is what it looks like if I
now click a New Tab structure.
So this, to be clear,
is just phpMyAdmin's way
of saying your database table
has an ID, a name, and a number
with those particular configurations
and we'll ignore the rest of the fields
there for now.
>> So now what do I want to do?
So if I go now into my
source code, if all is well
I want to execute the following query.
Insert into, and I can just
say users I don't strictly
need those back ticks if it's
not a dangerous word like users.
I'm going to say name,
number, and then here I'm
not going to hard code the
digit of the values yet.
I'm going to put two question marks.
And this is a convention
in many languages
whereby if you want to have
a placeholder for a string
you're going to use the question
marks, for reasons we'll
come back to chat about
security, and here
I'm going to pass in those
two fields post name,
and then post number,
and now save the file.
>> And now I'm going to
go down here is a super
simply say rendersuccess.php, which
is going to be another template.
I'm going to create really fast.
Geditsuccess.php and I'm just going
to say H1 success in that file.
All right.
So now, let's go back to the
browser, where I visited before.
Let's go ahead and confirm I wrote
in David, I wrote in a phone number,
register.
Damn it.
What did I do wrong?
So I'm seeing an error here, you
have an error in your SQL syntax.
Let me jump back to gedit, let
me go back to register.php,
and what did I omit that
was important last time?
I need this.
You want to know that other than from
having noticed before, but I need this.
>> So now let's go back, and this
was helpful to see in the browser
and that's why in config.php
we spit out errors.
Let's go ahead and reload,
click Continue, success.
So now let me go over to my
database here and click on Users,
and browse, and notice I now
have David in my database here.
Now technically this website is
not yet on the public internet,
so I can't have other
people in putting here,
but if I now wanted to, for
instance, send myself a text message.
Let's go out on a limb here
and see if this actually works.
I'm going to go ahead
and delete this row
and we'll blur this
out in the video later
so we don't have the
entire internet texting me,
and we will now go up to the
browser and we'll go over to lecture
and we'll type in different
number here, register, success.
>> So now, my own number's presumably in
the database, and now the fun part.
Let's actually use PHP to do
something programmatically,
either from the command
line or from somewhere else,
and for now I'm just
going to keep it simple
and I'm going to go into my
directory here and do the following.
Gedit script let's say, we'll
call it text, #!/user/bin/env PHP,
like we saw last time.
PHP.
>> Now I'm going to do require
includes config.php,
even though this might
induce a slight error.
And now I'm going to go ahead and say
rows, query, select star from users,
and now here I'm going to do a technique
from last time for each rows as row.
And I'm going to do something simple.
Printf let's say name is this,
and number is this, backslash n.
And now I'm going to pass
in row quote unquote name,
and row quote unquote number,
and now let's go ahead
and my terminal window
chmod this a + x to make
this script called text executable.
And now let's run text.
>> OK, so progress.
So I've now written a
command line script,
in a language called PHP, that,
because of that require line,
has access to all those configuration
constants that I specified.
The name of the database and so forth.
In fact, just to be clear
that this isn't a fluke,
let me go ahead and register,
really fast, someone else like Rob
and will give him the 555-1212 number.
>> And now, if I run the script
again, notice the power
of what we're doing with the database.
Now I've immediately seen what the
other two rows are in my database.
So now let's try to do something
even fancier inside of,
and this is the part we've
not tested in advance,
so the last time I did this
things went horribly awry,
we have video to that effect.
>> Actually, yeah, funny aside.
So the last time, in a
lecture like two years ago,
we decided, I decided, to be
all this would be a great idea
to dynamically generate emails in
class, using the entire database CS50
students, who had given us their numbers
and their cellphone carriers which you
might recall from pset0,
how to reason, it turns out
I had a minor bug in my program and
did a couple mistakes in 2012, I think.
>> Whereby, one I had for loop that
did exactly this kind of thing,
iterating over the database,
getting a name from the database,
name from the database, and then on each
iteration of that loop I sent an email.
But instead of sending one email, I
sent one email the first iteration,
and two emails a second iteration, sent
three emails a second iteration, which
as you might recall from our
discussion of asymptotic notation
this big O of bad, like n squared
is how many messages I sent,
but it wasn't even emails
it was text messages.
>> And as you know, attendance isn't
super high toward the end the semester
and so I thought it would be cute at
the time to say, "Why aren't you class?"
In the text message I
sent to the whole class,
and it was funny to like 50% of the
class, but the other 50%, some of whom
freaked out, i sent incredibly
apologetic sweet notes
to the staff apologizing for
having missed the lecture just
this once, right?
>> So that would horribly awry.
So in that spirit, let's try this
again but just with my number.
In advance, in functions.php,
I've written this function here.
It's called text, and it
takes in three arguments.
A number, a carrier, and a message.
>> I'm using a switch statement, which
wonderfully PHP take strings, not just
integers, and I didn't implement
all the support for this yet,
I've just done AT&T and Verizon.
Because it turns out
that with these carriers
they have email to SMS gateways,
whereby you can actually
send an email to an address
like phone number at vtext.com
and if the user hasn't blocked
the messages, it'll go through
is a text message.
>> Now to do this, I'm going to have to add
one field really fast to my database.
I'm going to go into
my structure, and I'm
going to go ahead and add a
field at the end of the table.
Let's click Go, and I'm
going to call this carrier
and for now I'm going to
leave this as a bar text,
but we can be fancier in the future.
I'm going to quickly go
into my table, and I'm
going to get rid of Rob,
because that's a fake number,
I'm going to go into edit here and I'm
going to change my carrier manually
to be Verizon, which it
is, and now over here.
>> Let's do a quick sanity check.
Let's open up our text script, which
looks like this, carrier is %s.
We're doing a lot more error
checking than I did in 2012, carrier.
And now, I'm going to go
ahead and re-run the script.
OK.
Carrier is Verizon, which means
now hopefully I can do just this.
Correctly this year,
hopefully, here we go.
>> So inside of this for loop, I'm
going to not only have this printf,
I'm also going to call text and
the usage of this function recall
was it takes a number, a
carrier, and a message.
So let's see, number is going to
be row quote unquote "number,"
row quote unquote "carrier,"
and the last one was message.
Don't screw up this year, semicolon.
>> OK.
Fingers crossed.
Let's see if this works.
All right, so.
Here we go.
Let's unlock the phone,
cross your fingers, damn it.
Undefined variable may-- oh
wait, wait, wait, real fast.
Real fast, real fast.
This is totally worth it.
Let me grab, let me grab, uh-oh.
Thank you, the texts have
started from someone else.
Let me go ahead and open up real
fast, dropbox.php/mail in here.
Standby.
Totally worth it.
Downloads.
OK, source src8m.
OK.
>> Need one more line here.
Oh there it is, it's in Frosh
IMs, it's in register at three.
Oh hello, Margo, thank you very much.
OK, and I was missing this line here.
So let me quickly grab
this line of code,
which includes the mail or library
that I actually want to use,
I'm going to quickly
go back into functions,
I'm going to go to the top of this
file and require this file as well,
and now I'm going to really cross my
fingers when I go back to the command
line script, which is inside of
today's local host directory.
Run text.
Enter.
Mail.
Standby.
Oh, OK.
Here we go.
>> Mail gets new PHP mailer.
Did I do this right?
Damn it.
To-- oh, wait, wait, wait.
Stand by.
I promise, this is
going to be so worth it.
Address.
This is why I don't make the
examples right before class.
Ugh.
The following recipients failed.
Let's try one last thing.
SMTP set from, add address,
the address is indeed that.
Let's try this last part in address.
Aw, I'm really sad right now.
Thank you.
But I really appreciate all
the texts you've been sending.
You've got this David.
You're blowing it.
Let's leave it there and
we will fix on Monday.
See you then.
>> DAVEN FARNHAM: And now Deep
Thoughts by Daven Farnham.
If a binary tree falls in a forest and
no one is around to C it-- [CHUCKLING].