>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID MALAN: This is CS 50, and
this is the start of week nine.
And what we thought we'd do today is not
only close the chapter on last week's
material where we focused on server
side web programming with PHP and SQL,
some database stuff.
We'll talk about a bit of
security today and then
transition to a client side programming
language known as JavaScript.
But first, some redemption.
>> You may recall that on
Wednesday, I set out
to write a website that
took in user's input
by an HTML form that then stored
that user input names, phone
numbers, and cellphone
carriers in the database.
And then I had a little command
line script written in PHP
that was supposed to iterate
over the rows in the database
and send out text messages.
Despite several, several attempts, we
didn't get that working by the end.
>> So I spent this entire week working
on that code to get us past the point
where we left off, whereby all
I got by the end of Wednesday
was this text message
from Margo as I struggled,
followed by a text message from another
classmate, You've got this David.
Followed by this one,
wonderfully encouraging.
Kept on going, very heartening.
I almost got it until then-- and
that's the note we ended on Wednesday.
And then actually perhaps my favorite,
a moment later, this came in.
Damn Live Stream.
>> So today, we fix this with a quick
look at what I've done since.
So all of this code is available
online from last week's, week eight,
source code.
And you'll see that I went through,
and I actually cleaned up things a bit.
I introduced a couple other
features of an SQL database.
For instance, rather than
just make carrier of var char
as I think I did on the fly last week.
I instead defined it as
what's called an enum.
>> And some of you might have seen this
as we explored C. Enum is actually
a feature of C where you can
enumerate a whole bunch of constants
and assign them automatic values,
like one, two, three, four
without having to hard code numbers.
So SQL supports the same, whereby if
you have a database field that you only
want to take on one of finite
values, you can literally specify it
as I have done there for four
popular US cellphone carriers.
>> So I did that.
And I made a number of changes as
well, the most important of which
was to get email working because recall,
that this program relied on which
generally called an email to
SMS gateway, which is just
a fancy way of saying that Verizon, and
AT&T, and other folks support a server,
whereby if it receives
email, it converts it to SMS
and sends out a text
message to someone's phone.
So if I did this correctly,
here is a new and improved form
that is going to talk to
new and improved code, which
you can play with online.
And it will hopefully make my
phone beep in just a moment.
>> So first, I'm going to type in my name.
Second, I'm not going
to do this this time.
I'm going to do Inspect Element.
And this is just a
little thing so I don't
create hours of post production
work as I did last time.
There now is my phone number.
>> I'll select Verizon.
And here, let's turn on this microphone
here, and aim this at my phone here.
I'm going to click Register,
which should hopefully
put it into the database.
Now I'm going to go to the
command line program, which
recall was called dot slash
text, and cross your fingers.
Here we go.
>> [PHONE DINGS]
>> [APPLAUSE]
DAVID MALAN: So more fun than this--
it's fun, of course, if I get into it.
But it's more fun, I thought, if we
created one of those movie moments
where like something really
bad has happened in the world,
and like all the NSA people's
cellphones start beeping
with text messages
alerting them to this fact.
So I thought we would try
to recreate the same here,
whereby not using a database,
I instead in advance
wrote a program that looks like this.
>> This is an index.php--
and I put this code online
as well-- that apparently
just renders form.php,
using an MVC style paradigm that we
talk about in more detail in problem set
seven.
That form is pretty simple.
It's going to submit to a
file called here.php via post.
And it's apparently going to ask
for a name, and a phone number,
and then via of so-called
Select menu, it's
going to give you at least four
popular US cellphone carriers,
and then allow you to effectively
take attendance by clicking here.
>> And here, meanwhile, is going to
borrow some of the code from last time.
And if you just skim this,
you'll see that there's
a whole bunch of error checking.
But the beauty at the end is that
we're not writing to a database today.
We're keeping it simple and
just sending out hopefully
a text message via function I
wrote over the past few days call
Text, which is in Functions. php,
which is again available online.
>> So if you would like to partake in this.
We're not going to be storing anything.
Go to this URL here in real time.
Don't submit it just yet, but let's
see if we can have one of these movie
moments where everyone's cellphone
starts beeping, hopefully just
once this year unlike in 2011
where this went horribly awry.
And once you go to that address,
you should see a super simple form
that if you have a name, a cell phone
number, and a cellphone carrier that
matches the list there, go
ahead and fill out the form.
But don't hit submit just yet.
>> The form's going to look like this.
Go ahead and type in
your name, phone number.
Oop, someone's going ahead of the curve.
It's OK.
OK, everyone's filled out the form.
This should work on a
phone, too, if you want.
All right, on your marks, get set, go.
Hit Here.
What?
No.
I swear to God, I tested
this multiple times today.
You got it?
>> [INTERPOSING VOICES]
>> DAVID MALAN: OK, user error perhaps.
That's two.
It worked for two out of a
few hundred, three, four.
OK, that's good.
Four out of five for
correctness how about.
>> So what just happened?
So presumably, without seeing your
screens, why might it have errored?
It's probably that we were just
trying to make too many connections
to Harvard's mail server all at
once from the same IP address.
I'm just guessing since I didn't
have the luxury of testing
this code with some
300 people in advance
but for now realize that
that at least should
have gotten the job done this time.
>> All right, so why is this all the
more germane to what's going on?
Well first, a quick
couple of announcements.
So one, if you'd like to join Chang, and
Nick, and others at lunch this Friday,
do RSVP at the usual URL there.
If you are thinking of concentrating
in or doing a secondary in CS,
whether you're a sophomore, or freshman,
or even junior or senior at this point
and can still squeeze in the courses,
realize that the engineering school
is gathering for free Ben and
Jerry's ice cream and advice
this Wednesday shortly after class
at 4:00 PM in the CS building
at Maxwell Dworkin.
If this is too fast
on the screen, just go
to cs50.harvard.edu for a
link to the Facebook event
where you can see more details.
>> Meanwhile, I thought I would correct
one other thing I goofed on Wednesday.
Turns out that Mark's ID
on Facebook wasn't three.
It was four.
Turns out he had more test
accounts than I recall.
But what this felt like an opportunity
to do is to pull up a URL like this.
>> So it turns out that Facebook has an
API, Application Programming Interface,
which is a mechanism whereby you
can request data programmatically
at Facebook and get back machine
readable information, not web pages
but just raw text, something
called JavaScript Object Notation.
And in fact, if I visit this
URL, and zoom in, by default,
this is Mark's publicly
accessible information.
>> And the interesting detail
here is just that his ID
is indeed, number four, which I
realized as soon as I did this.
You can do this yourself if you know
your Facebook username if you have one.
Just type it up top there.
And none of this is private.
I'm just doing this even
in the incognito mode.
So I'm not even logged in.
And you're seeing that I
apparently was user number 6,454
on Facebook, which isn't
too bad these days.
So anyhow, you'll also see
additional information there.
>> And the useful aspect
of that is that you
could write your own software that
somehow integrates data like this
into your own application.
You can empower users to
log into your website,
not using their own custom username and
password but maybe their Facebook login
and get information even
about their friends,
if they approve such, or similar.
So note that CS50, too,
has some of its own APIs,
one for the course catalog data,
some for the hugs menus in the dining
halls, all of the
buildings and locations
on campus we have an API for as well
that you can query similarly and get
back textual data that you can integrate
into a PHP, or JavaScript, or even,
though less commonly, a
C based final project.
>> Indeed ahead for the final
project are a few milestones.
You got an email from us the other day.
Realize that the proposal
is due this coming Monday.
It's not necessarily binding, but you
do need to receive your teaching fellows
approval before making
any changes thereafter.
And then ahead are a
number of other milestones.
>> So to tease you, too,
with some possibilities,
we have a bunch of
these hue light bulbs.
And some of you guys now have some
of these in your dorm room as well.
And they too have an API.
So recall those binary bulbs weeks
ago that Dan Bradley and Ansel
Duff created for us.
They used a software interface to
this light bulb, which at the moment
is plugged into electricity
and then via wireless
is connected to a little thing
called the Bridge down here,
like a little router proprietary
to this particular device.
>> But it turns out if I know how to
send HTTP messages, as we all now do,
I can send a message like this to
this light bulb to turn it on or off
or do any number of
other operations on it.
Notice that it's not get, it's not post.
There's another one called put.
There's actually a few other such verbs.
But notice there's a path there,
slash API, slash new developer,
slash light, slash one, slash state.
>> That's apparently just the
path that the company, Philips,
decided you have to hit
with an HTTP request
if you want to change the state
of the bulb using HTTP 1.1.
Then notice the blank line.
And then lastly what looks like
kind of an array of some sort,
this again is going to be called
JavaScript Object Notation, or Jason.
And what you see here is that
there are three key value pairs.
>> One key is called on.
And its value apparently
is going to be true.
Brightness is 128, which
is some kind of int.
And then transition time is
zero, which is apparently
how long it's going to
take to turn this thing on.
>> So right now this light bulb is off.
But if I do exactly this-- let
me go to a little cheat sheet
that Dan set up in
advance-- and I'm going
to go ahead and copy
the following command.
Curl, as some of you
might have gleaned on CS50
Discuss is a utility like Telnet such
that you can simulate HTTP requests,
specifically puts.
I can send this data,
specifically what we just
saw a moment ago specifically
to this URL over here.
And then Curl is going to handle
all of the requisite headers
and parsing there of.
>> So all I have to do is copy this into
a terminal window and then hit Enter.
And the light bulb goes on.
And this is all going through
my computer wirelessly
somehow down to the bridge, which
is then talking to this light bulb.
I can do something else.
I can make this thing
go red for instance.
I can for instance make
this thing go green.
I can make it go blue.
>> And notice in each of these
instances, all that I'm changing
is the so-called hue value to
actually give it some color.
So let me paste this one in as well.
Now it's blue.
>> And you can do even fancier
things where-- let's go to green.
And I could do this of
course with my own code.
But even the API itself
supports funky operations
like this, which will now bother
us for the next 30 seconds.
>> So that's one taste of what you might
do with an API, this one involving
light bulbs.
Note that CS50 has a couple
pairs of Google Glass if you'd
like to tackle something along
those lines, Arduino Unos, which
are tiny little computers,
essentially, on a little circuit board
that you can connect
wires and other things
to and actually control
your real world environment.
And then there are a couple
of new toys that we have.
This one literally just arrived the
other day by mail, a Myo Armband.
And I thought it's a way to
get you excited about projects
that you might use with
this hardware would
be to play this short clip
that they use to tease folks
that we're now living in the future.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID MALAN: So in just a few weeks, you
too can be that cool at the CS50 fair.
Another device that we
have a bunch of that we're
happy to loan out for projects
is called a motion controller.
This is a little USB device
you connect to a computer that
allows you to interact with
your laptop, Mac or PC,
as though you had like an Xbox Kinect
and actually make physical motions much
like we see in this
vision of the future.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID MALAN: So even if you have
no idea how something like that
could possibly be invented or work
on a hardware level, no matter.
Even after just a few months of CS50,
and an understanding of programming
more generally, and web programming more
recently, and then also APIs, and HTTP,
you'll have access via
software APIs if you
do want to borrow one of these
devices to actually talk to it
and not have to worry about
the underlying implementation
details, which is completely
consistent with this notion of layering
an abstraction that we've
seen throughout the semester.
>> So also over the weekend,
saw a couple pieces of news.
Go first, go to seminars if you
would like to learn something
more on any number of topics.
See the URL there.
And this one was sent to
me by Chang, who you know,
who's printing our army of elephants.
And it was a headline as follows.
I'm terrified of my new TV.
Why I'm scared to turn this
thing on and you'd be too.
So we're now at the
point in the semester,
too, where even if you have
the slightest of understanding
of how the web works, and HTTP,
and security, things like this
should start to catch your eye.
But also, you'll understand
whether these things are or are not
actual threats.
>> So I took a few excerpts
from this article here.
And the story is as follows.
I'm now the owner of
a new smart TV, which
promises to deliver streaming
multimedia content, games, app,
social media, and internet
browsing, oh and TV too.
The only problem is that I'm now
afraid to use it, says the author.
You would be, too, if you read through
the 46 page privacy policy for your TV.
The amount of data this
thing collects is staggering.
It logs where, when, how, and
for how long you use the TV.
It sets tracking cookies,
as we've discussed,
and beacons designed
to detect when you have
viewed particular content or
a particular email message
if you want to check email on your TV.
It records the apps you
use, the websites you visit,
and how you interact with content,
doing all of that via your smart TV.
It also, creepier yet--
that's my addition--
has a built in camera
with facial recognition.
>> The purpose is to provide
gesture control for the TV
and enable you to log in to
personalized account using your face.
On the upside, the images are
saved on the TV instead of uploaded
to a corporate server.
On the downside, the internet
connection makes the whole TV
vulnerable to hackers who
have demonstrated the ability
to take complete control of the machine.
>> More troubling, as if that wasn't
smart enough, is the microphone.
The TV boasts a voice
recognition feature
that allows viewers to control
the screen with voice commands.
But the service comes with
a rather ominous warning.
Please be aware that if
your spoken words include
personal or other sensitive
information, that information
will be among the data captured
and transmitted to a third party.
Got that?
Don't say personal or sensitive
stuff in front of your TV.
>> So this is actually for real.
And it's hard not to see if you
go to Best Buy or the like for TVs
these days.
They're all smart in some way.
And they're getting
smarter and creepier.
And they're simply collecting data
in ways that we've talked about
and then uploading it via HTTP or
some other protocol to some server.
>> So this was of a fun article
in this online website
here, which talked about a
particular bug or mistaken code
that we can actually tie
into last week's discussion.
So this headline was as
follows, the story goes here,
Josh Breckman worked for a
company that landed a contract
to develop a content management
system, or CMS as they're called,
for a fairly large government website.
Much of the project involved
developing a content management system
so that employees would be
able to build and maintain
the ever changing
content for their site.
Things went pretty well for
a few days after going live.
But on day six, things went not so well.
All of the content on the
website had completely vanished.
And all pages led to the default,
please enter content web page.
Whoops.
Josh was called in to
investigate and noticed
that one particularly troublesome
external IP address had
gone in and deleted all of
the content on the system.
>> The IP address did not belong
to some overseas hacker bent
on destroying helpful
government information.
It resolved to googlebot.com,
Google's very own web crawling spider.
Whoops.
After a bit of research and scrambling
around to find a noncorrupt backup,
Josh found the problem.
>> A user had copied and
pasted some content from one
page to another, including
an Edit Hyperlink
to edit the content on the page.
Normally this wouldn't be an
issue since an outside user would
need to enter a name and password,
but the CMS authentication system,
the login system,
didn't take into account
sophisticated hacking
techniques of Google Spider.
Whoops.
>> As it turns out, Google
Spider doesn't use
cookies, which means that it can
easily bypass a check for the
is logged on cookie set to be false.
It also doesn't pay attention to
JavaScript, which would normally
prompt and redirect users
who are not logged in.
It does however follow every
hyperlink on every page it finds,
including those with
Delete Page in the title.
Whoops.
>> So what does this mean in more
technical but fairly accessible terms?
It just means that
throughout their website,
they had URLs not unlike this one that
you might see in problem set seven.
Recall in problem set seven
or know in problem set seven
that you're challenged,
among other things,
to sell stocks on behalf of users.
But implementing that feature by way
of get via hyperlinks in your user
interface, probably
not the smartest idea
because if your site is somehow
accessible either by a human
who's clicking around or buy a
bot like Google's or a Spider
as they're called that's just
crawling the web trying to index
the web as a search engine,
they could very easily
hit via get this kind of URL.
And that's functionally
equivalent to, in this case,
selling all shares of Google.
>> Now frankly, it's completely
asinine that the CMS
used JavaScript and cookies
to implement its login system
and not doing that server side, as
you guys do and will in PSet 7--
there's a login.php
file-- always, always,
always security should be
done on the server side,
not on the client side because, as this
article suggests and you might yourself
see at some point, it is
trivial for a user, good or bad,
to just turn off JavaScript
not to mention cookies.
So that is your daily WTF.
>> There's one more, which
is just kind of scary,
so I'll mention it if
only as a life lesson.
Whenever you use an application
called like Snapchat or the like
that says these photos only last for
five seconds, ten seconds, or whatnot.
They're ephemeral That is
absolutely not the case.
Like there is no way, digitally,
to implement some form of video,
or image, or textual sharing such
that a recipient on the other end
can't somehow save the data.
>> In the most naive way, someone
could take their phone.
And they have a 10 second window
while looking at some snap
to just take some other phone
and photograph it, obviously.
So you can preserve
something digitally that way.
Some of you know how to take
screenshots on your phone.
In fact, if you don't know this,
realize that at least Snapchat,
and I think other
applications these days,
at least tell you if the
recipient has actually
taken a screenshot of your image.
>> But worse yet, this was the snappening,
as someone coined it recently,
where some 100,000
snaps had been released
in what's called a torrent file
on various websites ultimately.
And these contained a whole bunch
of private messages and posts.
It turns out most of them benign,
so not what you might expect.
But because people had
used a third party website,
logging in with their Snapchat
username and password and then
saving all of their snaps
on this third party website.
And it was that third party
website that was hacked,
which just meant someone figured out how
to get all 100,000 plus of those images
into their own hard drive
for subsequent sharing.
Frankly, here too, it's sort
of asinine that Snapchat
is implemented in such a way that
a third party can sort of intercept
the data and that it's not tied to your
own application running on the phone.
But here, too, realize that these
things should not catch you by surprise,
or at least there should
be a life lesson in here.
If you'd like the technical
details, go to that URL there
that's in today's slides.
All right, any questions on
today's life lessons in CS?
Turn that off.
Anything at all?
I've got a lot of people checking
their Snapchat or something now.
>> All right, so SQL,
Structured Query Language.
Let's wrap this.
And also, even though
we're just scratching
the surface of this
language, we'll give you
enough of the language
in the form of PSet 7
so that you can tackle some
fairly common functionality.
But realize there are a couple
things we don't require of you,
but they're going to be
important come final projects
and certainly come making actual
websites with actual users
is this design decision.
>> It turns out that in
a MySQL database, you
have bunches of choices like
the data types for your columns
and other things, but you also have
the choice of a so-called storage
engine for all of your data,
the sort of file system,
if you're familiar,
for all of your data.
What format is it ultimately stored in?
And the most common, perhaps, has been
MyiSAM and InnoDB, technical terms
that we'll care about only
to the extent that one has
and one doesn't have
the following feature.
>> Suppose that you have
a little dorm fridge.
And suppose that you and your
roommate, who share this fridge,
are really fond of say milk.
And this is, in fact, how the
story was told to me way back
in the day when I took a course
called CS 161 Operating Systems, which
similarly explores this topic.
So you've got this fridge.
You're out of milk.
And you come home, your roommate's
still at class or whatever,
and you decide I'm going to
go out and get some milk.
So you close the fridge, lockup
the dorm room, go across the street
to CVS or wherever, and get
in line to buy some milk.
>> Meanwhile, your roommate gets home
from class, gets into the dorm room,
opens the fridge, also realizes
ooph, we're out of milk.
So he or she closes the
fridge and then happens
to go to the other CVS,
which happens to be
one block away from the other CVS
in the square, and gets in line
there to get some milk.
Now, of course, a few minutes
later, you both get back,
and the worst of all possible
outcomes has happened.
Both of you have milk.
And you don't really
like milk that much.
So one of them is just
going to sour at some point.
So now you have an excessive amount
of milk in the fridge all because why?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, you didn't
somehow communicate with each other
that you were getting milk.
So in the simplest of
ways in the human world,
how might you avoid this silly
scenario from happening such
that you only end up with one.
Text them, yes good.
But how else?
Post-it notes.
DAVID MALAN: A Post-it note.
Any form of communication
that tells your roommate
don't go into the fridge for milk.
I'm going to go restock on my own.
So you somehow need
to lock this resource.
So we can make this-- we can kind of
ruin the story and turn into a CS story
whereby think of this as just like a
variable, which is storing some value.
And right now, the
value of milk is zero,
which you don't want your
roommate to inspect that variable
and then make a decision him or herself
based on the state of that variable
if you're in the process of
changing the state of that variable.
>> So one of the lines of SQL that we
give you in PSet 7 specification
is this one here.
And we don't spend a huge
amount of time talking about it.
But it turns out, if you are trying
to buy some stock in CS50 finance
that you already have
some shares of, you
want to be able to do a number
of things instantly together.
You want to be able to
effectively, on a high level,
check all right, if I want
to buy more shares of Free,
the penny stock we
talk about in the spec,
I want to first check
how many shares I have.
And suppose it's five.
And suppose I want to
buy 10 more, I ultimately
want to have 15 shares of stock.
So I have to ask two questions.
What's the state of the variable?
What's the state of the row?
How many shares do I currently have?
Then you want to go ahead and update it.
So that's the analog to the
milk in that you check the row,
and then you want to update it
because if you want to buy 10 shares,
you don't want to change
the row to 10, you
want to change it to 5
plus 10 or, of course, 15.
>> This line of code ensures that
those two conceptual ideas
happen together or not at all.
No one, including some other user
who's logged into the same website,
can somehow interrupt
the checking of the row
and the updating of the row, the
select and the update if you will.
And the syntax isn't super obvious,
but this one line, long is it is,
ensures that those two operations
check the variable or check the row
and update the row happen atomically.
>> Oh here we go again.
Text message on my phone.
So let's make this a
little more concrete.
Suppose that you're not
implementing a refrigerator,
and you're not implementing
PSet 7 but an actual bank,
or an ATM, an Automated Teller
Machine, whereby you somehow
want to be able to empower
users to transfer money
from one account to another.
OK, hang on.
I'm going to mute this now, thank you.
So we want to move money
from one account number
into a different account
number, specifically $100.
So this is kind of an arbitrary
example, whereby you, the ATM,
might want to execute two SQL
queries, subtract from one account,
and add to the other account.
But you want to ensure that these
two lines both happen or not at all.
You don't want something
getting interrupted.
You don't some smart bad guy
somehow standing at Bank of America
with two ATMs in front
of him and somehow
sort of typing in the
commands at the same time,
hopefully trying to deduct $200 instead
of $100 and only having $100 credited.
In short, you want this to
behave exactly as you expect.
>> And the way you do
this in SQL database is
you wrap it in what's
called a transaction.
Literally in SQL, you can call CS50's
query function with quote unquote start
transaction.
Then you can execute any number
of subsequent SQL queries,
but none of them take
effect on the database
until you call query quote unquote
commit, if again using PHP.
And in this way, you can ensure that
even if you have 1,000 users all
hitting your database
at the same time, SQL
will promise that these
two queries will be
implemented one right after the other.
So you don't end up with excess of
milk or the wrong amount, ultimately,
of money.
>> So keep this in mind,
not so much for PSet 7
but for final projects
if you're actually
trying to move data around
across tables as you might here.
But perhaps even simpler and more
obvious to understand with an example
is this one here.
And someone emailed us about
this just the other day
when he saw something similar online.
>> So to my knowledge, the pin system
is not vulnerable to this attack.
And I have no idea if it even uses
the SQL database underneath the hood.
But let's use it for
the sake of discussion.
Here's the screen that
Harvard folks tend
to see when logging in with their
Harvard ID number and their pin.
And suppose that the pin system were
implemented in PHP and with a MySQL
database, the code that someone
might have written years ago
might look like this.
First, declare a
variable called username.
And just get that from
the POST superglobal.
Then get another variable
called password and do the same.
And then just execute
this long query here,
select star from users where
username equals such and such
and password equals such and such.
>> Notice that the curly
braces I've used here
just mean to PHP, go
ahead and substitute
the value of those two
variables right there.
They're not strictly necessary, but
they tend to avoid subtle syntax errors.
So this looks completely
correct at first glance.
And it is.
You could implement the
pin system in this way.
>> But suppose that a super
smart and malicious student
input this as his or her pin.
So I've removed the bullet
signs here in the mock up,
and I've actually revealed
what he or she might be typing.
And it's a little strange.
But what jumps out at you at potentially
worrisome about the user's input,
even if you have no idea what
a SQL injection attack means.
Why does this look a little fishy?
What's that?
[INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: The or is
a little suspicious.
In fact, that's a keyword from SQL.
So that doesn't bode well.
The fact that there's
all these single quotes
there-- in fact, one of the easiest
ways to break some databases
is by typing in a name like O'Reilly
that has an apostrophe in it
because if the human who wrote
the code behind the scenes
doesn't take into account that there
might be single quotes in a user's
input, and he or she is using
single quotes in their code,
bad things can happen.
>> In fact, worse yet, consider this.
If this was again the code
that someone at Harvard years
ago wrote for the pin
system, notice what's
about to get substituted
for username and password
if the user types in again
skroob as their username
and then one, two, three, four, five,
quote or quote unquote one equals
quote one.
And notice what's key
here is the user has not
started their password or
their pin with a quote.
And they haven't ended it
with a quote because he or she
is assuming that if the
programmer wasn't so sharp,
they are going to have those
single quotes in their code.
>> So here's the code.
And the substitution that
might now happen is this.
And I've underlined what
the user has typed in.
So before, after.
And notice what's mildly worrisome now
about the right half of this SQL code?
It's a little more complex, admittedly,
than the queries we've seen.
But this can't possibly
be a good thing if you're
saying select star, which is select
everything from the user's table
where username equals skroob and
password equals one, two, three, four,
five or one equals one.
What's the logical implication
of that last clause presumably?
It's just always true.
>> And because we have sort of guessed
or figured out by trial and error
that the programmer who
wrote this code did not
anticipate a human or bad person
typing in single quotes as well,
we can syntactically
complete the SQL query
with something nonsensical
but something that
is syntactically incorrect
that always evaluates to true.
So if this code is being used to answer
the question true or false should
this user be allowed to pass, the
answer is always apparently going
to be true because this is always going
to select something from the database
because one of course always equals one.
>> So what's the solution?
Well in PSet 7, we actually
avoid this all together.
We give you a query function, and we
encourage you to use question marks
as placeholders, similar
in spirit to printf's %s,
but what's key about the question marks
here is if you actually read through
functions.php, where our
query function is implemented,
those question marks are escaped,
whereby anything potentially dangerous
like a single quote is turned
into an escaped single quote.
>> So this is what's
really happening if you
use CS50's query function or any number
of third party free libraries that
do the same.
Doesn't matter in this case, in green,
if the user has typed in a single quote
because the query
function that we wrote is
going to add backslashes before
any such dangerous quote.
So this is not, in
fact, going to be legit.
This is like typing in a crazy looking
password that's, of course, not going
to be skroob's actual password.
>> So the takeaway for CS50 is one,
absolutely always use something
like CS50's query function
or the underlying library,
which happens to be called PDO.
But never, never,
never do code like this
without escaping or scrubbing
as they say your inputs.
And you will at some point probably
come across some website like this.
In fact, it seems to be the case
like at airports and hotels in places
where they have free Wi-Fi
access that you have to login to,
these websites are always
horribly implemented.
And so a sort of fun at home exercise,
not for malicious purposes or more
of a fun on the road
exercise, is to just type
an apostrophe, a single quote,
into a form on some website
and see what happens.
And if the server crashes or gives
you some kind of error message,
it may very well be that
someone hasn't anticipated this.
And then you should alert the proper
authorities and proceed no further.
>> So now you guys should hopefully
understand a bit more geek humor here.
>> [LAUGHTER]
DAVID MALAN: You know you're a geek.
For the next several
years, you will remember
who little Bobby Tables is
because of this cartoon here.
So keep that in mind as we
context switch one last time
today to JavaScript.
We've spent relatively little
time on the syntax of PHP
because it's actually
super similar to C.
And nicely enough, JavaScript too
is super similar to C's syntax
as well as we'll see in
just a moment and as we'll
see later this week in particular.
What you can do with this language,
though, is all the more powerful,
especially with APIs.
>> But first a quick tour.
So one, in JavaScript, there's
no main function, which is nice.
As with PHP, you can just write code.
Conditions look like this.
And Boolean expressions might
look like this or like this.
Switches exist, and they
might look like this.
Four loops look like this.
While loops look like this.
Do whiles look like this.
And then arrays look like
this, very similar to PHP.
But notice, that in JavaScript you
declare a variable not with a dollar
sign, not with a data type but literally
by saying var for variable before it.
It too is loosely typed
in that it has types,
but you don't explicitly declare them.
And then a string, for
instance, might look
like this, that string
being called s in this case.
And then an object.
And these we'll see more before long.
And an object is perhaps one of the
most commonly seen data structures
in a JavaScript based
program because it allows
you to associate arbitrary
key value pairs just
like PHP's associative arrays
and just like your own hash table
or try as we implemented
a few weeks back.
So let's actually see what
we can do with JavaScript.
And in particular, this is
a laundry list of features
that browsers have that
allow us to hook JavaScript
into a website in the following way.
JavaScript is often used as a
client side scripting language.
It's not compiled.
It too is interpreted.
But unlike PHP, which has been running
on the server, in the web server,
or deep inside of the
clients, JavaScript
is different in that it
usually runs in the browser.
>> So any JavaScript code you start writing
for PSet 8, or your final project,
or in the real world is generally going
to be saved on the server, absolutely
in a dot HTML or dot
JS for JavaScript file.
But the browser is going
to download that JavaScript
code to your own instance of Chrome,
or IE, or Firefox, or whatever.
And the code is actually going to get
executed inside of your own browser.
Just to make this more real,
let's see this in concrete form.
>> We have no idea what this code does
without really reading through it.
But let me go to Facebook.com
without logging in.
Let me go to Inspect Element and go to,
let's say, Network and Reload the Page.
And we'll see-- let me shift Reload the
Page to get all the requests to new.
And the very first
file I see is CSS, CSS.
Here's the first
JavaScript file, and I have
no idea what this does, but here
is some of the JavaScript code
that drives Facebook.
It's not even really that
revealing to zoom in.
It's still just as nonsensical.
>> But you'll see even down below, there's
even more of these JavaScript files.
Whoops.
That's a ping.
Let's go down a little
further, further, further.
There's one.
>> So even though Facebook, behind the
scenes, is written in part in PHP
and Facebook's own version thereof,
there's a huge amount of JavaScript.
In fact, any of the
chatting you do on Facebook,
any of the inline timeline updates
that happen in real time, all of that
is driven by JavaScript.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: I'm not sure
if this is Facebook,
but I thought that Facebook developed
their own in-house code language?
DAVID MALAN: They did.
So that's why I say a variance of
PHP called Hip Hop that they actually
added features to such that when
Mark first implemented Facebook,
it was written in PHP.
And that sort of has remained
the sort of front end language
that they use for much
of their coding, but it
hasn't been a language that's
scales particularly well to billions
of people.
And so they have added their own
improvements behind the scenes.
And they use any number
of other languages
for various pieces of
their infrastructure.
So yes, it's a variance of
what we now know as PHP.
>> So let's take a look
at a couple of examples
of how we might use JavaScript here.
In today's source code, we have a
bunch of files, the first of which,
let's called DOM zero.
So DOM zero looks as follows.
Let me go into this directory
and open up domzero.html,
the top of which has a doc type
declaration, saying here comes HTML 5.
And now here's an HTML tag.
Here's the head tag.
And here's what's new today.
>> We now have a script tag
inside of the head of the page.
And this apparently does
very little, but notice
that I've defined a
script, a JavaScript.
And as an aside, since this
is a common misconception,
JavaScript has absolutely nothing
to do with Java, the language
that some of you might
have learned in APCS.
It was more of a marketing
thing than anything,
riding the coattails of Java years ago.
But JavaScript, nothing to do with
Java, just similarly, and annoyingly,
confusingly named.
>> So here is how you declare a function
in JavaScript, literally say function,
then the name of the function,
then any arguments it might take,
just like in PHP.
Turns out in JavaScript, one of the most
annoying functions that exist is Alert.
This is a little window that
will pop up and alert you
to some piece of information.
It's generally frowned upon.
But we'll use it as our
first exercise here.
>> Notice a few features of JavaScript.
Single quotes and double quotes
don't actually matter anymore.
Single quotes and double
quotes can be interchanged,
whereas in C, you have to use
double quotes for strings,
and you have two single
quotes for chars.
In the JavaScript world,
many people, most people
use single quotes around strings
just because it's a stylistic thing.
But what's the plus operator here,
which we haven't seen before?
>> AUDIENCE: Concatenation.
DAVID MALAN: Concatenation.
So C does not even have this.
PHP has the dot operator,
which does this.
JavaScript has the plus operator,
which confusingly is just like Java.
Now what's going on here?
>> So here's where a basic
understanding of that picture
we threw up a couple
days ago comes into play.
Remember when we had a simple
version of an HTML page--
it just said, hello world.
And then we drew a tree
to the right, which
had a bunch of rectangles and lines
connecting them like a family tree.
So that's the so-called DOM
or Document Object Model.
And it turns out that you can access
rectangles in that tree with syntax
like the following.
You literally say document, which is a
special global variable in a JavaScript
program that has a function
associated with it that you can access
similar to a struct, but you simply
say dot and then the function's name,
get element by ID.
>> The element I want to get is
apparently quote unquote name.
And then I want to get its value.
Now we're getting ahead of ourselves.
I'm not even sure what
all this is about.
Let's fast forward to the HTML on
the page, which is super simple.
>> Notice that I've defined
a form down here.
Notice I've given it a unique
ID, even though we've not used
this attribute before.
But this exists in HTML.
You can uniquely identify some chunk
of HTML with an identifier like this.
>> Notice now this-- turns out HTML
supports, per that laundry list
a moment ago, a whole
bunch of event handlers.
And this event handler says on submit.
On the user submission of this
form, call the following code.
And the code that's going
to be called or executed
is exactly this, the Greek
function followed by return false.
Everything else should
be pretty familiar.
>> Here is an input of type text, whose
ID, in this case, is going to be name.
We don't have an actual name attribute
this time-- and a submit button.
So the resulting page looks like this.
And the resulting behavior,
you'll see, looks like this.
The page it local hosts says, hello
David, hardly an aesthetically pleasing
way to greet a user.
But what's actually going on?
>> Well, consider what this is.
This is a text field.
And according to the
HTML here, I've given it
a unique identifier
called quote unquote name.
Meanwhile, I've said when
the user submits this form
by hitting Enter or clicking the Submit
button, call the function called Greet
and then return False.
Let's consider those in reverse.
Notice when I click Submit, the
URL of this page does not change.
The browser's icon
didn't start spinning.
I didn't go anywhere, and that's
literally because I said return False.
Return False short circuits or stops
the default behavior of a form.
So that then leaves us with
this one final question.
What does Greet do?
Well, Greet apparently
calls a function called
Alert, passes in one
long argument that's
the result of concatenating together a
bunch of substrings, hello comma space,
then whatever this returns.
So document is like a global
variable to that root of that tree,
calling a special function,
otherwise now known as a method.
A function that's
inside of a variable is
called a method instead of a function.
>> So get element by ID.
What element do you
want to get by its ID?
Quote unquote name and
then specifically value.
So in other words, that code simply
finds the text field whose ID is name
and then gets its value.
So if I were to change this
and say Davin instead of David,
and click Submit, now we
have a greeting for Davin.
>> All right, so all fine and good.
But let's see if we can make
this a little cleaner since just
writing code like this is
generally going to be frowned upon.
This is going to look scarier.
But what's the first
difference that you note here
in this version besides the
name changing to DOM one?
What structurally looks different
about this versus the other?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Is the form on
top of the script now?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the form is on top
of the script for some curious reason.
So that's the first thing
that jumps out at me, too.
And thankfully at least,
this part is identical.
So the only thing that seems
to be different is this.
>> So here's what's neat
about JavaScript 2.
And it makes it hard to
understand at first glance,
especially for final projects if
you're looking at sample code online,
but it boils down to some
basic syntactic features.
Here again is that
global variable document.
Here again is that method or function
that says get the element by ID.
This time I want to
get the ID called demo.
Where is that?
That's apparently right
here, the form itself.
>> And now notice that apparently if I
get back that node from the tree that
represents the form
itself, not a text field,
it turns out that form, that
node or rectangle from the tree,
has what we'll call a property,
very, very, very similar
in spirit to a struct in C. It's just
a data member inside of this rectangle.
>> So I've got the form
here, and I'm attaching,
or I'm assigning, to its On Submit
handler or rather On Submit property
the following function.
And this is, by far, the craziest
thing thus far syntactically.
It turns out in JavaScript and in
PHP, and frankly for that matter in C,
even though we don't do it, you can
add nameless, anonymous, or AKA lambda
functions that don't have a name
but can be called nonetheless.
>> So what I'm doing here is I'm assigning
this On Submit property, which
is inside of this node of my DOM tree, a
function, function pointer if you will.
That function has no
name, but that doesn't
matter because we'll see
in a moment how to call it.
When this function is called,
this code gets executed, then
false is returned just like before.
>> But notice what I've done.
At this point in the
story, I have a form.
It's got a unique ID called demo.
Down here, I have a script tag
that executes the following code.
It attaches to that node in
the tree to it's On Submit
property this function here.
And just by nature of how browsers work,
when I now click Submit or hit Enter,
that function is going to get called.
It doesn't need a name because who
the heck cares what it's called.
The only time it's ever going to get
called is when I submit the form.
There's no need for me,
the human developer,
to actually call it anywhere else.
>> Now just as a teaser, as if that
weren't mind bending enough,
we can even make this
look more cryptic using
a super popular library called jQuery.
In fact jQuery and JavaScript
are often conflated.
And what we'll do on Wednesday is start
using this language and these libraries
to build increasingly asynchronous
and dynamic applications
like map getting
applications, applications
that update the webpage in real
time, much like Facebook or Gchat
do, and no longer confine ourselves to
hitting Submit by a get or just post
alone.
So I will see you on Wednesday.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]