>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, and this
is the start of week two.
So let us begin today with a bug.
A bug, of course, is a
mistake in a program,
and you'll get very
familiar with this concept
if you've never programmed
before. pset0 and now pset1.
But let's consider something
a little simple at first.
This program here that I
threw together in advance,
and I claim that this should print
10 stars on the screen using printf,
but it's apparently buggy in some way.
>> Given that specification that
it should print 10 stars,
but it doesn't apparently, what
would you claim is the bug?
Yeah?
So it's an off by one error,
and what do you mean by that?
OK.
Excellent.
So we've specified a
start value of zero for i,
and we've specified an n value of 10,
but we've used less than or equal to.
And the reason that this is two
characters and not just one symbol,
like in a math book,
is that you don't have
a way of expressing the
one character equivalent.
>> So that means less than, but
if you start counting at zero,
but you count all the way
up through and equal to 10,
you're of course going to
count 11 things in total.
And so you're going to print 11 stars.
So what might be a fix for this?
Yeah?
>> So just adjust the less than
or equal to just be less than,
and there's, I claim, perhaps
another solution, too.
What might else you do?
Yeah?
>> So start equaling it to 1, and
leave the less than or equal to.
And frankly I would claim
that, for a typical human,
this is probably more straightforward.
Start counting at 1 and
count up through 10.
Essentially do what you mean.
>> But the reality is in
programming, as we've seen,
computer scientists and programmers
generally do start counting at zero.
And so that's fine once
you get used to it.
Your condition will generally
be something like less than.
So simply a logical
error that we could now
fix and ultimately recompile
this and get just 10.
>> Well how about this bug here?
Here, again, I claim that I have
a goal of printing 10 stars--
one per line this time, but it doesn't.
Before we propose what
the fix is, what does this
print visually if I were to compile
and run this program do you think?
Yeah?
>> Star.
So all the stars on the
same line is what I heard,
and then the new line character.
So let's try that.
So make buggy-1, enter,
and I see the clang command
that we talked about last time.
./buggy-1, and indeed I see all 10 stars
on the same line even though I claim
in my specification just a comment atop
the code that I intended to do one per
line.
But this looks right.
>> Now line 15 it looks like I'm
printing a star, and then line 16
it looks like I'm printing
a new line character,
and they're both indented so
I'm inside of the loop clearly.
So shouldn't I be doing star, new
line, star, new line, star, new line?
Yes?
>> Yeah, unlike a language like
Python, if you're familiar,
indentation doesn't
matter to the computer.
It only matters to the human.
So whereas here I've invented lines
15 and 16-- that looks beautiful,
but the computer doesn't care.
The computer cares about
actually having curly braces
around these lines of code.
>> So that it's clear-- just like in
Scratch-- that those two lines of code
should be executed.
Like one of those yellow Scratch puzzle
pieces again and again and again.
>> So now if I re-run this
program-- ./buggy-2-- Hm.
I have an error now.
What did I forget to do?
Yeah, so I didn't compile it.
So make buggy-2.
No such file because I didn't
actually compile the second version.
So now interesting
undeclared variable-- not 2.
We're doing 1.
Make buggy-1-- ./buggy-1-- and now
each of them is on the same line.
>> Now there is an exception to
this supposed claim of mine
that you need these curly braces.
When is it actually OK-- if you've
noticed in section or textbooks--
to omit the curly braces?
Yeah?
>> Exactly.
When there's only one
line of code that you
want to be associated with the
loop as in our first example.
It is perfectly legitimate
to omit the curly braces
just as sort of a convenience
from the compiler to you.
Yeah?
Good question.
Would it be considered a style error?
We would promote-- as in CS50
style guide, the URL for which
is in pset1-- that always
use the curly braces.
Certainly if you're new to programming.
The reality is we're not
going to prohibit you
from doing these conveniences.
But if you're just getting
into the swing of things,
absolutely just always use the curly
braces until you get the hang of it.
Good question.
>> All right.
So that then was a bug.
At least in something fairly simple.
And yet you might think this
is fairly rudimentary, right?
This is sort of the first week
of looking at the language
like, see your bugs therein.
But the reality these are
actually representative
of some pretty frightening problems
that can arise in the real world.
>> So some of you might recall
if you follow tech news,
or maybe even caught
wind of this in February
of this past year that Apple had
made a bit of a mistake in both iOS,
the operating system on
their phones, and also
Mac OS, the operating system
on their desktops and laptops.
And you saw such headlines as this.
And thereafter, Apple
promised to fix this bug,
and very quickly did fix it in iOS,
but then ultimately fixed it in Mac OS
as well.
>> Now none of these headlines alone really
reveal what the underlying problem was,
but the bug was ultimately reduced to
a bug in SSL, secure sockets layer.
And long story short,
this is the software
that our browsers and other
software used to do what?
>> If I said that SSL is
involved, whenever you
visit a URL that starts with HTTPS,
what then might SSL be related to?
Encryption.
So we'll talk about
this in the coming days.
Encryption, the art of
scrambling information.
>> But long story short, Apple
sometime ago had made a mistake
in their implementation of SSL, the
software that ultimately implements
URLs like HTTPS or max
connections there too.
The result of which is that your
connections could potentially
be intercepted.
And your connections were
not necessarily encrypted
if you had some bad guy in between
you and the destination website who
knew how to take advantage of this.
>> Now Apple ultimately posted
a fix for this finally,
and the description
of their fix was this.
Secure transport failed to validate
the authenticity of the connection.
The issue was addressed by
restoring missing validation steps.
>> So this is a very hand wavy explanation
for simply saying that we screwed up.
There is literally one
line of code that was buggy
in their implementation of SSL, and
if you go online and search for this
you can actually find
the original source code.
For instance, this is a screen shot of
just a portion of a fairly large file,
but this is a function apparently called
SSL verify sign server key exchange.
And it takes a bunch of
arguments and inputs.
And we're not going to focus
too much on the minutia there,
but if you focus on the code inside
of that topmost function-- let's
zoom in on that.
You might already suspect
what the error might
be even if you have no idea
ultimately what you're looking at.
There's kind of an anomaly
here, which is what?
>> Yeah, I don't really like
the look of two goto fails.
Frankly, I don't really know what goto
fail means, but having two of them
back to back.
That just kind of rubs me
intellectually the wrong way,
and indeed if we zoom in on
just those lines, this is C.
>> So a lot of Apple's code
is itself written in C,
and this apparently
is really equivalent--
not to that pretty indentation
version, but if you recognize the fact
that there's no curly braces, what
Apple really wrote was code that looks
like this.
So I've zoomed out and I just
fixed the indentation in the sense
that if there's no curly braces, that
second goto fail that's in yellow
is going to execute no matter what.
It's not associated with
the if condition above it.
>> So even again, if you don't quite
understand what this could possibly
be doing, know that each of these
conditions-- each of these lines
is a very important step
in the process of checking
if your data is in fact encrypted.
So skipping one of these
steps, not the best idea.
>> But because we have this
second goto fail in yellow,
and because once we
sort of aesthetically
move it to the left where it
logically is at the moment, what
does this mean for the line
of code below that second goto
fail would you think?
It's always going to be skipped.
So gotos are generally frowned upon
for reasons we won't really go into,
and indeed in CS50 we tend not
to teach this statement goto,
but you can think of goto
fail as meaning go jump
to some other part of the code.
>> In other words jump over
this last line altogether,
and so the result of this stupid
simple mistake that was just
a result of probably someone
copying and pasting one too
many times was that the entire
security of iOS and Mac OS
was vulnerable to interception
by bad guys for quite some time.
Until Apple finally fixed this.
>> Now if some of you are actually
running old versions of iOS or Mac OS,
you can go to gotofail.com which
is a website that someone set up
to essentially determine
programmatically
if your computer is still vulnerable.
And frankly, if it is,
it's probably a good idea
to update your phone or
your Mac at this point.
But there, just testament to just how
an appreciation of these lower level
details and fairly
simple ideas can really
translate into decisions
and problems that
affected-- in this case--
millions of people.
>> Now a word on administration.
Section will start this coming Sunday.
You will receive an email by the
weekend about section, at which point
the resectioning process
will begin if you've
realized you now have
some new conflicts.
So this happens every year, and we
will accommodate in the days to come.
>> Office hours-- do keep an
eye on this schedule here.
Changes a little bit this week,
particularly the start time
and the location, so do consult
that before heading to office hours
any of the next four nights.
And now a word on assessment,
particularly as you dive into problem
sets one and beyond.
>> So per the specification,
these are generally
the axes along which
we evaluate your work.
Scope refers to what
extent your code implements
the features required
by our specification.
In other words, how much of
a piece set did you bite off.
Did you do a third of it,
a half of it, 100% of it.
Even if it's not correct,
how much did you attempt?
So that captures the level
of effort and the amount
to which you bit off the
problem set's problems.
>> Correctness-- this one, to
what extent, is your code
consistent with our
specifications and free of bugs.
So does it work correctly?
If we give it some input, does it
give us the output that we expect?
Design-- now this is the first of
the particularly qualitative ones,
or the ones that require human judgment.
And indeed, this is why we have a staff
of so many teaching fellows and course
assistants.
To what extent is your
code written well?
>> And again this is a very
qualitative assessment
that will work with you on
bi-directionally in the weeks to come.
So that when you get not
only numeric scores, but also
a written scores, or typed feedback,
or written feedback in English words.
That's what we'll use to drive you
toward actually writing better code.
And in lecture and section, we'll try
to point out-- as often as we can--
what makes a program not only
correct and functionally good,
but also well designed.
The most efficient it could be, or
even the most beautiful it can be.
>> Which leads us to style.
Style ultimately is
an aesthetic judgment.
Did you choose good
names for your variables?
Have you indented your code properly?
Does it look good, and therefore,
is it easy for another human being
to read your respective
of its correctness.
>> Now generally per the syllabus, we score
these things on a five point scale.
And let me hammer home the point
that a three is indeed good.
Very quickly do folks
start doing arithmetic.
When they get a three out of
five on correctness for some pset
and they think damn, I going to 60%
which is essentially a D or an E.
>> That's not the way we
think of these numbers.
A three is indeed good, and what we
generally expect at the beginning
of the term is that if you're getting
a bunch of three's-- maybe a couple
of fairs, a couple of fours-- or
a couple twos, a couple of fours--
that's a good place to start.
And so long as we see an
upward trajectory over time,
you're in a particularly good place.
>> The formula we use to
weight things is essentially
this per the syllabus,
which just means that we
give more weight to correctness.
Because it's very often correctness
that takes the most time.
Trust me now.
You will find-- at least
in one pset-- that you
spend 90% of your time
working on 10% of the problem.
>> And everything sort of works
except for one or two bugs,
and those are the bugs that
keep you up late at night.
Those are the ones that
sort of escape you.
But after sleeping on it,
or attending office hours
or asking questions online, is
when you get to that 100% goal,
and that's why we weight
correctness the most.
Design a little less, and
style a little less than that.
But keep in mind-- style
is perhaps the easiest
of these to bite off
as per the style guide.
>> And now, a more serious
note on academic honesty.
CS50 has the unfortunate distinction of
being the largest producer of Ad Board
cases almost every year historically.
This is not because students cheat in
CS50 any more so than any other class,
but because by nature of the work,
the fact that it's electronic,
the fact that we look for it, and
the fact we are computer scientists,
I can say we are unfortunately
very good at detecting it.
>> So what does this mean in real terms?
So it, per the syllabus,
the course's philosophy
really does boil down to be reasonable.
There is this line between
doing one's work on your own
and getting a little bit of
reasonable help from a friend,
and outright doing that work for your
friend, or sending him or her your code
so that he or she can simply
take or borrow it out right.
And that crosses the line
that we drawn in the class.
>> See, the syllabus
ultimately for the lines
that we draw as being reasonable
and unreasonable behavior,
but it really does boil
down to the essence
of your work needing to
be your own in the end.
Now with that said,
there is a heuristic.
Because as you might imagine--
from office hours and the visuals
and the videos we've
shown thus far-- CS50
is indeed meant to be as collaborative
and as cooperative and as social
as possible.
As collaborative as it is rigorous.
>> But with this said, the heuristic,
as you'll see in the syllabus,
is that when you're having some problem.
You have some bug in your code that you
can't solve, it is reasonable for you
to show your code to someone else.
A friend even in the class, a friend
sitting next to you at office hours,
or a member of the staff.
But they may not show their code to you.
>> In other words, an
answer to your question--
I need help-- is not oh, here's my code.
Take a look at this and
deduce from it what you will.
Now, of course, there's
a way clearly to game
this system whereby I'll show you
my code before having a question.
You show me my your code
before having a question.
But see the syllabus again for the
finer details of where this line is.
>> Just to now paint the picture and
share as transparently as possible
where we are at in recent years,
this is the number of Ad Board cases
that CS50 has had over
the past seven years.
With 14 cases this most recent fall.
In terms of the students involved,
it was 20 some odd students
this past fall.
There was a peak of 33
students some years ago.
Many of whom are unfortunately
no longer here on campus.
>> Students involved as a percentage of the
class has historically ranged from 0%
to 5.3%, which is only to say
this is annually a challenge.
And toward that end, what
we want to do is convey one
that we dd-- just FYI-- compare at
a fairness to those students who
are following the line accordingly.
We do compare all current
submissions against all past missions
from the past many years.
>> We know too how to Google around
and find code repositories
online, discussion forums
online, job sites online.
If a student can find it, we can surely
find it as much as we regretfully do.
So what you'll see in the syllabus
though is this regret clause.
I can certainly
appreciate, and we all has
staff having done the course like
this, or this one itself over time,
certainly know what it's like when
life gets in the way when you have
some late night deadline--
not only in this class,
but another-- when you're
completely exhausted, stressed out,
have an inordinate number
of other things to do.
You will make at some point in
life certainly a bad, perhaps late
night decision.
>> So per the syllabus,
there is this clause,
such that if within 72 hours of making
some poor decision, you own up to it
and reach out to me and
one of the course's heads
and we will have a conversation.
We will handle things
internally in hopes
of it becoming more of a
teaching moment or life lesson,
and not something with
particularly drastic ramifications
as you might see on these charts here.
>> So that's a very serious tone.
Let us pause for just a few
seconds to break the tension.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: All right,
so how was that for a segue?
To today's primary topics.
The first of which is abstraction.
Another of which is going to be the
representation of data, which frankly
is a really dry way of saying how can we
go about solving problems and thinking
about solving problems?
So you've seen in Scratch, and you've
seen perhaps already in pset1 with C
that you not only can use
functions, like printf,
that other people in
years past wrote for you.
You can also write your own functions.
>> And even though you might not have
done this in C, and frankly in pset1
you don't really need to write your
own function because the problem--
while perhaps daunting at
first glance-- you'll see
can ultimately be solved with
not all that many lines of code.
But with that said, in terms
of writing your own function,
realize that C does give
you this capability.
>> I'm going to go in today's source code,
which is available already online,
and I'm going to go ahead and open
up a program called function 0.C,
and in function zero
we'll see a few things.
In first lines 18 through
23 is my main function.
And now that we're beginning to read
code that we're not writing on the fly,
but instead I've written in advance
or that you in a problem set
might receive having
been written in advance.
A good way to start
reading someone else's code
is look for the main function.
Figure out where that entry
point is to running the program,
and then follow it logically from there.
>> So this program apparently prints
your name followed by a colon.
We then use GetString
from the CS50 library
to get a string, or a word or phrase
from the user at the keyboard.
And then there's this
thing here-- PrintName.
>> Now PrintName is not a
function that comes with C.
It's not in standard io.h.
It's not in CS50.h.
It's rather in the same file.
Notice if I scroll down
a bit-- lines 25 to 27--
it's just a pretty way of commenting
your code using the stars and slashes.
This is a multi-line
comment, and this is just
my description in blue of
what this function does.
>> Because in lines 28 through 31,
I've written a super simple function
whose name is PrintName.
It takes how many
arguments would you say?
So one argument-- because there's one
argument listed inside the parentheses.
The type of which is String.
Which is to say PrintName
is like this black box
or function that takes
as input a string.
>> And the name of that String
conveniently will be Name.
Not S, not N, but Name.
So what does PrintName do?
It's nice simple.
Just as one line of code for
the printf, but apparently it
prints out "Hello," so and so.
Where the so and so
comes from the argument.
>> Now this is not a huge innovation here.
Really, I've taken a program that could
have been written with one line of code
by putting this up here,
and changed it to something
that involves some six or seven or so
lines of code all the way down here.
>> But it's the practicing of a
principle known as abstraction.
Kind of encapsulating inside of a new
function that has a name, and better
yet that name literally
says what it does.
I mean printf-- that's not
particularly descriptive.
If I want to create a
puzzle piece, or if I
want to create a function
that prints someone's name,
the beauty of doing this
is that I can actually
give that function a name
that describes what it does.
>> Now it takes in an input that
I've arbitrarily called name,
but that too is wonderfully descriptive
instead of being a little more
generic like S. And
void, for now, just means
that this function doesn't
hand me back anything.
It's not like GetString that
literally hands me back a string
like we did with the pieces of paper
with your classmates last week,
but rather it just has a side effect.
It prints something to the screen.
>> So at the end of the day, if I
do make function-0, ./function-0,
we'll see that it asks for my name.
I type David, and it types out my name.
If I do it again with Rob,
it's going to say "Hello, Rob."
So a simple idea, but perhaps
extrapolate from this mentally
that as your programs get
a little more complicated,
and you want to write a chunk of
code and call that code-- invoke
that code-- by some descriptive
name like PrintName,
C does afford us this capability.
>> Here's another simple example.
For instance, if I open up a
file from today called return.c,
notice what I've done here.
Most of this main function is printf.
I first arbitrarily initialize a
variable called x to the number 2.
I then print out "x is now
%i" passing in the value of x.
So I'm just saying what it is.
>> Now I'm just boldly
claiming with printf.
I am cubing that value x, and I'm
doing so by calling a function
called cube passing
in x as the argument,
and then saving the output
in the variable itself, x.
So I'm clobbering the value of x.
I'm overriding the
value of x with whatever
the result of calling
this cube function is.
And then I just print out some
fluffy stuff here saying what I did.
>> So what then is cube?
Notice what's fundamentally
different here.
I've given the function
a name as before.
I've specified a name for an argument.
This time it's called n instead of name,
but I could call it anything I want.
But this is different.
This thing on the left.
Previously it was what keyword?
Boys.
Now it's obviously int.
>> So what's perhaps the take away?
Whereas void signifies sort of
nothingness, and that was the case.
PrintName returned nothing.
It did something, but
it didn't hand me back
something that I could put on the
left hand side of an equal sign
like I've done here on line 22.
>> So if I say into on line 30,
what's that probably implying
about what cube does for me?
Yeah?
It returns an integer.
So it hands me back, for
instance, a piece of paper
on which it has written the answer.
2 cubed, or 3 cubed, or 4
cubed-- whatever I passed in,
and how did I implement this?
Well, just n times n times n
is how I might cube a value.
So again, super simple
idea, but demonstrative
now how we can write functions
that actually had us back
values that might be of interest.
>> Let's look at one last example
here called function one.
In this example, it starts
to get more compelling.
So in function one, this
program-- notice ultimately
calls a function called GetPositiveInt.
GetPositiveInt is not a
function in the CS50 library,
but we decided we
would like it to exist.
>> So if we scroll down later in the file,
notice how I went about implementing
get positive int, and I
say it's more compelling
because this is a decent
number of lines of code.
It's not just a silly
little toy program.
It's actually got some error checking
and doing something more useful.
>> So if you've not seen the walkthrough
videos that we have embedded in pset1,
know that this is a type of
loop in C, similar in spirit
to the kinds of things Scratch can do.
And do says do this.
Print this out.
Then go ahead and get n--
get an int and store it in n,
and keep doing this again and again and
again so long as n is less than one.
>> So n is going to be less than one
only if the human's not cooperating.
If he or she is typing
in 0 or -1 or -50,
this loop is going to keep
executing again and again.
And ultimately notice, I
simply return the value.
So now we have a function
that would've been nice
if CS50 would implement in
CS50.h and CS50.c for you,
but here we can now
implement this ourselves.
>> But two comments on some key details.
One-- why did I declare int
n, do you think, on line 29
instead of just doing
this here, which is
more consistent with
what we did last week?
Yeah?
A good thought.
So if we were to put it
here, it's as though we
keep declaring it again and again.
That in and of itself is
not problematic, per se,
because we only need
the value once and then
we're going to get a new one anyway.
But a good thought.
Yeah?
>> Close.
So because I've declared n on
line 29 outside of the loop,
it's accessible throughout
this entire function.
Not the other functions because
n is still inside of these curly
braces here.
So-- sure.
>> Exactly.
So this is even more to the point.
If we instead declared
n right here on line 32,
it's problematic because guess
where else I need to access it?
On line 34, and the
simple rule of thumb is
that you can only use a variable
inside of the most recent curly braces
in which you declared it.
>> Unfortunately, line 34
is one line too late,
because I've already closed
the curly brace on line 33
that corresponds to the
curly brace on line 30.
And so this is a way of saying
that this variable int is scoped,
so to speak, to only inside
of those curly braces.
It just doesn't exist outside of them.
>> So indeed, if I do this
wrong, let me save the code
as it is-- incorrectly written.
Let me go ahead and do make
function-1, and notice-- error.
Use of undeclared identifier n
on line 35, which is right here.
And if we scroll up
further, another one.
Use of undeclared
identifier n on line 34.
>> So the compiler, Clang,
is noticing that it just
doesn't exist even though
clearly it's there visually.
So a simple fix is declaring it there.
>> Now let me scroll to
the top of the file.
What jumps out at you as
being a little different
from the stuff we looked at last week?
Not only do I have name, not only do
I have some sharp includes up top,
I have something I'm
calling a prototype.
Now that looks awfully similar to what
we just saw a moment ago on line 27.
>> So let's infer from a different
error message why I've done this.
Let me go ahead and
delete these lines there.
And so we know nothing about prototype.
Remake this file.
Make function one.
And now, damn, four errors.
Let's scroll up to the first one.
>> Implicit declaration of function
get positive int is invalid in C99.
C99 just means the 1999
version of the language
C, which is what we're indeed using.
So what does this mean?
Well C-- and more specifically C
compilers-- are pretty dumb programs.
They only know what you've
told them, and that's
actually thematic from last week.
>> The problem is that if I go
about implementing name up here,
and I call a function called
GetPositiveInt here on line 20,
that function technically doesn't
exist until the compiler sees line 27.
Unfortunately, the compiler is
doing things top, down, left, right,
so because it has not seen the
implementation of GetPositiveInt,
but it sees you trying
to use it up here,
it's just going to bail-- yell at
you with an error message-- perhaps
cryptic, and not actually
compile the file.
>> So a so-called prototype up
here is admittedly redundant.
Literally, I went down here and I copied
and pasted this, and I put it up here.
Void would be more proper, so we'll
literally copy and paste it this time.
I literally copied and pasted it.
Really just as like a bread crumb.
>> A little clue to the compiler.
I don't know what this does
yet, but I'm promising to you
that it will exist eventually.
And that's why this line-- in
line 16-- ends with a semicolon.
It is redundant by design.
Yes?
>> If you didn't link your library
to the-- oh, good question.
Sharp includes header file inclusions.
Need to be-- should almost
always be at the very top
of the file for a similar-- for
exactly the same reason, yes.
Because in standard
io.h is literally a line
like this, but with the word printf, and
with its arguments and its return type.
And so by doing sharp include up
here, what you're literally doing
is copying and pasting the contents
of someone else wrote up top.
Thereby cluing your code in to the
fact that those functions do exist.
Yeah?
>> Absolutely.
So a very clever and correct
solution would be, you know what?
I don't know what a
prototype is, but I know
if I understand that C is just
dumb and rethinks top to bottom.
Well let's give it what it wants.
Let's cut that code, paste it up
top, and now push main down below.
This too would solve the problem.
>> But you could very easily come up with
a scenario in which A need to call B,
and maybe B calls back to A. This
is something called recursion,
and we'll come back to that.
And it may or may not be a good
thing, but you can definitely
break this solution.
>> And moreover, I would
claim stylistically,
especially when your programs
become this long and this long,
it's just super convenient
to put main at the top
because it's the thing most
programmers are going to care about.
And so it's a little cleaner,
arguably, to do it the way
I originally did it
with a prototype even
though it looks a little
redundant at first glance.
Yeah?
Sorry, can you say it louder?
>> If you switch the locations of the
implementation and the prototype?
So that's a good question.
If you re-declare this down
here, let's see what happens.
So if I put this down
here, you're saying.
Oh, sorry.
Louder?
Even louder.
Oh, good question.
Would it invalidate the function?
You know, after all these years, I
have never put a prototype afterwards.
So let's do make function-1
after doing that.
>> [MUTTERING]
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, wait.
We still have to put everything up top.
So let's do this up here, if I'm
understanding your question correctly.
I'm putting everything, including
the prototype above main,
but I'm putting the prototype
below the implementation.
>> So if I make one, I'm getting
back an error-- unused variable n.
Oh, there.
Thank you.
Let's see, we get rid of this.
That's a different bug,
so let's ignore that.
Let's really quickly remake this.
>> OK, so data argument not
used by format String
n-- oh, that's because
I changed to these here.
All right, we know what the answer
is going to-- all right, here we go.
Ah, thanks for the positive.
All right, I will fix this code
after-- ignore this particular bug
since this was-- it works is the answer.
>> So it doesn't overwrite
what you've just done.
I suspect the compiler
is written in such a way
that it is ignoring your prototype
because the body, so to speak,
of the function has already
been implemented higher up.
I would have to actually consult
the manual of the compiler
to understand if there's any other
implication, but at first glance
just by trying and experimenting,
there seems to be no impact.
Good question.
>> So let's forge ahead now, moving
away from side effects which
are functions that do something like
visually on the screen with printf,
but don't return a value.
And functions that have return
values like we just saw a few of.
We already saw this notion of scope,
and we'll see this again and again.
But for now, again,
use the rule of thumb
that a variable can only be used
inside of the most recently opened
and closed curly braces as we
saw in that particular example.
>> And as you pointed out,
there is an ability--
you could solve some of these problems
by putting a variable globally
at the very top of a file.
But in almost all cases
we would frown upon that,
and indeed not even go
into that solution for now.
So for now, the takeaway is that
variables have this notion of scope.
>> But now let's look at another
dry way of actually looking
at some pretty interesting
implementation details.
How we might represent information.
And we already looked at this
in the first week of the class.
Looking at binaries, and
reminding ourselves of decimal.
>> But recall from last week that C has
different data types and bunches more,
but the most useful ones
for now might be these.
A char, or character, which happens
to be one byte, or eight bits total.
And that's to say that the size
of a char is just one byte.
A byte is eight bits, so this means that
we can represent how many characters.
How many letters or
symbols on the keyboard
if we have one byte or eight bits.
Think back to week zero.
If you have eight bits,
how many total values
can you represent with
patterns of zeros and ones?
One-- more than that.
So 256 total if you
start counting from zero.
So if you have eight bits-- so if we
had our binary bulbs up here again,
we could turn those light bulbs on
and off in any of 256 unique patterns.
>> Now this is a bit problematic.
Not so much for English and
romance languages, but certainly
when you introduce, for
instance, Asian languages, which
have far more symbols than like
26 letters of the alphabet.
We actually might need
more than one byte.
And thankfully in
recent years has society
adopted other standards that use
more than one byte per charge.
>> But for now in C, the default
is just one byte or eight bits.
An integer, meanwhile, is four
bytes, otherwise known as 32 bits.
Which means what's the largest possible
number we can represent with an int
apparently?
With a billion.
So it's four billion give or take.
2 to the 32th power, if we
assume no negative numbers
and just use all positive
numbers, it's four billion
give or take possibilities.
A float, meanwhile, is a different type
of data type in C. It's still a number,
but it's a real number.
Something with a decimal point.
And it turns out that
C also uses four bytes
to represent floating point values.
>> Unfortunately how many floating
point values are there in the world?
How many real numbers are there?
There's an infinite
number, and for that matter
there's an infinite number of integers.
So we're already kind of
digging ourselves a hole here.
Whereby apparently in computers-- at
least programs written in C on them--
can only count as high as
four billion give or take,
and floating point values
can only apparently
have some finite amount of precision.
Only so many digits after
their decimal point.
>> Because, of course, if
you only have 32 bits,
I don't know how we're going to go about
representing real numbers-- probably
with different types of patterns.
But there's surely a finite
number of such patterns,
so here, too, this is problematic.
>> Now we can avoid the problem slightly.
If you don't use a float,
you could use a double
in C, which gives you eight bytes, which
is way more possible patterns of zeros
and ones.
But it's still finite, which is going
to be problematic if you write software
for graphics or for fancy
mathematical formulas.
So you might actually want
to count up bigger than that.
A long long-- stupidly named--
is also eight bytes, or 64 bits,
and this is twice as long as an int,
and it's for a long integer value.
>> Fun fact-- if an int is four bytes,
how long is a long in C typically?
Also four bytes, but a
long long is eight bytes,
and this is for historical reasons.
>> But the takeaway now
is just that data has
to be represented in a computer-- that's
a physical device with electricity,
it's generally driving
those zeros and ones--
with finite amounts of precision.
So what's the problem then?
>> Well there's a problem
of integer overflow.
Not just in C, but in
computers in general.
For instance, if this
is a byte worth a bit--
so if this is eight bit-- all
of which are the number one.
What number is this
representing if we assume
it's all positive values in binary?
>> 255, and it's not 256, because
zero is the lowest number.
So 255 is the highest
one, but the problem
is suppose that I wanted to
increment this variable that
is using eight bits total
if I want to increment it.
>> Well as soon as I add a
one to all of these ones,
you can perhaps imagine visually-- just
like carrying the one using decimals--
something's going to flow to the left.
And indeed, if I add the number
one to this, what happens in binary
is that it overflows back to zero.
>> So if you only use-- not an int,
but a single byte to count integers
in a program, by default-- as soon as
you get to 250, 251, 252, 253, 254,
255-- 0 comes after 255,
which is probably not what
a user is going to expect.
>> Now meanwhile in floating point world,
you also have a similar problem.
Not so much with the largest number--
although that's still an issue.
But with the amount of precision
that you can represent.
So let's take a look at this example
here also from today's source code--
float-0.c.
>> And notice it's a super
simple program that
should apparently print out what value?
What do you wager this is going to print
even though there's a bit of new syntax
here?
So hopefully 0.1.
So the equivalent of one-tenth
because I'm doing 1 divided by 10.
I'm storing the answer
in a variable called f.
That variable is of type float, which
is a keyword I just proposed existed.
>> We've not seen this before, but
this is kind of a neat way in printf
to specify how many digits you
want to see after a decimal point.
So this notation just means
that here's a placeholder.
It's for a floating point
value, and oh, by the way,
show it with the decimal point with
one number after the decimal point.
So that's the number
of significant digits,
so to speak, that you might want.
>> So let me go ahead and do
make float-0, ./float-0,
and apparently 1 divided by 10 is 0.0.
Now why is this?
>> Well again, the computer is taking
me literally, and I have written 1
and I written 10, and take a guess what
is the assumed data type for those two
values?
An int, it's technically
something a little different.
It's typically a long, but it's
ultimately an integral value.
Not a floating point value.
>> Which is to say that if this
is an int and this is an int,
the problem is that the computer
doesn't have the ability
to even store that decimal point.
So when you do 1 divided
by 10 using integers
for both the numerator and the
denominator, the answer should be 0.1.
But the computer-- because
those are integers--
doesn't know what to do with the 0.1.
>> So what is it clearly doing?
It's just throwing it away,
and what I'm seeing ultimately
is 0.0 only because I insisted that
printf show me one decimal point.
But the problem is that if you
divide an integer by an integer,
you will get-- by definition
of C-- an integer.
And it's not going to do
something nice and conveniently
like round it up to the
nearest one up or down.
It's going to truncate
everything after the decimal.
>> So just intuitively,
what's probably a fix?
What's the simplest fix here?
Yeah?
Exactly.
Why don't we just treat these as
floating point values effectively
turning them into floats or doubles.
And now if I do make floats-0,
or if I compile floats-1,
which is identical to
what was just proposed.
And now I do floats-0, now I get my 0.1.
>> Now this is amazing.
But now I'm going to do
something a little different.
I'm curious to see what's really
going on underneath the hood,
and I'm going to print this
out to 28 decimal places.
I want to really see
0.1000-- an infinite--
[INAUDIBLE] 27 zeros after that 0.1.
>> Well let's see if that's
what I indeed get.
Make floats-0 same file.
./floats-0.
Let's zoom in on the dramatic answer.
All this time, you've been thinking
1 divided by 10 is 10%, or 0.1.
It's not.
At least so far as the
computer's concerned.
>> Now why-- OK, that's complete
lie 1 divided by 10 is 0.1.
But why-- that is not
the takeaway today.
So why does the computer think,
unlike all of us in the room,
that 1 divided by 10 is
actually that crazy value?
What's the computer doing apparently?
What's that?
>> It's not overflow, per se.
Overflow is typically when
you wrap around a value.
It's this issue of imprecision
in a floating point value
where you only have 32
or maybe even 64 bit.
But if there's an infinite
number of real numbers--
numbers with decimal points
and numbers thereafter-- surely
you can't represent all of them.
So the computer has given
us the closest match
to the value it can represent using that
many bits to the value I actually want,
which is 0.1.
>> Unfortunately, if you
start doing math, or you
start involving these kinds of floating
point values in important programs--
financial software,
military software-- anything
where perception is
probably pretty important.
And you start adding
numbers like this, and start
running that software
with really large inputs
or for lots of hours or lots
of days or lots of years,
these tiny little mistakes
surely can add up over time.
>> Now as an aside, if you've ever
seen Superman 3 or Office Space
and you might recall
how those guys stole
a lot of money from their computer
by using floating point values
and adding up the little
remainders, hopefully that movie
now makes more sense.
This is what they were
alluding to in that movie.
The fact that most
companies wouldn't look
after a certain number
of decimal places,
but those are fractions of cents.
So you start adding them up,
you start to make a lot of money
in your bank account.
So that's Office Space explained.
>> Now unfortunately beyond
Office Space, there
are some legitimately troubling
and significant impacts
of these kinds of
underlying design decisions,
and indeed one of the reasons
we use C in the course
is so that you really have this ground
up understanding of how computers work,
how software works, and don't
take anything for granted.
>> And indeed unfortunately, even with
that fundamental understanding,
we humans make mistakes.
And what I thought I'd share is
this eight minute video here taken
from a Modern Marvels episode, which is
an educational show on how things work
that paints two pictures
of when an improper use
and understanding of
floating point values
led to some significant
unfortunate results.
Let's take a look.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-We now return to "Engineering
Disasters" on Modern Marvels.
Computers.
We've all come to accept the
often frustrating problems that
got with them-- bugs, viruses, and
software glitches-- for small prices
to pay for the convenience.
But in high tech and high speed
military and space program applications,
the smallest problem can
be magnified into disaster.
>> On June 4, 1996, scientists prepared
to launch an unmanned Ariane 5 rocket.
It was carrying scientific
satellites designed
to establish precisely how the
Earth's magnetic field interacts
with solar winds.
The rocket was built for
the European Space Agency,
and lifted off from its facility
on the coast of French Guiana.
>> -At about 37 seconds into
the flight, they first
noticed something was going wrong.
That the nozzles were swiveling
in a way they really shouldn't.
Around 40 seconds into the flight,
clearly the vehicle was in trouble,
and that's when they made
the decision to destroy it.
The range safety officer, with
tremendous guts, pressed the button
and blew up the rocket before it could
become a hazard to public safety.
>> -This was the maiden
voyage of the Ariane 5,
and its destruction took
place because of the flaw
embedded in the rocket's software.
-The problem on the
Ariane was that there
was a number that required
64 bits to express,
and they wanted to convert
it to a 16-bit number.
They assumed that the number
was never going to be very big.
That most of those digits in
the 64-bit number were zeros.
They were wrong.
>> -The inability of one
software program to accept
the kind of number generated by
another was at the root of the failure.
Software development had become a
very costly part of new technology.
The Ariane 4 rocket had
been very successful.
So much of the software created for
it was also used in the Ariane 5.
>> -The basic problem
was that the Ariane 5.
Was faster-- accelerated faster, and
the software hadn't accounted for that.
>> -The destruction of the rocket
was a huge financial disaster.
All due to a minute software error.
But this wasn't the first
time data conversion problems
had plagued modern rocket technology.
>> -In 1991 with the start
of the first Gulf War,
the Patriot missile
experienced a similar kind
of a number conversion problem.
And as a result 28 people-- 28
American soldiers-- were killed,
and about a hundred others wounded.
When the Patriot, which was supposed
to protect against incoming Scuds,
failed to fire a missile.
>> -When Iraq invaded Kuwait, and America
launched Desert Storm in early 1991,
Patriot missile batteries were deployed
to protect Saudi Arabia and Israel
from Iraqi Scud missile attacks.
The Patriot is a US medium-range
surface-to-air system
manufactured by the Raytheon company.
>> -The size of the Patriot
interceptor itself--
it's about roughly 20 feet long,
and it weighs about 2,000 pounds.
And it carries a warhead of about,
I think it's roughly 150 pounds.
And the warhead itself is
a high explosive, which
has fragments around him.
So the casing of the warhead is
designed to act like a buckshot.
>> -The missiles are carried
four per container,
and are transported by a semi trailer.
>> -The Patriot anti-missile system
goes back at least 20 years now.
It was originally designed
as an air defense missile
to shoot down enemy airplanes.
In the first Gulf War
when that war came on,
the Army wanted to use it to
shoot down Scuds, not airplanes.
The Iraqi Air Force was
not so much of a problem,
but the Army was worried about Scuds.
And so they tried to
upgrade the Patriot.
>> -Intercepting an enemy
missile traveling at Mach 5
was going to be challenging enough.
But when the Patriot
was rushed into service,
the Army was not aware of
an Iraqi modification that
made their scuds nearly
impossible to it.
>> -What happened is the Scuds that
were coming in were unstable.
They were wobbly.
The reason for this was the Iraqis--
in order to get 600 kilometers out
of a 300-kilometer range missile--
took weight out of the front warhead,
and made the warhead lighter.
So now the Patriot's trying to come
at the Scud, and most of the time--
the overwhelming majority of the
time-- it would just fly by the Scud.
>> -Once the Patriot system operators
realized the Patriot missed its target,
they detonated the Patriot's warhead
to avoid possible casualties if it
was allowed to fall to the ground.
>> -That was what most people saw
as big fireballs in the sky,
and misunderstood as
intercepts of Scud warheads.
>> -Although in the night skies, Patriots
appeared to be successfully destroying
Scuds, at Dhahran there could be
no mistake about its performance.
There the Patriot's radar system
lost track of an incoming Scud
and never launched due
to a software flaw.
>> It was the Israelis who first discovered
that the longer the system was on,
the greater the time discrepancy became.
Due to a clock embedded
in the system's computer.
>> -About two weeks before
the tragedy in Dhahran,
the Israelis reported to
the Defense Department
that the system was losing time.
After about eight hours
of running, they noticed
that the system's becoming
noticeably less accurate.
The Defense Department responded by
telling all of the Patriot batteries
to not leave the systems
on for a long time.
They never said what a long time was.
8 hours, 10 hours, a thousand hours.
Nobody knew.
>> -The Patriot battery
stationed at the barracks
at Dhahran and its flawed internal
clock had been on for over 100 hours
on the night of February 25.
>> -It tracked time to an accuracy
of about a tenth of a second.
Now a tenth of a second
is an interesting number
because it can't be expressed
in binary exactly, which
means it can't be expressed exactly
in any modern digital computer.
It's hard to believe, but
use this as an example.
>> Let's take the number one third.
One third cannot be
expressed in decimal exactly.
One third is 0.333
going on for infinity.
There's no way to do that with
absolute accuracy in a decimal.
That's exactly the kind of problem
that happened in the Patriot.
The longer the system ran, the
worse the time error became.
>> -After 100 hours of operation, the
error in time was only about one third
of a second.
But in terms of targeting a
missile traveling at Mach 5,
it resulted in a tracking
error of over 600 meters.
It would be a fatal error
for the soldiers at Dhahran.
>> -What happened is a Scud launch was
detected by early warning satellites,
and they knew a Scud was coming
in their general direction.
They didn't know where it was coming.
It was now up to the radar
component of the Patriot system
defending Dhahran to locate and keep
track of the incoming enemy missile.
>> -The radar was very smart.
It would actually track
the position of the Scud
and then predict where
it probably would be
the next time the
radar sent a pulse out.
That was called the range gate.
>> -Then once the Patriot
decides enough time has
passed to go back and check the next
location for this detected object
it goes back.
So when it went back to the wrong
place, it then sees no object.
And it decides that there was no object.
That there was a false detection
and it drops the track.
>> -The incoming Scud disappeared
from the radar screen,
and seconds later, it
slammed into the barracks.
The Scud killed 28.
It was the last one fired
during the first Gulf War.
Tragically, the updated software
arrived at dawn on the following day.
The software flaw had
been fixed, closing
one chapter in the troubled
history of the Patriot missile.
>> [END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: That's it for CS50.
We will see you on Wednesday.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]