DAVID J. MALAN: All right,
so this here is the Myo arm
band, a couple of which we
have for CS50 final projects.
And that was a demonstration we queued
you up in advance where essentially
this fairly tight arm band up here
listens to your muscular movements
that are then mapped in software
to Colton's laptop over here which
had iTunes and that
song already queued up.
Rather than me demoing this,
Colton's been in the lab
clearly all week getting a demonstration
ready for one brave volunteer.
If someone would like to come
on up-- saw your hand first.
Come on up.
>> All right.
And what is your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Uh, Maria.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Maria, nice to see you.
Come on over here.
Let me introduce you to Colton.
Colton, this is Maria.
>> COLTON: Hi, nice to meet you.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: All
right, so step one, we're
going to have you put
this on to your forearm
so that it's pretty
tight up near your elbow.
And meanwhile, let's have
put on our Google Glass
and we'll mix technologies today.
>> COLTON: First we'll have to
hook this into the things.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Actually, let's put your arm as
close to this cable as possible
so that we can first sync it up.
>> COLTON: Let's do this.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And meanwhile, so
that everyone can get a closer glance,
we'll toss Andrew's camera
up on the screen there.
So we have a USB cable that's
being plugged into Maria's armband.
And let me toss Colton's screen
up on the projector next.
>> So Colton is registering the device
now as a Myo connected to this cable.
And now what Maria's
going to do momentarily
is actually walk through
the calibration steps
and teach the software
how her muscles respond
when she make certain pre-defined
gestures that the software understands.
If you'd like to go in
front of the screen.
OK, keep trying.
>> COLTON: Go like this.
And like that.
And all the way to the right.
Go back.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Different perspective.
It's not you.
It's us.
>> MARIA: OK.
DAVID J. MALAN: No.
Let's move it higher up so it's
closer to your elbow, or even tighter.
All right.
>> Here we go.
This would be a good time for CS52X.
There we go.
>> Very nice.
OK.
Thumb to pinky.
>> Very nice.
Spread your fingers.
Good.
Wave right.
It's curiously showing
you with the left hand--
>> COLTON: Yeah, that's wierd.
DAVID J. MALAN: Wave to
the right and move forward.
Fast forward to skip or next.
That's OK Wave right.
>> MARIA: I don't-- wait.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Need some help?
>> COLTON: So you're going like this.
MARIA: It's turning the
other thing, though.
COLTON: It is.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah I don't know
why it's showing you a leftie.
COLTON: Why don't you try--
just try going like this.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: No?
Maybe reach your arm
out a little straighter
and make it more abrupt like this.
Yeah, OK, come on.
>> MARIA: I'm sorry.
DAVID J. MALAN: It's not your fault.
COLTON: It's fine.
DAVID J. MALAN: All Right.
Well--
>> MARIA: Should we skip this, then?
DAVID J. MALAN: Yes, let's
let you off the hook.
So if anyone would like to do a
final project using this cutting edge
hardware, realize it might just
take a little getting used to.
And this-- the reality is this
is actually very bleeding edge.
>> This is what's called
the developer kit, which
is meant to be essentially a pre-release
so that people can do exactly
this-- fight with it, figure
out how people's bodies work
with the technology.
So if you want
afterwards, after lecture,
we can let you come and
take another stab at it.
But otherwise, a round of applause, if
we could, for Maria for coming on up.
>> MARIA: Thank you.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Thank you.
We'll hang on to this, but we will give
you-- how about a stress ball here?
Oh, and-- if-- yeah, thanks.
All right.
So for the curious, if you were
unfamiliar with the sound choice
that we made there
earlier, an amazing TV
show that you should absolutely
be binge-watching on Netflix
is this one here.
>> SPEAKER 1: Ladies and gentlemen,
a magician named Josh.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And apparently, it's
a thing to text me during lecture now.
I'm being told that Maria
had a birthday yesterday.
So happy birthday from
CS50 to Maria as well.
>> So you may have read in recent month
that this gentlemen here, Steve
Ballmer, who was actually
class of 1977 at the college,
recently retired for Microsoft.
He was an undergraduate here,
then a couple years later
found himself at
Stanford Business School
when he received a phone
call from a friend of his who
had lived down the hall
from him here at Harvard.
That friend's name was Bill
Gates, and at the time,
he was trying to recruit Steve to be
the first business person, really,
at a small company name Microsoft.
>> A long story short, Steve
was ultimately won over,
joined Microsoft when they
had just 30 employees.
And by the time he
retired quite recently,
the company had 100,000 employees
over the past few years.
And so a website known as The Verge
prepared this tribute on video
that we thought we'd
shared that gives you
a sense of just how much energy Steve
brings to any presentation he gives.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-Microsoft's like a fourth child.
Children do leave the house.
In this case, I guess
I'm leaving the house.
Hey Bill, whazzap?
>> -Wazzap?
>> -Hey, wazzap?
We've been given an
enormous opportunity.
And Bill gave us that opportunity.
I want to thank Bill for that.
I want you to too.
The pace of innovation
isn't going to slow.
>> It's going to get faster and faster.
There might be a few competitors
that are unfortunately eliminated!
>> I love this company.
Yes!
I am a PC, and I love this company!
>> Developers, developers, developers,
developers, developers, developers,
developers, developers.
Yes!
Web developers!
>> Web developers!
Listen to what else you
get at no extra charge!
>> The MS-DOS executive, an appointment
calender, a card pile, a note pad,
a clock, a control panel.
And, can you believe it?
Reversie!
>> Burn them to CD!
Post them to MSN!
You mail them to friends!
>> All with one click!
One Microsoft, one strategy, one team--
focused, disciplined, professional,
and expert in all that we do.
Let me use a line from an old movie.
>> Relationships are like sharks.
They move forward or they die.
I actually think tech
companies are the same.
>> [END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: So we are so pleased to
announce that Steve will be joining us
here in CS50 next Wednesday at
the usual place and time here.
Space will likely be limited.
And so to join us in person, please
head today or shortly thereafter
to cs50.harvard.edu/register.
>> And we will follow up by
Tuesday confirming spots.
Look forward to that next
Wednesday during lecture in CS50.
Now, in other news, I happened to
come across this in The Crimson just
the other day.
>> It turns out that one of CS50's staff
and at least one of CS50's students
is currently running for UC
president and vice president,
which brought me back
to my own days back
when I lost the UC election miserably.
But the silver lining
in that is I always
tell the story is that
one of the I'm sure
many reasons I lost the
election was a complete lack
of a talent for public speaking.
And so quite honestly, it
drove me, that experience
I think my junior year, to actually sign
up for Harvard Computer Society, which
is the group on campus that
holds various technical talks
and other things.
And I took over their teaching
seminars and therefore
had an opportunity, a
wonderful opportunity,
to start working on exactly this.
But also, I had an opportunity
during this experience
to teach myself all the more HTML.
And so I procrastinated last night by
looking through the HTML based website
I made in like 1997, '98, for my
campaign which looks like this here.
I know.
>> Because-- and of course, notice
this amazing design decision in 1998
or whatnot.
The first thing you want users
to do upon visiting your website
is to have to click another link just
to enter your website here with the monk
behind like a shrouded curtain where
apparently my campaign platform was.
And this is all you'll get
today is just a screenshot.
But I was reading through, like,
my campaign posters last night
and my platform.
>> And I was so angry at the time.
My platform was-- it was interesting.
So I've calmed down since then.
But someday, I will run again and
hopefully better off this time.
>> So HTML, that language in which I made
that in-- you'll soon make much more--
is something we've been
talking about of late
and largely taking for granted now
that we've moved on to other languages.
But let's pause for just a moment and
put some of these things in context.
So in a sentence, what is HTML?
>> Or, what is used for?
Anyone?
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: Markup for websites.
DAVID J. MALAN: Markup for website.
So it's a markup language that
lets you structure a web page.
Header goes up here, title
goes here, body goes here.
This is boldface, this is
italics-- that sort of detail.
>> OK, good.
So CSS lets you-- and I
took some liberties there
with the bold-facing and italics because
that's better implemented with this.
CSS is-- what?
Say in a sentence.
Anyone at all.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Embellishments and
stuff, like how to design it.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, good.
Embellishments that allow you
to design it or stylize it
with things like boldface and
italics and colors and also more fine
grained positioning of elements.
It sort of lets you take things the
last mile so that if, for instance,
in Pset7, you might have noticed on your
portfolio page if you're at this point
already that a default table that you
make to show the user's stock holdings
and cash probably looks pretty hideous
by default with no white space.
Everything's kind of crammed
together in rows and columns.
>> Well, with a bit of
CSS, as you may realize,
you can actually tweak that and make it
something much more familiar and much
prettier to look at.
So CSS is about the
stylization of websites.
But then we introduced yet another
language, PHP, which lets us do what?
>> Let's just do what?
Anyone.
Got to venture beyond
the first couple rows.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Generate dynamic content.
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
Generate dynamic content.
And you can do this in
any number of languages.
We happen to use PHP because it's
in part so similar to C syntax.
>> But PHP does exactly that.
It lets you dynamically generate output.
And some of that output could be
HTML, as we've typically been doing.
And it's also, because it's
a programming language, is
the mechanism via which
we can talk to databases.
>> And we can make queries to
other servers like Yahoos
and programmatically do anything
really that you might otherwise
want to compel a computer to do.
So PHP lets us start
dynamically outputting content.
So by this logic, I didn't have
a dynamic website back in 1998.
>> It was just a static web page.
My content had to be changed by
manually with gedit or some equivalent.
But PHP is what we used or
could have used, rather,
for something like the
Frosh IMs website, which
was supposed to take registrations and
manage a list of users-- things that
are actually changing over
time, even though we happen
to use Perl, a different
language at the time.
>> And then lastly, we introduced
SQL-- Structured Query Language.
So yet another language
that's used for what?
Used for what?
Can we venture slight--
OK, we're not going
to get much farther
than the orchestra here.
AUDIENCE: It's a protocol
used to talk to databases.
DAVID J. MALAN: A protocol
Let me tweak.
It's an natural language used
to talk to databases-- selects
and inserts and deletes
and updates and actually
even more features that
we haven't even dived
into but you may want to explore-- have
to explore for, say, a final project.
So there are these various pieces.
>> And hopefully Pset7, even though
its specification is quite long,
it's deliberately long to walk you
through how these things can all
be typed together.
Now, on Monday, we
introduced our last language
that we'll formally introduce in
the course-- that is, JavaScript.
This, like PHP, is an
interpreted language.
>> But a key distinction
I proposed on Monday
is that whereas PHP is executing or
being interpreted on the server, which
in this case is the CS50 appliance,
or might be some commercial web
server on the internet,
JavaScript generally
is a language that runs client side
not server side-- so in the browser.
Which is to say, just like when I opened
up Facebook source code and found all
of those .js files, the implication was
that when you visit Facebook or most
websites these days, you get
not only HTML, not only CSS,
but a whole bunch of JavaScript
code often in the form of .js files.
And then it's the browser-- your own
Mac or PC-- that executes that code.
>> But your browser executes it.
You can think in sort of a sandbox.
So that JavaScript code shouldn't be
able to delete files on your computer.
It shouldn't be able to
send emails on your behalf.
Your browser kind of restricts
what you can do with it.
>> So in that sense, it's a little
less powerful, perhaps, than C.
But JavaScript can, as an
aside, be used on the server,
though we'll tend not to talk
about it in that context.
So now let's tie these together.
A week plus ago, we presented some HTML
on the left-- super boring web page.
>> Just says hello world.
And then I proposed on the
right we can kind of steal ideas
from our discussion of
data structures in C
and think about how this hierarchical
markup language on the left
could be drawn or implemented in memory
as an actual tree structure with nodes
and pointers and those kinds of details.
On the right, we call
that a DOM-- Document
Object Model-- which is just
a fancy way of saying tree.
>> Now, why is this useful to
think of it in this way?
Because now with
JavaScript, because we have
code that gets to play in this
environment, the actual HTML that's
been sent to the browser
already and has already
been loaded into memory by the
browser into a tree in your computer's
RAM like this, we can use JavaScript
to actually traverse or walk or search
or change that DOM tree however we want.
So in fact, if you think
about facebook.com,
if you use the chat feature, if you
use Gmail and the gchat feature,
anything where you have
messages coming again and again
and again, those messages are probably,
like, LI tag, List Item tags, maybe.
>> Or maybe they're just
divs that keep appearing
every time you get an instant message.
And so that just means what
Facebook or Google is doing
is any time you get a
message from the server,
they are probably using JavaScript
to just add another node
to this tree-- another node to this
tree that then visually just looks
like a new line of text on your screen.
But they're inserting
into this data structure.
>> So in classes like
CS124 and others, you'll
actually write more code against
data structures like this.
But for now in JavaScript,
we'll just assume
we get all of this functionality
for free from the language itself.
So let's look at an example.
>> Let me open up a file called form.html.
It's super simple.
It just looks like this.
>> No CSS, no thought to aesthetics.
It's purely functional
and apparently I'm
asking for an email, a password,
password again, and then a check
to agree to some terms and conditions.
What the source code for this
looks like is probably something
you might guess with a
little bit of thought now.
I've got a form tag here.
>> An action is apparently going to
go to a file called register.php.
The method I'm going to use is get.
And then I've got a text
field whose name is email.
>> I've got a password field
whose name is password.
I've got another
password field whose name
is somewhat arbitrarily confirmation.
It's just another HTTP parameter.
>> And then we we've not used these except
since the Frosh IMs demo in class--
a check box which is
just type equals check.
And I'll call that agreement.
So I've kind of arbitrarily but
conveniently named these fields.
So that now when this form gets
submitted, let's see what happens.
If I do malan@harvard.edu,
I'll do a password of crimson.
I'll do a password of nothing.
Let's not cooperate.
>> And I won't check the box.
Let me click Register.
And it says, hm, you're registered.
Not really.
>> But the URL changed.
So this form was clearly allowed
to submit to register.php.
But presumably, I should be
catching some of these errors.
Now, in Pset7 and some
of our lecture examples,
we would generally print out
a big red error message here
saying, missing name,
or missing password.
We've done that before and we've
done server side error detection.
>> But many websites these days
do client side error detection
where the URL doesn't change.
The whole page doesn't refresh.
You get instant feedback
from the browser.
Maybe something goes red.
>> Maybe you get a pop up.
But you don't waste time sending to
the server data that's incomplete.
So let's see how we might
achieve that feature as well.
>> Let me go to form1.html,
which looks the same.
But if this time I do
malan@harvard.edu and I type crimson
and I don't cooperate further
but click Register, notice now.
It's not the sexiest solution.
I've at least caught this error.
And I've used the alert
function in JavaScript--
which we're only using in class.
In general, you should not use this
because it can very quickly get out
of control.
But passwords do not match is the error.
>> Let me go ahead and click OK.
But what the key takeaway here
is that the URL did not change.
So I've not bothered wasting
the server's time asking it
a question that I could have
figured out the answer to myself.
>> And the user, even though
been talking about this
longer than the user's
going to think about this,
is going to have instant feedback.
There's no latency with
the network connectivity.
So let's look at this source code.
>> Form1.html looks
structurally similar up here.
The form is in fact the same.
But let's see what I did down here.
And there's different ways to do this.
And I've done the most straight
follower but not most elegant way yet.
I have a script tag.
I then call
document.getElementByID('registration').
And I store that value
in form, a variable.
>> So what have I done?
You can think of
document.getElementByID as being
a special function that
JavaScript gives you
that literally hands you a
pointer to one of the nodes
or rectangles in this tree.
So now that's what our form variable
in JavaScript is actually pointing at.
>> So now the syntax is different from
C. But we're doing a few things here.
One, this one is a little strange
looking, certainly versus C.
But look at line 35.
So on the left form.onsubmit.
Recall that onsubmit is
like a field in a struct.
If you think of the form variable
is just being a C struct,
it might have some fields.
>> Back in the day, we had students names,
IDs, houses, those kind of fields.
Just think of onsubmit as another field.
But it's a special field because the
browser is preprogrammed to expect
.onsubmit to not be a value
like a number or string,
but to actually be a function
or the address of a function
in the computer's memory.
>> And indeed, that's what
this keyword here does.
This says, give me a new function.
But what is its name
going to be, apparently?
>> Thinking back to Monday.
What is the name of this
function based on this syntax?
No, I mean, there's clearly
no name associated-- certainly
not in what I've highlighted here.
>> But that's actually OK.
This is an anonymous function, or a
lambda function as some might call it.
And that just means
it's still a function.
It's just, you can't call it by name.
But that's OK.
Because again, the browser has been
preprogrammed by companies like Google
or Microsoft or Mozilla or others to
just know that if the .onsubmit field
inside of a form element has the
value, treat it as a function--
a function pointer, if you will.
And call it when the form is submitted.
>> So what code should be executed
when the form is submitted?
Apparently, everything
inside of the curly brace.
And this is just stylistic.
>> You could do this like
we tend to do in CS50.
But in JavaScript, most people
tend to keep it on the same line
just because it more clearly is
associated with that keyword function.
So now what am I doing?
>> If form.email.value equals equals
the empty string or nothing, here's
an alert where I'm going to say,
you must provide your email address,
and then return false.
And it's that return false that
prevents the form from being submitted.
Meanwhile, if the password value is
blank, I'm going to yell at the user
and say, you must provide a password.
>> Meanwhile things are getting
a little fancier here.
If form.password.value does not
equal form.confirmation.value,
the other field, yell at
the user that the passwords
don't match as they
did not a moment ago.
And then this one's a
little sexier because I
know I knew conceptually that
checked is a check box's name.
>> So I can just use an exclamation
point to say if the check is not
checked-- it's the Boolean
value, true or false--
I'll yell at the user for that reason.
Otherwise, if we get through
all of these conditions,
let's just return true.
Let the form be submitted.
And this will then happen.
>> Let's type in crimson.
Let's check the box, click Register.
And now I go through to the destination.
Now, there's no database there.
There's nothing interesting
in register.php.
I just needed something
to actually talk to.
So let me pause, here.
Any questions on what we've just done
or what some of this new syntax is?
OK, yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: So any checkbox
is automatically a Boolean .
You don't have to declare it like that.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Correct.
Any checkbox that's sent to you from
an HTML form to your JavaScript code
will be treated, yes, as a
Boolean value-- true or false.
It's a good question.
Whereas the other values, of
course, have been text, AKA strings.
>> All right, so let me
rewind a bit further.
What was the whole point of this?
Just to be clear.
Like, we already know, even from Pset7
and even from last week's lecture
examples, that we can obviously check
$_GET $_POST see if the user give us
an empty value.
Remember the empty function in PHP.
>> So just to be clear, what's
one reason we might also
want to do this error checking
inside of the browser?
What's the motivation here?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Faster, and you don't
send useless data to the server.
DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
It's faster.
You don't send useless
data to the server.
>> So you get back a more
immediate response.
And overall, the user
experience is better.
Think about the alternative.
>> If for Gmail-- and was
the case many years ago.
Suppose you got a new email your Gmail
account, but the only way through
to see that is to, like,
reload the whole page.
Or suppose you click on
a link to read an email.
>> Everything has to reload so
that you can see the email.
Or Facebook-- you get a chat message.
You don't see it until you reload
the page or click some link.
>> Like, this would be an awfully
annoying user experience.
And this is what it was like,
clearly, back when I ran for UC
and the web was much less dynamic
and JavaScript wasn't as popularized
as it is now.
And things are getting much
more dynamic and much more
client side in that sense.
>> But there is a catch here, and
this is kind of an annoying gotcha.
Just because you add client side
detection like this does not mean
you can or should abandon
server side detection.
You essentially want to put your
error checking in both places.
Because what was one
of the lesson learned
from the article I read some excerpts
from with this stupid CMS system--
Content Management System-- that was
implementing its authentication system,
its login via what mechanism?
JavaScript.
>> AUDIENCE: JavaScript.
DAVID J. MALAN:
JavaScript, exactly, right?
It was using JavaScript.
And literally, you guys have
played a little bit probably
with Chrome's Inspector.
And if I can find it, inspect element.
>> Let me go over to do
all of Chrome's options.
And this is how easy it is to
disable JavaScript in a browser.
Check, no more JavaScript.
>> So in fairness, a lot
of the web these days
is just going to break because
Gmail and other sites--
Facebook-- assume that
JavaScript is enabled.
But if you're doing something stupid
like only validating users input
and checking it for
errors on the client side,
an adversary could easily do this.
And then even smarter
adversary like you guys
now could use Telnet or Curl
or just command line commands
and actually send messages to the server
that similarly are not error checked.
>> So this is more of a
user interface decision
than it is an actual technical
improvement-- implementing
something client side like this.
So now a quick glance, but then
I'll defer to the online walk
through for this one.
In form two, we actually went through
and cleaned up the code a little bit.
But let me defer to one
of the videos we'll likely
embed in Pset8 that just shows you a
similar syntax using a library called
jQuery, which is a super, super
popular library in JavaScript
that frankly most people
just use these days
and even confuse as
being JavaScript itself.
>> And it tends to involve
some dollar signs
and keywords like document
in parentheses here.
But again, let me defer to
some slower tutorials online
rather than get tied up in just syntax.
Let's move on to
something a little cooler
in terms of the applications of this.
>> So in particular, let me go
ahead and open up this here.
Come on.
There we go.
>> Let me open up this picture here.
Unnecessarily complicated
looking, but it
describes a technique called AJAX--
Asynchronous JavaScript and XML, where
the X for XML is actually
no longer really used.
It tends to use something
else called JSON.
>> But here is how something like
Google Maps or Google Earth works.
Let's try this on the fly, actually.
Let me go ahead and open
up Chrome on my browser.
>> And let me go into,
say, maps.google.com.
And actually, if you're old
enough to remember what,
like, MapQuest was like back in the day,
and maybe they still work like this.
When you used to search for something--
33 Oxford Street, Cambridge, Mass,
let's do this-- you
would actually, if you
wanted to pan up and
down, left and right,
you would look like a
big arrow on top, and it
would show you another
frame of the map up here.
Or you would click left and you
would go over here, or another click
and you would go over here.
But instead these
days, we of course just
take for granted that we can go
around Cambridge pretty quickly
just by clicking and dragging.
But notice there's some glitches.
>> If I do this fast enough,
what seems to be happening
as I drag a little too fast
for the computer to keep up?
What do you see?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: The pixels don't refresh.
DAVID J. MALAN: The
pixels don't refresh.
There's actually-- and you
could see this, actually,
if you're watching online and pause
this or actually slows things down
for once-- you'll see that there are
tiles, squares, or rectangles that
are missing from the map until
a split second later, more data,
more images actually
appear on the screen.
And in fact, if we do this by looking
up Chrome's-- let's say, Chrome--
let's see.
We can't do that.
>> Oh, whoops.
Let's open up maps.google.com.
Let me make the window bigger again.
>> Go back to 33 Oxford Street.
What was the website I was on recently?
I had this, like, private rant to
myself that I'd then instant message
any friend who was online
who wanted to hear it.
There's some website.
I think it's Comcast-- so
a very big American ISP.
You can, when signing up for new cable
modem service or cable TV service,
they have a form very reasonably
where they ask you for your address.
And have this amazing
feature called auto complete,
like Google, that starts to fill
in the answer to your question.
>> The problem is, they do auto complete
on the first things that you type.
So if you start typing in 33, it
will show you literally every house
in America that starts
with the number 33
before continuing to
expect you to type more.
So if you type 33 Oxford,
then it shows you every street
in America that has 33 Oxford in
its name, irrespective of the town
that you're in.
>> And then you continue typing.
And finally, it realizes that they don't
offer service to your home in Cambridge
or something like that.
But the point is, this is the most
asinine implementation of auto
complete ever.
>> And I'm just going off
on this tangent again.
But there are good ways to
use JavaScript and bad ways.
And that's not necessarily the best one.
>> But the point here, before this
tirade, was to open up tools down here
and open up developer tools,
as we've encouraged before,
and to watch the Network
tab as I click really fast.
And notice a whole bunch
of get requests happened.
All of this happened since I dragged.
>> And most likely, indeed
a lot of these rows
now are image slash JPEG
MIME types or content types.
That's because what chrome is doing
every time I click and drag, click
and drag, is it's realizing, oh, I
need to go ask Google for the tile
on the map that's over here,
quickly download it via HTTP,
and then add it to the so-called DOM
to the web browsers in memory tree
representation so that the user,
me, sees that updated tile.
And this is because of
a technique called AJAX.
Back in the day, it really
was the case that if you
wanted to change what's on the screen,
you would have to click up, down, left,
right.
And then a new page would open.
But these days, everything
is more dynamic.
It happens in the way we humans would
hope it actually would interactively.
And it achieves this by
way of a technique called
AJAX, which is perhaps best
explained by an example.
First, let me go ahead
and open up a file
called quote.php in
today's distribution code.
>> And then let me do symbol-- whoops.
Let me do symbol=GOOG
for just some stock.
Or actually, let's do the
one from the Pset FREE.
Enter.
>> And now notice what I get back.
So this is a really
short PHP file that I
wrote that simply borrows code
from Pset7's lookup function
and spits out using this curly brace and
quotes and colon notation, apparently,
the current stock's price for the
company that you pass in via get.
So this is different
from most of what we've
done in that notice I'm
literally spitting out
what looks like JavaScript code.
>> In fact, this is a JavaScript object.
In fact, just to be more clear,
JavaScript Object Notation-- JSON--
is just a fancy way of saying that you
can represent data in JavaScript much
like you can in PHP
using key value pairs.
So if I wanted to declare
a variable in JavaScript
to represents Zamyla, for
instance-- a struct for Zamyla--
and we'll call it
student, this variable.
Her ID is one, house is
Winthrop, and name is Zamyla.
>> But I can also have an array of objects.
So if I actually wanted to have
an array in JavaScript containing
multiple such objects, this
time representing staff,
I might have these three
chunks of code back
to back to back for these
three former staff members.
So the syntax, pretty
similar to both-- to PHP.
But this is particularly JavaScript.
It's object notation.
So what is this useful for?
>> If I write code that spits out JSON--
JavaScript Object Notation-- stuff that
looks like this or stuff that
looks like Zamyla's structure,
I can actually use this
in programs I write.
Let me go to ajax0.html.
And this too-- not much
thought given to aesthetics.
But watch what happens.
>> Let me go ahead and type free here.
Click get quote.
And notice the URL has not changed.
But I did get a pop up with apparently
today's penny stock price of $0.15.
So not all that bad.
But the difference is that somehow,
this data came back to me directly.
But let's take a step toward
something more familiar.
In version one of this, let me
type free again, click Get quote,
and now-- oh, this was
actually the jQuery version.
So let me-- I didn't
fast-forward quite far enough.
Let me go to version two,
which is where I wanted.
Notice what I've done here.
I have a web page-- a super
simple version of any web page
you might use today with a text field
here for free and then apparently just
text.
>> This is not a form here, apparently.
But if I click get
quote, notice my web page
is about to change as though I
just got a new instant message
or as though I just moved the
map and needed to get more data
added dynamically to the web page
without the URL changing and the user
experience getting interrupted.
Indeed, I'm still at the
exact same place-- ajax2.html.
>> So let's look only at this example
and see how this is happening.
Let me go into ajax2.html.
And notice the form first.
>> Down here, I'm turning
off auto complete.
Sometimes it gets
annoying if the browser
is trying to show you
your whole history.
So you can do it in HTML by
just saying auto complete off.
>> I've given this text field a
symbol-- rather, an ID of symbol.
And now, this is an interesting feature.
We haven't talked about span,
but you can think about it
like a paragraph tag or div tag.
It's what's called an
in-line element, which
means you won't get a paragraph
break above and below it.
It's just going to stay in-line without
hitting the equivalent of enter.
So I have given this chunk of HTML
to be determined a unique identifier
that I arbitrarily called price.
And I have a Submit button.
>> Because now up here-- and this is
actually super amazing how little code
you can write to do
relatively neat things--
notice what I've done up here if I
scroll up to the head of this page.
I've included first in
my head a script tag
that actually references a
JavaScript file elsewhere.
This is from the organization
that writes jQuery,
and this is just giving you the latest
version of their jQuery library.
>> So this is kind of like sharp
include in C or require in PHP.
You use the script tag
with a source attribute.
But now my own code is
going to be right in here.
>> Notice I have a function called Quotes.
And it looks a little
cryptic at first glance.
But let's tease this apart.
Give me a variable called URL.
Assign it literally this string.
So, single quotes, double quotes in
JavaScript just gives me a string.
What does the plus do?
Concatenation.
>> So this now is the jQuery syntax
which takes a little getting used to.
But this just means go get me the DOM
node whose unique identifier is symbol.
The hashtag there means
unique identifier symbol.
>> The dollar sign in the
parentheses just mean, wrap this
in jQuery a sort of secret sauce so
you get additional functionality.
And then .val is apparently
a function, or as we say now,
a method inside of this node
that just gives you the value.
So in short, ugly and confusing
as this looks at first glance,
this just means get with the user typed
in, put it at the end of the string
by concatenating it.
That's all.
>> So now, last three lines.
You can squeeze a lot of
functionality out of three lines.
This dollar sign, as an
aside, is just a nickname
for a special global variable
called literally jQuery.
>> Dollar sign just looks cool.
So the jQuery community just kind
of used it as their special symbol.
It does not mean what it means in PHP.
In JavaScript, dollar sign is
just like a letter of the alphabet
or a number for a variable.
>> You can just have it as the name.
Just looks cool.
So the community
adopted it as a nickname
for their own library called jQuery.
>> And it's super popular.
So get JSON is exactly that.
It's a function that the
folks at jQuery wrote
that gets JSON from a server--
JavaScript Object Notation.
From what URL is it going
to get that information?
Apparently from this URL here.
>> And what should the browser do as
soon as it gets back this response?
And this is the magic of AJAX, so to
speak-- Asynchronous JavaScript in XML.
It's hard to see with such a
simple example as we had here.
>> But this was asynchronous in
the sense that my code when
executed sent a message to the
server to go get me some JSON.
And it happened super fast
that I got a response.
But what's interesting is that this
line of code didn't hang my computer.
>> I didn't see a spinning icon.
I didn't lose the
ability to move my mouse.
My browser was actually perfectly fine.
>> Because the way JavaScript handles the
response from the server is as follows.
You register what you'd call
a callback function, which
just means, hey, JavaScript.
As soon as the server
responds with JSON,
please call this anonymous function.
>> And please passed into this function
whatever string the server spit out
as an argument called data.
So in other, words, if
I'm assembling dynamically
a URL quote.php passing in this
symbol like FREE or GOOG or whatnot,
I'm then telling
JavaScript go get that URL.
Remember that the browser
is going to return something
that looks like we saw earlier-- this.
>> And what the second argument
here to get JSON is saying
is call this function
when the server gets back
whether it's 10 milliseconds
from now or 10 seconds from now.
And as soon as you do,
add the price to the page.
This syntax here just
means go get the node
from the tree whose unique identifier
is price-- that span we saw earlier.
>> This method called HTML
just says, go replace
the HTML that's there with data.price.
What's data.price?
Well, the browser, recall,
showed me this coming back.
So this is data.
>> And so it's a little cryptic
to see the commas here.
But in fact, let me do this.
Let me just paste this
real fast into gedit
and show this like we showed
Zamyla's structure earlier.
>> What the server is sending back is a
little object that looks like this.
And so data.price is
just giving me 0.1515.
So a lot of moving
parts here all at once.
>> But the key takeaways is
that we have this ability
to make additional HTTP
requests using JavaScript
without having to reload the page.
And then we can actually
change the web page on the fly.
And it turns out that
JavaScript and other languages
can be used now not only
to mutate web pages,
but to actually write software
in an actual computer,
not just confined to Chrome or the like.
>> In fact, if-- Colton, would you
like to join us back up here
with your lab code, and Chang as well?
Let's go ahead, having talked about
anonymous functions and callbacks
and really tempt fate here
with a live demo with bleeding
edge technology, one of
these Elite Motion devices.
Now, this device, recall,
is a little USB device
as well that-- that's beautiful--
that plugs in to your USB ports.
>> And then it provides input
in the form of human gestures
by detecting using infrared beams,
essentially, movements from your arm.
So whereas what Maria tried
on before was muscular,
actually feeling what's changing
your arm, this is infrared based.
So it's looking for movements within
the sort of sphere of a foot or so
of the device itself.
>> So why don't I take
a stab at this first?
And let's go ahead and throw
you up on the overhead here.
So let's put Colton's laptop up here.
We've got Andrew on the TV.
And what would you like me to do first?
>> COLTON: Go ahead and just
put your hands over this guy
and you'll see some fabulous glitter.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Very nice.
This is all happening in real time.
OK.
All right, and yep.
So nice.
All right, what else can we do?
>> COLTON: Go to the next screen and see.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
>> COLTON: A fun little game
where you get to make robots.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: All right, so this
is fake hands showing me what to do.
COLTON: Yes So go ahead
and grab one of the blocks
and put it on top of that robot's body.
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, there's my hand.
Oh.
OK, adorable.
Wait a minute, OK.
There we go.
>> COLTON: I made one on accident.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK, I'll get this guy.
Damn it!
When we were practicing this last
night, you know what this devolved into?
>> Like this.
OK.
Next one?
>> COLTON: Sure.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: All right,
and there's a third.
All right.
COLTON: And in this one, you get to--
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh,
this one's beautiful.
COLTON: --yeah, pick apart this flower.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
No?
Missed.
>> COLTON: Oh, there you go.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Ah, Look at that.
Very nice.
Well, why dont' we take
out one volunteer here
who would like to come on up.
How about right there
in the green, is it?
>> All right, and let's have--
instead of doing that, some of you
might know this game here--
cut the rope, perhaps?
Let's see.
We have our glasses on over here?
>> OK.
Thank you.
What's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Laura.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Laura?
Nice to see.
If you don't mind putting
Google Glass over your glasses.
This is Colton.
>> COLTON: Hi.
Nice to meet you.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK, come on around.
All right, so what you're going to
do here, having played this before,
is put your hand over
the Leap Motion here.
And now your arrow should move.
Oh, nope.
>> AUDIENCE: No.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: We
don't want to quit yet.
OK, wait.
Over here.
So notice as you hold your
finger over something,
the mouse starts to go green,
which is how you click.
>> So hover over Play.
And just one finger is fine.
And now click on the little
green guy on the left.
And now hold until it fills up green.
Good.
Now, like, level one up top.
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah, we want level one, here.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
OK, so all you have
to do is cut the rope.
Your cursor's the white one down there.
>> Very nice.
All right, it's about to get harder.
So hold your finger over next now.
Good.
This one's hard.
>> AUDIENCE: Oh crap.
OK.
It wants to go that way.
Oh crap, that--
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
Secondary goal is to get all the stars.
All right, next.
>> Let's see if you can get this third one.
Good.
OK, go over there.
>> Sure.
Oh, very nice.
All right.
>> So why don't we adjourn here today?
Let anyone come on up who wants to play.
Thanks so much to Laura our volunteer.
And we will see you on Monday.
>> AUDIENCE: You probably want these back.
>> SPEAKER 2: At the next CS50--