[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50.
This is week five continued, and we
have some good news and some bad news.
So good news is that CS50
launches this Friday.
If you would like to join us,
head to the usual URL here.
Even better news, no lecture
this coming Monday the 13th.
Slightly less better news,
quiz zero is next Wednesday.
More details can be
found at this URL here.
And over the next couple days
we'll be filling in the blanks
with regards to the rooms
that we will have reserved.
Better news is that there'll
be a course-wide review
session this coming
Monday in the evening.
Stay tuned to the course's
website for location and details.
Sections, even though it is a
holiday, will also meet as well.
Best news, lecture next Friday.
So this is a tradition we
have, as per the syllabus.
Just-- it's going to be amazing.
You will see things like
constant time data structures
and hash tables and trees and tries.
And we'll talk about birthday problems.
A whole bunch of stuff
awaits next Friday.
OK.
Anyhow.
>> So recall that we've been
focusing on this picture of what's
inside of our computer's memory.
So memory or RAM is where programs
exist while you're running them.
If you double-click an
icon to run some program
or double-click an
icon to open some file,
it's loaded from your hard
drive or solid state drive
into RAM, Random Access Memory, where
it lives until the power goes off,
the laptop lid closes,
or you quit the program.
>> Now that memory, of
which you probably have
1 gigabyte these days, 2
gigabytes, or even much more,
is generally laid out
for a given program
in this sort of rectangular
conceptual model
whereby we have the stack at the bottom
and a bunch of other stuff at the top.
The thing at the very top
we've seen on this picture
before but never talked about
is the so-called text segment.
Text segment is just a fancy way
of saying the zeros and ones that
compose your actual compiled program.
>> So when you double-click
Microsoft Word on your Mac or PC,
or when you run dot slash Mario on a
Linux computer at your terminal window,
the zeros and ones that compose
Word or Mario are stored temporarily
in your computer's RAM in the so-called
text segment for a particular program.
Below that goes initialized
and uninitialized data.
This is stuff like global variables,
that we've not used many of,
but on occasion we've
had global variables
or statically defined strings that
is hard coded words like "hello"
that aren't taken in from the user
that are hard-coded into your program.
>> Now, down at the bottom we
have the so-called stack.
And the stack, thus far, we've been
using for what kinds of purposes?
What's the stack been used for?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Functions.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: For functions?
In what sense for functions?
>> AUDIENCE: When you call a function, the
arguments are copied onto the stack.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
When you call a function, its
arguments are copied onto the stack.
So any X's or Y's or A's or B's
that you're passing into a function
are temporarily put on
the so-called stack,
just like one of the Annenberg
dining hall trays, and also things
like local variables.
If your foo function or your swap
function have local variables,
like temp, those two
end up on the stack.
Now, we won't talk too much about
them, but these environment variables
at the bottom we saw a while ago when
I was futzing at the keyboard one day
and I started accessing things
like argv 100 or argv 1,000,
just elements-- I forget
the numbers-- but that
weren't supposed to be accessed by me.
We started seeing some
funky symbols on the screen.
Those were so-called
environment variables
like global settings for my
program or for my computer, not
unrelated to the recent
bug that we discussed,
Shellshock, that's been
plaguing quite a few computers.
>> Now lastly, in today's focus
we'll ultimately be on the heap.
This is another chunk of memory.
And fundamentally all this
memory is the same stuff.
It's the same hardware.
We're just sort of
treating different clusters
of bytes for different purposes.
The heap is also going to be where
variables and memory that you request
from the operating system
is temporarily stored.
>> But there's kind of a problem
here, as the picture implies.
We sort of have two
ships about to collide.
Because as you use more and more
of the stack, and as we see today
onward, as you use more and more of the
heap, surely bad things might happen.
And indeed, we can induce that
intentionally or unintentionally.
So the cliffhanger last
time was this program,
which didn't serve any functional
purpose other than to demonstrate
how you as a bad guy can actually take
advantage of bugs in someone's program
and take over a program or even a
whole computer system or server.
So just to glance briefly, you
notice that main at the bottom
takes in command line
arguments, as per argv.
And it has a call to a function f,
essentially a nameless function called
f, and it's passing in argv[1].
>> So whatever word the user types in at
the prompt after this program's name,
and then this arbitrary function up
top, f, takes in a string, AKA char*,
as we've begun to discuss,
and it just calls it "bar."
But we could call it anything.
And then it declares, inside
of f, an array of characters
called c-- 12 such characters.
>> Now, by the story I was telling
a moment ago, where in memory
is c, or are those 12
chars going to end up?
Just to be clear.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: On the stack.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: On the stack.
So c is a local variable.
We're asking for 12 chars or 12 bytes.
Those are going to end up
on the so-called stack.
Now finally is this other function
that's actually pretty useful,
but we've not really used
it ourselves, strncopy.
It means string copy, but
only n letters, n characters.
So n characters will be
copied from bar into c.
And how many?
The length of bar.
So in other words, that
one line, strncopy,
is going to copy
effectively bar in to c.
>> Now, just to kind of anticipate
the moral of this story,
what is potentially problematic here?
Even though we're checking the length
of bar and passing it into strncopy,
what is your gut telling you is
still broken about this program?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Doesn't include
room for the null character.
DAVID J. MALAN: Doesn't include
Potentially, unlike in
past practice we don't even
have so much as a plus 1 to
accommodate that null character.
But it's even worse than that.
What else are we failing to do?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
We've hard coded 12 pretty arbitrarily.
That isn't so much the
problem, but the fact
that we're not even checking if
the length of bar is less than 12,
in which case it's going to be
safe to put it into the memory
called c that we've allocated.
Indeed, if bar is like
20 characters long,
this function appears to be copying
20 characters from bar into c, thereby
taking at least 8 bytes
that it shouldn't be.
That's the implication here.
>> So in short, broken program.
Not such a big deal.
Maybe you get a segmentation fault.
We've all had bugs in programs.
We all might have bugs
in programs right now.
But what's the implication?
Well, here's a zoomed-in version of
that picture of my computer's memory.
This is the bottom of my stack.
And indeed, at the very bottom is what's
called parent routine stack, fancy way
of saying that's main.
So that whoever called the function
f that we're talking about.
So this is the bottom of the stack.
Return address is something new.
It's always been there,
always been in that picture.
We just never called attention to it.
Because it turns out the way c works is
that when one function calls another,
not only do the arguments to that
function get pushed onto the stack,
not only do the function's local
variables get pushed onto the stack,
something called a return address
also gets put onto the stack.
Specifically, if main calls foo, main's
own address in memory, ox something,
effectively gets put onto the stack
so that when f is done executing it
knows where to jump back to in the text
segment in order to continue executing.
>> So if we're here conceptually,
in main, then f gets called.
How does f know who
to hand control back?
Well, this little
breadcrumb in red here,
called the return address, it just
checks, what is that return address?
Oh, let me jump back to main here.
And that's a little bit
of an oversimplification,
because the zeros and ones
for main are technically
up here in the tech segment.
But that's the idea. f
just has to know what
to where control ultimately goes back.
>> But the way computers
have long laid out things
like local variables and
arguments is like this.
So in the top of this picture in
blue is the stack frame for f, so all
of the memory that f
specifically is using.
So accordingly, notice that
bar is in this picture.
Bar was its argument.
And we claimed that arguments to
functions get pushed onto the stack.
And c, of course, is
also in this picture.
>> And just for notational purposes,
notice at the top left-hand corner
is what would be c bracket 0 and
then slightly down to the right
is c bracket 11.
So in other words, you can imagine
that there's a grid of bytes
there, first of which is
top left, bottom of which
is the last of those 12 bytes.
>> But now try to fast forward.
What is about to happen if we pass
in a string bar that's longer than c?
And we're not checking if
it's indeed longer than 12.
Which part of this picture is going to
get overwritten by bytes 0, 1, 2, 3,
dot dot dot, 11, and then
bad, 12, 13 through 19?
What's going to happen here,
if you infer from the ordering
that c bracket 0 is on the top
and c bracket 11 is sort of down
to the right?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Well, it's going
to overwrite the char* bar.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, it looks like
you're going to overwrite char* bar.
And worse, if you send in a really long
string, you might even overwrite what?
The return address.
Which again, is just like a
breadcrumb to tell the program where
to go back to when f
is done being called.
>> So what bad guys typically do
is if they come across a program
that they're curious whether is
exploitable, buggy in such a way
that he or she can take
advantage of that bug,
generally they don't get
this right the first time.
They just start sending, for instance,
random strings into your program,
whether at the keyboard,
or frankly they probably
write a little program to just
automatically generate strings,
and start banging on your program by
sending in lots of different inputs
at different lengths.
>> As soon as your program crashes,
that's an amazing thing.
Because it means he
or she has discovered
what is probably indeed a bug.
And then they can get more clever
and start focusing more narrowly
on how to exploit that bug.
In particular, what he or she might
do is send, in the best case, hello.
No big deal.
It's a string that's sufficiently short.
But what if he or she sends,
and we'll generalize it as,
attack code-- so zeros
and ones that do things
like rm-rf, that remove everything
from the hard drive or send spam
or somehow attack the machine?
>> So if each of these
letters A just represents,
conceptually, attack, attack,
attack, attack, some bad code
that someone else wrote, but
if that person is smart enough
to not only include all
of those rm-rfs, but also
have his or her last few bytes
be a number that corresponds
to the address of his
or her own attack code
that he or she passed in just
by providing it at the prompt,
you can effectively trick the computer
into noticing when f is done executing,
oh, it's time for me to jump
back to the red return address.
But because he or she has somehow
overlapped that return address
with their own number,
and they're smart enough
to have configured that
number to refer, as you
see in the super top
left-hand corner there,
the actual address in the computer's
memory of some of their attack code,
a bad guy can trick the computer
into executing his or her own code.
>> And that code, again, can be anything.
It's generally called
shell code, which is just
a way of saying that it's not
generally something as simple as rm-rf.
It's actually something like Bash,
or an actual program that gives him
or her programmatic control to execute
anything else that they want to.
So in short, this all
derives from the simple fact
that this bug involved not checking
the boundaries of your array.
And because the way
computers work is that they
use the stack from
effectively, conceptually,
bottom on up, but then the elements
you push onto the stack grow top down,
this is incredibly problematic.
Now, there are ways to work around this.
And frankly, there are languages
with which to work around this.
Java is immune, for instance,
to this particular issue.
Because they don't give you pointers.
They don't give you
direct memory addresses.
So with this power that we have
to touch anything in memory
we want comes, admittedly, great risk.
>> So keep an eye out.
If, frankly, in the months
or years to come, anytime
you read about some exploitation
of a program or a server,
if you ever see a hint of something
like a buffer overflow attack,
or stack overflow is another type
of attack, similar in spirit,
much as inspires the website's
name, if you know it,
it's all talking about just
overflowing the size of some character
array or some array more generally.
Any questions, then, on this?
Don't try this at home.
>> All right.
So malloc thus far has been our new
friend in that we can allocate memory
that we don't necessarily know in
advance that we want so we don't have
to hard code into our
program numbers like 12.
Once the user tells us how much
data he or she wants to input,
we can malloc that much memory.
>> So malloc it turns out, to the
extent we've been using it,
explicitly last time, and then
you guys have been using it
for getstring unknowingly for
several weeks, all of malloc's memory
comes from the so-called heap.
And this is why getstring, for instance,
can allocate memory dynamically
without knowing what you're
going to type in advance,
hand you back a pointer to that memory,
and that memory is still yours to keep,
even after getstring returns.
Because recall after all that the
stack is constantly going up and down,
up and down.
And as soon as it goes
down, that means any memory
this function used should
not be used by anyone else.
It's garbage values now.
>> But the heap is up here.
And what's nice about malloc is that
when malloc allocates memory up here,
it's not impacted, for the
most part, by the stack.
And so any function can access
memory that has been malloc'd,
even by a function like getstring,
even after it is returned.
>> Now, the converse of malloc is free.
And indeed, the rule you
need to start adopting
is any, any, any time you use malloc
you must yourself use free, eventually,
on that same pointer.
All this time we have been writing
buggy, buggy code, for many reasons.
But one of which has been
using the CS50 library, which
itself is deliberately
buggy, it leaks memory.
Any time you've called getstring
over the past few weeks
we're asking the operating
system, Linux, for memory.
And you have never once given it back.
And this is not, in
practice, a good thing.
>> And Valgrind, one of the
tools introduced in Pset 4,
is all about helping you
now find bugs like that.
But thankfully for Pset 4 you don't need
to use the CS50 library or getstring.
So any bugs related to memory are
ultimately going to be your own.
>> So malloc is more than just
convenient for this purpose.
We can actually now solve
fundamentally different problems,
and fundamentally solve problems more
effectively as per week zero's promise.
Thus far this is the sexiest
data structure we've had.
And by data structure I just mean
a way of conceptualizing memory
in a way that goes beyond just saying,
this is an int, this is a char.
We can start to cluster things together.
>> So an array looked like this.
And what was key in about an
array is that it gives you
back-to-back chunks of
memory, each of which
is going to be of the same type, int,
int, int, int, or char, char, char,
char.
But there's a few downsides.
This for instance, is
an array of size six.
Suppose you fill this array with six
numbers and then, for whatever reasons,
your user wants to give
you a seventh number.
Where do you put it?
>> What's the solution if you have
created an array on the stack,
for instance, just with the week
two notation that we introduced,
of square brackets with a number inside?
Well, you've got six
numbers in these boxes.
What would your instincts be?
Where would you want to put it?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Sorry?
>> AUDIENCE: Put it on the end.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Put it on the end.
So just over to the right,
outside of this box.
Which would be nice, but it
turns out you can't do that.
Because if you've not asked
for this chunk of memory,
it could be by coincidence that this
is being used by some other variable
altogether.
Think back a week or so when we laid
out Zamyla and Davin and Gabe's names
in memory.
They were literally
back to back to back.
So we can't necessarily
trust that whatever's
over here is available for me to use.
>> So what else might you do?
Well, once realizing you
need an array of size seven,
you could just create an
array of size seven then use
a for loop or a while loop,
copy it into the new array,
and then somehow just get rid of
this array or just stop using it.
But that's not particularly efficient.
In short, arrays don't let
you dynamically resize.
>> So on the one hand you get
random access, which is amazing.
Because it lets us do things
like divide and conquer,
binary search, all of which we've
talked about on the screen here.
But you paint yourself into a corner.
As soon as you hit
the end of your array,
you have to do a very
expensive operation
or write a whole bunch of code
to now deal with that problem.
>> So what if instead we had
something called a list,
or a linked list in particular?
What if instead of having
rectangles back to back to back,
we have rectangles that leave a little
bit of wiggle room in between them?
And even though I've drawn this
picture or adapted this picture
from one of the texts here to be back to
back to back very orderly, in reality,
one of those rectangles
could be up here in memory.
One of them could be up here.
One of them could be up here,
over here, and so forth.
>> But what if we drew,
in this case, arrows
that somehow link these
rectangles together?
Indeed, we've seen a technical
incarnation of an arrow.
What have we used in recent
days that, underneath the hood,
is representative of an arrow?
A pointer, right?
>> So what if, instead of
just storing the numbers,
like 9, 17, 22, 26, 34,
what if we stored not
only a number but a pointer
next to each such number?
So that much like you would thread a
needle through a whole bunch of fabric,
somehow tying things
together, similarly can
we with pointers, as
incarnated by arrows here,
kind of weave together
these individual rectangles
by effectively using a pointer
next to each number that
points to some next number, that
points to, in turn, some next number?
So in other words, what
if we actually wanted
to implement something like this?
Well unfortunately, these rectangles,
at least the one with 9, 17, 22,
and so forth, these are no longer
nice squares with single numbers.
The bottom, rectangle
below 9, for instance,
represents what should
be a pointer, 32 bits.
Now, I'm not yet aware of any data type
in C that gives you not only an int
but a pointer altogether.
>> So what's the solution if we want
to invent our own answer to this?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: What's that?
>> AUDIENCE: New structure.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so why
don't we create a new structure,
or in C, a struct?
We've seen structs before, if briefly,
where we dealt with a student structure
like this, who had a name and a house.
In Pset 3 breakout you used a whole
bunch of structs-- GRect and GOvals
that Stanford created to
cluster information together.
So what if we take this same idea of
the keywords "typedef" and "struct,"
and then some student-specific stuff,
and evolve this into the following:
typedef struct node-- and node is
just a very generic computer science
term for something in a data structure,
a container in a data structure.
A node I claim is going to have
an int n, totally straightforward,
and then a little more cryptically,
this second line, struct node* next.
But in less technical terms,
what is that second line
of code inside the curly braces?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: A
pointer to another node.
So admittedly, syntax a little cryptic.
But if you read it literally,
next is the name of a variable.
What is its data type?
It's a little verbose this time,
but it's of type struct node*.
Any time we've seen something star, that
means it's a pointer to that data type.
So next is apparently a
pointer to a struct node.
>> Now, what is a struct node?
Well, notice you see those
same words at top right.
And indeed, you also see the word
"node" down here at the bottom left.
And this is actually just a convenience.
Notice that in our student definition
there's the word "student" only once.
And that's because a student
object was not self-referential.
There's nothing inside of a student
that needs to point to another student,
persay.
That would be sort of
weird in the real world.
>> But with a node in a linked
list, we do want a node
to be referential to a similar object.
And so notice the change here is not
just what's inside the curly braces.
But we add the word "node"
at the top as well as
adding it to the bottom
in lieu of "student."
And this is only a technical detail
so that, again, your data structure
can be self-referential, so that a
node can point to another such node.
>> So what is this ultimately
going to mean for us?
Well, one, this stuff inside
is the contents of our node.
This thing up here,
top right, is just so
that, again, we can refer to ourselves.
And then the outermost stuff,
even though node is a new term,
perhaps, it's still the
same as student and what
was underneath the hood in SPL.
>> So if we now wanted to start
implementing this linked list,
how might we translate
something like this to code?
Well, let's just see an
example of a program that
actually uses a linked list.
Among today's distribution code
is a program called List Zero.
And if I run this I created a super
simple GUI, Graphical User Interface,
but it's really just printf.
And now I've given myself a few menu
options-- Delete, Insert, Search,
and Traverse.
And Quit.
These are just common operations on a
data structure known as a link list.
>> Now, Delete is going to
delete a number from the list.
Insert's going to add
a number to the list.
Search is going to look
for number in the list.
And traverse is just a fancy way
of saying, walk through the list,
print it out, but that's it.
Don't change it in any way.
>> So let's try this.
Let's go ahead and type 2.
And then I'm going to
insert the number, say 9.
Enter.
And now my program is just
programmed to say, list is now 9.
Now, if I go ahead and
do Insert again, let
me go ahead and zoom out and type in 17.
Now my list is 9, then 17.
If I do insert again, let's skip one.
Instead of 22, as per the picture we've
been looking at here, let me jump ahead
and insert 26 next.
So I'm going to type 26.
The list is as I expect.
But now, just to see if this code
is going to be flexible, let me now
type 22, which at least
conceptually, if we're
keeping this sorted, which is indeed
going to be another goal right now,
should go in between 17 and 26.
So I hit Enter.
Indeed, that works.
And so now let me insert the
last, per the picture, 34.
>> All right.
So for now let me stipulate that
Delete and Traverse and Search do,
in fact, work.
In fact, if I do run Search, let's
search for the number 22, Enter.
It found 22.
So that is what this
program List Zero does.
>> But what is actually going
on that implements this?
Well, first I might have, and indeed
I do have, a file called list0.h.
And somewhere in there is this
line, typedef, struct node,
then I have my curly braces, int n, and
then struct-- what was the definition?
Struct node next.
So we need the star.
Now technically we get into
the habit of drawing it here.
You might see textbooks and
online references do it there.
It's functionally equivalent.
In fact, this is a little more typical.
But I'll be consistent with what
we did last time and do this.
And then lastly, I'm going to do this.
>> So in a header file
somewhere, in list0.h
today is this struct definition,
and maybe some other stuff.
Meanwhile in list0c there's
going to be a few things.
But we're going to just
start and not finish this.
List0.h is a file I want
to include in my C file.
And then at some point I'm
going to have int, main, void.
And then I'm going to
have some to-do's here.
I'm also going to have a
prototype, like void, search, int,
n, whose purpose in life is
to search for an element.
And then down here I claim in
today's code, void, search, int, n,
no semicolon but open curly braces.
And now I want to somehow search
for an element in this list.
But we don't have enough
information on the screen yet.
I haven't actually
represented the list itself.
So one way we could implement
a linked list in a program
is I kind of want to do something
like declare linked list up here.
For simplicity, I'm going to make
this global, even though in general we
shouldn't do this too much.
But it will simplify this example.
So I want to declare
a linked list up here.
Now, how might I do that?
>> Here's the picture of a linked list.
And I don't really
know at the moment how
I'm going to go about representing
so many things with just one
variable in memory.
But think back a moment.
All this time we've had
strings, which we then
revealed to be arrays of
characters, which we then
revealed to just be a pointer
to the first character
in an array of characters
that's null terminated.
So by that logic, and with this
picture kind of seeding your thoughts,
what need we actually write in our
code to represent a linked list?
How much of this information do we need
to capture in C code, would you say?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: We need a pointer to a node.
DAVID J. MALAN: A pointer to a node.
In particular, which node would your
instincts be to keep a pointer to?
>> AUDIENCE: The first node.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
probably just the first.
And notice, the first
node is a different shape.
It's only half the size of the struct,
because it's indeed only a pointer.
So what you can indeed do is declare
a linked list to be of type node*.
And let's just call it first
and initialize it to null.
So null, again, is coming
into the picture here.
Not only is null used as like a special
return value for things like getstring
and malloc, null is also the zero
pointer, the lack of a pointer,
if you will.
It just means nothing is yet here.
Now first, I could've
called this anything.
I could have called it "list"
or any number of other things.
But I'm calling it "first" so that
it lines up with this picture.
So just like a string can be represented
with the address of its first byte,
so can a linked list.
And we'll see other data
structures be represented
with just one pointer,
a 32-bit arrow, pointing
at the very first node in the structure.
>> But now let's anticipate a problem.
If I'm only remembering
in my program the address
of the first node, the first
rectangle in this data structure,
what had better be the case about the
implementation of the rest of my list?
What's a key detail that's going
to ensure this actually works?
And by "actually works" I
mean, much like a string,
lets us go from the first character
in Davin's name to the second,
to the third, to the
fourth, to the very end,
how do we know when we're at the end
of a linked list that looks like this?
When it's null.
And I've represented this sort of as
like an electrical engineer might,
with the little grounding
symbol, of sorts.
But that just means null in this case.
You can draw it any number
of ways, but this author
happened to use this symbol here.
>> So long as we're stringing
all of these nodes together,
only remembering where
the first one is, so long
as we put a special symbol at
the very last node in the list,
and we'll use null, because that's
what we have available to us,
this list is complete.
And even if I only give you a pointer to
the first element, you, the programmer,
can certainly access the rest of it.
But let's let your minds
wander a little bit,
if they're not already
quite wandered-- what's
going to be the running time of
finding anything in this list?
Damn it, it's big O of n,
which isn't bad, in fairness.
But it is linear.
We have given up what feature
of arrays by moving more
toward this picture of dynamically
woven together or linked nodes?
We've given up random access.
An array is nice because
mathematically everything
is back to back to back to back.
Even though this picture
looks pretty, and even
though it looks like these nodes
are nicely spaced apart, in reality
they could be anywhere.
Ox1, Ox50, Ox123, Ox99, these
nodes could be anywhere.
Because malloc does allocate memory
from the heap, but anywhere in the heap.
You don't necessarily know that it's
going to be back to back to back.
And so this picture in reality's
not going to be quite this pretty.
>> So it's going to take a bit of
work to implement this function.
So let's implement search now.
And we'll see kind of a
clever way of doing this.
So if I am a search function and
I'm given a variable, integer n
to look for, I need to know the
new syntax for looking inside
of a structure that's
pointed to, to find n.
So let's do this.
>> So first I'm going to go
ahead and declare a node*.
And I'm going to call it
pointer, just by convention.
And I'm going to initialize it to first.
And now I can do this
in a number of ways.
But I'm going to take a common approach.
While pointer is not equal to
null, and that's valid syntax.
And it just means do the following, so
long as you're not pointing at nothing.
What do I want to do?
>> If pointer dot n, let me come back
to that, equals-- equals what?
What value am I looking for?
The actual n that was passed in.
So here's another feature
of C and many languages.
Even though the structure called node
has a value n, totally legitimate
to also have a local argument
or variable called n.
Because even we, with
human eyes, can distinguish
that this n is presumably
different from this n.
Because the syntax is different.
You've got a dot and a pointer,
whereas this one has no such thing.
So this is OK.
That's OK to call them the same things.
>> If I do you find this, I'm
going to want to do something
like announce that we found n.
And we'll leave that as a
comment or pseudocode code.
Else, and here's the
interesting part, what
do I want to do if the current node
is not containing n that I care about?
How do I achieve the following?
If my finger at the
moment is PTR, and it's
pointing at whatever
first is pointing at,
how do I move my finger
to the next node in code?
Well, what's the breadcrumb we're
going to follow in this case?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so next.
So if I go back to my
code here, indeed, I'm
going to go ahead and say pointer, which
is just a temporary variable-- it's
a weird name, ptr, but
it's just like temp--
I'm going to set pointer
equal to whatever pointer is--
and again, this is going to be a
little buggy for a moment-- dot next.
In other words, I'm going to take my
finger that's pointing at this node
here and I'm going to say, you know
what, take a look at the next field
and move your finger to
whatever it's pointing at.
And this is going to
repeat, repeat, repeat.
But when does my finger
stop doing anything at all?
As soon as what line of code kicks in?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: If point while
pointer is not equal to null.
At some point my finger's
going to be pointing at null
and I'm going to realize
that's the end of this list.
Now, this is a little
white lie for simplicity.
It turns out that even though we
just learned this dot notation
for structures, pointer is not a struct.
ptr is what?
Just to be more nitpicky.
It's a pointer to a node.
It's not a node itself.
If I had no star here, pointer
absolutely-- it's a node.
This is like week one
declaration of a variable,
even though the word "node" is new.
>> But as soon as we introduce a
star, it's now a pointer to a node.
And unfortunately you can't use
the dot notation for a pointer.
You have to use the arrow
notation, which, strikingly,
is the first time any piece
of syntax looks intuitive.
This literally looks like an arrow.
And so that's a good thing.
And down here literally
looks like an arrow.
So I think that's the la-- I don't
think I'm over-committing here-- I
think that's the last new piece
of syntax we're going to see.
And thankfully, it's indeed
a little more intuitive.
>> Now, for those of you who
might prefer the old way,
you can still use the dot notation.
But as per Monday's
conversation, we first
need to go there, go to that
address, and then access the field.
So this is also correct.
And frankly, this is a
little more pedantic.
You're literally saying, dereference
the pointer and go there.
Then grab .n, the field called n.
But frankly, no one wants
to type or read this.
And so the world invented
the arrow notation, which
is equivalent, identical,
it's just syntactic sugar.
So a fancy way of saying this
looks better, or looks simpler.
>> So now I'm going to do one other thing.
I'm going to say "break" once I've
found it so I don't keep looking for it.
But this is the gist
of a search function.
But it's a lot easier, in the
end, not to walk through the code.
This is indeed the formal implementation
of search in today's distribution code.
I dare say that insert is not
particularly fun to walk through
visually, nor is delete, even
though at the end of the day
they boil down to fairly
simple heuristics.
>> So let's do this.
If you'll humor me here, I did
bring a bunch of stress balls.
I brought a bunch of numbers.
And could we get just a few volunteers
to represent 9, 17, 20, 22, 29, and 34?
So essentially everyone
who's here today.
That was one, two, three,
four, five, six people.
And I've been asked to go-- see, no
one in the back raises their hands.
OK, one, two, three, four,
five-- let me load balance-- six.
OK, you six come on up.
We'll need other people.
We brought extra stress balls.
And if you could, for
just a moment, line
yourselves up just
like this picture here.
>> All right.
Let's see, what's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Andrew.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Andrew,
you are number 9.
Nice to meet you.
Here you go.
AUDIENCE: Jen.
DAVID J. MALAN: Jen.
David.
Number 17.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: I'm Julia.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Julia, David.
Number 20.
AUDIENCE: Christian.
DAVID J. MALAN: Christian, David.
Number 22.
And?
>> AUDIENCE: JP.
DAVID J. MALAN: JP.
Number 29.
So go ahead and get in-- Uh oh.
Uh oh.
Standby.
20.
Does anyone have a marker?
AUDIENCE: I've got a Sharpie.
DAVID J. MALAN: You got a Sharpie?
OK.
And does anyone have a piece of paper?
Save the lecture.
Come on.
AUDIENCE: We've got it.
DAVID J. MALAN: We got it?
All right, thank you.
Here we go.
Was this from you?
You just saved the day.
So 29.
All right.
I misspelled 29, but OK.
Go ahead.
All right, I'll give you
your pen back momentarily.
So we have these folks here.
Let's have one other.
Gabe, do you want to play
the first element here?
We'll need you to point
at these fine folks.
So 9, 17, 20, 22, sort
of 29, and then 34.
Did we lose someone?
I do have a 34.
Where did-- OK, who wants to be 34?
OK, come on up, 34.
All right, this will be
well worth the climax.
What's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Peter.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Peter, come on up.
All right, so here's a
whole bunch of nodes.
Each of you guys represents
one of these rectangles.
And Gabe, the slightly odd
man out, represents first.
So his pointer is a little smaller
on the screen than everyone else.
And in this case, each of your left
hands is going to either point down,
thereby representing null, so
just the absence of a pointer,
or it's going to be pointing
at a node next to you.
>> So right now if you adorn
yourselves like the picture
here, go ahead and point
at each other, with Gabe
in particular pointing at
number 9 to represent the list.
OK, and number 34, your left hand
should just be pointing at the floor.
>> OK, so this is the linked list.
So this is the scenario in question.
And indeed, this is representative
of a class of problems
that you might try to solve with code.
You want to ultimately insert
a new element into the list.
In this case, we're going to
try inserting the number 55.
But there's going to be
different cases to consider.
And indeed, this is going to be one
of the big-picture takeaways here, is,
what are the different cases.
What are the different if conditions or
branches that your program might have?
>> Well, the number you're trying to
insert, which we know now to be 55,
but if you didn't know
in advance, I daresay
falls into at least three
possible situations.
Where might a new element be?
AUDIENCE: And the end or middle.
DAVID J. MALAN: At the end, in
the middle, or at the beginning.
So I claim there's at least
three problems we need to solve.
Let's choose what's perhaps
arguably the simplest
one, where the new element
belongs at the beginning.
So I'm going to have code quite
like search, which I just wrote.
And I'm going to have ptr, which
I'll represent here with my finger,
as usual.
>> And remember, what value
did we initialize ptr to?
So we initialized it to null initially.
But then what did we do once we
were inside our search function?
We set it equal to first,
which doesn't mean doing this.
If I set ptr equal to first, what
should my hand really be pointing at?
Right.
So if Gabe and I are going
to be equal values here,
we need to both point at number 9.
>> So this was the beginning of our story.
And now this is just straightforward,
even though the syntax is new.
Conceptually this is just linear search.
Is 55 equal to 9?
Or rather, let's say less than 9.
Because I'm trying to
figure out where to put 55.
Less than 9, less than 17, less
than 20, less than 22, less than 29,
less than 34, no.
So now we're in case
one of at least three.
>> If I want to insert 55 over here, what
lines of code need to get executed?
How does this picture of
humans need to change?
What do I do with my left hand?
This should be null initially,
because I'm at the end of the list.
And what should happen
here with Peter, was it?
He's obviously going to point to me.
So I claim there's at least two lines
of code in the sample code from today
that's going to implement this
scenario of adding 55 at the tail.
And could I have someone hop
up and just represent 55?
All right, you are the new 55.
>> So now what if the next
scenario comes along,
and we want to insert at the
beginning or the head of this list?
And what's your name, number 55?
>> AUDIENCE: Jack.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Jack?
OK, nice to meet you.
Welcome aboard.
So now we're going to
insert, say, the number 5.
Here's the second case of the
three we came up with before.
So if 5 belongs at the beginning,
let's see how we find that out.
I initialize my ptr
pointer to number 9 again.
And I realized, oh, 5 is less than 9.
So fix this picture for us.
Whose hands, Gabe's or David's
or-- what's number 9's name?
>> AUDIENCE: Jen.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Jen's hands--
which of our hands need to change?
OK, so Gabe points at what now?
At me.
I am the new node.
So I'll just kind of move
here to see it visually.
And meanwhile what do I point that?
Still where I'm pointing.
So that's it.
So just really one line of code fixes
this particular issue, it would seem.
All right, so that's good.
And can someone be a placeholder for 5?
Come on up.
We'll get you next time.
>> All right, so now-- and
as an aside, the names
I'm not making explicit mention of right
now, pred pointer, predecessor pointer
and new pointer, that's
just the names given
in the sample code to the pointers or
my hands that's kind of pointing around.
What's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Christine.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Christine.
Welcome aboard.
All right, so let's consider now
a slightly more annoying scenario,
whereby I want to insert
something like 26 into this.
20?
What?
These are-- good thing we have this pen.
All right, 20.
If someone could get another piece of
paper ready, just in case-- all right.
Oh, interesting.
Well this is an example
of a lecture bug.
OK so what's your name again?
AUDIENCE: Julia.
DAVID J. MALAN: Julia, can you pop
out and pretend you were never there?
OK, this never happened.
Thank you.
So suppose we want insert
Julia into this linked list.
She is the number 20.
And of course she's
going to belong at the
begin-- don't point at anything yet.
So your hand can kind of be
down null or some garbage value.
Let's tell the quick story.
I'm pointing at number 5 this time.
Then I check 9.
Then I check 17.
Then I check 22.
And I realize, ooh, Julia
needs to go before 22.
So what needs to happen?
Whose hands need to change?
Julia's, mine, or--
what's your name again?
>> AUDIENCE: Christian.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Christian or?
>> AUDIENCE: Andy.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Andy.
Christian or Andy?
Andy needs to point at?
Julia.
All right.
So Andy, do you want to point at Julia?
But wait a minute.
In the story thus far,
I'm the sort of one
in charge, in the sense that
pointer is the thing that's
moving through the list.
We might have a name for Andy, but
there's no variable called Andy.
The only other variable we have is
first, who's represented by Gabe.
>> So this is actually why thus
far we've not needed this.
But now on the screen there is
mention again of pred pointer.
So let me be more explicit.
If this is pointer, I had better
get a little more intelligent
about my iteration.
If you don't mind my going through here
again, pointing here, pointing here.
But let me have a pred pointer,
predecessor pointer, that's
kind of pointing at the
element I was just at.
So when I go here, now
my left hand updates.
When I go here my left hand updates.
And now I have not only a pointer to
the element that goes after Julia,
I still have a pointer to
Andy, the element before.
So you have access, essentially,
breadcrumbs, if you will,
to all of the requisite pointers.
>> So if I'm pointing at
Andy and I'm also pointing
at Christian, whose hands
should now be pointed elsewhere?
So Andy can now point at Julia.
Julia can now point at Christian.
Because she can copy my
right hand's pointer.
And that effectively puts you
back into this place here.
So in short, even though this
is taking us kind of forever
to actually update a
linked list, realize
that the operations
are relatively simple.
It's of one, two, three
lines of code ultimately.
But wrapped around those
lines of code presumably
is a bit of logic that effectively
asks the question, where are we?
Are we at the beginning,
the middle, or the end?
>> Now, there are certainly some other
operations we might implement.
And these pictures here just depict
what we just did with humans.
What about removal?
If I want to, for instance,
remove the number 34 or 55,
I might have the same kind of code,
but I'm going to need one or two steps.
Because what's new?
If I remove someone at the end,
like number 55 and then 34,
what also has to change as I do that?
I have to not evict--
what's your name again?
>> AUDIENCE: Jack.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Jack.
I have to not only evict-- free Jack,
so literally call free Jack, or at least
the pointer there too, but now
what needs to change with Peter?
His hand better start pointing down.
Because as soon as I call free on
Jack, if Peter's still pointing at Jack
and I therefore keep traversing
the list and access this pointer,
that's when our old friend segmentation
fault might actually kick in.
Because we've given the
memory back to Jack.
>> You can stay there
awkwardly for just a moment.
Because we have just a couple
final operations to consider.
Removing the head of the list,
or the beginning-- and this one's
a little annoying.
Because we have to know that Gabe
is kind of special in this program.
Because indeed, he has his own pointer.
He's not just being pointed at,
as is almost everyone else here.
>> So when the head of the list is
removed, whose hands need to change now?
What's your name again?
>> AUDIENCE: Christine.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: I'm awful
at names, apparently.
So Christine and Gabe,
whose hands need to change
when we try to remove Christine,
number 5, from the picture?
OK, so let's do Gabe.
Gabe's going to point,
presumably, at number 9.
But what next should happen?
AUDIENCE: Christine should
be null [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, we should probably
make-- I heard "null" somewhere.
AUDIENCE: Null and free her.
DAVID J. MALAN: Null what?
DAVID J. MALAN: Null and free her.
So this is very easy.
And it's perfect that you're now sort
of standing there, not belonging.
Because you've been
decoupled from the list.
You've effectively been
orphaned from the list.
And so we had better call free now on
Christine to give that memory back.
Otherwise every time we
delete a node from the list
we might be making the list
shorter, but not actually decreasing
the size in memory.
And so if we keep adding and
adding, adding things to the list,
my computer might get slower
and slower and slower,
because I'm running out of
memory, even if I'm not actually
using Christine's bytes
of memory anymore.
>> So in the end there are other
scenarios, of course-- removal
in the middle, removal
at the end, as we saw.
But the more interesting
challenge now is
going to be to consider exactly
what the running time is.
So not only can you keep your
pieces of paper, if, Gabe,
you wouldn't mind giving
everyone a stress ball.
Thank you so much to our linked list
of volunteers here, if you could.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
So a couple of analytical
questions then, if I could.
We've seen this notation before,
big O and omega, upper bounds
and lower bounds on the
running time of some algorithm.
So let's consider just
a couple of questions.
>> One, and we said it
before, what's the running
time of search for a
list in terms of big O?
What's an upper bound on the running
time of searching a linked list
as implemented by our volunteers here?
It's big O of n, linear.
Because in the worst case,
the element, like 55,
we might be looking for might be where
Jack was, all the way at the end.
And unfortunately, unlike an array
we can't get fancy this time.
Even though all of our humans were
sorted from small elements, 5,
all the way up to the bigger element,
55, that's usually a good thing.
But what does that assumption
no longer allow us to do?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Say again?
AUDIENCE: Random access.
DAVID J. MALAN: Random access.
And in turn that means we can no
longer use weak zeros, intuition,
and obviousness of using binary
search and divide and conquer.
Because even though we
humans could obviously
see that Andy or Christian were
roughly in the middle of the list,
we only know that as a
computer by skimming the list
from the very beginning.
So we've given up that random access.
>> So big O of n now is the upper
bound on our search time.
What about omega of our search?
What's the lower bound on searching
for some number in this list?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Say again?
AUDIENCE: One.
DAVID J. MALAN: One.
So constant time.
In the best case, Christine is
indeed at the beginning of the list.
And we're looking for
number 5, so we found her.
So no big deal.
But she's got to be at the
beginning of the list in this case.
What about something like Delete?
What if you want to delete an element?
What's the upper bound and lower bound
on deleting something from a linked
list?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Say again?
AUDIENCE: n.
DAVID J. MALAN: n is
indeed the upper bound.
Because in the worst case we try
to delete Jack, like we just did.
He's all the way at the end.
Takes us forever, or
n steps to find him.
So that's an upper bound.
That's linear, sure.
And the best case running time, or
the lower bounds in the best case
would be constant time.
Because maybe we try to delete
Christine, and we just get lucky
she's at the beginning.
Now wait a minute.
Gabe was also at the beginning,
and we also had to update Gabe.
So that wasn't just one step.
So is it indeed constant
time, in the best case,
to remove the smallest element?
It is, even though it might be two,
three, or even 100 lines of code,
if it's the same number of
lines, not in some loop,
and independent of the size
of the list, absolutely.
Deleting the element at
the beginning of the list,
even if we have to deal with
Gabe, is still constant time.
>> So this seems like a
massive step backwards.
And what a waste of time
if, in week one and week
zero we had not only
pseudocode code but actual code
to implement something that's log
base n, or log, rather, of n, base 2,
in terms of its running time.
So why the heck would we want to start
using something like a linked list?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: So you can add
elements to the array.
DAVID J. MALAN: So you can
add elements to the array.
And this too is thematic.
And we'll continue to see
this, this trade-off, much
like we've seen a
trade-off with merge sort.
We could really speed up
search or sorting, rather,
if we spend a bit more space and
have an additional chunk of a memory
or an array for merge sort.
But we spend more
space, but we save time.
In this case, we're
giving up time but we're
gaining flexibility,
dynamism if you will,
which is arguably a positive feature.
>> We're also spending space.
In what sense is a linked
list more expensive
in terms of space than an array?
Where is the extra space coming from?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] pointer.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, we
also have the pointer.
So this is minorly annoying
in that no longer am
I storing just an int
to represent an int.
I'm storing an int and a
pointer, which is also 32 bits.
So I'm literally doubling
the amount of space involved.
So that's a trade-off, but
that's in the case of int.
Suppose that you're not storing int,
but suppose each of these rectangles
or each of these humans was representing
a word, an English word that
might be five characters, 10
characters, maybe even more.
Then adding just 32 more bits
might be less of a big deal.
>> What if each of the students
in the demonstration
were literally student structs that
have names and houses and maybe
phone numbers and Twitter
handles and the like.
So all of the fields we started
talking about the other day,
much less of a big deal as
our nodes get more interesting
and big to spend, eh, an additional
pointer just to link them together.
But indeed, it's a trade-off.
And indeed, the code is
more complex, as you'll
see by skimming through
that particular example.
But what if there were
some holy grail here.
What if we don't take a step
backwards but a massive step forward
and implement a data
structure via which we
can find elements like Jack or
Christine or any other elements
in this array in true constant time?
Search is constant.
Delete is constant.
Insert is constant.
All of these operations are constant.
That would be our holy grail.
And that is where we
will pick up next time.
See you then.