[MUSIC PLAYING]
>> [MUSIC ARMIN VAN BUUREN, "THIS IS WHAT
IT FEELS LIKE"]
>> [MUSIC - M4SONIC, "WEAPON 2.0"]
>> [CLAPPING]
>> STEVE BALLMER: Woo!
This is CS50.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID MALAN: This is CS50.
And this is the start, and end,
of Week 12 for the very last time.
You'll recall from
Week 0 that we promised
this, that what ultimately
matters in this course
is not so much where you end
up relative to your classmates,
but where you, in Week 12, end up
relative to yourself in Week 0.
>> Well, we are here now
in Week 12, and you
might look back fondly, or
remarkadly, at just how far you've
come when this was the worst of
your problems, some weeks ago.
But consider how far
you've come since then.
Particularly, if among those with no
prior experience, just weeks later,
were you implementing a
fairly sophisticated data
structure like this hash table
here, or even this TRI here.
>> Just a few weeks later,
and just a week ago,
were you implementing this, a mash-up
of multiple APIs uisng asynchronus
JavaScript calls and HTTP
requests behind the scene.
Ultimately, creating an
entire web app from something
that began with just a few hash marks.
Now, indeed you might recall that
78% of you had no prior experience,
and we proposed that
you might be feeling
a little lonely at the
beginning, but realize
that you are now very much among
friends and supporters here.
>> Now, it's a tradition in CS50
to not only start the semester,
but also end the semester
with a bit of cake.
Indeed the team has been downstairs
cutting it up, and sampling the cake,
but that awaits in just
a little bit of time.
But I thought I'd pick up where we
left off and get some closure today.
>> You may recall this here website, I
thought the only good thing I could do
is write these kind folks upon having
endorsed them so in class just a couple
of weeks ago.
And I will say to their
credit, I got back this reply
from ediblearrangments.com.
Good morning, Mr. Malan.
We have inquired with our IT
department regarding your concern.
They advise that as of next week,
there will be a website patch applied.
We appreciate the feedback.
And indeed--
>> [APPLAUSE]
DAVID MALAN: And indeed if you
go to editablearrangments.com
now, click login, you are indeed sent
to the HTTPS version of the site.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> So there you have it, CS50 here making
a difference, one website at a time.
So now, the final project is,
of course, all that awaits now.
And realize that there's
any number of ingredients
that you can weave into
this project of yours.
>> Indeed what many students do, if
tackling a web based final project,
will take p set 7's
distribution code, CS50 Finance,
and then will rip out
parts of it that are
of interest, or germane
to their final project,
like the look up function, which is
surely very specific to Yahoo Finance.
And they'll add in their own code,
and build atop the login mechanism
that we provide you with.
And so that is absolutely a
great place to get started.
>> Especially if over break, and
shortly thereafter, you're
just not really sure where to begin to
create something that hasn't already
been handed to you at least in part.
p set 8.2, if you want to
do something with AJAX,
or you want to write a script
that imports a really big data set
into a database, use p
set 8 as a model in which
you can build your own code, ultimately.
But realize, too, that there's
even fancier ways to get started.
>> A very popular framework, that
we're fans of, is called Laravel.
This is a PHP framework
that essentially adds
to PHP a number of
features that are already
commonplace in the world
of Ruby and Python,
other programming languages
that have built into them,
or on top of them,
additional frameworks.
And so Laravel will take p set
7's framework, essentially,
and give you a whole lot
more tools for your tool kit.
So if curious, and if you'd like
to not only apply lessons learned,
but tackle some new lessons
for your final project,
check out this and similar
types of frameworks online.
>> How about hosting your website?
You can certainly put your final
project, if doing something web based,
on your CS50 appliance,
and most students do.
But if you'd like to actually take
the worldwide web out for a spin
and put your code out
there, realize that it's
pretty straightforward these days to
buy a domain name for a few dollars,
to set up your domain name's DNS
settings for the IP address stuff.
And then actually push your
code to some remote server
so that someone can visit
you at something.com,
or whatever domain
name you happen to buy.
>> Stay tuned to CS50's home
page in the days to come,
where we'll post some instructions
for doing exactly that.
If you'd like to follow
some guidance, or if you'd
like to venture out on
your own, there's so
many popular frameworks
and systems out there.
Many of which are free, or super
cheap, or at least free for students.
AWS, or Amazon Web Services, is one.
In fact, that's where CS50 runs most of
its own servers in the so-called cloud,
using virtual machines, servers
that aren't really physical.
>> They're the illusion of physical
servers, but that we, and you,
could have complete control over.
And we just had a seminar, in
fact, a couple weeks ago on that.
Parse.com is a super
popular back-end tool
that you can use to
actually host a database.
If you don't want to figure out, or
stand up your own MySQL database,
there's this and other
related services that
let you focus on the part
of your app that you really
like, the front-end
or the user interface,
or the features, and then outsource
to someone else, often for free.
Certainly for student scale
prototypes, any back-end services
like email or databases
that you might need.
>> Now, for authentication,
a super common FAQ in CS50
is, how do you authenticate users?
Not with their own user
names and passwords,
but with like Harvard IDs and PINS.
Well, realize CS50 has
a service called CS50
ID, via which you can do exactly that.
And then those of you tackling,
say, mobile projects, where you're
kind of conflicted if you want to
do an iPhone app, a Windows Phone
app, an Android app, or any
number of other devices out there,
realize that there are
actually tools that
allow you to write your app,
in typically JavaScript,
or some similar language.
And then deploy it to multiple
platforms like iOS and Android
and the like, phonegap
being one, Titanium another.
>> So if you're sort of
conflicted, and realize
that there's a bit of a
learning curve to learning
just one of these
languages, realize you can
take your own new found familiarity
with JavaScript out for a spin,
and apply it there.
And there's so much more that
you can find on your own,
or by consulting your TFs.
Now, what about life after CS50?
Just so that this is
said, at least once,
you're not going to be handed problem
set specifications and distribution
code in perpetuity, but realize
that you don't need the CS50
appliance to continue coding on Mac OS.
>> It's a wonderful, useful
environment in that
it's pre-configured to be
representative of a nice Linux system.
But you can certainly use any
number of freely available tools
these days to write code on your own Mac
without the overhead of an appliance,
or on your own Windows computer, or if
you're running Linux, a number of tools
exist there as well.
So that's just a whirlwind
tour that you might
want to curl up with at some point.
But for now, let's take a
look ahead and what remains.
>> In particular among the
course's historical events
is the CS50 hackathon.
An epic all nighter, at which
you'll arrive around 7:00 PM,
set up shop with your laptop,
and project, and friends.
And dive into final
projects in an environment
that looks a little
like this upon arrival.
You'll check in here, you'll
then get down to work,
you'll help out a classmate.
>> You'll indulge in first dinner around
9:00 PM, second dinner around 1:00 AM.
And then for those still
standing at the end of the night,
we'll take you to IHOP.
But along the way there
will be a photo booth,
not like this, and indeed actual
CS50 shuttles on our way to IHOP.
>> Now, the CS50 fair, for
students in the class,
this is your opportunity to exhibit
proudly your final projects.
Not only to others, but typically 2,000
plus attendees from across campus,
students, faculty, folks who see
the balloons along Oxford Street
and come on in.
So realize that what awaits there are
glimpses of maybe each other's projects
here, where you'll bring your laptop.
We'll set up tall tables on which you
put your laptop, hop on the Wi-Fi,
and demo your projects to passers by.
>> Meanwhile, there will be music,
and popcorn, and candy, and more.
So that you'll have ample
opportunities to mingle.
We'll have friends of
ours from industry,
recruiters from any
number of these companies
here there just to chat up
students about life after college,
or internships during
college, and the like.
You'll see, too, that there's a
raffle to incentivize not only
you to strike up these
chats with friends,
but also to invite your
own friends, or convince
your own friends to
come see your project.
>> You can sweeten the deal by these
little cards that will be handed out.
Each of them will have placeholders
for little Smiley face stickers.
You guys as the students will
be given Smiley face stickers.
And for anyone who ventures up to
you and says, hey, what did you do?
Or asks you for a demo of your
project, you hand them a sticker.
They put it on their card.
And that qualifies them for
any number of fabulous prizes,
including those pictured
here, which are then
raffled off at the end of the event.
That's it for CS50.
And along the way, there will be ample
popcorn, and stress balls, and candy,
and even last year the
Harvard band, who was not
expected, but was in attendance.
>> There will be a photo booth there as
well, and massive numbers of balloons
like these ones here.
So many so, that
invariably the staff try
to pull this trick at the end
of the night, never quite works.
But for you, if you'd like to
invite your friends to this event--
>> SAM CLARK: Now, as we come over
to the next stop on the tour.
You'll notice a distinct--
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> File on in.
You'll notice a distinct departure
from the Gothic architecture
that we saw on the rest of
the tour of Yale's campus.
Now, here we are at Sanders Theater.
Sanders Theater is really a cultural
and academic hub here at Harvard.
Commencement was held here until 1922.
It's modeled after the Sheldonian
Theater in Oxford, England,
as a matter of fact.
And it serves as a location
for many cultural events,
and big academic events here.
>> Many A cappella groups
perform in Sanders,
the Crocodillos perform
here frequently, they're
sort of like the
Wippenpoofs 2.0, almost.
As well as the largest class actually
at Harvard, CS50, is taught here.
Who on the tour is interested
in computer science?
Anyone interested?
Terrific.
Well, if you happen to
matriculate at Yale,
you'll really, really
want to be taking CS50.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> You won't actually be able to take
it physically within Sanders Theater,
however, CS50 will be live
streamed over to you in New Haven.
As well as you'll have an entire
support staff, support network of staff
there to take CS50, to learn
all about computer science.
So this is Sanders Theater.
It's not Gothic, but it's great.
Does anyone have any questions
before we move on to the next stop?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Is that David Malan?
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> SAM CLARK: Oh, my God it is!
Let's take a selfie.
Selfie!
Take a selfie!
Right here, right here.
Here, someone hold it up.
Someone hold it up.
How are you, David?
>> DAVID MALAN: Hello, DA
>> SAM CLARK: I'm doing well.
I got to flip it around.
And duck face, David.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> Yeah, he likes that.
Terrific.
Well, we'll move on to the next stop.
Our next stop is the
Harvard stadium, where
we've had great luck
in the last 13 years.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID MALAN: So the
rumors are indeed true.
For the first time in history,
students at Harvard and Yale
alike will be able to take a course
called CS50 this coming Fall in 2015.
We will put asie the rivalry
for nearly 100 years,
and ultimately, in Fall
2015, actual Yale students
will be able to take
CS50 for the first time.
The lectures will indeed
be streamed from here,
your successors in this audience,
to New Haven, where students
will be able to engage in
person, or as some of you
have so optimized, online
live, or on demand after.
>> But we will be standing
up a local support
structure, complete
with teaching fellows,
course assistants will be leading
sections, and office hours.
CS50 Puzzle Day will
be held in Cambridge,
and we will invite our
Yale friends to Cambridge
for CS50 Puzzle Day, as
well as the CS50 hackathon.
And then at semester's end, there will
be an epic display in both Cambridge
and in New Haven of CS50
students from Harvard,
and Yale alike on display
in those respective towns.
>> And indeed if you have any
friends who go to Yale,
we do need some TFs and CSs so
do send them to this URL here.
But we will in the meantime, be
sending one of CS50's own best teaching
fellows, Jason Hirschhorn, who's about
to graduate, having just finished
his thesis on the intersection of
computer science and education.
Jason will be working full time at
Yale, and will be on the ground there
helping us to stand this up and
bring these two universities together
via CS50.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Now, along with CS50's
production team, I
had an opportunity to hop
in the car with this guy
and take a look at what
awaits us in New Haven.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> [MUSIC - "MOVIN' RIGHT ALONG"]
>> -Movin' right along in search
of good times and good news
with good friends who can't lose.
>> -This could become a habit.
>> -Opportunity knocks once
let's reach out and grab it.
>> -Yeah!
>> -Together we'll nab it.
>> -We'll hitchhike, bus, or yellow cab it.
>> -Cab it?
>> -Movin' right along,
footloose and fancy free.
>> -Getting there is half the
fun come share it with me.
>> -Movin' right along.
>> -We'll learn to share the load.
>> -We don't need a map to
keep this show on the road.
>> -Hey, Fozzy, I want you to turn left
if you come to a fork in the road.
>> -Yes, Sir.
Turn left at the fork in the road.
Kermit?
>> -I don't believe that.
Movin' right along, we've
found a life on the highway.
>> -And your way is my way.
>> -So trust my navigation.
>> -Movie stars with flashy cars,
and life with the top down.
>> -We're storming the big town.
-Yeah.
Storm is right.
Should it be snowing?
>> -No, I don't think so.
>> -Movin' right along.
>> -Footloose and fancy free.
>> -Be ready for the big time
>> -Is it ready for me?
>> -Movin' right along.
Movin' right along.
-Maybe you better pull over.
-Yes, Sir.
Oh, look at that.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> DAVID MALAN: We'll see Yale in 2015.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> So now some thank yous.
Suffice it to say there's an
entire family, both in front of
and behind the camera, in this class
that makes everything work ultimately.
And I'd like to acknowledge a
few, and then the entire staff
by way first of Colton, whose EDM
has permeated the start of lectures
for some number of weeks now.
As well as the entire production
team, who's been making
everything look so beautiful this year.
Dan in Chile, and Andrew, and Cheng, and
Colton, and Ramon, and Barry in back,
and Kenny and everyone who's been
involved behind these cameras,
making everything possible.
To Gabriel, as well, our
head teaching fellow.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> If you didn't already
know, Gabriel actually
found CS50 by way of the
production team's videos.
Indeed growing up in
Brazil a few years back,
he discovered that all of
CS50's material was online,
and he dropped me a
kind note asking if he
might be able to translate it to
Portuguese for his classmates.
And indeed he did, ultimately, lecturing
to some 50 students, his classmates,
in high school.
Followed by 150 students the next
year, and wonderfully his dad
was in fact filming the whole thing so
you can find Gabe's lectures of CS50
in Brazil online as well.
>> And now Davon here, Davon here
has been running the course,
and has been making
everything run so smoothly,
and without him we could not
manage the team that we now have.
And then of course, Rob Bowden.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Rob's now been with the
course some five years,
having approached me sophomore
year with an interest
in getting involved in the class.
And then became assistant head TF,
and then Head TF, and then Preceptor.
And now, believe it or not,
the very distinguished role
of Member of Technical Staff,
which in the computer world
actually carries with it some weight.
And so that understatement is actually
meant to be of the highest regard
to Rob.
>> Allison, of course, who's been leading
our official sections on camera once
a week, and making sure
there's a resource available
online for students who are
unable to tune-in in person.
And then, of course, a TF, who I think
has been at every single office hours
this year, including these here,
these here, those here as well.
And indeed [? Zamila, ?] who has walked
everyone through the course's problem
sets, and without whom, we could
not expect, I dare say, so much.
>> And then lastly, Cheng
here, who is known
for much more than
these elephants, which
have been appearing
at most every lecture.
Indeed Cheng recently got together
with CS50's production team
to put together this thank
you for the entire team,
by way of a little segment
we call, Cheng On The Street.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> -This is Cheng with Cheng on the Street.
And today, I'm here at
CS50's Quiz One Grading
Party, where the staff members of
CS50 have gathered to grade quiz one.
I wouldn't really consider it
a party, but you get the idea.
I'll be asking them some questions
about their experiences this semester,
and maybe a few technical
questions, then we'll solve them.
>> -I don't think I'm ready for this.
>> -It's OK.
>> -OK.
-How many bits are in a byte?
>> -4, 8.
>> -What does PHP stand for?
>> -PHP?
Hypertext protocol.
>> -Is it a protocol, though?
-I don't know.
Is it?
>> -Eh, eh.
Buzzer.
>> -I know that P stands for PHP.
>> -So where does it stop?
>> -It never stops.
>> -It has to stop at somewhere.
-No, it doesn't.
-Acronyms simplify to a word.
-No, mm-mm. [? Recouragin? ?]
-This is a serious question.
[LAUGHTER]
What comes next in this
sequence of numbers?
2, 4, 8, 16, 32, 955.
>> -I thought you were
going to say 64, but OK.
-What's the next number in the sequence?
-CS50.
-That's not even a number.
-I have no clue.
-None of you are right.
Please, go back to grading.
What's 2 to the power of 64?
-Oh, jeez.
I should know this.
>> -I don't know.
-OK.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> -How many stress balls does it
take to fill Sanders Theater?
>> -Too many.
>> -You can never have
too many stress balls.
>> -Am I right?
What's the correct answer?
-There is no correct answer.
-I'm sure there is.
-It depends on the size
of the stress ball.
Do you know who Rob Bowden is?
>> -Yes.
He has better hair this year
than he did previous years.
So it was a little difficult
recognizing him, but I managed it.
>> -Is he the buff guy?
>> -Yeah.
-OK.
Yeah, I like him.
>> -Now that you mention that,
I have a question for you.
>> -All right.
>> -What's Rob Bowden's bench press?
>> -IT max.
>> -What is his max bench press?
-You.
>> -Thank you so much to CS50's TFs, CAs,
producers, designers, researchers,
and everyone else who's been involved
both in front of and behind the camera
here in CS50.
We surely could not do this without
you, and we cannot wait to welcome new
members to the staff.
-Everyone at this
table, can we get a hug?
>> -Thank you.
>> -Thank you very much, staff.
Thank you for becoming staff.
This concludes our interview.
Thank you for being on staff this year.
>> -Thank you so much.
>> -Thank you.
>> -No, no, thank you.
>> -Did I do a good job or what?
>> -You did wonderfully.
This was Cheng, with Cheng on the
Street, and this was CS50 2014.
>> -What did we talk about?
We just had this conversation.
This is not a toy.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID MALAN: So CS50 is
indeed now recruiting
for TFs, course assistants,
producers, designers,
and any number of other roles that
enable this to go on behind the scenes.
And now, for something a little special.
As you know, Colton has
introduced his EDM to the class,
but today he got the band together and
CS50, before we bring some students up
on stage, I give you
Colton, Gabe, and Taylor.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> COLTON: Feel my way
through the darkness.
Guided by a beating heart.
I can't tell where the journey will end.
But I know where to start.
>> Try to tell me I'm too
young to understand.
Say I'm caught up in a dream.
Life will pass me by if
I don't open up my eyes.
That's fine by me.
>> So wake me up when it's all over.
When I'm wiser and I'm older.
All this time I was finding myself
and I didn't know I was lost.
So wake me up when it's all over.
When I'm wiser and I'm older.
All this time I was finding myself
and I didn't know I was lost.
>> I tried carrying the
weight of the world.
But I only got two hands.
Hope I get the chance
to travel the world.
I don't have any plans.
Wish that I could stay
forever this young.
Not afraid to close my eyes.
Life's a game made for
everyone and love is a prize.
>> So wake me up when it's all over.
When I'm wiser and I'm older.
All this time I was finding myself
and I didn't know I was lost.
Everybody!
So wake me up when it's all over.
When I'm wiser and I'm older.
All this time I was finding myself
and I didn't know I was lost.
Didn't know I was lost.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID MALAN: Coming this year to
the CS50 Fair, live music as well.
So now, our last opportunity for
a bit of audience participation.
For this we need six
students and three staff.
Let's see here, OK, you're
practically jumping out of your chair.
Come on up.
>> OK.
How about you two together
over here, come on up.
And how about you two
and you one, come on up.
Let's grow the teams a bit.
OK.
Right there.
Come on.
Yeah.
You, come on down.
That's going to be hard.
>> OK.
OK.
Fine, come on down.
See you in a few minutes.
All right, so come on over here.
We're going to get two more
chairs and let's do Nick,
and Alison, and this Yale student
over here, and Rob Bowden, come on up.
Meanwhile, if Cheng
could join me on stage.
>> If you guys would like to form two
student teams, and one staff team.
And Cheng, if you could distribute these
chairs here, I'll get the board ready.
This is incredibly awkward.
OK.
Make your way to a chair there.
>> Come on over.
Come on down.
And I think the Yale student will
be playing for the staff team.
Excellent.
We should have enough chairs, hopefully.
If not, we'll grab another.
Where do we need it?
Over here, come on over.
All right.
>> CHENG GONG: Do we need more staff?
>> DAVID MALAN: No, no.
It's going to be two student teams
and one Harvard/Yale staff team.
All right, so we do have this
tradition of playing Jeopardy,
or really, our own version of Jeopardy
where we just ask questions and expect
answers.
But the questions we're going
to ask were not written by us,
they were written by you.
You may recall a rather
long form for Problem Set A.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> I have to admit, most of them
didn't make it into quiz one.
We got maybe 500 questions
asking, what is HTML?
What is HTTP?
What is CSS?
So they weren't exactly the
most challenging of questions,
but we went through hundreds
and hundreds of questions
to sample the following.
>> So Cheng here has kindly
offered to run the board.
We'll go ahead here and call this
Team One, Team Two, and Team Three.
And let's say that Team
Three has won the toss,
so you guys are going to glance to
your left or above you, pick a week,
and pick a dollar amount.
>> We will then ask the
question, and Cheng will
award you, or deduct from
you the requisite points.
Team Three, what would you like?
I'm hearing a lot of Week 0 here.
>> [LAUGHTER]
STUDENT 1: Can we pick any?
DAVID MALAN: Any category, any amount.
STUDENT 2: Week 0, 500.
DAVID MALAN: You're putting more
thought into choosing the question
than I wrote into selecting them
All right, so what did you say?
OK.
And then the first
hand that goes up will
be considered the one who has buzzed in.
What is the difference between
global and local variables?
I saw Team Two.
STUDENT 3: Global-- do we just
speak into the microphone?
Global is for the entire
scope of the program,
whereas local is just defined
within an isolated part.
DAVID MALAN: Let's take a look.
We're going to hold you to the
answer that your classmates gave.
If you click on the
text, SCOPE in all caps.
>> [LAUGHTER]
DAVID MALAN: I think we're going
to have to take this literally.
So we're not going to give those points.
We're going to expect exactly
what your classmates gave.
So unfortunately, we're at minus
500, but you're still in control.
But you're still in control--
now you're in control-- well, no.
You're still in control.
>> STUDENT 2: OK.
DAVID MALAN: You're still in control.
Yeah, let's go for 500 again.
OK.
Week 1, 500, Cheng.
What are the data types and their sizes?
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID MALAN: Oh, I saw
a hand over here first.
Rob Bowden.
>> ROB BOWDEN: A char is 1 byte, a short
is two bytes, an int is 4 bytes,
a long is 4 bytes, a long long is
8 bytes, a char star is 4 bytes,
an int star is 4 bytes, a
long long star is 4 bytes.
DAVID MALAN: Cheng, what
is the correct answer?
ROB BOWDEN: Oh, float and double.
DAVID MALAN: You left out the
part of the reference sheet,
but I think we should
give it to him for 500.
ROB BOWDEN: Yeah.
STUDENT: This is biased!
ROB BOWDEN: What are you talking about?
>> DAVID MALAN: It's OK the points
went-- that's right, Team One.
I am not a good judge, apparently.
All right, we're going to move on.
You guys have control.
Yale student.
We'll do Week 4 for 500 points.
I think I saw Team Three.
STUDENT 1: You free the memory.
DAVID MALAN: You free the memory?
Free it.
We'll give it to you.
All right, Team's One and Three
are tied, Team Three has control.
What category would you like?
>> STUDENT 2: Week Two, 500.
>> [DAILY DOUBLE ALARM]
>> DAVID MALAN: Amazing.
STUDENT 2: Everything?
DAVID MALAN: You get
to choose your amount.
STUDENT 1: Why not?
STUDENT 3: Yes.
STUDENT 4: All in.
STUDENT 2: 500.
DAVID MALAN: 500?
STUDENT 2: Yes.
DAVID MALAN: 500, Daily Double.
STUDENT 3: No, you can't.
DAVID MALAN: Cheng?
No!
>> [CHEERING]
>> DAVID MALAN: 500 and
control of the board.
We have--
>> ROB BOWDEN: So a double
was a yes or no question?
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID MALAN: We have time for one or
two more questions in Single Jeopardy.
OK.
Team Three.
Week 0, for 100.
What team are you on?
STUDENT 5: I'm Two.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
Team Two.
>> STUDENT 5: You use the Say block in
MIT Scratch to say, hello, world.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID MALAN: Minus 100.
All right, one more
question in Single Jeopardy.
You guys are still in control.
>> STUDENT 2: Week 3, 100.
>> DAVID MALAN: Week Three, 100.
What is the--
ROB BOWDEN: Team Three.
DAVID MALAN: Team Three?
OK.
We're going with Team Three.
STUDENT 3: The best case
scenario, or run time?
Because the best case
scenario is it's in order.
>> DAVID MALAN: Let's see
what the correct answer is.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID MALAN: All right.
Let's move on to Double Jeopardy.
>> ALEX TREBEK (RECORDING):
This is Jeopardy.
>> DAVID MALAN: Double Jeopardy,
in this Double Jeopardy
we have the categories of
Week 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9.
>> STUDENT 3: Where did our points go?
Where did our points go?
>> DAVID MALAN: We are
going to manually adjust.
There we go.
Team Two had 2,000?
OK.
All right, so now we
tossed the coin again
and we're giving control to Team Two.
Go ahead and choose your
category and amount.
>> STUDENT 2: We'll go Week 6, 1,000.
>> DAVID MALAN: Week 6, 1,000.
How does the stack grow?
Team Two.
>> STUDENT 5: You add a
new function into Scope.
>> DAVID MALAN: Add a
new function to Scope.
It grows up.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID MALAN: All right, but
you're still in control.
>> STUDENT 5: All right, someone else pick.
>> STUDENT 6: I'll pick.
DAVID MALAN: It is all relative.
Even though we tend to draw
the stack as growing up,
you'll recall that the addresses
actually grow in a different direction.
But just needed to make Rob happy there.
All right, Team Two.
>> STUDENT 4: Week 8, 1,000.
>> DAVID MALAN: Week 8 for 1,000.
True or false, is HTML
a programming language?
Is there another judge who can decide?
>> ROB BOWDEN: It was all me.
>> DAVID MALAN: All right, Rob has called.
>> ROB BOWDEN: It is not, so false.
DAVID MALAN: Rob says
false, and the answer is no.
[LAUGHTER]
CHENG GONG: Wait, wait, wait.
Wait, wait, wait.
>> DAVID MALAN: All right, Yale student?
STUDENT 2: It was a poorly written
question, it said true or false,
and then it was a question.
I object.
DAVID MALAN: Noted.
We have time for one more
Double Jeopardy question.
Team Two.
>> STUDENT 6: Week 9, 1,000.
>> DAVID MALAN: Week 9 for 1,000.
What's the difference
between ID and class?
Team Three?
Team Three.
>> STUDENT 3: You can apply ID to
only one type of thing in HTML,
but you can apply class
too many different things.
>> [APPLAUSE]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
We'll give it to you.
So if we proceed to Final Jeopardy,
I think, Team Three just wins, right?
So let's do one more question.
One more question, Double Jeopardy.
>> So at least we can pull--
that's not going to help.
It might help Team One.
All right, who's in control?
Not me, apparently.
OK.
You guys.
Yes, you just got it right.
>> STUDENT 2: Week 9, 200.
>> DAVID MALAN: Well played, Week 9, 200.
What symbol do all PHP--
>> STUDENT 2: Rob.
>> DAVID MALAN: Rob?
ROB BOWDEN: Cash tag.
[LAUGHTER]
DAVID MALAN: All right, let's proceed.
Let's proceed to Final Jeopardy.
Let's have everyone
come up with an answer,
and we'll have you write it on this
slip of paper as we play some music.
And then we'll pretend like this
was going according to plan.
>> All right, so Final Jeopardy
category is Week 12.
You all have to decide--
I didn't bring pens, no.
Pens, please.
Thank you.
All right, OK.
No more pens, please.
OK.
So Team One is at 0, Team Two
is at 0, and Team Three is at 2.
You can wager up to $2,000.
So let's go ahead and make your wager.
Wagers down.
And now Cheng is going
to reveal the question,
then play some music until we adjourn.
>> [JEOPARDY THEME PLAYING]
>> DAVID MALAN: All right, let
us begin here with Team Three.
You wagered $1,000 and answered?
>> STUDENT 1: 955.
>> DAVID MALAN: 955.
Team Two here wagered.
STUDENT 7: $2,000.
DAVID MALAN: $2,000 and your answer was?
STUDENT 6: 955.
DAVID MALAN: Team Three wagered
$2,000, and your answer was?
ROB BOWDEN: 955.
DAVID MALAN: 955, which is correct.
Which means our winner today, I think,
is still just Team Three, right?
Team Three takes the game!
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID MALAN: That then, is it for CS50.
Thank you so much for CS50's team.
Thank you so much!
Thank you so much to our
friends on Harvard time.
This was CS50.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVEN FARNHAM: And now Deep
Thoughts, by Daven Farnham.
How am I supposed to figure out MySQL,
if I can't even figure out my present?
>> [CHUCKLING]