>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
HANNAH: Hi, everyone.
Thank you guys so much for coming out
in the disgusting weather for quiz one
review session.
As you guys know, quiz
one is this Wednesday.
So we're going to go
through a bunch of topics.
DAVIN: Hey, can I say
something real quick?
HANNAH: Yeah, Davin's going
to say something real quick.
DAVIN: Sorry.
Just real quick, if you have questions
about the quiz, you can go online.
Go to 2014 quiz one, about the quiz.
It's got logistics about
where to go, when to go.
If you're simultaneously enrolled, we're
going to have a makeup quiz at 5:30.
Or if you sent me an issue,
you have some other issue.
But 5:30 is the make-up
time on Wednesday.
But if you have questions,
general questions,
online has all the logistics.
So check there first.
>> HANNAH: Awesome.
So here's the big list of topics
that we're going to go through today.
I'm going to cover all of the C
stuff, which is that first column.
So the C stuff that we
covered after quiz zero.
Starting with a linked list,
which includes pointers.
>> All right, so we saw this
in the last review session,
so I'm going to go through
this is a little bit quicker.
Just raise your hand if you want me to
slow down or address something further.
But we use linked lists because
we started in C with arrays.
And arrays are great, but the
problem is they have a fixed size.
Linked lists allow us to create
dynamically sized data structures.
>> And we have our basic operations,
insert, delete, and search.
And we can do insert in
worst case constant time
if we just put it at the very beginning.
Delete and search, worst
case big oh of n time.
So again, just to flip
through these pictures,
I know we saw these last time, but we
want to keep track of our linked list
by keeping track of the
head of our linked list.
Because we know that
each one of our nodes
is just going to point to the
next node in our linked list.
>> So that's how we keep track.
Even though these aren't
continuous pieces of memory,
we can find them by just
following the different arrows.
Here is our structure
for a linked list node.
We saw this last time.
We have our struct node.
And it has two properties.
Number one, the actual
value we want to store.
In this case, it's an integer.
It could be a string, it could
be a char, whatever you want.
And then, we have to keep track of
the next node in our linked list.
So that's going to be a
pointer to the next node.
If you were just doing
search, like I said before,
you'd have to follow your arrows down.
Insertion, you would keep track
of where the rest of your list is.
And you want to redirect the head
to point to our new element, which
in this case is one,
and then one will point
to the remainder of the linked list.
So again, I know this is a little
bit of a repeat from quiz zero.
So we have to be very careful
about the order in which we
do these pointings so we don't
lose track of the back of the list.
OK, any questions with
just singly linked lists?
Awesome, OK, cool.
>> So now, we're going to go onto something
just slightly more complicated,
doubly linked lists.
So in addition to keeping
track of the next node,
we also want to keep track
of the previous node.
And this allows us to, if we're
at some point in our linked list,
not only go forwards, but
also iterate backwards.
Because as we saw in
a singly linked list,
if we were at some node, and
all of a sudden, we decided,
actually, I want to go to
the node right before me,
you'd have to go all
the way back to the head
and iterate through until you found
the node you were looking for.
>> So this makes things
slightly easier as we're
trying to iterate
through our linked list.
But it requires us to keep track of one
more pointer, so one more node star.
All right, so here comes the fun part.
We're going to practice implementing
remove for doubly linked lists.
So this is something that's
totally fair game for the quiz.
It showed up on past quizzes.
So definitely be prepared
to code a little bit in C.
Don't forget that with all
this fun PHP and JavaScript,
we still have to remember
to do C. So brush up on that
if you're feeling rusty.
>> All right, let's see if we can do this.
OK, cool.
So we're going to try
to edit right in here,
and hopefully this goes as planned.
All right, does anyone want to give me
a suggestion as to how I should start?
The only assumption I'm
making is that I already
have a structure defined, the
one I showed on the last page,
on the last slide.
And I'm storing the head of my linked
list in some pointer called list.
Does anyone want to get me started?
>> AUDIENCE: Can you create a new
node to call through the list?
>> HANNAH: Awesome, so
we're going to create
a new node to crawl through the list.
I like that.
I'll just call it pointer if that's OK.
And where should it originally start?
>> AUDIENCE: Probably at
the head of the list.
HANNAH: Beautiful.
We want to start at the head, which
I said is going to be stored in list.
Awesome.
So far, so good.
And now, our goal is to
iterate through the list
until we find the node with
value n that we want to delete.
OK?
>> So now is the part where
we want to iterate through.
Can anyone suggest a
way to iterate through?
>> AUDIENCE: A loop.
>> HANNAH: A loop.
I love it.
Specifically, we can try a while loop.
OK, and we know that we've reached
the end of our list when what?
AUDIENCE: When pointer is null.
HANNAH: When pointer is null.
Beautiful, I love it.
OK, cool.
So sorry if my bounding brace is
kind of falling off the screen.
We brought it back.
OK, cool.
What's next?
>> So we know we want to delete
the node that has value n.
So let's find the case where
we actually find our node.
So how would I check that?
I'd just say if pointer, and then if I
want to get the value out of pointer,
I just do arrow n,
equals n, the parameter
that we gave to this function, the
node that we want to actually delete.
Any questions up until here?
All right.
OK, so now let's draw a quick picture
on the board in order to visualize this.
>> So let's say there's our lovely node.
And it has a value, I'll just say four.
And it points to the next
node in our linked list.
And there's nothing before it.
So we have our previous
pointing to nothing.
In this case, we point backwards.
OK, just setting up my
linked list over here.
And we have a list that points
to this structure to begin with.
I'll draw one more for
the sake of completeness.
OK.
I'll point this forward.
And I'll point that one back.
Oops, sorry.
Yeah, got this backwards.
Do it again.
OK, there we go.
All right, got it.
OK, here's our picture.
>> OK, so we want to consider two cases.
The first case is if the
node we want to delete
is at the very start of our list.
And then, the second case that we want
to consider is if it's anywhere else.
I understand that this a totally
messy drawing with all my erasing,
but hopefully we'll try to
make this clear with some code.
>> OK, so let's cover the case
where we found our node,
and it's at the very
start of our linked list.
Anyone give me a
suggestion here as to what
I should do to actually remove our node?
It's a little tricky.
OK?
>> AUDIENCE: You have to take the
node that would be before it
and make it point to the
one that would be after it,
and take the node that
would be after it and make
it point to the node before it.
HANNAH: Exactly.
OK, so this is the case
where-- we have two cases.
We have the case where the
node that we're looking for
is the front of the list.
OK, and then the case that you
described is otherwise, right?
It's somewhere else in the list.
So you said, we need to
look at the node previous,
and make the previous node
point to the next node.
So let's say we're
trying to take out five
in my very messy drawing over here.
We want to make sure that
four now points to six.
Four's next points to six.
And six's previous points to four.
That's our goal here, right?
This is what I think you
just said over there.
>> OK, so let's get that first piece.
Let's do the have the
previous pointer previous.
So four's next should point to what?
Exactly, in this case, six.
So we should say pointer, next.
OK?
All right.
So let's get rid of this ugly picture
and try to draw a slightly nicer one.
We have our list head here.
And that points to the first node in
our linked list, which we said is four.
Here's our second node, five.
And our third node, six.
Just trying to draw the exact same
picture, just a little more cleanly.
OK, so four's next
originally points to five.
Five's next points to six.
Six's previous points to five.
And five's previous points to four.
So much nicer!
OK, cool.
>> So now, what we did just
here, this line of code,
which says pointer previous
next, so what does that mean?
That means if we're looking at
five, go to the previous node,
and it's next should now
point to five's next.
So essentially, what that's doing
is that's erasing this arrow
and making it skip right over five.
Is that clear?
I know that can be a little bit sketchy.
I see some head nods.
That's good.
OK, cool.
Now, what's the next step?
>> I've reset the next.
Now, which other arrow
do I need to change?
This one right here.
Six's previous.
We don't want six's previous
to point to five anymore.
We want it to point to four.
Does that picture make sense?
So now we can actually take five out.
So let's get that piece.
What should I do before I
reset six's previous to four?
Any ideas there?
>> AUDIENCE: Free the node between
them by setting it to null?
HANNAH: Cool.
Definitely, our end goal is
going to be to free the node.
So we can do that right here.
Free pointer.
Absolutely.
But even before that,
let's just-- our goal right
here is to set pointer next
previous equal to pointer previous.
I know this is getting covered up.
OK, let's take-- cool.
Can everyone see this bottom line?
Or is it super tiny?
>> So before we execute
this line here, we want
to make sure that
pointer next is not null.
Because if pointer next is
null, what kind of error
will I get when I try to
reference a null pointer?
AUDIENCE: Seg fault.
HANNAH: A seg fault, beautiful.
OK, so if that's not
null, then we can reset.
And we have six point again to four.
Questions up until this point?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: In your first
if statement, did you
mean to have the arrow
next, or [INAUDIBLE]?
HANNAH: I meant pointer arrow n.
So basically, what I'm trying to do
is say, the current node that I'm
iterating over, the current node that
I'm looking at, I'm storing in pointer.
And I want to know pointer's
value, which in this case is n.
And I want to see, is
the node I'm looking
for the node I'm aiming to delete?
So that's why we have here pointer n.
>> AUDIENCE: So the arrow going
to n, you set the value
and store it in a node called n?
>> HANNAH: So it's like if I am
going through this linked list
and pointing to five.
If I want to get that value, if
I want to get that number, 5,
I have to do pointer arrow n.
Cool?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Is n the name of the variable?
HANNAH: Yes.
So if we flip back one
slide, n is the name
of the value inside of the
node in our linked list.
And I know it can get a little
bit confusing because we also
are calling the thing
that we want to delete n.
So that's where that
one line comes from.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: What do you have
[INAUDIBLE] how they work?
A pointer [INAUDIBLE]?
>> HANNAH: Sure.
Are you talking about-- which line?
AUDIENCE: The last line [INAUDIBLE].
>> HANNAH: Sure, OK.
So let's look at the picture in
order to try to explain this.
I'm sorry, for the
camera, the question was
can we explain pointer
arrow next pointer previous.
OK, so let's say we're at five
and our goal is to delete five.
So pointer next, which of these
three nodes does that give us?
That brings us to the sixth node, right?
>> OK, so now we're asking
for the six's previous.
OK?
And we're resetting this
to be equal to four,
which happened to be five's previous.
I know, it's super
hard to keep track of.
I really recommend you draw pictures
if you get a question like this.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Is the reason that
we don't have a [INAUDIBLE]?
>> HANNAH: Exactly.
So the question was, why do
we not need to check here?
Why don't we need to check that
pointer previous is not equal to null?
And it's because we've
already separated out
the case if the pointer's
at the very beginning.
Very good question.
Anything else on this?
OK, cool.
So let's finish it up.
We're almost there.
>> So what if it is at the head?
What if instead of
trying to delete five,
we actually wanted to delete four?
What would I have to do?
Well, I want to reset my head to what?
Shout it out?
AUDIENCE: The one after it.
HANNAH: Beautiful.
OK, so we want list to be pointing
to whatever our pointer next node is.
Good.
And just for completeness's
sake, we would
want to check that as long as our list
is not null, as long as our list is not
empty, then we want to set
our previous equal to null.
Question so far?
One step away from--?
>> AUDIENCE: Would it be if
list is not equal to null?
>> HANNAH: Yes, you're totally right.
I'm so sorry.
Is list is not equal to null.
Awesome.
Trying to bring this all on the screen.
It's kind of falling off.
Sorry, guys.
And last but not least, all
we have to do is return.
OK.
That was a lot crammed
in really quickly.
Take a second to look this over.
Tell me if you have any questions.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: If list is at the
head, then-- wait, nevermind.
>> HANNAH: OK, good.
So this is if list is at the head,
we remove it to whatever we inserted.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Can you explain
the first if statement again?
If the pointer to n is equal to n?
HANNAH: Sure.
So our goal of this whole function is
to delete the node that has value n.
So if we find, as we're
iterating through our list,
the node with value n, that's
the one we want to delete.
So all of the deleting happens
inside of that big if statement.
Does that makes sense?
Cool.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Maybe you just can't see
it, but don't you also need a line
for scrolling through the list?
HANNAH: Awesome.
Let's bring this up a little bit, and
we'll throw that right in the bottom.
Maybe the board would've
been a slightly better idea.
So how would I move pointer forward?
>> AUDIENCE: Pointer
equals pointer plus one.
>> HANNAH: Beautiful.
So that allows us to
continue iterating through.
OK.
AUDIENCE: Wouldn't there be an else?
HANNAH: One more time?
AUDIENCE: Wouldn't there be
an else after the big old if
statement [INAUDIBLE]?
HANNAH: Which part?
I'm sorry.
>> AUDIENCE: The traversal,
shouldn't there be an else?
HANNAH: You absolutely
could have an else.
Because I have a return right
there, you don't need an else.
But yeah, good question.
OK, yes?
AUDIENCE: Can we think of pointer
that is moving through the list
as taking on the value
of each node in the list?
Or should we think of it as
sort of external to the list?
>> HANNAH: Either one is fine, I think.
The way I imagine it is
I say, OK, I am pointer.
And this is me.
This is my hand.
I'm going to point to the different
things that I want to iterate through.
First, I'm going to point
to the head of the list.
And that tells me I'm
going to point to four.
And so me, being external to the list,
I can point to each of these elements.
So I think of myself as pointer.
AUDIENCE: So when you delete
one of those elements,
you delete yourself, so to speak.
HANNAH: Exactly.
So you delete the thing
you're pointing to.
So in the example that
we saw where we're
trying to delete five,
when I'm pointing to five,
I want to delete the
thing I'm pointing to.
Exactly right.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Have we taken care of the
case where n is not in the list?
HANNAH: If n is not in the list?
All that's going to happen is you're
going to iterate through and iterate
through, and then, you're going
to get to pointer being null,
and then you're going to be done.
>> AUDIENCE: So do we have
to return anything?
HANNAH: We could.
The way that if defined this
function, I just say that it returns
void regardless.
But you could have something
like returning an integer,
and have it return
negative 1 if it fails.
Something like that.
Questions with-- yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
HANNAH: Sorry?
HANNAH: Sure.
So that's the actual-- once we've
done all this work of moving
all these arrows around, our whole
goal was to get rid of the node
that we're looking for.
So in this case, freeing
pointer, if I'm pointing to five,
it's like erasing this middle node.
That's the free pointer part.
That make sense?
>> AUDIENCE: So even thought
you didn't [INAUDIBLE]?
>> HANNAH: So we assumed at the beginning
we had some list that was already--
they had put this together.
So in order to construct this
list, they must've [INAUDIBLE].
Cool.
Anything else with this?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: What if the list
doesn't equal the null line?
[INAUDIBLE]?
HANNAH: Right here?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
HANNAH: OK, all I'm doing
is I'm just making sure
that before I try to dereference list,
before I try to access the previous,
I want to make sure that it's not
null so I don't get a seg fault.
Cool.
>> OK, I know this was quite
a lot to get through.
So this slide will be
made available to you.
So you can go through it in more detail.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Why does the list [INAUDIBLE]?
HANNAH: Sure.
So list really points to
this element right here,
the first element in the list.
So it can't have a previous.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Does the pointer point
to the same address in memory?
Does it point to the same
address in memory as the node
that it's pointing to?
>> HANNAH: Yes, it points
to this node in memory.
>> AUDIENCE: Right, so
when you [INAUDIBLE]?
>> HANNAH: In a sense, yes.
OK.
All right, let's move along with this.
And if you have more questions,
stick around at the end,
and we can go through it again.
OK, cool.
Now, we get to move on
to hash tables, tries,
and trees, which you got super
familiar with in p-set five, speller.
>> So hash table is just an
array with singly linked lists
or doubly linked lists coming off of it.
So we have some sort
of associative array.
And how we know which of these
arrays buckets to get into,
we use a hash function.
So in this case, can anyone
guess what the hash function
would be just based on some
of the input and output?
>> AUDIENCE: Letter number of the alphabet.
HANNAH: Exactly.
It just puts them in alphabetical order.
Everything that starts with an
A is put into the first bucket.
Everything with a B is put into the
second bucket, so on, and so forth.
Awesome, OK.
And a hash function is any
function that takes in a word
and will tell you what
bucket it belongs in.
So which entry in our
array it belongs in.
>> So every time I give my
hash function a word,
it should tell me the same
place every single time.
So if we use the hash function
from the previous slide
where we're sorting by the
first letter of the alphabet,
every time I give my
hash function "apple,"
it should always give me back 0.
So if I have an apple
to put in my hash table,
if I give "apple" to my hash function,
it should say, go put it in bucket 0.
If I'm looking for an
apple in my hash table
and I say, where might apple
live, you ask your hash function.
And it says, go to bucket 0.
All right?
Questions with hash functions?
Awesome.
>> Here is a slightly more
detailed explanation
of what a hash function might look like.
All right.
Now, the problem with hash
functions is in an ideal world,
we would only have one
thing in each bucket.
But in reality, there's
not only one word
that starts with A. There's not
only one word that starts with B. So
in this case, if we
suddenly get "berry,"
and we want to put it
into our hash table,
and we see, oh, no, banana is
already there, what are we gonna do?
>> Well, we have two options.
The first option is
linear probing, which
just means go find
the next empty bucket.
Go find the next empty array entry.
And just put "berry" there.
So I know it's supposed to
go with banana in bucket one.
But just put it in bucket three,
because bucket three is empty.
Another option is probably
what you implement
in your p-set, where you
had separate chaining.
So each of your buckets,
each of your array elements,
not only holds one words, but actually
holds a pointer to a list of words.
So that if you had
banana in your hash table
and you suddenly wanted
to add berry, no problem.
Just add berry on to the end, or to
the beginning, of your linked list.
OK, awesome.
Questions with hash
tables before we go on?
>> All right.
Trees and tries.
OK, so this was another option
for implementing dictionary.
You could have made a try.
So it's a special kind of tree that
behaves like a multi-level hash table.
So you'll see the picture
where you have an array that
points to a bunch of arrays
that point to a bunch of arrays
that point to a bunch of arrays.
And we'll see exactly what that
would look like on a future slide.
And more generally, a tree
is just any data structure
in which the data is
organized in some hierarchy.
So where we saw we have
some sort of understanding
of a top level, a next level,
a next level, a next level.
So this is probably most clear
with some specific examples.
So here's our tree.
You can see that it
has particular levels
that we start with that root node, one.
And we can go down through our tree.
>> A binary tree is a
particular type of tree.
And the only specification
for a binary tree
is that each node has
at most two leaves.
So you're not going to see any
of these nodes have three or four
or some other number of leaves.
And then even more specific
is a binary search tree
where every node to the left of the
node is going to have a value smaller.
And every value to the
right is going to be bigger.
So if you see 44 is at our root,
to the left, 11, 22, and 33
are all less than our root.
And on the right are all
numbers bigger-- 66, 55, and 77.
And this property holds true
at every level of the tree.
>> So when we go down to
22, 11, and 33, still 11
is smaller than 22 and
33 is bigger than 22.
And this makes it easier to search
because if we're looking for a number,
we know exactly which
branch to follow down.
So this should remind you a
little bit of binary search.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: So when you're
describing binary,
you said it has at most two leaves?
HANNAH: Mm-hm.
AUDIENCE: Could it have less?
HANNAH: Yeah.
So let's say, for example, you
didn't have an even number of things
and you couldn't fill up all your
leaves, it's fine if one has one.
OK?
Awesome.
Any other questions on trees?
OK.
>> Back to our tries as I was talking
about a little bit earlier,
how we have these multi-level arrays.
So in this case, we start at the top.
And we can follow any given word down.
So let's say we wanted
to look for Turing.
We start at T, follow it down
to an array that contains U,
and follow it down until we
reach this little delta which
tells us, yes, you found a word.
Clear on tries?
Anything to go over there?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Does the symbol of delta
have to occupy space within the try?
HANNAH: Yeah, so it doesn't
necessarily even need to be a delta.
But we need some way to
tell our computer-- sorry,
so that we know that TUR is not a word.
Because let's say we didn't have
this concept of a delta, this concept
of congratulations, you found a word,
it would go through and iterate T-U-R,
and then say, awesome, I found it!
It must be a word.
But it's really not.
We want whole Turing to be a word.
So we must have something at the
end that says, congratulations,
you've found a legitimate word.
AUDIENCE: So if you had like
26 letters in the alphabet,
would you actually have
27 keys in your try?
>> HANNAH: Awesome, yeah.
So actually, I think that
will be on the next slide.
Ta-da!
Where if you have a
node in your try, you're
going to have 27 children instead of 26.
Any questions with that?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Why do tries take up so
much space [INAUDIBLE] as you go?
Why is it considered to be [INAUDIBLE]?
HANNAH: Sure.
Let's go back.
The question is, why
are tries so much bigger
than something like a hash table.
So for each of these levels,
even if they're not drawn here,
you have to have all 26 characters.
And the reason that you can't
say, oh, but like for Turing, I
don't need to have any of those
same things on the level of U. Well,
if suddenly you wanted to add
something that was like T-H,
you'd need to have the
capability of adding that word.
So for every single letter,
you're going to have
to have a bunch of
arrays coming off of it.
So you can see how it'd get
really big, really fast.
Any other questions?
All right.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: When are tries
faster than hash tables?
>> HANNAH: When are tries
So if you had a really
bad hash function.
So let's say I was like,
here's your hash function.
No matter what word
you give me, I'm always
going to put it in array entry 0.
And so we end up with just putting
everything in one big long linked list.
And so a lookup time would take at worst
n if it's at the very end of our list.
With the try, we just have to iterate
through the letters in the word.
So even if we added a bunch
more words to our try,
it wouldn't take us any longer
to find a particular word.
>> All we have to do is, for
example, in this case,
let's say we're looking for zoom,
we would just have to iterate over
Z-O-O-M, four letters.
So that's just the
length of the word zoom.
It doesn't matter how many
more words we put in this try.
We can always get it
in those four steps.
Awesome.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: So [INAUDIBLE]
is an array, right?
>> HANNAH: Mm-hm.
AUDIENCE: If you're
looking for [INAUDIBLE],
would you have to go through
your array to find [INAUDIBLE]?
HANNAH: Sure.
AUDIENCE: Doesn't that take more time?
HANNAH: If I'm going to
say that my array is always
going to be A, B, C, D,
E, F, G, blah blah blah,
so if I always know it's
in the same exact order,
if I always know it's
in alphabetical order,
I can just say O is number
so and so in the alphabet.
Just jump to that place.
Because remember, with
arrays, we can access
any element of that array in constant
time if we know where we're looking.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: On the previous
slide [INAUDIBLE] 27,
but 26 for the first one.
>> HANNAH: Sorry?
>> AUDIENCE: Isn't the first
one 0, so wouldn't it be 26?
>> HANNAH: Sure, so when we say 27, that's
going to give us indices 0 through 26.
But if you actually count
those out, it's going to be 27.
Good question.
Anything else?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: So are tries
slower than hash tables?
>> HANNAH: Tries are going to be, in
theory, faster than hash tables
but take up more memory.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
>> HANNAH: I'm sorry, I didn't hear you.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
0 to 25 gives you 26.
>> HANNAH: 0 to 25 would
give you 26, right.
>> AUDIENCE: And then [INAUDIBLE].
HANNAH: Right.
So the number we're specifying is
the number of things in our array.
So if we have 27, it's
going to give us 0
through 26, which will give
us room for, in this case,
I'm not including an apostrophe.
So we're getting 0 through 25 are
the first 26 letters of the alphabet,
or all 26 letters of the alphabet.
And then that last
thing, at entry 26, is
going to be the check
mark, or the delta.
Anything else?
Awesome.
Lost my space.
OK, cool.
>> So we already touched upon this.
But the big trade off
between tries and hash tables
is that tries provide, in
theory, constant look up
times but use a whole lot of memory.
All right, now we have slightly
less complicated structures,
and we'll be done with C,
and we'll move right along.
>> So stacks, we saw this
in lecture where you
have something like a
stack of trays where
the last thing you put
on the stack is going
to be the first thing you take off.
So that's what really defines a stack
is that the last thing you put on
is going to be the first
thing you take off.
And the terminology that we use
if we're going to put something,
if we're going to add something to
our stack, we call that pushing.
And if we take something
off, we call it popping.
And if we're going to
implement a stack, we
need to be sure to keep track of
both the size and the capacity.
So the total number of elements we can
hold and the current number of elements
that we are holding.
>> And very similarly, we have queues.
And the only difference
is instead of with stacks,
we said the last thing we put on
is the first thing we take off.
So with queues, the
first thing we put in
is going to be the
first thing we take out.
So this is like if you're
actually lining up at a store
and you're being helped,
then the first person in line
should be the first person to be helped.
So that would be a queue.
>> So we need to keep track of the
size, capacity, and head since we're
going to take everyone off the front
of the list instead of the back.
Questions on that?
Any C questions that are bothering you?
Data structures, any of that fun stuff?
All right, cool.
So I'll hand it over to Alison to
jump into some more programming.
>> ALISON: Oh, we'll see.
We'll see how well I do here.
OK, I'm going to try and fly
through this stuff, guys.
Hannah went very in
depth on all her things.
I'm going to try to give
you a quick blast overview
so that we can get to Davin with all
the fun JavaScript and security things
that maybe you actually
want to hear more about.
>> OK, as Hannah said, if
you have any questions,
I'm going too fast, please, let me know.
I will answer questions as necessary.
So to start, we're going to start with
probably one of the very first things
you learned with web
programming, permissions.
So chmod, you guys should've been
masters at this with all the web
programming that you've
been doing lately.
It's basically just a command
that changes the permissions
or the access permissions
of our file system objects.
Of course, to actually
see these, if you're
having any trouble with these
during your problem sets,
you may have used ls -l, which is long,
to get the view kind of like this,
where you actually see all
the permissions for a file.
>> And really, we're just going to go
through pretty quickly just pretty
much what each of these mean.
So we have d right here, which
just stands for the directory.
Obviously right here, we see rwx, which
is readable, writeable, and executable.
These could also be represented as bits,
which we'll get into on the next page.
So each triad that we saw
here, so it's three triads.
We have rwx, r nothing x and r
nothing x for this first file.
It's this general structure.
>> So we have some directory.
We have some user group
with these permissions.
Some group that has these permissions,
and a world that has a permission.
You can think of these as a triad.
You can think of these as three bits.
So they can hold values
anywhere from 0 up
to 7, which is why sometimes
we had you do chmod
600 instead of chmod rw whatever.
We'll get into an example there.
But basically, you can think
of these as either just rwx,
or you can think of them as some
number where this first one here
represents a number between
0 and 7, this second one
0 and 7, and the third one
represents a number between 0 and 7, OK?
>> r has a value of 4. w
has a value of 2, and x
has a value of 1, which is why this
permission here would be chmod 700.
Because in this case here, it says we
have the first bit there is flipped on.
So we have 4 for read.
The second bit is flipped on for
w, which is 2, so now we have 6.
And the third bit is flipped on
for x, which is 1, so we get seven.
And of course, our group
and our world are each 0.
So this is also the
equivalent of chmod 700.
And I would definitely try to
understand the mapping between those.
I'm not sure if it has
come up on a quiz before,
but it would be a
question that I might ask.
>> Just a little bit going even
further into chmod here, here
is the very general
structure of a chmod call.
So of course, we have chmod here.
References, what this refers to is
who are we giving these permissions to
or who are we taking these
permissions away from.
So we have a here in the permissions,
like we've given you chmod a plus x,
as we'll see soon.
a just means give these specific
permissions to everyone.
Give them to all.
So you could very well have u plus x
or g plus x or o plus x or multiple
thereof.
So that first part is always
going to be references.
Who are we giving these permissions to,
or who are we taking them away from?
>> The second one is the operator.
So you guys have mostly dealt with plus.
This gives permissions to
whoever you're giving them,
whereas minus, logically, removes them.
So nothing too terrible there.
And then modes is what we talked about
with reading, writing, or executing.
So a plus x means give executable
permissions to everyone.
And then, of course, on which
specific file or directory.
OK?
Everyone good with chmod?
Not too bad?
>> OK, so HTML, any of you are
old enough to-- MySpace age?
I sent this to my section,
and literally half the people
looked at me like I was crazy.
And I was like, guys,
we're not that old.
Come on.
So HyperText Markup Language,
it's honestly just a way for you
to display certain things on the web.
So it's a markup language.
It's not a scripting language.
There's no logic in it.
It is simply to change the
way something is displayed.
OK, so that's an important
distinction to make.
It's considered a markup language,
not a scripting language.
>> So here we have our HTML tags.
On this slide are probably most of the
ones that you should be familiar with
and be really comfortable with.
So obviously, we have
our HTML tag, which
designates that everything in
between these two will be HTML.
We have some link, which
obviously will give you
a link to an external web page.
Some title, within our head here.
And we have our body with
h1, which is a header,
so it'll make it nice
and bold and bigger.
And then, we have some
p, which is a paragraph.
You should probably know
and be familiar with things
like how you insert an image, are
there any other header classes?
I would definitely be
comfortable with div.
So these have the majority of tags
that you should be familiar with.
But of course, as with everything in
CS 50, the list is not exhaustive.
So make sure you brush up on that.
>> CSS, so CSS, if any of you watch
my seminar from two weeks ago,
is really just a way
to style your web page?
OK, so we have some markup language.
HTML, that takes care of just the text
and where it might be on the page.
But CSS is really what makes it pretty.
You could have these in your HTML
files, but as we will talk about later,
I'm pretty sure it might
be the next slide, it
is common practice, and actually
practice that we really encourage,
for you to keep them separated when we
talk about MVC and that whole paradigm.
That's really what this feeds into.
>> So CSS is just a way to
make things look pretty.
The things here, like
body and #title and .info,
these are called selectors and what
they do is they select specific things
within your HTML file
and apply whatever style,
whatever sort of things that you want,
to that specific element of your web
page.
So here, we have a
background color and a color
and a font family that's being
applied to whatever is in the body.
So if we looked back here, it
wouldn't apply to the title.
It would only apply to what is
in these body selectors, OK?
>> With title here, this is
going to be the same thing,
the color of the text
being blue is only going
to affect what is within
the title selectors.
As well as info here,
the text will be pink,
whatever's info, which is right here.
So the only thing that
would be pink on this page
is date, Monday, November 17, 2014.
OK, so CSS is just a way to
have more control over-- yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Why do you have
to use the hash with title?
>> HANNAH: Next slide, promise!
We'll get there.
So this is why we have to use hash.
So selectors take on three main
forms that we talk to you guys about.
I fyou want to learn more,
there's plenty out there.
There's great CSS documentation.
There's a tag name, which has to do
with just your normal tags in HTML.
So h1, p, div, h2,
those sorts of things.
And we can just name those as is.
So as we see here with
body, it's a normal tag.
So we can just put body when
we're talking in our CSS file.
>> With title, the whole reason we
have this hash is we have what's
considered an ID.
So an ID should always be
unique within your HTML page
so that when you are
referring to it, you
know that you're only referring
to one specific thing.
So in this case here, with our
h1 here, CS 50 review session,
we have an id of title.
So in order to just refer to that
piece of our HTML, we do a hash title.
Just by convention, IDs are designated
with a hash in front of them.
In the same way, we see
info here is a class.
And so class with CSS is
designated as a dot class
or dot whatever that class is.
So in this case here, it's info.
>> So I take it back.
Both of these would be
pink for our CSS here
because they both have a class of info.
And in our CSS file, we have designated
that anything with a class of info
shall be pink.
Does that make sense?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: If you were to make
everything in the body white,
and then you try to make
something inside it blue,
would that cause problems?
>> HANNAH: So CSS is
cascading style sheets.
So whatever is toward the
bottom will take precedence.
So if you do something with body,
and you make everything white,
and then later on you change the title
or you change the text within body,
it overwrites that.
So anything toward the
bottom will take precedence.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: And IDs are unique,
but classes can be more?
HANNAH: Right.
So IDs should be unique, and classes can
refer to as many things as you'd like.
Any other questions?
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
I'm wondering whether
that makes a difference.
HANNAH: I'm sorry,
what was the question?
AUDIENCE: There's small
"f" and capital "F."
HANNAH: So the difference
between small "f" and capital "F"
shouldn't make a difference.
So "f" will be 15 either way.
Cool, anything else?
Everyone good, CSS?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Sorry.
Can you have a class and an ID?
>> HANNAH: Yes, you can.
Things can have both a class and an ID.
And I highly recommend
testing these on your own.
CSS you will learn best just by making
something, very simple web page,
drawing up some CSS, and just
seeing how they interact.
And you'll gain a very good,
intuitive sense for how it works.
>> OK, everyone good with CSS?
You're all going to make
beautiful websites with CSS now.
OK, best practices, just
things to keep in mind, things
that-- this is why we dock
you for designer and whatnot.
So close all your HTML tags.
So if you have an open body,
there should be a close body.
If you have an open paragraph,
there should be a close paragraph.
Check to see your page validates.
You guys should be very familiar
with this from p-set seven
with CS 50 finance
with the W3 validator.
And as I said before,
one of our big paradigms
is separating your style with CSS
from your markup, which is HTML.
And then, of course, we have
this great XKCD down here.
Yay, comic relief!
>> OK, TCP/IP.
Between these and HTTP,
basically they're both protocols.
So you could just think
of them as a set of rules
that govern how things
move across the internet.
So transmission control
protocol, or internet protocol,
is just a way to make sure
that data gets where it's going
and that we know if
we're ever missing data.
So if you guys think back to lecture
a couple weeks ago with David
where we had four envelopes, they
were all numbered like one of four,
two of four, three of four, four of
four, this is just a set of rules.
We said, OK, whenever we're
sending more than one packet,
we are going to number
it with what number it is
and how many total that
the user should get.
>> And this is just telling whoever
is receiving the data whether they
have gotten everything or if
something got lost along the way.
And they need to ask for it again.
This is really just a set of rules.
That's how you can think of it, OK?
And also, it specifies the port, which
you guys can-- I know during lecture,
they had a whole list of ports.
But we don't have them here right now.
>> So hypertext transfer protocol
is, again, it's another protocol.
So it's another set of rules
that govern, in this case,
how hypertext is transferred.
So it just allows browsers
to speak to web servers.
And as we said here, it's
like human handshaking.
It's just a way to govern
how the web server is
going to interact with your browser.
And we have just a couple of examples.
We have some requests here
where GET is the method.
We have HTTP 1.1, which is
protocol version for us.
And then, the host, which is what
we're actually trying to access.
And then, as you see here, we
get some response with this 200
OK as our HTTP response code.
We have a big list I'm going
to pull up in one second
that you guys should be familiar with.
And we have this content type text/HTML,
which just says what type of data
are we receiving from the server, OK?
This host and this content type
are part of the HTTP headers.
You can have as few or as little as
necessary for the context of what
you're dealing with.
Sometimes you'll have a lot of
information coming from your server.
Maybe they're requesting a lot
of information from the user.
It varies depending on the context.
If you look at CS 50 Study,
there's a lot more on that.
But we have a lot to get
through, so I'm going
to go right ahead if
that's OK with you guys?
Cool.
Hold on.
I definitely have that
whole list of-- huh!
I don't know why this is
all the way over here.
I thought I literally moved
it while I was sitting--
>> DAVIN: Do you want to teach it?
Or do you want me to teach it?
>> AUDIENCE: I thought we could
just show them to start with.
I mean, you can go into
them further, but I
thought it made more sense since I
was just talking about HTTP statuses.
So here's the whole list.
I guess what's going to happen is
Davin is going to go into them later.
But there's a whole list, a
preview of the taste to come.
OK, we're going to blow-- this is going
to be a PHP crash course like no other.
>> So PHP, hypertext preprocessor,
it's a recursive backronym,
which means it was named something else.
And then they were like, this
doesn't really make sense.
So they just named it--
and it was an acronym,
so they just made it PHP
hypertext preprocessor, which
just makes no sense.
Fun story.
It's a programming language.
So as much as I emphasize that
HTML is not a programming language,
it's a markup language, PHP
is a programming language.
How you know this is
because there is logic.
There are conditionals.
We have variables, whereas we
have none of those things in HTML.
>> All right, then we have this little
bit here that's like a taste of PHP.
So basics, variable names
start with a dollar sign.
Lots of people like it.
Reminds of us money.
It's all great.
We all want PHP.
So we don't specify a
variable's type anymore.
It is determined at run time.
The interpreter will be like,
oh, we'll just run through,
and according to the context,
we'll see what types of types
these variables need to have.
There's no main function.
Things will just run.
You guys with your import in your
last p-set, you'll notice this.
There wasn't really a main function.
You just wrote what
you wanted to happen.
And it just kind of happened.
So that's PHP for you.
>> Arrays are very similar.
We still have this bracket.
Here, we have some variable
called arr, and it's equal
to-- we have our normal
bracket notation.
And we have some key value.
And the big difference
between C and PHP arrays
is that we can have this associate--
we can associate values to keys.
So instead of just having
an array that is indexed
by the number or the position
of that element in the array,
we can actually associate it with a key.
Where we can say, OK, I want whatever
value is associated with fruit.
And maybe we have fruit went to banana.
So it'd return banana to us.
>> But basically, the most
powerful thing about this
is that if you guys remember the
demo from lecture where we basically
rewrote speller in PHP, and it
was-- lookup was really just like,
does this key exist?
That's really kind of the power of it.
You don't need to iterate
through your array.
You don't need to know
what space it's in.
It could be at the end or the beginning.
As long as you know the key
that's associated with the value,
PHP can just spit that value
right back out at you, OK?
>> And then, we also just
have just because we
can have key value pairs
doesn't mean you have to.
You can also just create
a normal array like here,
at the bottom, where it's
just one, two, three, four.
Those are our values.
And in fact, their keys are the indices.
So the key for one would be zero.
The key for two would be one.
So on and so forth, unless
you explicitly assign a key,
you could assume that the
value is just their index.
Does that make sense to everyone?
No questions?
Awesome.
>> OK, foreach is a way to
iterate through your arrays.
So we have something here,
just the general structure.
So foreach, the name of
our array, as whatever
you want to call each
element in your array,
and we can do something with
that element or with that value.
So we have an example here.
We have an associative
array with these two entries
with bar being associated with foo
and qux being associated with baz.
So keys are foo and baz.
Values are bar and qux.
So foreach, we have our array
here, as the key value pair.
This allows us to access
both the key and value.
Maybe you just want the
value, in which case
you could just do like arr
as $value, and then you
are just accessing the value
as you iterate through.
But maybe, for some
reason, you want the key,
which is why I chose
this example instead.
So you can actually manipulate
key and value in this case.
OK?
Question?
>> AUDIENCE: If you wanted to
just manipulate the key, would
you have to do foreach--
>> ALISON: Right.
So if you wanted to
manipulate just the key,
you would still need this
syntax because if you just
have arr as something,
as one thing, it's
going to assume you want
the value, not the key.
So if you ever just have just like
arr as, maybe this is like $element,
it's going to assume that you're asking
for just the value at each point.
If you explicitly want to
do something with the key,
even if you're not going to
do anything with the value,
you need this structure
that we have here
where you're explicitly asking
for both the key and the value.
Great question.
Anything else?
Cool.
>> All right, PHP and HTML.
Oh, we're back to p-set seven again.
So this should look a little familiar.
So this is some simple HTML form
that has some input name of hello.
And we see we have our method of GET.
And if we remember from our p-set,
when this form is submitted,
it sends an array called $_GET that has
all of these inputs or variables from
the form that should be
manipulated in our PHP.
So in this case, the user
would put in their name.
They submit it.
And we see that we get some array here.
We have our GET array.
And we are accessing the name.
>> So that says, OK, give me the
value that's associated with name,
name being the key here.
And that maps directly to what
we said our input name is.
So this was giving you the key to what
is going to be in your array here.
Does that make sense to everyone?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Does the name in GET refer
to the purple line in [INAUDIBLE]?
>> ALISON: It refers to this here.
So this field right here,
it refers to this name here.
So this could have been named
like phone number, or whatever.
This name actually says, what
are you calling this field?
How are you going to
refer to this field?
And this name is actually like, we're
saying this field is called name.
That's how we're going to access it.
>> AUDIENCE: So is it like,
input name equals Bob, and--
>> ALISON: Right, then you
would get Bob down there.
Exactly.
Everyone cool?
All right, so GET versus POST,
these are the two main ways
that we pass data in an HTTP request.
You guys should have seen
both of these hopefully.
So with GET, the information
is passed through the URL.
So if you ever do Google
searches, YouTube, you'll
probably notice some question mark.
And then, all the words
that you just put in there.
And POST passes the data
in the HTTP message body.
So unlike GET, you kind of consider
that the data is hidden from the user.
But what's really
important to understand
is that this is still
just as insecure as GET.
The analogy I like to use is if
you have your bank account number
and you write it on the outside of
an envelope, that's pretty unsafe.
If you were to write it on a piece of
paper and put it inside the envelope,
it's still really unsafe because
all you have to do is open that up
and look at the actual contents
of the message to see that.
So this is "hidden," and people like to
think it's secure, but it's really not.
And I'm sure Davin will
get into that more, maybe.
But it's an important
distinction to make
and something really good to understand.
>> OK, SQL, Structured Query Language.
All the stuff that
we've seen so recently!
So it's basically just designed,
obviously, for managing data.
You guys had a lot of experience with
this in your tables with PHP MyAdmin.
And there are four common queries
that we want you guys to know.
So there's update, insert,
select, and delete.
So make sure you know those really well.
We're going to go
through them really fast.
>> So update, really, as what
you might think it does,
it just updates data in your database.
So we have some example here.
This is the general
structure of an update query.
So we update the table
that we're talking about.
And we want to set certain
values, certain columns
equal to specific values.
So this just updates the table, changing
values in all rows in this case.
So in this one down here, an actual
example, we have insert-- sorry.
That slide advanced
without me realizing it.
>> So this updates table set col1 equal
to val1 where house equals "Currier."
What this one does is
it only changes, it only
updates these values in specific places.
So in this first one, it changes these
values for everything in your table,
OK?
It's going to change this
column for every single entry,
for every single row.
But this where, you could
think of it as a qualifier.
So it's only going to change
it in very specific places.
So in p-set seven, when you
maybe updated the amount of cash
that your user had, you probably had
some where ID equals session ID, right?
>> Because you didn't want to
change the amount of cash
for every person who
was using your website.
You wanted to change it for one
specific person, that person being
whoever was using it at that time.
Right?
OK, so insert, insert
certain values into tables.
This is like when you're
creating a brand new user.
The general structure here
is insert into whatever table
we're talking about.
Values, being the values that
we actually want to insert.
OK, so as we see here, we
have insert into table.
This is specific columns with
their corresponded values.
So this says, insert
a new row containing
values val1 and val2 under
these specific columns.
>> So maybe you only want to fill
out half the things in this row.
That's what this part here lets you do.
It lets you actually
determine which part.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Can you only [INAUDIBLE]
cells in the row [INAUDIBLE]?
>> ALISON: If you only fill in
certain parts of your row,
the rest of those cells are just empty.
As long as you allow them to
be empty, it's not a problem.
If you try to access them, it's
going to return some empty element.
But it is important to know
that in certain tables,
they have to be allowed to be null.
You may have run into a
problem during your p-set
because we didn't let any
of your values be null.
But you can specify an
optional value in your table.
>> OK, select, so this is
just a way of getting
specific data from a table at
some identifier that you want.
So select star from table where
col equals something just means,
give me all the data associated
where this specific column is true.
So the star in this case will
return the entire row to you, OK?
>> And then, in this case, select star from
table just gives you the entire table.
And then, delete obviously, it just
deletes the row from the table.
So delete from table,
whatever table we're
referencing, where some specific
identifier or some condition is true.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Question.
Why are you using double
quotes, and whether you
do double quotes or single
quotes, does it make a difference?
>> ALISON: Double quotes or single quotes
doesn't make a difference in SQL.
I thought I saw another question.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Doesn't it affect what
gets escaped from the query?
>> ALISON: Rob?
>> ROB: What do you mean by
escaped from the query?
>> AUDIENCE: If someone has a
single query in the form of--
>> ROB: If someone were to
put a single quote in,
then as long as you're sanitizing
your input, then it doesn't matter.
But if you're using a single
quote and you are incorrectly
escaping your inputs,
then yes, they need
to put a single quote in order to break
your code. if you use double quotes,
they need to put a double
quote to break your code.
But as long as you escape things
correctly, it doesn't matter.
It's just going to be translated
to the correct symbol anyway.
>> AUDIENCE: What does escape mean?
ALISON: Well, like
sanitizing and escape.
The exam that we have, the great XKCD
comic that they pull up where you have,
oh--
ROB: It's the last slide.
ALISON: It's the last slide, really?
Oh my god.
There we go, perfect.
OK, so basically, you can inject
something into this SQL query
where it breaks your
code, or as David showed
in class, if we have some single
quote 1 equals 1 and if in our code,
we just directly copy that in, and
we have an ending single quote,
what happens is we get
some expression that
evaluates to true that will
let someone enter our database
and get data that we
don't want them to get.
So sanitizing the inputs
just means making sure
that we are escaping these
characters and designating them
as chars and not things
that should be allowed
to be taken literally
as our SQL statement.
>> So the big thing that we said
that you guys should be using
were HTML special chars,
which is something
that you might want to take a look at.
OK, delete.
Data types, this will all be online.
Since we have 15 minutes left, I'm
just going to go right through this.
PHP and SQL, basically this is
just we had a query function that
helped protect against
these malicious attacks.
So whenever you use
query, we were making sure
that things were sanitized and whatnot.
>> MVC is just a design paradigm,
so model, view, controller.
It's just a way to keep things
nice and split up in the same way
that we tend to factor
out code into functions.
This is just a web design framework
that allows you to do the same thing.
I'm going to skip this.
>> This is something that I
would be super comfy with.
It's a great little table there.
It gives you the function
example of the model.
I'm just going through this because I
really want Davin to be able to talk.
If you have any questions,
please feel free.
I'll be here after.
Just come talk to me.
With that, we have HTTP statuses.
And Davin's going to blow
through this in 15 minutes.
This is going to be great.
>> DAVIN: OK.
Uh, your mic?
Yeah.
Sorry.
ALISON: Way to be prepared.
DAVIN: No, I'm ready.
I'm ready.
Let's do this.
It's ready.
OK.
Sorry.
I spilled coffee on myself.
I don't know if I'm more
upset that I look silly,
or that I don't have coffee anymore.
Anyway, just a quick announcement
about the sheet you guys have.
So this sheet you guys have is not
the official what's on the quiz.
This is the official what's on the quiz.
Also, on the website, we tell
you, OK, this will be on the quiz.
So in the little cheat sheet
you have, not official.
And there are mistakes on it.
So best not to just blindly use it.
So yeah, that's that.
So let's get into this real quick.
>> So HTTP statuses.
So what happens when the
website, everything is all right.
Everything's OK.
Everything comes back to
you the way you want it to.
You get a 200 OK.
301, where have we seen that 301 before?
Wait, what's up?
Sorry.
We saw i tin lecture during security.
So during security, so if David typed in
http and then tried to go to cs50.net,
you're going to see 301 moved.
Why?
Because it's going to redirect
you automatically to our HTTPS.
>> So 301 moved, just it's
basically a redirection.
And you can think about it like this.
Any of the statuses that start with 2's,
those are like, OK, everything's OK.
Any of the statuses that start
with 3, those are redirection.
Statuses that start with 4, that means
there's some kind of client error.
Statuses that start with 5,
that's some kind of server error.
So you kind of break up
the statuses like that.
So 304 not not modified, so in your
server.c p-sets, so let's say you
loaded cat.html.
Everything comes back,
you get 200s, OK, great.
>> Let's say you refreshed it.
Well, inside that
cat.html, you have a JPEG.
Well, that JPEG isn't
going to get reloaded.
You're not going to post another
GET request to the server,
and then get all that information back.
It's going to just be-- that image is
going to be cached on your machine.
And so that image will be a 304.
So it's not been modified.
If you then close out, clear
cookies, and then refresh
and try to load that page
again, you're going to see 200s.
You're not going to see that 304.
>> 400, bad request, real
quick, like if you
were going to send a
JSON object to the server
and your JSON object was incorrect,
you'll see something like that.
403, forbidden.
When would you see a forbidden?
Probably Probably?
AUDIENCE: Chmod.
DAVIN: Chmod, yeah.
So you haven't set
permissions correctly.
404, not found.
It's just not there.
So if you type in the wrong URL.
500, internal server error, the server
probably wasn't configured correctly.
Something not on your end, but
something on the server side.
And 503?
A lot of people saw
503s in the last p-set.
When would that happen?
I heard whispers.
>> AUDIENCE: When Google
decides you're a robot.
DAVIN: Yeah, when Google decides
you're a robot, you get 503s.
So that's an overload.
If you've requested from the server
too much, it's usually temporary.
And most of you noticed it.
So you saw 503.
You might have taken a little
break, then the 503s went away,
and everything was all right.
>> GABE: Real quick, when do you guys get
500 in probably this last problem set?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Usually if the
server has a file misplaced
or [INAUDIBLE] their
machine [INAUDIBLE].
>> GABE: So it might be a configuration
issue in your PHP on your server.
But it might be just something
like a semicolon that your forgot.
If you're typing PHP,
some incorrect syntax
might get you something like that.
OK?
>> DAVIN: Cool.
Do you want me to do just up until AJAX?
>> GABE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVIN: OK.
So what's the DOM?
What does DOM stand for?
>> AUDIENCE: Document object model.
DAVIN: Nice.
And why do we like it?
Awesome.
Right, so it just allows us to access
the HTML, access our page very quickly.
Why?
Because we're treating our
page, treating our HTML tags,
treating everything
as if they're objects.
If we're treating them like they're
objects, then what can we do?
Well, we can call functions on them.
And this is important why?
Well, because we're going to use
JavaScript to update our HTML,
update these objects.
So if we treat them like objects,
we can then call functions on them.
I'm going to get into this a little
more when I go into JavaScript,
but you've all seen like
document.getElementByID.
So document is your
element, get element by ID,
so you're going to look
for some ID in an HTML tag.
And then, you can do
something else to that.
For example, like document.body,
then you can append child.
So you're going to find the document.
You have the document.
You're going to find the body.
You found the body.
And then, you're going to
call some function on it.
So append child, and you can append
some HTML onto the end inside your body.
So basically, you're just
treating it like an object.
You're treating HTML
tags like an object.
And it makes it very easy
and quick to go through them.
But it also allows you
to call functions on them
so you can manipulate
and change the elements.
>> GABE: Given this, why is JavaScript such
a nice language to interact with HTML?
Odds are, when people were choosing
the language for the browser,
for client side,
JavaScript is really nice,
it's really good at handling objects.
And the objects are kind of like
the objects that appear in the HTML,
so it's very easy for JavaScript
to do that kind of handling.
DAVIN: Nice.
So here's just an example.
So I think on last year's quiz,
or maybe two years ago, we
asked you to create a tree.
So this is exactly what you'd do.
So you start out with document.
And then you basically
just look at the tags.
So if you look, we
start with an HTML tag.
And then, you get clues about how to
do this based upon the indentation.
So head kind of branches off.
Inside head, we have
another tag for title.
So then, we have a title tag.
And inside that, we have some string.
And so we represent
a string in a circle.
And all the tags are in squares.
>> And if you look, if we
think of this as a tree,
and let's say that HTML is
a parent, then head and body
are going to be siblings.
They're both going to be
children of that parent.
So because they're
both siblings, they're
going to be kind of next to
each other in our tree model.
And then, you basically
do the exact same thing.
So not difficult, but we have asked
questions like this before on the quiz.
GABE: Does anybody
have questions so far?
Is it good?
DAVIN: Cool.
JavaScript, OK, the good stuff.
So JavaScript, what is JavaScript?
Well, JavaScript is-- it's
complicated, but these
are some of the highlights
that you should keep in mind.
First, it's loosely typed.
What does that mean?
So PHP was-- yeah, what's up?
>> AUDIENCE: You don't have to explicitly
state what type of variable it is.
DAVIN: Perfect.
So he said you don't have to
explicitly state the type of variable.
That's exactly right.
So in C, if I had int i equals 50,
then in PHP, it's just like this, $i,
equals 50.
Then in JavaScript,
what would the call be?
Var, right?
It'd be like var i equals 50.
But you don't have to be
like, OK, this is an int.
OK, this is a string.
No need to do that.
It's an interpreted language.
So what does that mean?
>> AUDIENCE: Not compiled.
>> DAVIN: What does not compiled mean?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: You don't have
to restructure the code
to get it ready for
the computer to run it.
It's just taken at the time of
execution and the computer [INAUDIBLE].
DAVIN: Yeah, so it's going to
pass through an interpreter.
But you're exactly right.
So you're never going
to compile it, right?
When you were doing your
PHP and JavaScript code,
you never called compile.
You never called something like
make or anything like that.
That's because it's interpreted.
So every time it goes through browser,
it goes through an interpreter.
And that's going to interpret it
just in real time right away for you.
So what are some positives and negatives
to having an interpreted language
and having a compiled language?
So compiling-- yeah, what's up?
>> AUDIENCE: Interpreted is slower.
DAVIN: In what sense?
>> AUDIENCE: After you
compile, you don't have
to do any extra steps to execute
it, whereas this [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVIN: Right, perfect.
So what you said is
basically that compiling,
when you compile, you have a
lot of upfront costs, right?
You're going to compile it.
But after you compile it, the
compiler's going to optimize it.
It's going to be fast.
It's going to basically
be as fast as it can be.
With interpreting, you never
have that upfront cost.
Rather, it's going to be slightly slower
every single time you interpret it.
And you're going to have to
interpret it every single time.
So instead of having this
one time cost, now you're
going to have to interpret it
every time the page renders.
>> So interpreters are good because
you don't have to compile it,
but they're bad in that every
time the page loads, it's
going to have to
interpret this JavaScript.
And it's going to run slightly slower
than if you were to compile it.
Allows you to communicate-- oh, wait.
Used to manipulate the
content and appearance.
We just talked about that.
It uses the DOM.
AJAX, we'll get into
AJAX in a little bit.
And then, it's client side.
So PHP is server side.
JavaScript is client side.
What are positive to that?
It says it.
It's faster, right?
Because you don't have to-- it's faster.
You don't have to communicate
with some other device.
If you're just on your
client, you're never
going to have to go and
see what's on the server
and then report back
or something like that.
So client side tends to
be a little bit faster.
>> GABE: Yeah, but this
does not mean PHP is
faster than JavaScript
or anything of the like.
They run kind of in the same
speed because they're both
interpreted languages.
The thing that's slow
here is the request.
So you're actually going
all the way over to Brazil
to get some information
that lives there.
But PHP and JavaScript, they
kind of run in the same speed.
It's not that one is
faster than the other.
This, also, trick question here.
So JavaScript never becomes
machine code, true or false?
>> AUDIENCE: False.
GABE: False.
It has to become machine
code because machine code is
the only thing the machine understands.
Even though it's not compiled,
it still becomes machine code
because the interpreter is just
a program that goes line by line
and transforms that line into
something the computer understands.
OK?
Cool.
>> DAVIN: Here is just a very basic
hello world JavaScript program.
So I don't know if-- you've seen this.
But you just have HTML here.
And instead of actually putting
the JavaScript in the script tags,
so you'd normally put it in head.
You have script tags.
You drop it there.
All we've done here is we've linked in--
so we've linked in a JavaScript file
like this.
And you've all done this, right?
So when you were using jQuery and
underscore.js in the last p-set,
you don't have tons of code up in
your script tags, up in your head.
You could do that, but instead
you're just linking it in.
And you're linking it in
just like you do with CSS.
So it just makes it easier to read so
your code isn't like 1,000 lines long
with tons of functions that
you might not be using.
>> Instead, you just link it in.
It compartmentalizes it.
It's like writing some header file, and
then including that header file in C.
Think of it just like this.
So what does this do?
Well, this is going to run.
It's going to alert.
So you're going to get a little
pop up called hello world.
Quick question, just sanity check,
so you see here in the body,
say body, HTML here.
What comes first?
Do I see body, HTML here,
or do I see the alert first?
>> AUDIENCE: Alert.
>> DAVIN: Right.
He says alert.
Why?
>> AUDIENCE: Because you
go from top to bottom.
>> DAVIN: Yes.
Perfect.
So he says, you go from top to
bottom, which is absolutely correct.
You're going to go from top to bottom.
And in JavaScript, jQuery, you have a
function that's like onload, or ready,
and that says, OK, wait until
all of this HTML has loaded.
And then, call the JavaScript.
Because we don't have that here, the
very first thing that's going to happen
is it's going to go from top to bottom.
It's going to hit that JS
call, it's going to alert.
After that you click OK,
that alert goes away.
Then it's going to show
you the body HTML here.
Nice.
>> OK, so just real quick, writing
in JavaScript is super quick.
In order to declare
a variable, var name.
So in C, you have int i, you have
to declare what kind of type it is.
PHP, $.
JavaScript, var.
We talked about this.
All right, let's go.
>> Loops, same thing.
Same thing.
Function declarations, so
just like you've seen in C.
The only thing different is so when
you get to other programming languages,
like when you take 51 next semester
and you're doing with OCAML,
you can deal with anonymous functions.
So that's exactly what you have here.
So you want to put in sum,
some kind of sum value.
But you might only be doing it one time.
So you don't want to call it function
sum, give it a function declaration.
Instead, you just use it
as an anonymous function.
And you've seen this a lot.
You'll see an example of
this in a couple slides.
Yeah, we'll see.
GABE: Good question.
When might you want to use
an anonymous function here?
Basically, when you want something,
like an event, to happen.
So when the mouse is
clicked, for example,
you want some function to be called.
So you pass to the event
handler, you pass to the event,
kind of, the function that
you want to be called.
And what you're passing
is like, at the end
of the day, just a pointer to
that instruction, to the function.
So it's not like you're passing
the entire code, just as
a pointer to the function.
And then, when somebody clicks the
mouse, then that function gets called.
>> DAVIN: Arrays, so you
have an array declaration.
Then, an array to put things in.
Real quick, what will this print out?
What will the third element be?
>> AUDIENCE: "JS".
>> DAVIN: Right, it would be "JS."
Wait, go back.
What is the length?
>> AUDIENCE: Three.
DAVIN: Three, right?
Exactly what you think.
OK, now go.
Arrays, you can add things to them.
So you can go beyond
their initial bounds.
Just something to keep in mind.
PHP, JavaScript, they're a little
bit more forgiving in terms of things
like that.
Objects, very much like
structs in C, very much
like associative arrays in PHP.
You've all had experience with this.
So JSON, when you're passing JSON
back and forth in p-set eight,
that's your object.
>> So yeah, example, real quick example.
Here is an object.
The way you reference this
object, so just real quick,
let's say I wanted to find
out, OK, what is the course?
And so the object name here is CS50.
And then if I had an associative
array, how would I do that?
I'll be using a key, right?
So I have the name of the array.
I have bracket, quotes, key,
end quotes, end bracket,
and that will reference that
element inside my associative array.
How do I referenced
course inside my object?
Anybody know?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVIN: What's up?
AUDIENCE: CS50.course.
DAVIN: Right, yeah.
So CS50.course.
So the way you reference things
inside a JSON object is with a dot.
>> AUDIENCE: You can also use array syntax.
>> DAVIN: OK, fine.
>> GABE: You can also use CS50 bracket,
string, like quotation marks.
AUDIENCE: I think it's identical to PHP.
GABE: It's the same thing.
DAVIN: Fine!
But you will see this other places.
Yeah, so keep going.
This is what I just said.
So into a JavaScript jQuery example.
So this is my DOM, right?
Real quick, so I have a
head, hello world, body.
I have a button.
It says "push me," so I want to push it.
And I want to do something
when it's clicked.
Right, next.
>> Right, so this is my JavaScript.
So jQuery is just an easier
way to write JavaScript.
So this, and what I'm going to show
you next, is going to be jQuery,
are identical.
So they will do the same things.
Just jQuery tends to be a little easier.
People tend to like it more.
It has a lot of functionality.
So people tend to use jQuery.
You all used jQuery in the last p-set.
So what will this do?
What will this JavaScript-- so
this is just plain JavaScript.
What will this do?
What will it do?
>> So first, you see window onload.
Right?
So we didn't see that before.
So this is going to wait
until the entire window loads.
So it's going to wait until
the HTML, all the images load
before it does anything.
So let's say our DOM has loaded.
Everything's there.
Then what's going to happen?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Button appears.
>> DAVIN: The button's already there.
Yeah, so the button's already there.
But this is going to say,
OK, if I click the button,
so the button's already
there, like that HTML tag.
Wait, go back real quick.
This tag right right here is
going to be a button already.
There's already a button.
But then, the JavaScript
tag, right here,
it says, OK, I want
to get element by ID,
so search button just says, OK, I want
to map this variable to that button.
So that variable is just an
easier way to access that button.
And I say, OK, if I click that
button, so if I click that element,
and this element refers to
the button, if I click it,
then I want to call a function.
Here is one of those anonymous
functions we were talking about.
>> Just call some function.
Inside that function, basically
something we've seen a lot, alert.
You click the search button.
It's going to basically have a button.
You click it.
You get that alert.
X out.
That's it.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: So if you put the script
[INAUDIBLE], script tag in your HTML?
>> DAVIN: You can put the script
tag straight in the head
because you have this onload.
It's also that you have a click.
So it's going to wait until
you click for something.
But onload is just to be safe, to make
sure everything loads into your HTML
beforehand.
Yeah?
You want to say something?
>> GABE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVIN: Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: So onload avoids
defining the variable search button
by just saying document.getElementByID
search button dot [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVIN: Definitely, but then
your string just gets huge.
Exactly, so this is just to
make it easier for you, yeah.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Where did we
create window.onload?
Or document.ready?
>> DAVIN: Yes, there is.
Yes, there is, I checked.
>> GABE: Not for them to care about.
>> DAVIN: OK, so I'm going
to tell you anyway.
So basically, just in general, so
window.onload waits until your DOM, all
your HTML, loads.
It waits until your images load.
It waits until everything loads.
document.ready, it just
waits until your DOM loads.
Once the HTML is all there, once
your DOM is there, starts running.
That's the only difference.
>> GABE: Quick sanity check here.
So this can be seen kind of
like a line of code, right?
Because it's window.onload
equals a bunch of stuff.
When JavaScript reads this, true or
false, the function gets executed.
False.
OK?
What happens here, you're just passing
this function as an anonymous functions
to window.onload.
And then when is it going
to actually get executed?
When the window loads.
That's an event.
So that's jus t thing we're
talking about earlier, right?
So when the event happens,
the function happens.
Same thing with the onclick.
>> DAVIN: OK, so somebody took
away the document.ready.
But this will be the exact same--
AUDIENCE: The dollar sign,
that is a document.ready.
That's a shortcut.
>> DAVIN: Oh, that is?
OK, so this means
document.ready, shortcut.
But this is the same as window.onload
except for that little difference
I told you about.
And this is jQuery.
So this is the exact same
thing-- this is JavaScript.
This is just-- some people think of it
as a more light weight, sleek version
that has lots of functionality
that you'll probably be using.
So this does the exact same thing.
>> So things to kind of point out.
So in the other example, we
had document.getElementByID,
so we had this long
string that's going to get
the element by whatever ID it has.
That's replaced by this call right here.
So you see the dollar sign,
then you see quote, hashtag.
Hashtag is always a selector.
It says, OK, this has to do with an ID.
What's the selector for a class?
>> AUDIENCE: Dot.
>> DAVIN: Dot, right.
If you're just going to
select a tag, what is it?
It's just the tag, exactly.
And you could use that here, as well.
>> GABE: And by tag, we mean like
div, for example, or head.
>> DAVIN: Or body or p or
anything like that, yeah.
So here, OK, instead of saying
document.getElementByID,
this is just the exact same thing.
Just in jQuery, it's shorter.
So it's simpler.
So then, no more onclick, just click.
jQuery function, call this function.
Alert is the exact same.
So it's a little bit
smaller, or little bit
shorter, a little bit-- people think
it's a little easier to write out,
a little bit easier to understand.
But this is jQuery.
A lot of people get a little
bit confused and worried
and they think, OK, jQuery
is different than JavaScript.
I have to remember these
two different things.
It's not.
I mean, it's different syntax.
But jQuery is JavaScript.
It's just a seemingly
better version that
might be easier to
understand that people use.
GABE: Yeah, to be
honest, that dollar sign
that you see in jQuery, that's just the
name of a function that jQuery defines.
It doesn't have anything special.
Is It's just the name of a function,
just like you could define dollar sign.
>> DAVIN: Yeah, so talked about this.
Some useful things.
I was looking back at the old quizzes.
In the past couple quizzes, they've
had to use things like this.
So document.ready, so
make sure everything's
loaded before you start doing things.
Select an ID, or select
a class, it'd just
be quote dot some class, end quote.
Submit, so if you're
submitting a form and call
this function after the form submits.
Value, so let's say I had a form
submission, like a user name, an email,
whatever.
I had a text box.
So I'm typing into that text box.
Well, if you want to get the value
out of that text box, you use dot val.
And then, down here,
dot HTML is the same
is like document dot
getElementByID dot innerHTML.
So that's going to return
you the HTML from that ID.
Here, you just use some
ID or whatever dot HTML.
That'll get the HTML from that element.
If you wanted to then change that
HTML, you can pass it something.
So you'd be like dot HTML, and then
inside, quotes, new HTML or something.
>> GABE: OK, so AJAX.
I really like to understand
AJAX really well.
So I want you guys to
understand AJAX really well.
Because if you do,
you're pretty much going
to understand everything that
has to do with HTTP, PHP,
JavaScript because it all
comes together in AJAX.
AJAX is not a language.
AJAX is a technique.
And it uses lots of different tools.
AJAX stands for
asynchronous JavaScript XML.
So the method, the language, the data.
>> So the main language that we use
in AJAX to trigger everything
and to handle everything
later on is JavaScript.
That's why it relates
very close to JavaScript.
And then asynchronous is
because we don't do it
all at once when we're loading the page.
This is the thing that we can
do things kind of in parallel.
The main idea behind
AJAX is that you want
it to get some specific information.
For example, when you're typing new
user name when you register a user name,
my user name is abc123.
And then, at the end of the
form, you have to click Submit.
And it had to go to the server,
and then check if in the database,
abc123 is already there.
And if it's already there, it says,
user name already in the database.
And they, you have to fill
out the entire form again.
And it was really, really bad.
>> And then people say,
OK, why can't we just
do a small HTTP request to just check
to see if this user is in the database
before the user had to
submit the entire form?
So for example, when the
user finishes typing abc123,
let's just go to the server a little
bit and just get a true or false
from the server to see if
that's a valid user name or not.
OK, so that's one of the main
uses of AJAX nowadays still.
>> DAVIN: So real quick, in
an Ajax call in jQuery,
you could signify that you
want it to be synchronous.
You shouldn't do this.
But you can do that.
And if you did that, what would happen?
Well, for example, when you're
getting news or whatever,
your browser is just going to wait
until that entire call is complete
instead of letting you do other
things right after you click it.
>> GABE: It's not passing anymore.
Oh my god.
Sorry!
Yup.
"In the past, the
client needed to request
the entire content of a website."
That's what I said.
It allows us to send
additional GET or POST
requests without having
to reload our browser.
So at the end of the day, we're
actually making an HTTP requests
here using JavaScript.
Because before, we only used JavaScript
to change the HTML that already came.
And now, we can use it to interface
with the web servers as well.
The way this happens
is we have the client.
Davin is a client.
And he has all the JavaScript
running because HTML is dumb.
JavaScript is smart.
So davin Davin has his smart
part and his dumb part.
He's going to use his smart part now.
He's going to use JavaScript
to request, for example,
whether abc123 is in
the database or not.
>> So Davin, please, you just
send me an HTTP request.
Thank you.
So he just sent an HTTP request.
You see that?
And that's just the same way
that any HTTP request is sent.
The browser, Google
Chrome or something, is
going to see that Davin's
trying to send an HTTP request,
going to help hm a little bit.
And that's going to go
all the way to the server.
Now, the server is going to have
PHP here, or any other language.
Just like in a normal HTTP request.
It's pretty much a normal HTTP request.
>> And then, the server
is going to say, OK,
Davin wants me to check whether
this abc123 is in the database.
Go talk to the model.
The model says it's not.
abc123 is a good user name.
And then, the web server is going to
use PHP to render some form of file.
It could be literally just a file
that contains "yes" in it, or "no,
or something like that.
It could be any file.
>> It could be like I'm going to
send Davin a picture of a duck
if it's in the database and
send a picture of a hamster
if it's not in the database.
That would be kind of
dumb, but it will work.
OK, so I send a duck to Davin.
Davin got a duck.
And now, who is going
to handle the duck?
Davin's smart part again,
so JavaScript, right?
JavaScript sent the
request, and JavaScript
is going to receive the request
and interpret it in some form.
>> And in this sense, it's going to
say, OK, if duck then I'm good.
If hamster, then I'm going
to say, no, user name already
exists in the database.
But usually, you're not
going to send a duck.
You're going to send
something slightly smarter.
And what we use is XML.
And more recently, we use JSON.
JSON is just JavaScript
Object Notation, which
is basically you get an
entire JavaScript object.
And you put it in a file, just like
that CS50 object that you guys saw.
You put it in a file, and
you send it over to Davin.
>> So in this case, I would
make a JavaScript object
and just say, user exists, yes.
Or user exists, no.
And send it back to him.
And why JSON?
Because the person
who's receiving this is
going to use JavaScript
to handle the response.
And JavaScript works so well because
it's called JavaScript Object Notation.
Right?
So he can just call a function and get
this nice object from the response.
And then, he's going to know whether
that user is in the database or not.
>> So you see, all of it coming
together in the web server,
and then there's one HTTP to request
and one HTTP response and everything.
So make sure you guys
understand this AJAX call
because it helps you understand all
of the concepts we're talking about.
>> So here's an example
of AJAX with jQuery.
And here, we do with get JSON.
So we're not trying to get an
image of a cat here, or a duck.
We're trying to get a JSON file.
And then we wait until
it's done, dot done.
That means I'm waiting for the response.
It might take a little while.
Then, you see a little loading.
If you want to do that in your website.
So dot done, and then what
happens when it's done?
You pass in an anonymous
function, just like we saw before.
Because done is an event, just
like clicking a mouse or whatever,
for jQuery.
So you pass in this function with
data, text, status, and jqXHR.
And basically, that's
just some variables
that you can use later on to have
the status of the HTTP request,
the data that it's going
to send back to you.
So then you can later on interpret it
and do something meaningful with it.
And if it fails, when might it fail?
Well, when the HTTP request gives
you a 500 or something like that.
Then, it's going to tell you the
status, what kind of failure that was,
and all sorts of things.
You have to make sure
to handle both cases,
otherwise the program goes crazy.
>> DAVIN: So yeah, this is exactly
what you saw on your last p-set.
The actual AJAX call is in the get JSON.
That is the call.
And then, dot done is like
it checks if it's successful.
If it is successful, you want
to do something with the data.
You get back from that
JSON request data.
That is what you get back.
So if you remember from your p-set,
a lot of you were like data bracket i
or whatever, dot link or title.
Whatever's coming back
from that JSON, whatever
the fields are in that JSON object,
that's what you're getting back.
Data is what you're getting back.
Text status, just something that
lets you know what happened.
And then, the jqXHR, that's just
the jQuery XML HTTP request.
That's just like an object.
And then fail, just like Gabe said.
GABE: In our little example of abc123
just to check if that's in the database
or not, the data would be something you
would do, if data dot user name exists,
which is what your PHP generated for
you, if data dot user name exists, then
I'm going to alert, user
name already exists.
Else, I'm just going to let the
user proceed filling out the form.
OK, security, cool.
>> DAVIN: Want me to?
>> GABE: I like this one.
So something that looks familiar.
We're almost done.
So this is just the example
you guys saw in class.
You were using argv1 here.
That's like a command line argument.
And we're mem copying that
into a buffer of size 12.
What's the problem here?
Buffer overflow!
Because we have a buffer of size 12.
argv1 might have a size of two billion.
We don't do any boundary checking.
So we might copy a lot of memory.
And we'll be particularly
bad about this.
What could we do that's
very, very mean in this case?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Part of the two billion things
contains executable code that returns
[INAUDIBLE].
GABE: Exactly.
So that's the kind of
thing that people use
to jailbreak an iPhone, for example.
So that kind of thing.
Because you can just make the device
execute any code that you like.
The fix, so the fix is easy.
Just check for the bounds.
You check for null because
we always check for null
when we're dealing with strings.
And then, you take the
string length before.
And if the string
length is a valid string
length, which is within 0
and 12, then we're good.
>> DAVIN: If you don't check for
null, real quick, what will happen?
It'll seg fault.
Why will it seg fault?
Because you're calling strlen on null.
GABE: Yeah.
True or false, using one
password is a good idea.
>> AUDIENCE: False.
>> GABE: False.
Use many passwords, and big, long ones.
Padlock icons ensure security.
>> AUDIENCE: False.
>> GABE: False.
It doesn't mean anything.
It's just an icon.
SSL protects against a
man in the middle attack.
AUDIENCE: False.
GABE: False.
OK, so all those are false.
Nice.
[INAUDIBLE]
Want to talk about this?
Your turn.
DAVIN: Types of attacks,
man in the middle.
What's a man in the middle attack?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVIN: If you send an HTTP
request, they could do this, right?
But if you're sending HTTPS, they
probably won't be able to do this.
There's lots of points
along your connection.
You have routers.
You have DNS servers.
If someone is able to physically
see what you're sending,
so someone is able to
actually get between you,
the client, and the server, and is
able to see what you're sending,
this is a man in the middle attack.
So to see what you're trying to get from
the server, or is able to see-- worse,
you might be able to see
cookies or something like that.
>> So for example, if
you're not using SSL, he
might be able to see
your session ID cookies.
And this is called session hijacking
because he sees your ID cookies,
and then he's able to go to that
website and pretend to be you.
Because just like in PHP, remember
when we logged in, what do we do?
We set session ID equal to ID.
So that identifies you.
That's why you can see your portfolio
and not everybody else's portfolio.
>> Well, if I'm able to get that cookie,
then I can log onto that page.
And then, I can just see your stuff
and start buying and selling stuff.
So that's session hijacking.
But you shouldn't be able to-- so you
can use the man in the middle attack
even if they're using SSL.
But you shouldn't be able to.
If they are using SSL,
you can't session hijack.
Why?
Because it's all encrypted,
right? if it's encrypted,
and I'm still a man in the
middle, I still get your data.
That's fine.
But it's encrypted.
So I can't really use it.
So that's two.
>> Real quick, cross site request forgery.
That's just if there's a link
and that link does something
that you don't think it should do.
So for example, if the link was
going to buy stocks or sell stocks,
and you didn't know that.
You clicked on the link,
sent a request, bought
or sold something that
you didn't mean to do.
That's that.
>> Cross site scripting, so here,
you're passing in via variable q,
instead of passing in some kind
of value, maybe q is like a name.
So instead of passing q equals
Davin or something like that,
if you don't use HTML
special chars, if you
don't escape this to make sure it's
OK, then I could pass in instead,
let's say in here I'm saying
print or something like that,
then I could pass in here a script call.
>> So then, instead of
just getting a variable,
I would then execute this script call.
So inside that script
call, what does it do?
Document dot location, that's going to
change the location of the document.
So I'm going to redirect
to somewhere else.
It's called bad guy in
this example, very good.
Couldn't think of the word.
And then, what's even
worse is that I'm going
to then set cookie, which is some
variable I have in this website.
I'm going to set it equal
to the document dot cookie.
Therefore, I'm going
to steal your cookie.
And I'm going to redirect
some information to a website
that you shouldn't be accessing.
And this all happens because you're
not escaping what you've seen.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: So just to
make that clear, it's
vulnerable.com that
is vulnerable to this.
So that link can appear
on any given page.
Someone clicks on it,
goes to vulnerable.com.
You have a cookie to vulnerable.com.
Let's say Facebook is
vulnerable, so facebook.com.
You have your Facebook cookie.
What this is doing, you're
going to facebook.com,
it's immediately redirecting
you to badguy.com,
but including your cookie information.
So it's a quick redirect,
but your Facebook cookie
is included with that redirect,
and that's how they [INAUDIBLE].
GABE: Yeah, there's
some very mean things
that people can do if there's this.
For example, if Facebook allowed
everybody to change your user name,
and they didn't do any
sanity checks, so you
could insert a JavaScript thing that
changes your image to a hamster.
And that inserts the same JavaScript
into everybody who views your page.
So everybody who views your page
has the same thing in the user name.
And because it's a virus,
it spreads exponentially.
DAVIN: We'll skip the last
one, and then we're done.
So this is just another example.
So this is they're not
escaping their SQL table.
So you can drop it.
So you want to escape things.
That was the previous example
with the cross site scripting.
Sorry we ran a little bit late.
Tomorrow, sorry!
Tomorrow, we have office hours.
So office hours in Cabbot 8:00 to 11:00.
The office hours are
strictly for quiz questions.