>> DOUG LLOYD: So in CS50 we learned about
a variety of sorting and searching
algorithms.
And sometimes it can be
a little tricky to keep
track of what algorithm does what.
We've really only
skimmed the surface too,
there are many other searching
and sorting algorithms.
So in this video let's
just take a few minutes
to try and distill each algorithm
down to its core elements
so you can remember the most
important information about them
and be able to articulate the
differences, if necessary.
>> The first is selection sort.
The basic idea behind selection sort
is find the smallest unsorted element
in an array and swap it with the
first unsorted element of that array.
We said that the worst-case
run time of that was n squared.
And if you want to recall why, take
a look at the selection sort video.
The best-case run time
is also n squared.
>> Bubble sort, the idea behind that
one is to swap adjacent pairs.
So that's the key that helps you
remember the difference here.
Selection sort is, so far,
find the smallest-- bubble
sort is swap adjacent pairs.
We swap adjacent pairs
of elements if they
are out of order, which effectively
bubbles larger elements to the right,
and at the same time it also begins
to move smaller elements to the left.
The worst-case case run time
of bubble sort is n squared.
The best-case run time
of bubble sort is n.
Because in that situation
we don't actually--
we might not need to
make any swaps at all.
We only have to make one
pass across all n elements.
>> In insertion sort, the
basic idea here is shifting.
That's the keyword for insertion sort.
We're going to step once through
the array from left to right.
And as we do, we're
going to shift elements
we've already seen to make room for
smaller ones that need to fit somewhere
back in that sorted portion.
So we build the sorted array one
element at a time, left to right,
and we shift things to make room.
The worst-case run time of
insertion sort is n squared.
The best-case run time is n.
>> Merge sort-- the keyword
here is split and merge.
We split the full array, whether
it's six elements, eight elements,
10,000 elements-- we split it
down by half, by half, by half,
until we have under array
of n one element arrays.
A set of n one element arrays.
So we started with one
1,000-element array,
and we get to the point where we
have 1,000 one-element arrays.
Then we begin to merge those sub arrays
back together in the correct order.
So we take two one-element arrays
and create a two-element array.
We take two two-element arrays
and create a four-element array
and so on and so on until we've
again rebuilt one n element array.
>> The worst-case run time of
merge sort is n times log n.
We have n elements, but
this recombining process
takes log n steps to get
back to a full array.
The best case run time is also n log
n because this process doesn't really
care whether the array was
sorted or not to start with.
The process is the same, there's
no way to short circuit things.
So n log n in the worst case,
n log n in the best case.
>> We talked about two
searching algorithms.
So linear search is about iterating.
We proceed across the array
once, from left to right,
trying to find the number
that we're looking for.
The worst-case run time is big O of n.
It might take us iterating
across every single element
to find the element we're looking
for, either in the last position,
or not at all.
But we can't confirm that until
we've looked at everything.
m the best-case, we find immediately.
The best-case run time of
linear search is omega of 1.
>> Lastly, there was binary search,
which requires assorted array.
Remember that's a very
important consideration
when working with binary search.
It's a prerequisite to using it--
the array that you're looking through
must be sorted.
Otherwise, the keyword
is divide and conquer.
Split the array into half and
eliminate half of the elements
every time as you proceed through.
Because of this divide and conquer
and splitting things in half approach,
the worst-case run time
of binary search is
log n, which is substantially
better than linear search's n.
The best-case run time is still one.
>> We might find it immediately the
first time we make a division, but,
again, remember that
although binary search is
substantially better than linear search
by virtue of being log n versus n,
you might have to go through the work
of sorting your array first, which
might make it less effective depending
on the size of the iterating sorted.
>> I'm Doug Lloyd, this is CS50.