>> All right, so, computational complexity.
Just a bit of a warning
before we dive in too far--
this'll probably be among
the most math-heavy things
we talk about in CS50.
Hopefully it won't be too overwhelming
and we'll try and guide you
through the process, but
just a bit of a fair warning.
There's a little bit
of math involved here.
All right, so in order to make
use of our computational resources
in the real world-- it's really
important to understand algorithms
and how they process data.
If we have a really
efficient algorithm, we
can minimize the amount of resources
we have available to deal with it.
If we have an algorithm that
is going to take a lot of work
to process a really
large set of data, it's
going to require more
and more resources, which
is money, RAM, all that kind of stuff.
>> So, being able to analyze an
algorithm using this tool set,
basically, asks the question--
how does this algorithm scale
as we throw more and more data at it?
In CS50, the amount of data we're
working with is pretty small.
Generally, our programs are going
to run in a second or less--
probably a lot less
particularly early on.
>> But think about a company that deals
with hundreds of millions of customers.
And they need to process
that customer data.
As the number of customers they
have gets bigger and bigger,
it's going to require
more and more resources.
How many more resources?
Well, that depends on how
we analyze the algorithm,
using the tools in this toolbox.
When we talk about the complexity of
an algorithm-- which sometimes you'll
hear it referred to as time
complexity or space complexity
but we're just going
to call complexity--
we're generally talking about
the worst-case scenario.
Given the absolute worst pile of
data that we could be throwing at it,
how is this algorithm going to
process or deal with that data?
We generally call the worst-case
runtime of an algorithm big-O.
So an algorithm might be said to
run in O of n or O of n squared.
And more about what
those mean in a second.
>> Sometimes, though, we do care
about the best-case scenario.
If the data is everything we wanted
it to be and it was absolutely perfect
and we were sending this perfect
set of data through our algorithm.
How would it handle in that situation?
We sometimes refer to that as
big-Omega, so in contrast with big-O,
we have big-Omega.
Big-Omega for the best-case scenario.
Big-O for the worst-case scenario.
Generally, when we talk about
the complexity of an algorithm,
we're talking about the
worst-case scenario.
So keep that in mind.
>> And in this class, we're generally going
to leave the rigorous analysis aside.
There are sciences and fields
devoted to this kind of stuff.
When we talk about reasoning
through algorithms,
which we'll do piece-by-piece for many
algorithms we talk about in the class.
We're really just talking about
reasoning through it with common sense,
not with formulas, or proofs,
or anything like that.
So don't worry, We won't be
turning into a big math class.
>> So I said we care about complexity
because it asks the question, how
do our algorithms handle larger and
larger data sets being thrown at them.
Well, what is a data set?
What did I mean when I said that?
It means whatever makes the most
sense in context, to be honest.
If we have an algorithm, the
Processes Strings-- we're probably
talking about the size of the string.
That's the data set--
the size, the number
of characters that make up the string.
If we're talking about an
algorithm that processes files,
we might be talking about how
many kilobytes comprise that file.
And that's the data set.
If we're talking about an algorithm
that handles arrays more generally,
such as sorting algorithms
or searching algorithms,
we're probably talking about the number
of elements that comprise an array.
>> Now, we can measure an
algorithm-- in particular,
when I say we can
measure an algorithm, I
mean we can measure how
many resources it takes up.
Whether those resources are, how many
bytes of RAM-- or megabytes of RAM
it uses.
Or how much time it takes to run.
And we can call this
measure, arbitrarily, f of n.
Where n is the number of
elements in the data set.
And f of n is how many somethings.
How many units of resources does
it require to process that data.
>> Now, we actually don't care
about what f of n is exactly.
In fact, we very rarely will--
certainly will never in this class-- I
dive into any really deep
analysis of what f of n is.
We're just going to talk about what f of
n is approximately or what it tends to.
And the tendency of an algorithm is
dictated by its highest order term.
And we can see what I
mean by that by taking
a look at a more concrete example.
>> So let's say that we have
three different algorithms.
The first of which takes n
cubed, some units of resources
to process a data set of size n.
We have a second algorithm that takes
n cubed plus n squared resources
to process a data set of size n.
And we have a third
algorithm that runs in-- that
takes up n cubed minus 8n squared
plus 20 n units of resources
to process an algorithm
with data set of size n.
>> Now again, we really aren't going
to get into this level of detail.
I'm really just have these up
here as an illustration of a point
that I'm going to be
making in a second, which
is that we only really care
about the tendency of things
as the data sets get bigger.
So if the data set is small, there's
actually a pretty big difference
in these algorithms.
The third algorithm there
takes 13 times longer,
13 times the amount of resources
to run relative to the first one.
>> If our data set is size 10, which
is bigger, but not necessarily huge,
we can see that there's
actually a bit of a difference.
The third algorithm
becomes more efficient.
It's about actually 40%--
or 60% more efficient.
It takes 40% the amount of time.
It can run-- it can take
400 units of resources
to process a data set of size 10.
Whereas the first
algorithm, by contrast,
takes 1,000 units of resources
to process a data set of size 10.
But look what happens as
our numbers get even bigger.
>> Now, the difference
between these algorithms
start to become a little less apparent.
And the fact that there are
lower-order terms-- or rather,
terms with lower exponents--
start to become irrelevant.
If a data set is of size
1,000 and the first algorithm
runs in a billion steps.
And the second algorithm runs in
a billion and a million steps.
And the third algorithm runs
in just shy of a billion steps.
It's pretty much a billion steps.
Those lower-order terms start
to become really irrelevant.
And just to really
hammer home the point--
if the data input is of size a
million-- all three of these pretty much
take one quintillion-- if
my math is correct-- steps
to process a data input
of size a million.
That's a lot of steps.
And the fact that one of them might
take a couple 100,000, or a couple 100
million even less when
we're talking about a number
that big-- it's kind of irrelevant.
They all tend to take
approximately n cubed,
and so we would actually refer
to all of these algorithms
as being on the order of n
cubed or big-O of n cubed.
>> Here's a list of some of the more
common computational complexity classes
that we'll encounter in
algorithms, generally.
And also specifically in CS50.
These are ordered from
generally fastest at the top,
to generally slowest at the bottom.
So constant time algorithms tend
to be the fastest, regardless
of the size of the
data input you pass in.
They always take one operation or
one unit of resources to deal with.
It might be 2, it might
be 3, it might be 4.
But it's a constant number.
It doesn't vary.
>> Logarithmic time algorithms
are slightly better.
And a really good example of
a logarithmic time algorithm
you've surely seen by now is the
tearing apart of the phone book
to find Mike Smith in the phone book.
We cut the problem in half.
And so as n gets larger
and larger and larger--
in fact, every time you double
n, it only takes one more step.
So that's a lot better
than, say, linear time.
Which is if you double n, it
takes double the number of steps.
If you triple n, it takes
triple the number of steps.
One step per unit.
>> Then things get a little more--
little less great from there.
You have linear rhythmic time, sometimes
called log linear time or just n log n.
And we'll an example
of an algorithm that
runs in n log n, which is still better
than quadratic time-- n squared.
Or polynomial time, n two
any number greater than two.
Or exponential time, which
is even worse-- C to the n.
So some constant number raised to
the power of the size of the input.
So if there's 1,000-- if the
data input is of size 1,000,
it would take C to the 1,000th power.
It's a lot worse than polynomial time.
>> Factorial time is even worse.
And in fact, there really do
exist infinite time algorithms,
such as, so-called stupid sort-- whose
job is to randomly shuffle an array
and then check to see
whether it's sorted.
And if it's not, randomly
shuffle the array again
and check to see whether it's sorted.
And as you can probably imagine--
you can imagine a situation
where in the worst-case, that will
never actually start with the array.
That algorithm would run forever.
And so that would be an
infinite time algorithm.
Hopefully you won't be writing
any factorial or infinite time
algorithms in CS50.
>> So, let's take a little more
concrete look at some simpler
computational complexity classes.
So we have an example--
or two examples here--
of constant time algorithms,
which always take
a single operation in the worst-case.
So the first example--
we have a function
called 4 for you, which
takes an array of size 1,000.
But then apparently
doesn't actually look
at it-- doesn't really care what's
inside of it, of that array.
Always just returns four.
So, that algorithm,
despite the fact that it
takes 1,000 elements doesn't
do anything with them.
Just returns four.
It's always a single step.
>> In fact, add 2 nums-- which
we've seen before as well--
just processes two integers.
It's not a single step.
It's actually a couple steps.
You get a, you get b, you add them
together, and you output the results.
So it's 84 steps.
But it's always constant,
regardless of a or b.
You have to get a, get b, add
them together, output the result.
So that's a constant time algorithm.
>> Here's an example of a
linear time algorithm--
an algorithm that gets-- that takes
one additional step, possibly,
as your input grows by 1.
So, let's say we're looking for
the number 5 inside of an array.
You might have a situation where
you can find it fairly early.
But you could also have
a situation where it
might be the last element of the array.
In an array of size 5, if
we're looking for the number 5.
It would take 5 steps.
And in fact, imagine that there's
not 5 anywhere in this array.
We still actually have to look at
every single element of the array
in order to determine
whether or not 5 is there.
>> So in the worst-case, which is that
the element is last in the array
or doesn't exist at all.
We still have to look at
all of the n elements.
And so this algorithm
runs in linear time.
You can confirm that by
extrapolating a little bit by saying,
if we had a 6-element array and
we were looking for the number 5,
it might take 6 steps.
If we have a 7-element array and
we're looking for the number 5.
It might take 7 steps.
As we add one more element to our
array, it takes one more step.
That's a linear algorithm
in the worst-case.
>> Couple quick questions for you.
What's the runtime-- what's
the worst-case runtime
of this particular snippet of code?
So I have a 4 loop here that runs
from j equals 0, all the way up to m.
And what I'm seeing here, is that the
body of the loop runs in constant time.
So using the terminology that
we've already talked about-- what
would be the worst-case
runtime of this algorithm?
Take a second.
The inner part of the loop
runs in constant time.
And the outer part of the
loop is going to run m times.
So what's the worst-case runtime here?
Did you guess big-O of m?
You'd be right.
>> How about another one?
This time we have a
loop inside of a loop.
We have an outer loop
that runs from zero to p.
And we have an inner loop that runs
from zero to p, and inside of that,
I state that the body the
loop runs in constant time.
So what's the worst-case runtime
of this particular snippet of code?
Well, again, we have an
outer loop that runs p times.
And each time-- iteration
of that loop, rather.
We have an inner loop
that also runs p times.
And then inside of that, there's the
constant time-- little snippet there.
>> So if we have an outer loop that
runs p times inside of which is
an inner loop that
runs p times-- what is
the worst-case runtime
of this snippet of code?
Did you guess big-O of p squared?
>> I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.