DOUG LLOYD: So in CS50, we've covered
a lot of different data structures,
right?
We've seen arrays, and linked
lists, and hash tables,
and tries, stacks and queues.
We'll also learn a little
about trees and heaps,
but really these all just end
up being variations on a theme.
There really are these
kind of four basic ideas
that everything else can boil down to.
Arrays, linked lists,
hash tables, and tries.
And like I said, there
are variations on them,
but this is pretty
much going to summarize
everything we're going to talk
about in this class in terms of C.
>> But how do these all measure up, right?
We've talked about the pros and cons
of each in separate videos on them,
but there's a lot of numbers
getting thrown around.
There's a lot of general
thoughts getting thrown around.
Let's try and consolidate
it into just one place.
Let's weigh the pros against
the cons, and consider
which data structure
might be the right data
structure for your particular situation,
whatever kind of data you're storing.
You don't necessarily always need to
use the super fast insertion, deletion,
and lookup of a trie if you really
don't care about inserting and deleting
too much.
If you need just quickly random
access, maybe an array is better.
So let's distill that.
Let's talk about each of the four
major kinds of data structures
that we've talked about, and
just see when they might be good,
and when they might not be so good.
So let's start with arrays.
So insertion, that's kind of bad.
>> Insertion at the end of an array is OK,
if we're building an array as we go.
But if we need to insert
elements into the middle,
think back to insertion
sort, there's a lot
of shifting to fit an element in there.
And so if we're going to insert
anywhere but the end of an array,
that's probably not so great.
>> Similarly, deletion, unless we're
deleting from the end of an array,
is probably also not so great if
we don't want to leave empty gaps,
which usually we don't.
We want to remove an element, and
then sort of make it snug again.
And so deleting elements from
an array, also not so great.
>> Lookup, though, is great.
We have random access,
constant time lookup.
We just say seven, and we go
to array relocation seven.
We say 20, with go to
array relocation 20.
We don't have to iterate across.
That's pretty good.
>> Arrays are also relatively easy to sort.
Every time we talked about a sorting
algorithm, such as selection sort,
insertion sort, bubble sort, merge
sort, we always used arrays to do it,
because arrays are pretty easy to
sort, relative to the data structures
we've seen so far.
>> They're also relatively small.
There's not a lot of extra space.
You just set aside exactly as much
as you need to hold your data,
and that's pretty much it.
So they're pretty small
and efficient in that way.
But another downside, though,
is that they are fixed in size.
We have to declare exactly how
big we want our array to be,
and we only get one shot at it.
We can't grow and shrink it.
>> If we need to grow or shrink it, we
need to declare an entirely new array,
copy all of the elements of the
first array into the second array.
And if we miscalculated that
time, we need to do it again.
Not so great.
So arrays don't give us the flexibility
to have variable numbers of elements.
>> With a linked list,
insertion is pretty easy.
We just tack onto the front.
Deletion is also pretty easy.
We have to find the elements.
That involve some searching.
>> But once you've found the element
you're looking for, all you need to do
is change a pointer,
possibly two if you have
a linked list-- a doubly
linked list, rather--
and then you can just free the node.
You don't have to shift
everything around.
You just change two pointers,
so that's pretty quick.
>> Lookup is bad though, right?
In order for us to find an
element in a linked list,
whether singly or doubly linked,
we have to linear search it.
We have to start at the beginning and
move the end, or start at the end move
to the beginning.
We don't have random access anymore.
So if we're doing a
lot of searching, maybe
a linked list isn't
quite so good for us.
>> They're also really
difficult to sort, right?
The only way you can
really sort a linked list
is to sort it as you construct it.
But if you sort it as you
construct it, you're no longer
making quick insertions anymore.
You're not just tacking
things onto the front.
You have to find the
right spot to put it,
and then your insertion
becomes just about as bad
as inserting into an array.
So linked lists are not
so great for sorting data.
>> They're also pretty small, size-wise.
Doubly linked list slightly
larger than singly linked lists,
which are slightly larger
than arrays, but it's not
a huge amount of wasted space.
So if space is at a premium, but
not a really intense premium,
this might be the right way to go.
>> Hash tables.
Insertion into a hash table
is fairly straightforward.
It's a two-step process.
First we need to run our data through
a hash function to get a hash code,
and then we insert the element into the
hash table at that hash code location.
>> Deletion, similar to linked list,
is easy once you find the element.
You have to find it first,
but then when you delete it,
you just need to exchange
a couple of pointers,
if you're using separate chaining.
If you're using probing,
or if you're not
using chaining at all
in your hash table,
deletion is actually really easy.
All you need to do is hash the
data, and then go to that location.
And assuming you don't
have any collisions,
you'll be able to delete very quickly.
>> Now, lookup is where things
get a little more complicated.
It's on average better
than linked lists.
If you're using chaining,
you still have a linked list,
which means you still have the
search detriment a linked list.
But because you're taking your linked
list and splitting it over 100 or 1,000
or n elements in your hash table, you're
linked lists are all one nth the size.
They're all substantially smaller.
You have n linked lists instead
of one linked list of size n.
>> And so this real-world constant
factor, which we generally
don't talk about in time complexity, it
does actually make a difference here.
So lookup is still linear
search if you're using chaining,
but the length of the list
you're searching through
is very, very short by comparison.
Again, if sorting is your
goal here, hash table's
probably not the right way to go.
Just use an array if sorting
is really important to you.
>> And they can run the gamut of size.
It's hard to say whether a
hash table is small or big,
because it really depends on
how large your hash table is.
If you're only going to be storing
five elements in your hash table,
and you have a hash table
with 10,000 elements in it,
you're probably wasting a lot of space.
Contrast being you can also
have very compact hash tables,
but the smaller your hash table gets,
the longer each of those linked lists
gets.
And so there's really no way to define
exactly the size of a hash table,
but it's probably safe
to say it's generally
going to be bigger than a linked
list storing the same data,
but smaller than a trie.
>> And tries are the fourth
of these structures
that we've been talking about.
Inserting into a trie is complex.
There's a lot of dynamic
memory allocation,
especially at the beginning,
as you're starting to build.
But it's constant time.
It's only the human element
here that makes it tricky.
Having to encounter null pointer, malloc
space, go there, possibly malloc space
from there again.
The sort of intimidation factor of
pointers in dynamic memory allocation
is the hurdle to clear.
But once you've cleared it, insertion
actually comes quite simple,
and it certainly is constant time.
>> Deletion is easy.
All you need to do is navigate down a
couple of pointers and free the node,
so that's pretty good.
Lookup is also pretty fast.
It's only based on the
length of your data.
So if all of your data is
five character strings,
for example, you're storing five
character strings in your trie,
it only takes five steps to
find what you're looking for.
Five is just a constant factor, so
again, insertion, deletion, and lookup
here are all constant time, effectively.
>> Another thing is that your trie is
actually kind of already sorted, right?
By virtue of how we're
inserting elements,
by going letter by letter of the
key, or digit by digit of the key,
typically, your trie ends up being
kind of sorted as you build it.
It doesn't really makes
sense to think about sorting
in the same way we think about
it with arrays, or linked lists,
or hash tables.
But in some sense, your
trie is sorted as you go.
>> The downside, of course, is that
a trie rapidly becomes huge.
From every junction point, you might
have-- if your key consists of digits,
you have 10 other
places you can go, which
means that every node
contains information
about the data you want to store
at that node, plus 10 pointers.
Which, on CS50 IDE, is 80 bytes.
So it's at least 80 bytes for
every node that you create,
and that's not even counting data.
And if your nodes are
letters instead of digits,
now you have 26 pointers
from every location.
And 26 times 8 is probably 200
bytes, or something like that.
And you have capital
and lowercase-- you can
see where I'm going with this, right?
Your nodes can get really
big, and so the trie
itself, overall, can
get really big, too.
So if space is at a high
premium on your system,
a trie might not be the right way to
go, even though its other benefits
come into play.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.