>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DOUG LLOYD: All right.
Kind of a strange topic, right?
Magic numbers.
What doe he mean when he's
talking about magic numbers?
Well, some of the programs
that we've written in CS50
so far have had some weird
numbers kind of thrown in them.
Perhaps for reasons we don't
entirely understand right now.
For example, in the Mario problem, we
capped the height of the pyramid at 23.
We explicitly said you
can't go higher than 23.
>> But what does 23 mean?
Well, if you read the
spec carefully, you
might have seen that the
reason we capped it at 23
is because the standard height
of a terminal window is 24.
And so if we have the
pyramid be taller than that,
it might do this weird thing
where it runs off the screen.
And you know, what does
that mean in context, right?
>> Is the meaning of 23 immediately obvious
to somebody who looks at your program
and maybe has a different
size terminal window?
Probably not.
It seems like, OK.
Well, why is it just less than 23?
In general, it's kind
of a bad habit actually
to write constants into your code.
In doing so, when you actually do
write a constant into your code,
it's sometimes referred to as using
magic numbers, which is something
we generally want to try and avoid.
>> For example, let's take a look
at this simple function here.
Obviously there's no data
type in C called card or deck.
So just bear with me.
It's a little bit of
pseudocode mixed in here.
This is a function called
deal card that apparently
takes a deck as its parameter, and
will output to me a single card.
>> And I'm doing something here where I
have a loop that runs from 0 to 52,
and I deal a card.
Well, we've got a magic
number in here, right.
Do you see what the magic number is?
Or more importantly, do you
see what the problem is here?
Particularly if this
is just one function
in its own file in a
folder that contains
a bunch of different
files, each of which
does another thing to a deck of cards.
Maybe it shuffles them, or deals a hand
of five cards instead of a single card.
>> Do you see what the
problem could be here?
Do you see the magic number
I've injected into the code?
It's 52, right.
>> Like, intuitively you probably know, OK.
Like a standard deck of
cards contains 52 cards.
But in our program, it's just
kind of floating around in there.
It's like all of a sudden there's a 52.
>> One way to resolve this
problem is to do this.
We're very explicitly now
calling out the deck size as 52.
It gives it a little more intuitive
meaning when in the for loop
later on we then say, i
is less than deck size.
It just seems better than saying 52.
Now this does actually fix the problem.
It does give some symbolic
meaning to the constant.
But it does kind of actually
introduce another problem
that might not be immediately apparent.
Even if this variable
is declared globally--
do you recall what it
means when we declare
a variable globally versus locally?
Even if we declare a variable
globally, what if there's
another function in
our suite of functions
that deal with card manipulation
that inadvertently changes deck size,
or it increases it by
1 or decreases it by 1.
That could spell trouble, right?
Especially if we're dealing with a set
of cards where shuffling the full deck
is required.
If deck size is decreased
by 1, for example, to 51,
we're not actually shuffling
all the cards possibly.
We're leaving one of them out.
And that value could perhaps be
predicted or exploited by a bad actor.
>> C provides what's called a
preprocessor directive, which
is also called a macro for
creating symbolic constants.
And in fact, you've already
seen a preprocessor directive,
even if you haven't heard it
called that with #include.
It's another example of a macro
or preprocessor directive.
>> The way to create symbolic constants,
or giving a name to a constant
so that it has more
meaning, is as follows.
#define, name, replacement.
Really important aside
here really quick.
Don't put a semicolon at
the end of your #defines.
So it's #define, name, replacement.
>> When your program is compiled,
what actually happens
is the compiler if going
to go through your code
and replace every instance of
the word "name" with whatever you
put as replacement.
Analogously, if #include is sort
of similar to copying and pasting,
then #define is sort of
similar to find and replace,
if you've ever used that feature in a
word processing program, for example.
>> So for example, if I
#define pi as 3.14159265,
if you're better mathematically
inclined and you suddenly
see 3.14159265 flying
around in your code,
you probably know it's talking about pi.
But maybe we can give it a
little more symbolic meaning.
And we can instead say #define
pi as that mouthful of numbers
that I'm not going to keep
reading over and over.
>> And what's going to happen then at
compile time is when the program is
compiled, the first thing that
will happen is it will go through
and it will replace every time
it sees capital P, capital I,
it'll literally replace it with
3.14 and so on, so that you
don't have to type it every
time while your program still
has the functionality that you
expect, because you're working
with manipulating, multiplying,
dividing, whatever it is by pi.
>> You are not limited to this
substitution for numbers only.
For example, I could #define
course as the string CS50.
In this case, when the
program is compiled,
#define will go through the
code, replace every time
it sees "course" with the string CS50.
>> You'll notice here
also that I frequently
#define all my defined symbolic
constants, so to speak,
are always in all caps.
It's a convention.
It's not required.
The reason generally people will use
all capitals when they're #defining
is just to make it really clear that
this particular element of my code
is a defined constant.
If it was lowercase, it's possible that
it might be confused with a variable.
And that's probably
not a good thing to do.
>> So this particular
solution is much better
than either of the previous ones.
If I first #define deck size 52, then
now my use of 52, or deck size here,
is a lot more intuitive and a lot safer.
You can't manipulate a constant.
You can't say 52 plus plus.
That's not going to convert it to 53.
You can't change 52 to something.
>> You can change a variable
whose value is 52,
which was the first fix we had before.
And you could increase
that variable to 53.
But you can't say 52 plus plus and
have that suddenly turn 52 into 53.
52 is always 52.
And so you can't inadvertently change
deck size here by manipulating it,
>> Another good side
effect of this though is
that are you aware that not
all countries around the world
use a deck of cards of size 52?
For example, it's really common in
Germany to use a deck size of 32,
where they strip out some
of the lower value cards.
And in this case, I
wanted to port my suite
of functions that deal with
card manipulation to Germany.
I could in the first instance we
showed, have to go and replace
all instances of 52 in my code with 32.
>> But here, if I #define deck size
as 32 at the very top of my code,
if I need to change it, I can
just go and change that one thing.
Recompile my code, and all of
a sudden it propagates through.
In fact, we can change deck
size to any value we want.
>> Can I interest you in a
game of deck size pickup?
>> I'm Doug Lloyd.
And this is CS50.