>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DOUG LLOYD: OK, so a merge
sort is yet another algorithm
that we can use to sort out
the elements of an array.
But as we'll see, it's got a
very fundamental difference
from selection sort, bubble
sort, and insertion sort
that make it really pretty clever.
>> The basic idea behind merge
sort is to sort smaller arrays
and then combine those arrays
together, or merge them--
hence the name-- in sorted order.
The way that merge sort does
this is by leveraging a tool
called recursion, which is what
we're going to be talking about soon,
but we haven't really talked about yet.
>> Here's the basic idea behind merge sort.
Sort the left half of the array,
assuming n is greater than 1.
And what I mean when I say
assuming n is greater than 1 is,
I think we can agree that if an array
only consists of a single element,
it's sorted.
We don't actually need
to do anything to it.
We can just declare it to be sorted.
It's only a single element.
>> So the pseudocode, again, is
sort the left half of the array,
then sort the right half the array,
then merge the two halves together.
Now, already you might be
thinking, it kind of just
sounds like you're putting off the--
you're not actually doing anything.
You're saying sort the left
half, sort the right half,
but you're not telling
me how you're doing it.
>> But remember that as long as
an array is a single element,
we can declare it sorted.
Then we can just combine them together.
And that's actually the
fundamental idea behind merge sort,
is to break it down so that
your arrays are of size one.
And then you rebuild from there.
>> Merge sort is definitely
a complicated algorithm.
And it's also a little
complicated to visualize.
So hopefully, the visualization that I
have here will help you follow along.
And I'll try my best to narrate things
and proceed through this a little more
slowly than the other ones
just to hopefully get your head
around the ideas behind merge sort.
>> So we have the same array as the
other sorting algorithm videos
if you've seen them--
a six element array.
And our pseudocode code here is sort
the left half, sort the right half,
merge the two halves together.
So let's take this very dark brick red
array and sort the left half of it.
>> So for the time being, we're going
to ignore the stuff on the right.
It's there, but we're
not at that step yet.
We're not at sort the
right half of the array.
We're at sort the left
half of the array.
And just for the sake
of being a little more
clear, so I can refer
to what step we're on,
I'm going to switch the
color of this set to orange.
Now, we're still talking about the
same left half of the original array.
But I'm hoping that by being able to
refer to the colors of various items,
it'll make it a little more
clear what's going on here.
>> OK, so now we have a
three element array.
How do we sort the left half of this
array, which is still this step?
We're trying to sort the left
half of the brick red array--
the left half of which
I've now colored orange.
>> Well, we could try and
repeat this process again.
So we're still in the
middle of trying to sort
the left half of the full array.
The left half of the
array, I'm just going
to arbitrarily decide that the left half
will be smaller than the right half,
because this happens to
consist of three elements.
>> And so I'm going to say that the
left half of the left half the array
is just the element five.
Five, being a single element
array, we know how to sort it.
And so five is sorted.
We're just going to declare that.
It's a single element array.
>> So we've now sorted the
left half of the left half--
or rather, we've sorted the
left half of the orange.
So now, in order to still complete
the overall array's left half,
we need to sort the right half
of the orange, or this stuff.
How do we do that?
Well, we have a two element array.
So we can sort the left half
of the array, which is two.
Two is a single element.
So it's sorted by default.
Then we can sort the right half
of that portion of the array, the one.
That's sort of by default.
>> This is now the first time
we've reached a merge step.
We have completed, although
we're now kind of nested down--
and that's sort of the tricky
thing with recursion is,
you need to keep your
head about where we are.
So we've sort of the left
half of the orange portion.
>> And now, we're in the middle of sorting
the right half of the orange portion.
And in that process, we are
now about to be on the step,
merge the two halves together.
When we look at the two halves
of the array, we see two and one.
Which element is smaller?
One.
>> Then which element is smaller?
Well, it's two or nothing.
So it's two.
So now, just to again frame
where we are in context,
we have sorted the
left half of the orange
and the right half of the origin.
I know I've changed the colors
again, but that's where we were.
And the reason I did this
is because this process is
going to keep going, iterating down.
We've sorted the left
half of the former orange
and the right half of the former orange.
>> Now, we need to merge those
two halves together too.
That's the step we're on.
So we consider all of the
elements that are now green,
the left half of the original array.
And we merge those
using the same process
we did for merging two
and one just a moment ago.
>> The left half, the smallest
element on the left half is five.
The smallest element on
the right half is one.
Which of those is smaller?
One.
>> The smallest element on
the left half is five.
The smallest element on
the right half is two.
What's the smallest?
Two.
And then lastly five and
nothing, we can say five.
>> OK, so big picture, let's
take a break for a second
and figure out where we are.
If we started from
the very beginning, we
have now completed for
the overall array just
one step of the pseudocode code here.
We have sorted the
left half of the array.
>> Recall that the original
order was five, two, one.
By going through this process
and nesting down and repeating,
continuing to break the problem
down into smaller and smaller parts,
we have now completed
step one of the pseudocode
for the entire starting array.
We have sorted its left half.
>> So now let's freeze there.
And now let's sort the right
half of the original array.
And we're going to do that by
going through the same iterative
process of breaking things down
and then merging them together.
>> So the left half of the
red, or the left half
of the right half of the original
array, I'm going to say is three.
Again, I'm being consistent here.
If you have an odd
number of elements, it
doesn't really matter whether
you make the left one smaller
or the right one smaller.
>> What matters is that whenever you
encounter this problem in conducting
a merge, you need to be consistent.
You either always need to
make a left side smaller
or always need to make
the right side smaller.
Here, I've chosen to always
make the left side smaller
when my array, or my
sub-array, is of an odd size.
>> Three is a single element,
and so it is sorted.
We've leveraged that assumption
throughout our entire process so far.
So now let's sort the right
half of the right half,
or the right half of the red.
>> Again, we need to split this down.
This is not a single element array.
We can't declare it sorted.
And so first, we're going
to sort the left half.
>> The left half is a single element,
so it's sort of by default.
Then we're going to sort the right
half, which is a single element.
It's sorted by default. And now,
we can merge those two together.
Four is smaller, and
then six is smaller.
>> Again, what have we done at this point?
We've sorted the left
half of the right half.
Or going back to the original
colors that were there,
we've sorted the left
half of the softer red.
It was originally a dark brick
red and now it's a softer red,
or it was a softer red.
>> And then we've sorted the
right half of the softer red.
Now, well, they're green again, just
because we're going through a process.
And we have to repeat
this over and over.
>> So now we can merge those
two halves together.
And that's what we do here.
So the black line just
divided the left half
and the right half of this sort part.
>> We compare the smallest value
on the left side of the array--
or excuse me, the smallest
value of the left half
to the smallest value of the right
half and find that three is smaller.
And now a bit of an optimization, right?
There's actually nothing
left on the left side.
>> There's nothing remaining
on the left side,
so we can efficiently
just move-- we can declare
the rest of it is actually
sorted and just tack it
on, because there's nothing
else to compare against.
And we know that the right side
of the right side is sorted.
>> OK, so now let's freeze again and
figure out where we are in the story.
In the overall array,
what have we accomplished?
We've actually accomplish
now steps one and step two.
We sorted the left half, and
we sorted the right half.
>> So now, all that remains is for us
to merge those two halves together.
So we compare the lowest valued
element of each half of the array
in turn and proceed.
One is less than three, so one goes.
>> Two is less than three, so two goes.
Three is less than 5, so three goes.
Four is less than 5, so four goes.
Then five is less than six,
and six is all that remains.
>> Now, I know, that was a lot of steps.
And we've left a lot
of memory in our wake.
And that's what those gray squares are.
And it probably felt like that took a
lot longer than insertion sort, bubble
sort, or selection sort.
>> But actually, because a
lot of these processes
are happening at the same time--
which is something we'll, again,
talk about when we talk about
recursion in a future video--
this algorithm actually
clearly is fundamentally
different than anything
we have seen before
but is also significantly
more efficient.
>> Why is that?
Well, in the worst
case scenario, we have
to split n elements up
and then recombine them.
But when we recombine
them, what we're doing
is basically doubling the
size of the smaller arrays.
We have a bunch of one element
arrays that we effectively
combine into two element arrays.
And then we take those
two element arrays
and combine them together into
four element arrays, and so on,
and so on, and so on, until we
have a single n element array.
>> But how many doublings
does it take to get to n?
Think back to the phone book example.
How many times do we have to tear
the phone book in half, how many more
times do we have to tear the phone book
in half, if the size of the phone book
doubled?
There's just one, right?
>> So there's some sort of
logarithmic element here.
But we also still have to at least
look at all of the n elements.
So in the worst case scenario,
merge sort runs in n log n.
We have to look at
all of the n elements,
and we have to combine them
together in log n sets of steps.
In the best case scenario,
the array is perfectly sorted.
That's great.
But based on the algorithm we have here,
we still have to split and recombine.
Although in this case, the
recombining is kind of ineffective.
It isn't needed.
But we still go through
the whole process anyway.
>> So in the best case
and in the worst case,
this algorithm runs in n log n time.
Merge sort is definitely a bit trickier
than the other main sorting algorithms
we've talked about CS50 but is
substantially more powerful.
>> And so if you ever find
occasion to need it
or to use it to sort a
large data set, getting
your head around the idea of recursion
is going to be really powerful.
And it's going to make your
programs really much more efficient
using merge sort versus anything else.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.