>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DOUG LLOYD: Hi, so let's
talk about operators in C.
So, we've already seen one, in fact,
equals the assignment operator.
It allows us to just put
a value into a variable.
That's the assignment
operator, single equal sign.
In order to manipulate and work
with values and variables in C,
we have a number of operators
at our disposal that we can use.
Let's take a look at
some of the common ones
starting with arithmetic operators.
As you might expect, we can do
pretty basic math operations in C.
We can add, subtract, multiply, and
divide numbers using plus, minus, star,
and slash, respectively.
Here's a couple of lines of
code in which we do that.
So, we have int x equals y plus 1.
Let's assume that somewhere
up above this line of code
we had said int y equals 10.
What's the value of x after I
execute this first line of code?
Did you say 11?
You'd right.
Why is that?
Well, y was 10.
Some I'm saying int x equals 10 plus 1.
10 plus 1 is 11.
So, the value 11 gets
stored in the variable x.
Not too bad, right?
>> How about this next line of
code? x equals x times 5.
Well, before we executed
this line of code, x was 11.
So, what is the value of
x after this line of code?
Take a second.
So, x equals x times 5.
x was 11.
So, x equals 11 times 5.
Or 55.
So if you said 55, you'd be right.
>> Now, it may be a little confusing, but
with the way that assignment works in C
is the value on the right gets
assigned to the value on the left.
So, first we evaluate x times 5.
So, 11 times 5 is 55.
And then we store that value in x.
The 11 that was there
before is now overwritten.
So x's value is now 55.
Hopefully that's fairly straightforward.
>> There's another operator that you've
probably not necessarily heard
called this, but you've
certainly worked with in the past
if you remember your days of long
division way back in grade school.
It's called the modulus operator.
What modulus does is it
gives you the remainder
when you divide two numbers together.
So, if I say 13 divided by
4, what's the remainder?
And that value would be calculated
by the modulus operator.
>> So, I have a line of code
here, int m equals 13 mod 4.
And I say here in a comment
that m's value is now 1.
Why do I say that?
Well, do the long division out in your
head, if you bear with me for a second.
So, I have 4 divided by 13.
4 goes into 13 three times
with a remainder of 1.
So, basically, all the
modulus operator does
is it tells you when you
divide, you get the remainder.
You might think that's actually
not a terribly useful thing,
but you'd be surprised, actually,
by how frequently that modulus
operator can come in handy.
>> There's a couple of problems
we'll do CS50 that deal with it.
It's also good for doing
things like random number.
So, for example if you've ever
heard of a random number generator,
that's going to give you a number
from 0 to some huge number.
But maybe you only really
need a number from 0 to 20.
If you use the modulus operator
on that giant number that
gets generated by the
random number generator,
you're going to take whatever
huge value it is, divide it by 20,
and get the remainder.
The remainder can only
be a value from 0 to 19.
So, you use modulus operator
to take this huge number
and whittle it down into something
a little more meaningful.
I'm pretty sure you'll be
able to use both of those
at some point in the future in CS50.
>> So, C also gives us a way
to apply an arithmetic
operator to a single variable
in a little more shorthand way.
So, in the previous slide,
we saw x equals x times 5.
That worked.
x times 5 then gets stored back in x.
There's a shorter way to do it, thought,
and it's the syntax x times equals 5.
It's the same exact thing as
saying x equals x times 5.
It's just a slightly
shorter way to do it.
And when you see some
distribution code or you
see some sample code that
does things like this,
just be familiar with
what the syntax means.
You certainly don't have
to use it, but if you do,
it might make your code
look a little slicker.
And know that you can also use any of
the different operators we've already
seen before instead of times.
You could say x plus equals 5, minus
equals 5, times, divide, and mod.
All of those work.
>> There's also something
that's so common in C
that we've decided to
refine that even further.
Incrementing a variable by 1
or decrementing a variable by 1
is such a common thing-- especially
when we talk about loops a little later
on-- that we've decided instead of
saying something like x plus equals 1,
or x equals x plus 1, we've even
short handed that to x plus plus.
So, x equals x plus 1, x plus equals 1,
and x plus plus all do the same thing.
They all increment x by 1.
But that incrementing
and decrementing by 1
is so common that we have
plus plus and minus minus
that allow us to shorthand
that even further.
>> So, let's switch gears for second
and talk about Boolean expressions.
All which are also kind of fall into
the overall category of operators.
But Boolean expressions,
unlike arithmetic operators,
are used for comparing values.
So, again, all Boolean expressions in C
evaluate to one of two possible values,
recall.
True or false.
That's the only two values that
Boolean variable can take on.
We can use the results
of a Boolean expression
in a lot of ways in programming.
In fact, you'll be
doing this quite a lot.
>> For example, we might decide,
well, if some condition is true,
maybe I'll take this
branch down my code.
A conditional, so to speak.
We'll learn about those soon too.
Or maybe, as long as
this is true, I want
to keep doing this
over and over and over.
A loop.
In both cases, know that we're using
a Boolean expression, a true or false,
to decide whether or not
to take a particular path.
Sometimes when we're working
with Boolean expressions,
we will use variables of type Bool.
You might have declared
a Bool typed variable,
and you'll use in your
Boolean expression.
But you don't always have to do.
As it turns out, in C, every non-0
value is the same as saying true.
If you had declared a
variable of type Boolean,
and assigned it the value true, that's
the same as declaring an integer
and assigning it the value
1, 2, 3, or really any value
whatsoever other than 0.
Because in C, every non-0 value is true.
0, on the other hand, is false.
This might come in
handy later on to know,
but just something to keep in mind.
We don't always have to use
Boolean type variables when we
are working with Boolean expressions.
>> There are two main types of Boolean
expressions that we'll work with.
Logical operators and
relational operators.
The language there is
not terribly important.
It's really just how I'm grouping them.
And you'll certainly, I think, quickly
realize what a relational operator is,
based on what they are when we
talk about them in a second.
But don't worry about necessarily
memorizing the term logical operator
or relational operator.
I'm just using it to group
them in a logical way.
>> So, let's take a look at
the three logical operators
that we'll see quite a
bit in programming in CS50
and in programming more generally.
Logical AND is true, if and
only if both operands are true.
Otherwise false.
Where does that mean?
So, let's say that I am at a
point in my code where I have
two variables, x and y.
And I want to decide whether
to do something in my code
based on if x is true and y is true.
I only want to do it if
both of them are true,
otherwise I don't want to go down that
path because it's not going to help me.
What I can say is if x & & y.
That will be a logical Boolean
expression comparing x and y
and taking a certain path
based on what their values are.
So, if x is true and y is true
based on this truth table here,
only then will we go down that path.
If x, & & y.
It's only true-- the and is only
true if x is true and y is true.
If either one is false,
as we see the truth table,
then both x and y are not true.
And so, x & & y is false.
>> Logical OR is true if and only
if at least one operand is true.
Otherwise false.
So logical AND required
both x and y to be true.
Logical OR requires x to be true or y
to be true or both x and y to be true.
So, again, we kind of find
ourselves in a situation
where we're going to our code,
and we reached a fork in the road.
And we want to go down a
particular path if x is true
or y is true, but not
necessarily if both are true.
But possibly if both are true.
So if x is true and y is
true, we'll go down that path.
x is true.
One of them is true, right?
If x is true and y is true.
If x is true, and y is false,
one of them is still true.
So, x or y is still true.
If x is false, and y is true,
one of them is still true, right?
y is true, in this case.
So, it's true that x or y is true.
Only if x is false and y is false
do we not go down that path,
because neither x nor y is true.
Now, if you're looking
at the screen right now
and wondering what that
symbol is for logical OR,
it's called the vertical bar.
And if you looking at your keyboard
for a minute, as I'm doing now,
it's usually just above the
Enter key, on most keyboards,
on the same key as the backslash.
It's also usually right
next to the square brackets.
So, it might be a key that you
haven't typed very much in the past.
But, if you're ever doing
logical comparisons,
as we'll be doing a
lot in the course, it's
going to be useful to
find that key and use it.
So, it's usually on the same key
as backslash just above Enter.
>> The final logical operator is NOT.
And NOT's pretty straightforward.
It inverts the value of its operand.
If x is true, then not x is false.
If x is false, then not x is true.
Sometimes you'll hear this symbol
pronounced as bang or exclamation
or not.
It's pretty much all the same thing.
In case you hear that spoken and
you're not sure what that means,
it's just the exclamation
point, but sometimes it's
called a couple different things.
All right, so that takes
care of logical operators.
So, let's talk about
relational operators.
Again, if you're familiar with this
arithmetic back in grade school,
you're probably familiar
with how these work already.
These behave exactly as you'd expect.
So less than it's true, in this
example, if x is less than y.
So, if x is 4 and y is
6, x is less than y.
That's true.
Less than or equal to
works pretty similarly.
If x is 4, and y is 4, then
x is less than or equal to y.
Greater than. x is greater than y.
And greater than or equal to, x
is greater than or equal to y.
If it's true, then you'll
pass that expression,
and you'll go down
that path on the road.
If you have an if x is greater than y,
and x is, in fact, is greater than y,
you'll do whatever is
subject to that condition.
>> Notice that we don't have a
single character for less than
or equal to, as you might be
familiar with from math textbooks.
So, we have the less than symbol,
followed by an equal sign.
That's how we represent
less than or equal to.
And similarly, do we do that
for greater than or equal to.
>> The final two relational
operators that are important
are testing for equality and inequality.
So, if x equals equals y, is true
if x and y's value is the same.
If x is 10, and y is 10, then
x equals equals y is true.
If x is 10 and y is 11, x
equals equals y is not true.
We can also test for inequality using
exclamation point or bang or NOT,
again.
If x is not equal to y, if
that's the test we're using here,
we'd be good to go.
So, if x is not equal to
y, we'll go down that path.
>> Be really careful here.
It's a really common mistake-- and
one I certainly made quite a lot when
I was getting started--
to accidentally mistake
the assignment operator, single equals,
for the equality comparison operator,
double equals.
It'll lead to some weird
behavior in your code,
and usually the compiler will
warn you about it when you try
and compile your code, but sometimes
you might be able to sneak it by.
It's not necessarily a good thing
that you sneak it by, though.
Just so if you are doing
an inequality test,
if you're checking whether two
different variables have the same value
inside of them, make sure to use
equals equals, and not single equals.
And that way your program will
have the behavior you intend.
I'm Doug Lloyd and this is CS50.