>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> ANDI PENG: Welcome to week 3 of section.
Thanks, you guys, for all coming
to this earlier start time today.
We've got a nice, little
intimate group today.
So hopefully we'll get to
finish, perhaps, early,
a little bit early today.
So quickly, just some
announcements for the agenda today.
Before we start, we're
going to just go over
some brief logistical issues, pset
questions, debrief, things like that.
And then we'll dive right in.
We'll use a debugger called GDB to
start debunking our code, which David
explained in lecture the other day.
We'll go over the four types of sorts.
We'll go over them pretty quickly
since they're pretty intensive.
But know that all the slides and
source code are always online.
So feel free, at your perusal, to
go back and take a look at that.
>> We'll go through
asymptotic notation, which
is just a fancy way
of saying "runtimes,"
where we have the big O, which
David explained in lecture.
And we also have Omega, which
is the lower bound runtime.
And we'll talk a bit more
in-depth regarding how those work.
And lastly, we'll go over binary search,
because a lot of you who have already
glanced at your psets probably know that
that is a question that's in your pset.
So you'll all be happy
that we cover this today.
>> And lastly, per your
section feedback, I actually
left about 15 minutes at
the end to just go over
logistics of pset3, any questions,
maybe a bit of guidance, if you will,
before we start programming.
So let's try to get through
the material pretty quickly.
And then we can spend some time
taking more questions for the pset.
OK.
>> Quickly, so just a few
announcements before we start today.
Firstly, welcome to making
it through two of your psets.
I took a look at your-- yeah, let's
get a round of applause for that one.
Actually, I was really,
really impressed.
I graded the first pset for you guys
last week and you guys did incredible.
>> Style was on point
besides a few comments.
Make sure you're always
commenting your code.
But your psets were on point.
And keep it up.
And it's good for the grader to
see that you guys are putting
in as much effort in your style
and your design in your code
that we would like for you to see.
So I'm passing along my gratitude
for the rest of the TAs.
>> However there are a
few debrief questions
I just want to go over that
would make both my life
and a lot of the other
TAs' lives a bit easier.
Firstly, I've noticed this
past week-- how many of you
have been running check50 on
your code before you submit?
OK.
So everyone should be doing check50,
because-- a secret-- we actually
run check50 as part of our correctness
scripts for testing your code.
So if your code is failing
check50, in all likelihood,
it's probably going to
fail our check as well.
Sometimes you guys
have the right answers.
Like, in greedy, some of
you have the right numbers,
you just print out some extra stuff.
And that extra stuff
actually fails the check,
because the computer doesn't
really know what it's looking for.
And so it will just run through,
see that your output doesn't
match what we expect the answer
to be, and mark it is wrong.
>> And I know that happened in
some of your cases this week.
So I went back and manually
regraded everyone's code.
In the future though,
please, please make sure
that you're running
check 50 on your code.
Because it's kind of a pain for the TA
to have to go back and manually regrade
every single pset for every
single, little missed instance.
So I didn't take off any points.
I think I took off maybe
one or two for design.
In the future though, if
you're failing check50,
points will be taken
off for correctness.
>> Furthermore, psets are
due Fridays at noon.
I think there's a seven-minute
late grace period that we give you.
Per Harvard time, they're allowed to
be seven minutes late to everything.
So here at Yale, we'll
adhere to that as well.
But pretty much, at 12:07,
if your pset is not in,
it's going to be marked as late.
And so while it is marked
as late, the TA-- I'm
still going to be grading your psets.
So you'll still see a grade appear.
However, know that at
the end of the semester,
all late psets will just be
automatically zeroed by the computer.
>> We do this for two reasons.
One, sometimes we get
excused, like dean's excuses,
later on that I don't know about yet.
So we like to make sure we're grading
everything just in case, like, I'm
missing a dean's excuse.
And secondly, keep in
mind, you can still
drop one pset that
has full scope points.
And so we like to grade
all of your psets just
to make sure that your scope's
there and you're trying them.
So even if it's late, you'll still
get credit for scope points, I think.
>> So moral of the story is, make
sure your psets are in on-time.
And if they aren't in on-time,
know that it's not great.
Yeah, before I move on, does anyone have
any questions regarding pset feedback?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Did you say we
can drop one of the psets?
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So there's nine psets overall
over the course of the semester.
And if you have scope
points-- so scope is just,
pretty much, are you attempting the
problem, are you putting in time,
are you showing that you've
demonstrated you've read the spec.
That's pretty much scope.
And if you are fulfilling
scope points, we
can drop the lowest
one out of full scope.
So that's in your advantage to
complete and try every pset.
>> Even upload-- if none of
them work, upload them all.
And then we'll hopefully be able to
give you some of those points back.
Cool.
Any other questions?
Great.
>> Secondly, office hours-- a few
quick notes about office hours.
So first, come early in the week.
No one is ever at
office hours on Mondays.
Christabel came to
office hours last night.
Yeah, Christabel.
And what did we have at office
hours last night, Christabel?
>> AUDIENCE: We had ice cream.
>> ANDI PENG: So that's right, we had
ice cream at office hours last night.
While I can't promise you that
we'll have ice cream at office hours
every week, what I can promise you
is that there will be a significantly
better student to TA ratio.
Like legit, it's like three to one.
Whereas, contrast that with
Thursday, you've got about 150
really stressed kids and no ice cream.
And it's just not productive for anyone.
So moral of the story is, come early
to office hours and good things
will happen.
>> Also, come prepared to ask questions.
You know?
Regardless of what TAs, I
think, have been saying,
we've been getting a couple students
who come in on Thursday at, like, 10:50
not having read the spec
being like help me, help me.
Unfortunately at that point, there's
not much we can do to help you.
So please come early in the week.
Come early to office hours.
Come prepared to ask questions.
Make sure that you, as
a student, are where
you need to be so that the
TAs can guide you along,
which is what office hours
should be allotted for.
>> Secondly, so I know professors
like to surprise us with tests.
I had a professor those
like, yo, by the way,
remember that midterm
you have next Monday.
Yeah, I didn't know about that midterm.
So I'm going to be that TA
that reminds you all that quiz
0-- because, you know, we're CS.
Now that we've done arrays, you get
why it's quiz 0, not quiz 1, eh?
OK.
Oh, I got some chuckles on that one.
>> So quiz 0 will be October 14 if
you're in the Monday-Wednesday section
and October 15 if you're in
the Tuesday-Thursday section.
This does not apply for
those of you at Harvard
who-- I think you'll all be
taking your quizzes on the 14th.
>> So yeah, next week, if
David, in lecture, goes,
yeah, so about that
quiz next week, you all
won't be shocked because
you came to section
and you know that your
quiz 0 is in two weeks.
And we'll have review
sessions and everything.
So no worries about
being scared for that.
Any questions before-- any questions
at all regarding logistical issues,
grading, office hours, sections?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: So the quiz is
going to be during lecture?
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So the quiz, I think, is 60
minutes allotted in that time slot
that you'll just take
in the lecture hall.
So you don't have to come in
on, like, a random 7:00 PM.
It's all good.
Yeah.
Cool.
>> All right.
So we're going to
introduce a concept to you
this week that David has already kind
of touched on in lecture this past week.
It's called GDB.
And how many of you, while in
the course of writing your psets,
have noticed a big button that says
"Debug" on the top of your IDE?
OK.
So now we'll actually get to unearth
the mystery of what that button actually
does.
And I guarantee you, it is a
beautiful, beautiful thing.
>> So up until now, I think
there's been two things
students have been typically
doing when debugging psets.
One, they either add in
printf()-- so every few lines,
they add in a printf()--
oh, what is this variable?
Oh, what is this variable now--
and you kind of see the progression
of your code as it runs.
Or the second method kids do is
that they just write the whole thing
and then go like this at the end.
Hopefully it works.
I guarantee you, GDB is better
than both of those methods.
Yeah.
So this will be your new best friend.
Because it's a beautiful thing
that visually displays both
what your code is doing
at a specific point
as well as what all of your
variables are carrying,
like what their values are,
at that specific point.
And in this way, you can really
set breakpoints in your code.
You can run through line by line.
And GDB will just have for
you, displayed for you,
what all of your variables
are, what are they doing,
what's going on in the code.
And in such a way, it's
so much easier to see
what's happening instead of printf-ing
or writing down your statements.
>> So we'll do an example of this later.
So this seems a bit abstract.
No worries, we'll do examples.
And so essentially, the three largest,
most-used functions you'll need in GDB
are the Next, Step over,
and Step into buttons.
I'm going to head over
there, actually, right now.
>> So can you guys all see that
or should I zoom in a bit?
In the back, can you see that?
Should I zoom in?
Just a little bit?
OK, cool.
There we go.
OK.
>> So I have, here, my
implementation for greedy.
And while a lot of you guys wrote
greedy in while loop form-- that
is a perfectly acceptable way to do
it-- another way to do it is to simply
divide in the modulo.
Because then you can have your
value and then have your remainder.
And then you can just
add it all together.
Does the logic of what I'm doing
here make sense to everyone,
before we begin?
Kind of?
Cool.
Great.
It's a pretty sexy piece
of code, I would say.
Like I said, David, in
lecture, after a while,
you'll all start seeing code
as something that's beautiful.
And sometimes when you see beautiful
code, it's such a wonderful feeling.
>> So however, whilst this code is very
beautiful, it does not work properly.
So let's run check50 on this.
Check 50 20-- oop.
2?
Is that pset2?
Yeah.
Oh, pset1.
OK.
So we run check50.
>> And as you guys can see here,
it's failing a couple of cases.
And for some of you, in the
course of doing your problem sets,
you're like, ah, why isn't it working.
Why is it working for some
values but not for others?
Well, GDB is going to help you figure
out why those inputs were not working.
>> OK.
So let's see, one of the
checks I was failing in check50
was the input value of 0.41.
So the correct answer that
you should be getting is a 4.
But instead what I am printing out
is the 3-n, which is incorrect.
So let's just run this manually, just
make sure that check50 is working.
Let's do ./greedy.
Oops, I have to make greedy.
There we go.
Now ./greedy.
>> How much is owed?
Let's do 0.41.
And yep, we see here
that it's outputting 3
when the correct answer,
in fact, should be 4.
So let's enter GDB and see how we
can go about fixing this problem.
>> So the first step in
always debugging your code
is to set a breakpoint,
or a point at which you
want the computer or the
debugger to start looking at.
So if you don't really
know what your problem is,
usually, the typical thing we want to
do is to set our breakpoint at main.
So if you guys can see this
red button right there,
yep, that was me setting a
breakpoint for the main function.
I click that.
>> And then I can go up to my Debug button.
I hit that button.
Let me zoom back out if I can.
There we go.
So we have, here, a panel on the right.
I'm sorry, guys in the back, you
can't really see really well.
But essentially, all
this right panel is doing
is keeping track of both the highlighted
line, which is the line of code
that the computer is currently running,
as well as all of your variables
down here.
>> So you've got cents, coins, n,
all declared to different things
at this point.
No worries, because we haven't actually
initialized them to any variables yet.
So in your computer, your
computer's just seeing,
oh, 32767 was the last used function
of that memory space in my computer.
And so that's where cents currently is.
But no that once you run the code,
it should become initialized.
>> So let's go through, line by
line, what's going on here.
OK.
So up here are the three
buttons that I just explained.
You have the Play, or the Run function,
button, you have the Step over button,
and you also have the Step into button.
And essentially, all three of
them just go through your code
and do different things.
>> So typically, when you're debugging,
we don't want to just hit Play,
because Play will just run
your code to the end of it.
And then you won't actually
know what your problem
is unless you set multiple breakpoints.
If you set multiple breakpoints,
it will just automatically
run from one breakpoint,
to the next, to the next.
But in this case we've
just that one, because we
want to work our way
from top down to bottom.
So we're going to ignore that button
right now for purposes of this program.
>> So the Step over function just
steps over every single line
and tells you what
the computer is doing.
The Step into function goes
into the actual function
that's on your line of code.
So for example, like printf(),
that is a function, right?
If I wanted to physically step
into the printf() function,
I would actually go into the piece of
code where printf() was written and see
what's going on there.
>> But typically, we assume that
the code that we give you works.
We assume the printf() is working.
We assume that GetInt() is working.
So there's no need to
step into those functions.
But if there's functions
that you write yourself
that you want to check
out what's going on,
you would want to step
into that function.
>> So right now we're just going
to step over this piece of code.
So let's see.
Oh, print, "Oh hai, how
much change is owed?"
We don't care.
We know that's working,
so we step over it.
>> So n, which is our float that
we've initialized-- or declared--
up at the top, we're now
equalling that to GetFloat().
So let's step over that.
And we see at the
bottom here, the program
is prompting me to input a value.
So let's input the value we want
to test here, which is 0.41.
Great.
>> So now n-- do you guys see
here, at the bottom-- it's
stored-- because we
haven't rounded yet, it's
stored in this like giant
float that is 0.4099999996,
which is close enough to our
purposes, right now, to 0.41.
And then we'll see later on, as we
continue stepping over the program,
after here, n has become
rounded and cents has become 41.
Great.
So we know that our rounding's working.
We know that we have the
correct number of cents,
so we know that that's
not really the problem.
>> So we continue stepping
on in this program.
We go here.
And so after this line of code, we
should know how many quarters we have.
We step over.
And you see we do, in fact, have one
quarter because we've subtracted 25
from our initial value of 41.
And we have 16 left for our cents.
>> Does everyone understand how
the program is stepping through
and why cents has now become 16
and why, now, coins has become 1?
Is everyone following that logic?
Cool.
So as of this point, the
program's working, right?
We know it's doing exactly
what we want it to.
And we didn't actually
have to print out, oh, what
is cents at this point,
what is coins at this point.
>> We continue going through the program.
Step over.
Cool.
We go over dimes.
Great.
We see that it's taken
off $0.10 for a dime.
And now we have two coins.
That's correct.
>> We go over pennies and we see
that we've got left over cents.
Hmm, that's strange.
Up here at the program, I was supposed
to have subtracted my pennies.
Perhaps I just wasn't
doing that line right.
And alas, you can see
here, because we know
that we are stepping
through lines 32 and 33,
that's where our program
improperly had variables run.
So we can look and see, oh,
I'm subtracting cents here,
but I'm not actually
adding to my coin value.
I'm adding to cents.
And I don't want to add to
cents, I want to add to coins.
So if we change that to coins,
we've got a working program.
I can run check50.
You can just exit out of GDB right
here and then run check50 again.
I could just do this.
I have to make greedy.
0.41.
And here, it's printing
out the right answer.
>> So as you guys can see, GDB
is a really powerful tool
for when we have so much code
going on and so many variables
that it's hard for us, as
a human, to keep track of.
The computer, in the GDB
debugger, has the ability
to keep track of everything.
I know, in Visionaire, you guys probably
might have hit some segmentation faults
because you were running
out of bounds of your array.
In the example of Caesar, that's
exactly what I've implemented here.
>> So I forgot to check for
what would happen if I
didn't have two command line arguments.
I just didn't put in that check.
And so if I run Debug-- I set
my breakpoint to right there.
I run Debug.
>> OK.
Yeah.
So actually, GDB was supposed
to have told me there
was a segmentation fault there.
I don't know what was going on
right there, but when I ran it,
it was working.
When you run lines of code through and
GDB might just suddenly quit on you,
go up and look what the red error is.
It'll tell you, hey, you
had a segmentation fault,
which means that you tried to access
space in an array that didn't exist.
Yeah.
>> So in the next problem
set this week, you guys
will probably have a lot of
variables floating around.
You're not going to be sure what
they all mean at a certain point.
So GDB will really help you in figuring
out what they are all equalling
and being able to see that visually.
Is anyone confused on how
any of that was working?
Cool.
All right.
So after that, we are
going to dive right
into are four different
types of sorts for this week.
How many of you, first
of all, before we start,
have read the entire spec for pset3?
OK.
I'm proud of you guys.
That's like half of the class, which
is significantly more than last time.
>> So that's great, because when
we talk about the content
in lecture-- or sorry,
in section-- I like
to relate a lot of that
back to what the pset is
and how you want to
implement that in your pset.
So if you come having
read the spec, it'll
be a lot easier for you to understand
what I'm talking about when I say,
oh hey, this might be a really
good place to implement this sort.
So those of you who have read the
spec know that, as part of your pset,
you're going to have to
write a type of sort.
So this may be very helpful
for a lot of you today.
>> So we'll start off with,
essentially, the most simple type
of sort, the selection sort.
The typical algorithm for
how we'd go about this
is-- David went through these all in
lecture, so I'll quickly move along
here-- is essentially, you
have an array of values.
And then you find the
smallest unsorted value
and you swap that value with
the first unsorted value.
And then you just keep repeating
with the rest of your list.
>> And here's a visual explanation
of how that would work.
So for example, if we were to start
with an array of five elements, index
0 to 4, with 3, 5, 2, 6, and 4 values
placed in the array-- so right now,
we're just going to assume
that they're all unsorted
because we haven't tested otherwise.
>> So how a selection sort would
work is that it would first
run through the entirety
of the unsorted array.
It would pick out the smallest value.
In this case, 3, right
now, is the smallest.
It gets to 5.
Nope, 5 is not greater than--
or sorry, is not less than-- 3.
So the minimum value is still 3.
And then you get to 2.
The computer sees, oh, 2 is less than 3.
2 must now be the minimum value.
And so 2 swaps with that first value.
>> So after one pass, we do indeed see
that the 2 and the 3 are swapped.
And we're just going to continue doing
this again with the rest of the array.
So we're going to just run through
the last four indexes of the array.
We'll see that 3 is
the next minimum value.
So we're going to swap that with 4.
And then we're just going to keep
running through until, eventually, you
get to a sorted array in which
2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 are all sorted.
Does everyone understand the logic
of how a selection sort works?
>> You just have some sort
of a minimum value.
You're keeping track of what that is.
And whenever you find it, you swap it
with the first value in the array--
or, not the first value--
the next value in the array.
Cool.
>> So as you guys kind of
saw from a brief glimpse,
we're going to pseudocode this out.
So if you guys in the back want to
form a group, everyone at a table
can form a little partner, I'm going
to give you guys like three minutes
to just talk through
the logic, in English,
of how we might be able to implement
pseudocode to write a selection sort.
And there's candy.
Please come up and get candy.
If you're in the back and you want
candy, I can throw candy at you.
Actually, do you-- cool.
Oh, sorry.
OK.
>> So if we would like to, as
a class, write pseudocode
for how one might approach
this problem, just feel free.
I'll just go around and,
in order, ask groups
for the next line of
what we should be doing.
So if you guys want to start
off, what's the first thing
to do when you're trying to
implement a way to solve this program
to selectively sort a list?
Let's just assume we
have an array, all right?
>> AUDIENCE: You want to create some
sort of [INAUDIBLE] that you're
running through your whole array.
>> ANDI PENG: Right.
So you're going to want to iterate
through every space, right?
So, great.
If you guys want to give me the
next line-- yeah, in the back.
>> AUDIENCE: Check them
all for the smallest.
>> ANDI PENG: There we go.
So we want to go through and check to
see what the minimum value is, right?
I'm going to abbreviate that to "min."
What do you guys want to do after
you've found the minimum value?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ANDI PENG: So you're going to want to
switch it with the first of that array,
right?
That's the beginning, I'm going to say.
All right.
So now that you've swapped the first
one, what do you want to do after that?
So now we know that this one here
must be the smallest value, right?
Then you have an additional rest
of the array that's unsorted.
So what you want to do here, if you
guys want to give me the next line?
AUDIENCE: So then you want to iterate
through the remainder of the array.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
And so what does iterating through
kind of imply we'll probably need?
What type of--
>> AUDIENCE: Oh, an additional variable?
ANDI PENG: Probably
another for loop, right?
So we're probably going to want
to iterate through-- great.
And then you're going to go back and
probably check the minimum again,
right?
And you're going to keep repeating
this, because the loops just going
to keep running, right?
>> So as you guys can see, we
just have a general pseudocode
of how we want this program to look.
This iterate here, what do we
typically need to write in our code
if we want to iterate through an
array, what type of structure?
I think Christabel
already said this before.
>> AUDIENCE: A for loop.
>> ANDI PENG: A for loop?
Exactly.
So this is probably
going to be a for loop.
What is a check here going to imply?
Typically, if you want to check
if something is something else--
>> AUDIENCE: If.
>> ANDI PENG: An if, right?
And then the swap here, we'll
go over later, because David
went through that in lecture as well.
And then the second iterate implies--
>> AUDIENCE: Another for loop.
>> ANDI PENG: --another for loop, exactly.
So if we're looking
at this correctly, we
can see that we're probably
going to need a nested for loop
with a conditional statement in there
and then an actual piece of code that's
going to swap the values.
So I've just generally written
a pseudocode code here.
And then we're actually going
to physically, as a class,
try to implement this today.
Let's go back into this IDE.
>> Uh-oh.
Why is that not-- there it is.
OK.
Sorry, let me try to zoom in a bit more.
There we go.
All I'm doing here is I've created
a program called "selection/sort.c."
I've created an array of nine
values, 4, 8, 2, 1, 6, 9, 7, 5, 3.
Currently, as you can
see, they are unordered.
n is going to be the number that
tells you the amount of values
you have in your array.
In this case, we have nine values.
And I've just got a for loop here
that prints out the unsorted array.
>> And at the end, I've also got a for
loop that just prints it out again.
So theoretically, if this program
is working correctly, at the end,
you should see a printed for loop
in which 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8,
9 are all correctly in order.
>> So we've got our pseudocode here.
Does anyone want to-- I'm just
going to go ask for volunteers--
tell me exactly what to type if
we want to, first, just iterate
through the beginning of this array?
What's the line of code I'm
probably going to need here?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah, feel
free to-- sorry, you
don't have to stand up-- feel
free to raise your voice a bit.
>> AUDIENCE: For int i equals 0--
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah, good.
>> AUDIENCE: i is less than array length.
>> ANDI PENG: So keep in
mind here, because we
don't have a function that
tells us the length of an array,
we already have a
value that stores that.
Right?
Another thing to keep
in mind-- in an array
of nine values, what are the indexes?
Let's just say this array was 0 to 3.
You see that the last
index is actually 3.
It's not 4, even though there's
four values in the array.
>> So in here, we have to be very careful
of what our condition for the length
is going to be.
>> AUDIENCE: Wouldn't it be n minus 1?
ANDI PENG: It's going
n minus 1, exactly.
Does that make sense, why
it's n minus 1, everyone?
It's because arrays are zero-indexed.
They start at 0 and run up to n minus 1.
Yeah, it's a bit tricky.
OK.
And then--
AUDIENCE: Isnt'1 that
already taken care of though,
by just not saying "less than or
equal to" and just saying "less than?"
>> ANDI PENG: That's a
really good question.
So, yes.
But also, the way that we're
implementing the checking right,
you need to compare two values.
So you actually want to
leave the "to" empty.
Because if you compare
this one, you're not going
have anything after it
to compare to, right?
Yeah.
So i++.
Let's add our brackets in.
Whoops.
Great.
So we have the beginning
of our outer loop.
So now we probably want to
create a variable for keeping
track of the smallest value, right?
Does anyone want to give me the
line of code that would do that?
What do we need if we're going
to want to store something?
>> Right.
Maybe a better name for that
would be-- "temp" totally works--
maybe a more aptly named would be,
if we want the smallest value--
>> AUDIENCE: Min.
ANDI PENG: min, there we go.
min would be good.
And so here, what do we
want to initialize it to?
This is a bit tricky.
Because right now at the
beginning of this array,
you haven't looked at anything, right?
So what, automatically, if
we're just on i equals 0,
what do we want to initialize
our first minimum value to?
AUDIENCE: i.
ANDI PENG: i, exactly.
Christabel, why do we want
to initialize it to i?
>> AUDIENCE: Because, well,
we're starting with 0.
So because we have nothing to compare
it to, the minimum will end up being 0.
>> ANDI PENG: Exactly.
So she's exactly right.
Because we haven't actually
looked at anything yet,
we don't know what our minimum value is.
We want to just initialize it to
i, which, currently, is right here.
And as we continue to
move down this array,
we'll see that, with each
additional pass, i increments.
And so at that point,
i is probably going
to want to be the minimum,
because it's going to be whatever
is the beginning of the unsorted array.
Cool.
>> So now we want to add
a for loop here that's
going to iterate through the
unsorted, or the rest of this array.
Does anyone want to give me a
line of code that would do that?
Hint-- what do we need down here?
What's going to go in this for loop?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So we'd want to
have a different integer,
because we're running through the rest
of the array instead of the i, so maybe
j.
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah, j sounds good to me.
Equals?
>> AUDIENCE: So would be i plus 1, because
you're starting at the next value.
And then to the end-- so again, j is
less than n minus 1, and then j++.
ANDI PENG: Great.
>> And then in here, we're going to want
to check to see if our condition is met,
right?
Because you want to
change the minimum value
if it's actually smaller than what
you're comparing it to, right?
So what are we going to want in here?
Check to see.
What type of statement
are we probably going
ti want to use if we
want to check something?
>> AUDIENCE: An if statement.
>> ANDI PENG: An if statement.
So if-- and what's going to be
the condition that we want inside
of our if statement?
>> AUDIENCE: If the value of j
is less than the value of i--
>> ANDI PENG: Exactly.
So if-- so this array is called "array."
Great.
So if array-- what was that?
Say that again.
>> AUDIENCE: If array-j is less than
array-i, then we would change the min.
So the min would be j.
>> ANDI PENG: Does that make sense?
OK.
And now down here, we actually
want to implement the swap, right?
So recall, in lecture, that David, when
he was trying to swap the-- what was
it-- orange juice and milk--
>> AUDIENCE: That was gross.
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah, that was kind of gross.
But it was a pretty good
concept demonstrating time.
So think of your values here.
You've got an array
of min, an array of i,
or whatever we were trying to swap here.
And you probably can't pour them into
each other at the same time, right?
So what are we going
to need to create here
in order to swap the values correctly?
>> AUDIENCE: A temporary variable.
>> ANDI PENG: A temporary variable.
So let's do int temp.
See, this would be a better
time to-- whoa, what was that?
OK.
So this would have been a better
time to name the variable "temp."
So let's do int temp.
What are we going to
set temp equal to here?
AUDIENCE: Min?
ANDI PENG: It's a bit tricky.
It actually doesn't matter in the end.
It doesn't matter what
order you choose to swap in
as long as you're making sure you're
keeping track of what you're swapping.
>> AUDIENCE: It could be array-i.
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah, let's do array-i.
And then what's the next line
of code we want to have here?
AUDIENCE: array-i equals array-j.
ANDI PENG: And lastly?
AUDIENCE: array-j equals array-i.
AUDIENCE: Or array-j equals
array-temp-- or, temp.
>> ANDI PENG: OK.
So let's run this and see
if it's going to work.
Where is that happening?
Oh, that's a problem.
See, on line 40, we're
trying to use array-j?
But where does j only exist in?
>> AUDIENCE: In the for loop.
ANDI PENG: Right.
So what are we going to need to do?
>> AUDIENCE: Define it outside the--
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I guess you have
to use another if statement, right?
So like, if the minimum--
all right, let me think.
>> ANDI PENG: Guys, try
to take a look Let's
see, what's something we can do here?
>> AUDIENCE: OK.
So if the minimum doesn't equal
j-- so if the minimum is still i--
then we wouldn't have to swap.
>> ANDI PENG: Does that equal i?
What do you want to say here?
>> AUDIENCE: Or yeah, if the
minimum doesn't equal i, yeah.
ANDI PENG: OK.
Well that solves, kind of, our problems.
But that still doesn't solve the
problem of what happens if j-- since j
doesn't exist outside of it, what
do you we want to do with it?
Declare it outside?
Let's try running this.
Uh-oh.
Our sort's not working.
>> As you can see, our initial
array had those values.
And afterwards it should have
been in 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
It's not working.
Ahh.
What do we do?
AUDIENCE: Debug.
ANDI PENG: All right, we can try that.
We can debug.
Zoom out a bit.
Let's set our breakpoint.
Let's go like-- OK.
>> So because we already know that
these lines, 15 through 22,
are working-- because all I'm doing is
just iterating through and printing--
I can go ahead and skip that.
Let's start at line 25.
Oop, let me get rid of that.
>> AUDIENCE: So the breakpoint's
where the debugging starts?
ANDI PENG: Or stops.
AUDIENCE: Or stops.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
You can set multiple breakpoints and
it can just jump from one to the other.
But in this case we don't know
where the error is happening.
So we just want to
start from the top down.
Yep.
OK.
>> So this line here, we can step in.
You can see down here,
we've got an array.
Those are the values
that are in the array.
Do you see that, how index 0, it
corresponds to the value-- oh,
I'm going to try to zoom in.
Sorry, it's really hard
to see-- at array index 0,
we have a value of 4 and
then so forth and so on.
We have our local variables.
Right now i is equal to
0, which we want it to be.
>> And so let's keep stepping through.
Our minimum is equal to 0,
which we also want it to be.
And then we enter our second for
loop, if array-j is less than array-i,
which it was not.
So did you see how
that skipped over that?
>> AUDIENCE: So should the if
minimum, all that-- shouldn't that
be inside the first for loop?
ANDI PENG: No, because
you still want to test.
You want to do a comparison every
time, even after you run through it.
You don't just want to do it
on the first pass-through.
You want to do it with
each additional pass again.
So you want to check for
your condition inside.
So we're just going to
keep running through here.
I'll give you guys a hint.
It has to do with the fact that when
you're checking your conditional,
you're not checking
for the correct index.
So right now you're checking for
array index of j is less than array
index of i.
But what are you doing up at
the beginning of the for loop?
Aren't you setting j equal to i?
>> Yeah, so we can actually
exit the debugger here.
So let's take a look at our pseudocode.
For-- we're going to
start at i equals 0.
We're going to go up to n minus 1.
Let's check, did we have that right?
Yep, that was right.
>> So then inside here, we're
going to create a minimum value
and set that equal to i.
Did we do that?
Yep, did that.
Now in our inner for loop, we're
going to do j equals i to n minus 1.
Did we do that?
Indeed, we did that.
>> So however, what are we comparing here?
>> AUDIENCE: j plus 1.
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
And then you're going to want to set
your minimum equal to j plus 1 as well.
So I went through that really quickly.
Do you guys understand
why it's j plus 1?
OK.
>> So in your array, in
your first pass through,
your for loop, for int
i equals 0, let's just
assume this hasn't been changed yet.
We have an array of, completely,
just four unsorted elements, right?
So we want to initialize i equal to 0.
And i is going to just
run through this loop.
And so in the first pass, we're going
to initialize a variable called "min"
that also equals i, because
we don't have a minimum value.
So that's currently equal to 0 as well.
And then we're going to go through.
And we want to iterate again.
Now that we've found what our minimum
is, we want to iterate through
again to see if it's comparing, right?
So j, here, is going
to equal i, which is 0.
And then if array j plus i, which
is the one that's next over, as less
than what your current minimum
value is, you want to swap.
>> So let's just say we've
got, like, 2, 5, 1, 8.
Right now, i is equal to
0 and j is equal to 0.
And that's our minimum value.
If array-j plus i-- so if the one
that's after the one we're looking at
is greater than the one before it,
it's going to become the minimum.
>> So here we see that 5
is not less than that.
So it's going to not be 5.
We see that 1 is less than 2, right?
So now we know that our minimum is
going to be the index value at 0, 1, 2.
Yeah?
And then when you get down here,
you can swap the correct values.
>> So when you guys were just having the j
before, you weren't looking at the one
after it.
You were looking at
the same value, which
is why it just wasn't doing anything.
Does that make sense to everybody,
why we needed that plus 1 there?
OK.
Now let's just run through it to make
sure the rest of the code is correct.
Why is that happening?
Ah, it's the min right here.
We were comparing the wrong value.
Oh no.
>> Oh yeah, down here we were
swapping the wrong values as well.
Because we were looking at i and j.
Those are the ones we were checking.
We actually want to swap the
minimum, the current minimum,
with whatever the one outside is.
And as you guys can see down
here, we have a sorted array.
It just had to do with
the fact that when
we were checking the
values we were comparing,
we weren't looking at the right values.
We were looking at the same one
here, not actually swapping it.
You have to look at the one next
to it and then you can swap.
So that's what was kind of
bugging our code before.
And what I did here is everything
the debugger could have done for you
I just did it on the
board, because it's easier
to see rather than trying
to zoom in on the debugger.
Does that make sense to everybody?
Cool.
>> All right.
We can move on to talking about
asymptotic notation, which
is just a fancy way of saying the
runtimes of all of these sorts.
So I know David, in lecture,
touched upon runtimes.
And he went through the whole formula
of how to calculate the runtimes.
No worries about that.
If you're really curious
on how that works,
feel free to talk to me after section.
We can walk through
the formulas together.
But all you guys have to really
know is that n squared over 2
is the same thing as n squared.
Because the largest number,
the exponent, grows the most.
And so for our purposes,
all we care about
is that giant number that's growing.
>> So what is the best case
runtime of selection sort?
If you're going to have
to iterate through a list
and then iterate through
the rest of that list,
how many times are
you going to probably,
in the worst case-- in the
best case, sorry-- run through?
Maybe the better question is
to ask, what is the worst case
runtime of selection sort.
AUDIENCE: n squared.
ANDI PENG: It's n squared, right.
So an easy way to think of this is like,
any time you have two nested for loops,
it's going to be n squared.
Because not only are you
running through once again,
you have to go back
around and run through it
once again inside for every value.
So in that case, you're running n
times n squared, which is-- sorry,
n times n, which equals n squared.
>> And sort is also a bit
unique in the sense
that it doesn't matter if these
values are already in order.
It's still going to run through anyways.
Let's just say this was 1, 2, 3, 4.
Regardless of whether or not it was in
order, it still would have ran through
and still checked the minimum value.
It would have made the
same number of checks
every single time, even if it
didn't actually touch anything.
>> So in such a case, the best and worst
runtimes are actually equivalent.
So the expected runtime
of selection sort,
which we designate by the symbol
of theta, theta, in this case,
would also be n squared.
All three of these would be n squared.
Is everyone clear on why
the runtime is n squared?
>> All right.
So I'm just going to quickly run
through the rest of the sorts.
The algorithm for
bubble sort-- remember,
this was the first one
David went over in lecture.
Essentially, you step
through the entire list
and you swap-- you just
compare two at a time.
And if one's greater,
than you just swap them.
So if these are greater, you would swap.
I've got official right here.
>> So let's just say you had 8, 6, 4, 2.
You'd compare the 8 and a 6.
You'd need to swap them.
You would compare the 8 and a 4.
If you have to swap the 8 and
the 2, change them as well.
So in such a sense, you can see,
played out over a long period of time,
how the values kind of bubble to
the ends, which is why we call it
bubble sort.
>> We would just run through again on
our second pass, and our third pass,
and our fourth pass.
Essentially, bubble sort just runs
until you don't make any more swaps.
So in that sense, this is just
the general pseudocode for it.
No worries, these will all be online.
We don't have to actually go over this.
>> We just initialize a counter
variable that starts at 0.
And we iterate through the entire array.
And if one value is-- if this
value is greater than that value,
you're going to swap them.
And then you're just
going to keep going.
And you're going to count.
And you're just going to keep doing
this while the counter is greater
than 0, which means that
every time you have to swap,
you know you want to go
back and check again.
You want to keep checking until you know
that you don't have to swap anymore.
>> So what are the best and worst
case runtimes for bubble sort?
And hint-- this is actually different
from selection sort in the sense
that these two answers aren't the same.
Think about what would happen in
a case if it was already sorted.
And think about what
would happen if it was
in the case in which it wasn't sorted.
And you can kind of run
through why that's happening.
I'll give you guys, like, 30
seconds to think about that.
>> OK.
Does anyone have a guess at what the
worst case runtime of bubble sort is?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Would it be, like, n times
n minus 1 or something like that?
Like, every time it runs,
it's just, like, one swap less
that whatever it was.
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah, so
you're totally right.
And this is a case in which your
answer was actually more complex
than the one we need to give.
So it's going to run-- I'm
going to erase all this here.
Is everyone good?
Can I erase this?
OK.
You're going to run through n
times the first time, right?
And they're going to run through
n minus 1 the second time, right?
And then you're going to keep
going, n mine 2, et cetera.
David did this in a lecture, where,
if you added up all those values,
you get something that's like-- yeah--
over 2, which essentially just reduces
down to n squared.
You're going to get a
weird fraction in there.
And so just know that
the n squared always
takes precedence over the fraction.
And so in this case, the worst
runtime would be n squared.
If it was in descending
order, think, you
have to make a swap every single time.
>> What would be, potentially,
the best case runtime?
Let's just say, if the list was already
in order, what would the runtime be?
>> AUDIENCE: n.
ANDI PENG: It's n, exactly.
And why is it n?
AUDIENCE: Because you just
have to check on each once.
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
So in the best possible runtime,
if this list was already
sorted-- let's say 1, 2, 3, 4-- you
would just go through, you would check,
you would see, oh, they all pan out.
I didn't have to swap.
I'm done.
So in that case, it's just n
or the number of steps you just
had to check in the first list.
>> And after, we now hit
insertion sort, where
the algorithm is essentially to divide
it into a sorted and unsorted portion.
And then one by one,
the unsorted values are
inserted in their appropriate
positions in the beginning of the list.
>> So for example, we have a
list of 3, 5, 2, 6, 4 again.
We know that it's currently
unsorted because we've just
started looking at it.
We take a look and we know that
the first value is sorted, right?
If you're only looking at an array of
size one, you know that it's sorted.
>> So then we know that the
other four are unsorted.
We go through and we see that value.
Let's go back.
See that value of 5?
We take a look at it.
We compare it to 3.
We know that it's greater than
3, so we know that that's sorted.
So we now know that the first two
are sorted and the last three aren't.
>> We take a look at 2.
We first check it with 5.
Is it less than 5?
It is not.
So we have to keep looking down.
Then you check 2 off 3.
Is it less than?
No.
So you know a 2 has to be inserted
into the front and 3 and 5
both have to be pushed out.
Do this again with 6 and 4.
And we just keep checking essentially,
where we just check, check, check.
And until it's in the right
position, we kind of just
insert it into the right position,
which is where the name of it came from.
>> So that's just the algorithm,
pseudocode per se, kind of,
on how we would implement
an insertion sort.
Pseudocode is here.
It's all online.
No worries if you guys are
trying to copy this down.
So once again, same question-- what
would be the best and worst runtimes
for insertion sort?
It's very similar to the last question.
I'll give you guys, like, 30
seconds to think about this as well.
>> OK Does anyone want to
give me the worst runtime?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: n squared.
>> ANDI PENG: It's n squared.
And why is it n squared?
>> AUDIENCE: Because in
reverse order, you have
to go through n times n, which is--
ANDI PENG: Yeah, exactly.
So same thing as in the bubble sort.
If this list is in
descending order, you're
going to have to check first once.
And then with every
additional value, you're
going to have to check it against
every single value, right?
And so altogether, you're going to make
an n pass times another n pass, which
is n squared.
What about the best case?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: n minus 1, because the
first one is already squared.
>> ANDI PENG: So, close.
The answer is actually n.
Because while the first one is
sorted, it may not actually-- it
we just lucked out, in
that example, that 2
happened to be the smallest number.
But that won't always be the case.
If 2 is already sorted in the beginning
but you look and there's a 1 here,
the 1 is going to bump it.
And it's going to end
up being bumped anyways.
>> So in the best case scenario,
it's actually just going to be n.
If you have 1, 2, 3,
4, 5, 6, 7, 8, you're
going to run through
that entire list once
to check to see if everything's fine.
Is everyone clear on running
times of selection as well?
I know I'm going through
these really fast.
But just know that if you know the
general concepts, you should be good.
OK.
So I'll just give you guys maybe, like,
a minute to talk to your neighbors
on what are just some
of the main differences
between these types of sorts.
We'll go over that soon.
AUDIENCE: Oh, OK.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
OK.
Cool, let's reconvene as a class.
So this was kind of an
open-ended question in the sense
that there's lots of answers to them.
And we'll go over some of them briefly.
I just wanted to get you guys
thinking about what differentiated
all three types of sorts.
And I heard, also, a great
question-- what does merge sort do?
Great question, because that's
what we're covering next.
>> So merge sort is the
one sort that functions
very differently from the other sorts.
As you guys can see--
did David do that demo
where he had all the cool
noises of seeing how merge
sort ran, like, infinitely
faster than the other two types?
OK.
So that's because merge
sort implements that divide
and conquer concept that we've
talked about a lot in lecture.
In that sense that we like to work
smarter, not harder, when you divide
and conquer problems, and break them
down, and then put them together,
good things always happen.
>> So the way that merge
sort essentially works
is that it divides an
unsorted array in half.
And then it's got two halves of arrays.
And it just sorts those two halves.
It just keeps dividing in half, in
half, in half until everything is sorted
and then recursively
puts it all together.
>> So that's really abstract.
So this is just a bit of pseudocode.
Does that make sense in
the way it's running?
So let's just say you have an
array of n elements, right?
If n is less than 2, you can return.
Because you know that if there's
only one thing, it must be sorted.
Else, you sort the left half,
and then you sort the right half,
and then you merge.
>> So while that looks really easy,
in reality, thinking about it's
kind of difficult. Because you're like,
well, that's kind of running on itself.
Right?
It's running on itself.
So in that sense, David touched
upon recursion in class.
And that's a concept
we'll talk about more.
It's that this, these two lines
here, actually is just the program
telling it to run itself
with different input.
So rather than run itself with
the entirety of n elements,
you can break it down into the
left half and the right half
and then run it again.
>> And then we'll look at it visually,
because I'm a visual learner.
It works better for me.
So we'll look at a visual example here.
>> Let's say we have an array, six
elements, 3, 5, 2, 6, 4, 1, not sorted.
All right, there's a lot on this page.
So if you guys can look at the
first step here, 3, 5, 2, 6, 4, 1,
you can split it in half.
You have 3, 5, 2, 6, 4, 1.
You know that these aren't-- you
don't know if they're sorted or not,
so you keep breaking them down, in half,
in half, in half, until eventually,
you only have one element.
And one element is always sorted, right?
>> So we know that 3, 5, 2, 4, 6,
1, by themselves, are sorted.
And now we can put them back together.
So we know the 3, 5.
We put those together.
We know that's sorted.
The 2's still there.
We can put the 4 and the 6 together.
We know that that's sorted,
so we put that together.
And the 1 is there.
>> And then you just look at
these two halves right here.
You have the 3, 5, 2, 2, 3, 5.
You can just compare the
beginning of everything.
Because you know that this is sorted
and you know that that's sorted.
So then you don't even have to
compare the 5, you just compare the 3.
And the 2 is less than 3, so
you know 2 must go in the end.
>> Same thing over there.
The 1 must go here.
And then when you go to put
those two values together,
you know that this is sorted and
you know that that is sorted.
So then the 1 and the
2, the 1 is less than 2.
That tells you that the 1
should go on the end of this
without even looking at 3 or 5.
And then the 4, you can just
check, it goes right in here.
You don't have to look at the 5.
Same thing with the 6.
You know that the 6-- it just
doesn't need to be looked.
>> And so in that way, you're
just saving yourself
a lot of steps when you're comparing.
You don't have to compare every
element against other elements.
You just compare against the ones
that you need to compare it against.
So that's kind of an abstract concept.
No worries if it's not
quite hitting you right yet.
But generally, this is
how a merge sort works.
Questions, quick questions,
before I move on?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: So you said that you take
the 1, and then the 4, and the 6
and put them in.
So aren't those-- aren't
you looking at them
as separate elements, not as the whole?
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So what's happening
is that you basically
are creating a brand new array.
So you know that, here, I have
two arrays of size 3, right?
So you know that my sorted array
needs to have six elements.
So you just create a
new amount of memory.
So you're kind of like
being wasteful of memory,
but that doesn't matter
because it's so small.
So you look at the 1
and you look at the 2.
And you know that the 1 is less than 2.
So you know that 1 should go in
the beginning of all of those.
>> You don't even need to
look at the 3 and the 5.
So you know 1 goes there.
Then you basically chop off the 1.
It's, like, dead to us.
Then we just have 2,
3, 5, and then 4 and 6.
And then you know that, you
compare the 4 and the 2,
oh, the 2 should go in there.
So you plop the 2 down, you chop it off.
So then you just have the 3
and the 5 in the 4 and the 6.
And you just keep chopping it off
until you put them in the array.
>> AUDIENCE: So you're just always
comparing the [INAUDIBLE]?
>> ANDI PENG: Exactly.
So in that sense, you're
just comparing, essentially,
one number against the other number.
And because you know
that it's sorted, you
don't have to look through
all of the numbers.
You just have to look at the first one.
And then you can just plop
them down, because you know
they belong where they need to belong.
Yeah.
Good question.
>> And then if any of you
are a bit ambitious,
feel free to look at this code.
This is actually the
physical implementation
of how we would write merge sort.
And you can see, it's very short.
But the ideas behind
it are pretty complex.
So if you feel like drawing this out
in your homework tonight, feel free to.
>> OK.
So David also went over this in lecture.
What are the best case
runtimes, worst case runtimes,
and the expected runtimes of merge sort?
A couple seconds to think.
This is pretty hard, but kind of
intuitive if you think about it.
All right.
>> AUDIENCE: Is the worst case n log n?
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
And why is it n log n.
>> AUDIENCE: Isn't it because it
becomes exponentially faster,
so it's like a function of that
instead of just simply being n
squared or something?
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
So the reason why the
runtime on this is n log
n is because-- what are you
doing in all of these steps?
You're just chopping it in half, right?
And so when we're doing the
log, all that it's doing
is dividing a problem in half,
in half, in half, in more halves.
And in that sense, you can kind
of eliminate the linear model
that we've been using.
Because when you chop
things in half, it's a log.
That's just the mathematical
way of representing it.
>> And then finally, at the end, you're
just making one last pass through
to put all of them in order, right?
And so if you just have to
check one thing, that's n.
And so you're kind of
multiplying the two together.
So it's like you've got that final
check for n down here with a log of n
up here.
And if you multiply
them, that's n log n.
>> And so the best case and worst
case and expected are all n log n.
It's also like another sort.
It's like selection sort
in the sense that it
doesn't matter what your
list is, it's just going
to do the same thing every single time.
OK.
So as you guys can see, even though
the sorts that we've gone through-- n
squared, it's not very efficient.
And even this n log n is
not the most efficient.
If you guys are curious,
there's sort mechanisms
that are so efficient that they're
almost essentially flat in runtime.
>> You've got some log n's.
You've got some log log n's.
We don't touch upon them
in this class right now.
But if you guys are curious,
feel free to google, what's
the most efficient sorting mechanisms.
I don't know, there are
some really funny ones,
like-- there's some really
funny ones that people make.
And you wonder how they
ever thought of that.
So google, if you have some spare
time, on, what are some funny ways
that people-- as well as
efficient ways-- people
have been able to implement sorts.
OK.
And here's just a handy little chart.
I know all of you, before that quiz 0,
will be in your room probably trying
to memorize that.
So that's nice in there for you guys.
Just don't forget the logic that made--
why those numbers were occurring.
If you're always lost, just make
sure you know what the sorts are.
And you can run through
them in your mind
to figure out why those
answers are those answers.
>> All right.
So we're going to move
on, finally, to searching.
Because as those of you
who have read the pset,
searching is also part of
this week's problem sets.
You'll be asked to implement
two types of searches.
One is a linear search and
one is a binary search.
>> So the linear search is fairly easy.
You just want to search element
of a list to see if you get it.
You just have to iterate through.
And if it equals something,
you can just return it, right?
But the one that we're most
interested in talking about
is binary search, right, which is the
divide and conquer mechanism which
David was demonstrating in lecture.
>> Remember the phone book example
that he keeps bringing up,
the one that he kind of struggled
a bit on this past year,
where you divide the problem in half,
in half, in half, again and again,
until you find what you're looking for?
And you've got the
runtime of that as well.
And you can see, it's
significantly more efficient
than any other type of search.
>> So the way that we would go about
implementing a binary search
is, if we had an array,
index 0 to 6, seven elements,
we can look in the middle, right--
sorry, if our question first--
if we want to ask the question of, does
the array contain the element of 7,
obviously, being humans, and having
such a small array, it's easy for us
to say yes.
But the way to implement a binary
search would be to look in the middle.
>> We know that index 3 is
the middle, because we
know there are seven elements.
What 7 divided by 2?
You can chop off that extra 1.
You've got 3 in the middle.
So is array of 3 equal to 7?
It is not, right?
But we can do a couple of checks.
Is array of 3 less than 7 or
is array of 3 greater than 7?
>> And we know that it's less than 7.
So we know that, oh, it must
not be in the left half.
We know that it must be
in the right half, right?
So we can just chop off half the array.
We don't even have to
look at it anymore.
Because we know that
half of our problem--
we know that the answer is in
the right half of our problem.
So we just look at that now.
>> So now we look at the
middle of what's left.
That index 5.
We do the same check again
and we see that it's smaller.
So we look to the left of that.
And then we see that check.
Is the array value at
index 4 equal to 7?
It is.
So we can return true, because
we found the value in our list.
Does the way I went through
that make sense to everybody?
OK.
I'll give you guys maybe, like,
three, four minutes to figure out
how to pseudocode this in.
>> So imagine I asked you to write a
function called search() that returned
a value, a Boolean value,
that was true or false-- like,
true if you found the
value, false if you didn't.
And then you were
passed in the value you
were looking for into values, which
is the array-- oh, I definitely put
that in the wrong place.
OK.
Anyways, that should have
been to the right of values.
And then int n is the number
of elements in that array.
How would you go about trying
to pseudocode that problem in?
I'll give you guys like
three minutes to do that.
No, I think there's only--
yeah, there's one right up here.
AUDIENCE: Can I?
ANDI PENG: Yeah, I got you.
Is that working?
OK, cool.
>> OK.
All right guys, we're
going to rein it in.
OK.
So assume we've got this lovely
little array with n values in it.
I didn't draw the lines.
But how would we go about
trying to write this?
Does anyone want to
give me the first line?
If you want to give me the
first line of this pseudocode.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: You'd want
to iterate through--
AUDIENCE: Just another for loop?
AUDIENCE: --for.
>> ANDI PENG: So this one's a bit tricky.
Think about-- you want
to keep running this loop
over and over again until when?
>> AUDIENCE: Until the [INAUDIBLE]
value is equal to that value.
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
So you can actually just write--
we can even simplify it more.
We can just do a while loop, right?
So you can just have loop--
we know that it's a while.
But for right now, I'm going
to say "loop"-- through what?
Loop until-- what is
our ending condition?
I think I heard it.
I heard someone say it.
>> AUDIENCE: Values equals middle.
ANDI PENG: Say it again.
AUDIENCE: Or, until the
value you're searching
for is equal to the middle value.
>> ANDI PENG: What if it's not in there?
What if the value you're searching
for isn't actually in this array?
AUDIENCE: You return 1.
>> ANDI PENG: But what do we want to
loop until if we have a condition?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Until there's only one value?
ANDI PENG: You can loop
until-- so you know that you're
going to have a max value, right?
And you know that you're going
to have a min value, right?
Because also, that's something
I forgot to say before,
that something that's
critical about binary search
is that your array is already sorted.
Because there's no way of doing
this if they're just random values.
You don't know if one's
larger than the other, right?
>> So you know that your max and
your mins are here, right?
If you're going to be adjusting
your max in your mins and the mid--
let's just assume your
mid value is right here--
you're going to basically
loop until your minimum is
about the same as your max, right, or
if your max is not the same as your min.
Right?
Because when that happens, you know that
you've eventually hit the same value.
So you want to loop until your min
is less than or equal to-- oops,
not less than or equal to,
the other way around-- max is.
>> Did that make sense?
I took a few tries to get that right.
But loop until your max value
is essentially almost less
than or equal to your minimum, right?
That's when you know
that you've converged.
AUDIENCE: When would your maximum
value be less than the minimum?
ANDI PENG: If you keep
adjusting it, which
is what we are going
to be doing in this.
Does that make sense?
Minimum and max are just
integers that we are probably
going to want to create to keep
track of where we're looking.
Because the array exists
regardless of what we're doing.
Like, we're not actually physically
chopping off the array, right?
We're just adjusting
where we're looking.
Does that make sense?
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah.
>> ANDI PENG: OK.
So if that's the condition for our loop,
what do we want inside of this loop?
What are we going to be wanting to do?
So right now, we've got
a max and a min, right,
probably created up here somewhere.
We're going to probably want
to find a middle, right?
How are we going to be
able to find the middle?
What's the mathematical--
AUDIENCE: Max plus min divided by 2.
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
Does that make sense?
And do you guys see why we
didn't just use-- why we did this
instead of doing just n divided by 2?
It's because n is a value
that's going to stay the same.
Right?
But as we adjust our minimum and
maximum values, they're going to change.
And as a result, our middle
is going to change too.
So that's why we want
to do this right here.
OK.
>> And then, now that
we've found our-- yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Just a quick question--
when you say min and max,
are we assuming that
it's already sorted?
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah, that's actually a
precondition for a binary search,
that you have to know it's sorted.
Which is why sort, you write in your
problem set before your binary search.
OK.
So now that we know where our midpoint
is, what do you want to do here?
>> AUDIENCE: We want to compare
that to the other one.
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
So you're going to compare
mid to value, right?
And what does that tell
us when we compare?
What do we want to do afterwards?
>> AUDIENCE: If the value is larger
than the mid, we want to cut it off.
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
So if the value is larger
than the mid, we're
going to want to change these
minimum and maxes, right?
What do we want to change?
So if we know the value is somewhere
in here, what do you we to change?
We want to change our
minimum to be mid, right?
And then else, if it's in this
half, what do we want to change?
>> AUDIENCE: Your maximum.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
And then you're just going
to keep looping, right?
Because now, after one iteration
through, you've got a max here.
And then you can recalculate a mid.
And then you can compare.
And you're going to keep going
until the mins and the maxes
have essentially converged.
And that's when you know that
you've hit the end of it.
And either you've found it
or you haven't at that point.
>> Does this make sense to everybody?
OK.
This is pretty important,
because you'll have
to write this in your code tonight.
But you guys have a pretty good
sense of what you should be doing,
which is good.
OK.
So we've got about seven
minutes left section.
So we're going to talk about
this pset that we'll be doing.
So the pset is divided into two halves.
The first half involves
implementing a find
in which you write a linear search, a
binary search, and a sorting algorithm.
>> So this is the first
time in a pset where
we'll be giving you guys what's called
distribution code, which is code
that we have pre-written,
but just left some pieces off
for you to finish writing.
So you guys, when you look at this
code, you might get really scared.
If you're just like, ahh, I
don't know what that's doing,
I don't know, like, that seems
so complicated, ahh, relax.
It's OK.
Read the spec.
The spec will explain to you exactly
what all of these programs are doing.
>> For example, generate.c is a program
that will come with your pset.
You don't actually have to touch it, but
you should understand what it's doing.
And generate.c, all it's doing is
either generating random numbers
or you can give it a seed, like a
prearranged number that it takes,
and it generates more numbers.
So there's a specific way to
implement generate.c in which
you can just make a bunch of numbers
for you to test your other methods on.
>> So if you wanted to, for
example, test your find,
you would want to run generate.c,
generate a bunch of numbers,
and then run your helpers function.
Your helpers function is where you're
actually physically writing code.
And think of helpers as a library file
you're writing that find is calling.
And so within helpers.c, you'll
do searching and sorting.
>> And then you're going to essentially
just put them all together.
The spec will tell you how to
put that on the command line.
And you'll be able to test whether or
not your sort and search are working.
Cool.
Has anyone already started and
encountered problems or questions
they have right now with this?
OK.
>> AUDIENCE: Wait.
I have a question.
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: So I started doing
the linear search in helpers.c
and it wasn't really working.
But then later, I found out we just
have to delete it and do binary search.
So does it matter if it doesn't work?
>> ANDI PENG: Short answer is no.
But since we're not--
AUDIENCE: But no one's
actually checking.
ANDI PENG: We're never
going to see that.
But you probably want to make
sure your search is working.
Because if your linear
search doesn't work,
then chances are your binary
search isn't going to work as well.
Because you have similar
logic in both of them.
And no, it doesn't really matter.
So the only ones you'll turn
in are sort and binary search.
Yeah.
>> And also, a lot of kids were
trying to compile helpers.c.
You're not actually allowed
to do that, because helpers.c
doesn't have a main function.
And so you should only
be actually compiling
generate and find, because find calls
helpers.c and the functions within it.
So that makes debugging
a pain in the butt.
But that's what we have to do.
AUDIENCE: You just make all, right?
ANDI PENG: You can just
make all as well, yeah.
OK.
So that's it in terms of what
the pset is asking you all to do.
If you have any questions, feel
free to ask me after section.
I'll be here for, like, 20 minutes.
>> And yeah, the pset's
really not that bad.
You guys should be OK.
These, just follow guidelines.
Kind of have a sense of, logically, what
should be happening and you'll be fine.
Don't be too scared.
There's a lot of code
already written there.
Don't be too scared if you don't
understand what all of that means.
If it's a lot, it's totally fine.
And come to office hours.
We'll help you take a look.
>> AUDIENCE: With the extra
functions, do we look those up?
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah, those are in the code.
In the game of 15, half of
it's already written for you.
So those functions are
already in the code.
Yep.
All right.
Well, best of luck.
It's a disgusting day.
So hopefully you guys don't feel too
bad about staying inside and coding.