ANDI PENG: All right.
Welcome to week four of section.
It's a beautiful day
out here in New Haven
so I really think the sparse
scattering of kids that
joined me for section today, thank you.
So quickly, just before we
start, the agenda for today.
We are going to go over a
few brief announcements.
We have a really wacky schedule
coming up in the next two weeks
or so so we're going to go over that.
Secondly, I know
everyone's favorite topic--
I'm sure this melted your mind
during lecture, don't worry,
I still kind of don't get it.
It's fine.
That was a joke.
I actually do get it.
But I will make sure that
you guys get it, too.
So we're going to spend a
really, really good amount
of time talking about pointer today.
As you can see, Candy's
talk is huge today.
We're really going to keep
that-- yeah, that's right.
Keep taking candy.
I'm going to pass them around right now.
No worries.
We're going to really try
to keep people's blood sugar
up because that brain is going to burn
some oxygen today because pointers
are really, really hard.
Then we're going to talk about
memory management which kind of is
in the same realm.
And we're going to move
on to redirection and file
I/O which are just syntax, nice
things that we should talk about.
And then lastly, I'm
going to once again try
to leave like 10, 15 minutes for pset4.
That's due in a few days so we're
going to really kind of give you
some helpful hints if you
already got started on that.
Cool.
OK.
So some announcements
for this upcoming week.
Grading.
I don't actually know at
this point how many of you
guys are actually in my
section-- you OK there?
OK.
But, for those of you
who are in my section,
just a couple comments on grading.
First, really good job of commenting.
Those of you who don't comment, you
know who you are because you probably
got some style points dinged this week.
Just make sure that in all of your
programs add a couple comments.
Really, style is really easy to
get correct points as a scope.
So for us, just make
sure that you're kind
of adding a brief description in all
your programs about what you're doing.
Secondly-- this is a huge issue for
a lot of the TAs this past week--
so make sure you're uploading to
the correct folder with correctly
named programs.
And the reason why we ask for this is
because we, in the course of grading,
actually run a script on your
code that downloads automatically
all of your psets, runs
correctness tests on all of them,
and then uploads your scores
directly into the gradebook.
However, at any point, if you
named your program incorrectly,
it screws up the entire
program for everyone.
And so, legitimately,
this beautiful script
that we've written that does
all of this for us, completely
crashes if you don't have
your program named correctly.
So just upload to the correct
folder, have them named correctly,
and then life is good.
I get your psets back
to you guys earlier
because I get to grade them quickly.
Yeah.
OK.
And also we're going to talk
about-- Yale has a really, really
wacky schedule in these next two weeks.
So those of you guys at
Harvard, this does not apply.
But for us lovely kids at Yale we have
something called fall break-- sorry,
Harvard-- where we have
five days off of school.
And while this is lovely, it
kind of messes up our pset rhythm
because psets are due Thursday, Fridays.
And so if we're not here
Thursday, Fridays, we
can't have work for you guys
due on Thursday, Fridays.
So what we're going to do is-- we're
like 99% sure this is what's happening,
there may be some
change but I think it's
subtle-- is we're going to
have-- this week is normal.
So we have our section on
Tuesdays followed by office hours
throughout the rest of the week
and then pset4 is due on Friday.
Then, as you guys all know, as
I reminded you guys last week,
we have our quiz 0
coming up on Wednesday.
And so, being a student myself,
I know that very few of you
guys will actually be working on
pset5 the two days before your quiz.
So what we're going to
probably end up doing is,
that Monday night, we're going
to actually, from 5:30 to 7:00,
have a brief review
session on topics covered.
Unclear if it's a
review session or a Q&A.
It will be some sort of review
form in which we'll cover
some topics relevant for you guys.
And then Monday and Tuesday nights
of that week from 8:00 to 11:00,
we're going to have office hours.
Those office hours will most
likely be more of just come in,
ask TAs your questions regarding
any concepts you're confused about,
and they'll kind of go over with you
and review concepts for the quiz.
Quiz 0, if you're in the
Monday, Wednesday section,
will be Wednesday's during
class-- on Wednesday during class.
And then if you're in the
Tuesday, Thursday section,
will be also during class on Thursday.
You can't really choose
which one you go to.
If you're a Monday, Wednesday,
you have to go to Wednesday.
If you're on Tuesday, Thursday
you have to go to Thursday.
But then that night,
us lovely staff, will
have a giant quiz grading party in
which we'll get your scores back to you
that night.
At what time?
Unclear, who knows, but it will
be back to you within 24 hours
so that you guys hopefully
have some feedback by Friday.
And then we have a really wacky week.
So pset5 is one of the
hardest psets of the year.
So sorry guys.
What we're going to try to
do is we're going to have
some actual support that weekend.
Because, as you guys can see, the
pset is due before fall break.
We don't have support for
you guys during fall break
and so we really kind of
want to phrase this as,
let's get this over with,
let's work really, really hard
these next two weeks, get this quiz
and add these two psets done with
and then you guys have a nice relaxing
seven days without thinking about CS.
So in order for that to
happen, we are probably
going to move my section
to Sunday afternoons.
It will be filmed so no
worries if you can't come.
But the online filming will
be there and accessible
so that you guys have Sunday,
Monday, Tuesdays, to work on pset5.
And then it's fall
break and no CS and then
we come back and its back in the grind.
But it's going to be a
lovely week for fall break
and we really want to make it as stress
free for everyone as possible which
is why we moved the pset to be due
before fall break rather than after.
Because it's-- I mean, I kind of feel
like it defeats the purpose of having
the deadline after fall break if there's
no support anyways during fall break.
So it's rather-- I think
we'd rather focus on it now.
Does anyone have questions
about that schedule?
Anything confusing?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Do we still have
a lecture on the 21st?
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So on the 21st, there is going to be
a lecture that is live from Harvard.
I don't know if David is filming
it or if he's actually lecturing,
but it's going to be available
online for you guys to access.
So just make sure you carve an
hour out somewhere in fall break
so you guys can catch
up on that lecture.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Sorry.
I got here a couple--
ANDI PENG: No worries.
Here, take some candy.
AUDIENCE: Hey, I caught that.
So just to recap, not tomorrow but the
Wednesday after that, we have a quiz.
ANDI PENG: Correct.
AUDIENCE: And it's going to be--
what's the format of the quiz?
ANDI PENG: Oh.
So we'll send out an email that
covers all that more in depth.
But, essentially, it just covers
basic topics already covered
in the first half of the semester.
We'll have review sessions and question
and answers so no worries about that.
But we'll be going over that too.
AUDIENCE: Is it going to be, we
bring our computers and code there--
ANDI PENG: No.
It's going to be you guys writing
and answering questions by hand.
AUDIENCE: Oh.
ANDI PENG: So we'll give
out practices and stuff
so you guys may want to perhaps go
back and rewrite Mario by hand just
to make sure you guys have
an idea of how to do that.
Because sometimes when
you write by hand you
forget semicolons and stuff
and that's really bad.
AUDIENCE: Won't that be [INAUDIBLE]?
Like, you're getting
a semicolon on your--
ANDI PENG: Yes and no.
We'll talk more in depth
regarding how the quiz layout is
and how we're going to grade.
But essentially, just know that the
general format is going to be you
guys either interpreting code--
answering basic questions.
If I asked you, what is a library?
You guys should know what a
library does and write that down.
Or I may say, write a program that
prints Hello World to the screen.
You guys would write, int main
void printf hello world semicolon.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So it's not going
to be anywhere [INAUDIBLE]
difficulty level of the problem set?
ANDI PENG: No.
No.
We won't-- yeah.
Write the entirety of the
game of 15 in 20 minutes, go.
No, it won't be that.
No.
AUDIENCE: OK.
So that is Wednesday.
During that week we also
have the hardest problem set?
ANDI PENG: No.
So the problem set it due
the day before fall break.
The schedule-- the email
was actually send out
20 minutes ago regarding all of this.
So you guys just check your emails.
It'll be there.
Yeah.
No worries.
Cool.
Any general questions regarding
announcements, grading, quizzes,
before we dive right into
pointers which will consume
the majority of our section time today?
Cool.
All right.
So did you guys all watch this lovely--
I don't know what they call it.
The thing where the claymation
blew itself up because it
didn't use a pointer correctly.
Well, your program is going to
probably blow itself up if you
don't use pointers correctly as well.
So we're going to make
sure that doesn't happen.
Today we're going to
do some pointer fun.
I'm going to go over things
as smoothly as I think
is possible in a small time frame.
But there's just so much to cover
that I really want you guys,
if you don't understand something,
to not just let me keep going.
Because if you don't
understand something,
you're probably not going to
understand anything I say after that.
So please stop me and ask a question.
Because it all kind
of snowballs together.
Like, pointers lead into
memory lead into other things.
And so if you don't understand pointers,
stop me and we'll figure it out
and life will be fine.
Cool.
So how many of you guys in lecture,
when David mentioned pointers,
your brains kind of turned into Jell-O?
Yeah.
Good.
We're going to try to
de-Jell-O your brains today.
We're going to really systematically
go through what exactly a pointer is,
what it does, and how we use them.
So all pointers-- so
normally with the variables
we've been using in coding, like
variables such as integers or strings
or floats, they're all essentially
a value assigned to them
as well as an address
pointing to that value.
So I'm going to draw this right now.
We have almost no chalk but that's OK.
So for example, normally
the way that we've
been using variables is we create the
name of the variable of type int, let's
just say.
So here we've got int x and we're
initializing that int to 50.
So here in this block of memory on our
computers we've stored a number of 50.
So where pointers come into play is
that your computer itself-- like, here,
physically in the hard drive
in the RAM of my computer--
it only has a finite amount of memory.
You can't just keep storing things
on top of things on top of things
and have them all.
So the way that we dynamically allot
memory to be able to store what we want
and access it, is by having pointers.
So imagine in your memory space, right.
If this is the RAM of your
computer, you have these little bits
or blocks or bytes of memory in
which-- these are just little
blocks that have been allocated out on
the hard drive or RAM of your computer,
and within each of those blocks
you can store different things.
So for example, one
array in this example
here is one byte which is
consisting of eight bits.
The number changes depending on the
operating system of your computer.
For example, how many of you have
heard of 32-bit versus 64-bit operating
systems?
Exactly.
So all that's saying
is that the memory--
that the way that your computer
manages the memory is different.
Which is why it's really
important to understand
why memory itself functions rather
than pay attention to the numbers.
So we don't really care
how large this array
is, we just need to care about
how large do we need an int to be,
how large do we need a string
to be, how large is a pointer?
OK.
So it's going to be a lot
of heavy, dense information.
I'm going to give you guys a
couple comic relief moments here.
You guys should all be able
to understand this now.
Because we know that
pointers are addresses,
and those are different from variables.
OK.
Cool.
CS jokes are the best, yeah?
So the way that we go
about creating a pointer
is a very specific sort of syntax.
As with creating any
type of variable, it's
going to be a specific
syntax we use to create it.
So when declaring any pointer,
a pointer is just essentially--
I think the important
part of pointers is
that whereas a variable has
both a value and an address,
a pointer is an address.
Its value is an address.
So it's an address stored
at a different address.
If that makes any sense.
We'll go over this in more detail,
but that's the generic form
of why-- of how a printer is stored.
So the way that you create a pointer
is by doing whatever type of data
that the pointer is going
to be referencing and then--
with the star-- and then
the name of the pointer.
So here, if we wanted
to create a pointer that
pointed towards an integer, and we
wanted the name of the pointer to be x,
we would do int star x.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: And so if
the following line you
do int x, will the int star x
indicate the location of the x
you're defining afterwards?
ANDI PENG: Really good question.
We'll go over this in
a couple slides later.
Yeah.
And then same thing with
char and same thing floats.
Just know that at this point
we've created a pointer,
we haven't actually set
it to equal anything yet.
We haven't actually referenced it.
The same thing here when
you create a variable,
you've created the name of the variable,
you haven't actually set a value to it.
Same thing here.
OK.
So how do we set values to pointers?
It's by referencing and dereferencing.
So the way that we can reference
a varia-- a pointer, in essence
we return the address in memory
of which a variable is stored.
So if I had a pointer-- I'll draw
this once we get to the next slide,
but just know that, essentially,
the and-- the ampersand
and the variable-- all that
does is tell you the address
of where something is stored.
And dereferencing is the opposite
of that, which is just the star.
The star just gives you the actual
data stored at that address.
So one gives you the address
stored at an address,
the other gives you the actual
value stored at the address.
So the two of them give
you different things.
Once again, the slides are
all online so no worries
if you guys can't copy
this down in time.
So let's take a look
at this example here.
So we've got a giant
memory array here, right?
Where we just have blocks of
memory, or bytes of memory,
in which we can store different things.
Let's just say these are the
address points in memory.
So anytime you have--see the 0x,
all that is telling you is that
that's a hexadecimal digits.
As you guys all know, numbers
could be based in different bases.
Base 10 is how we typically
interpret numbers.
There's also base 2, which is binary.
And in this case,
hexadecimal is base 16.
It's just a different way of saying
from zero to 10-- or zero to nine
and then also A, B, C, D, E, F.
Also references different numbers.
David went over this in lecture briefly.
If you guys are
confused, just Google it.
There's really easy ways to learn
what a hexadecimal digit is.
All that's really relevant
right now is for you
guys to know that a
hexadecimal digits in C
tells you-- that typically
tells you that it's a pointer.
Or that's a address.
So in this example here, int x equals 5.
We're creating an integer--
sorry, a variable of type
integer and we're initializing it to 5.
So here on our memory board, we can
see that x is at the address of 0x0
and the value that you've
stored inside of it is 5.
That should make sense
to everyone, right?
OK.
And then what we've done
in the second line of code
is that we've created
a pointer of type int.
That's what the int
star pointer is doing.
And that equals that the ampersand x
is giving you the address of something.
So the address of x in
this example is 0x0.
And so that address is being
stored in that pointer.
Does that make sense to everybody?
So think of this--
think of pointers-- here
at Yale we have a PO box system
where every student has a mailing
address where you can go
into the basement of LW
and you can just go and grab
whatever you need from that address.
The same thing is happening
here in a computer.
You have these memory bytes that
you can store information into,
but in order to know which
pieces of information
match up of what you're trying to find
and where, you need a pointer that
tells you how to go there.
So for example, for me, my PO box,
I have a specific five digit number.
That's my address.
So I can physically go to memory,
I can look at the address,
I can go to that PO box
and access the data inside.
Does that make sense to Everybody
Your computer is essentially
doing the exact same thing.
So all pointer is doing is that
it's just creating a memory
and its memory data is actually
the address of something else.
Then you can go and find that.
Everyone good?
Everyone good with me so far?
OK.
Cool.
All right.
So almost the same thing as before.
So we have, first, a variable
called x in which case--
I'm going to change this value to 5.
Let's just say the address
of this in memory is 0x0.
00.
Great.
So then, on our second
line of code, we're
going to create a pointer
called ptr pointer.
And the address of that, let's
just say that's 0x01 in memory.
And we actually want to
store-- the ampersand
x gives you the address of what x was.
And the address of x was 0x00.
So this pointer now
actually has the address
stored as its value of what x was.
Everyone with me so far?
Cool.
And then, the way that
we would copy that,
is if we would declare and initialize
another block of memory of type int.
Right?
This would be an int.
It would be called copy.
And you're going to get-- so
the star pointer gives you
the actual data from that address.
The ampersand gives you the address,
the star gives you the data.
So the data at pointer.
This pointer is pointing to 5.
And so this function
here-- the star pointer--
goes, gets whatever is in
this block and stores it here.
Everyone clear on how that happened?
So the two operators right there--
the ampersand and the star--
just do different things
when used on pointers.
One gets you the address, one
gets you the actual value.
So make sure when you guys are
coding that you don't confuse the two
because they're vastly different.
Here we have a nice example of a 0x01.
That's a really nice
small number to remember.
In your actual computer
you're going to have
a giant ass number that is something
that's not nice, not pleasant.
It's going to be some garbage value.
And so it's going to really,
really mess up your programs.
It's very important
right now that we have
the fundamentals down for why-- like,
what is physically happening when
you're running those blocks of code.
Everyone-- yeah?
AUDIENCE: So int x equals int copy?
ANDI PENG: No because, in this case, int
x-- the value of x-- equals 5, right?
And then int copy equals 5.
So if you were to equate them to
each other because they're integers,
yes, they would evaluate to true.
But if they were strings in memory, like
the one that David did during example,
that's different because
they're referencing
the addresses of places in memory
and they would equate to false.
So here it would be true because you're
directly comparing values-- integers--
but in the others you're
referencing points.
Because a string is in an array, and
all-- we'll talk about this later--
but array is essentially just a
pointer to a bunch of chars in memory.
So those are a bit different.
But in this case, yes,
you could do that.
AUDIENCE: Can you explain
the address of copy?
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So that's just-- I
didn't fill in a value
but it's just some random other
garbage value that we don't care about.
Because once you start program
you realize that we don't actually
really care what the
actual addresses are,
we just need to know
what's at the addresses.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: The star next to int on the
second line, that's different than--
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: --the dereferencing
and referencing star?
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So the authors of C-- whoever
decided to write the language of C--
was not very smart.
They were not very smart in trying
to figure out why we should do this.
If it was me, I would definitely
use two different characters.
But they decided to use the same one.
So the star after an int,
that tells the computer
that you're about to create a pointer.
But if you're trying to dereference
something-- in other words,
go to the address and pull
the data from somewhere--
the star is used differently.
So you guys just be careful about
not messing up the two uses.
Cool.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So just to repeat to
make sure that I'm following--
ANDI PENG: Totally fine.
AUDIENCE: --in the left-hand side of
that slide, we do a thing that we know.
We declare an integer
[INAUDIBLE] that are equal to 5.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Right.
And then we have an int star thing and
that says that, OK, kind of like we
declared an integer, now
we're declaring a pointer.
ANDI PENG: Correctly.
Correct.
AUDIENCE: Right?
And our pointer is ptr.
ANDI PENG: Yep.
The name of the pointer is ptr.
Pointer.
AUDIENCE: And then it
equals nx that just tells C
that it wants to access the value at
integer x-- the value that integer x
was assigned.
ANDI PENG: Be careful
because ampersand x actually
tells you-- the computer that you
want to pull the address of what x is.
So ampersand gives you the
address, star gives you the value.
AUDIENCE: So we want the address.
Let's say x was at--
ANDI PENG: We actually
know what x is, right?
Because we know that x was-- I'm
making this up but let's just say,
arbitrarily, it was 0x00.
Right?
So we know the address is 0x00,
and so when we go and ampersand x,
we know that that
should evaluate to 0x00.
Which is why we stored that
as the value of our pointer.
Does that make sense?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
And copy goes to dereference ptr--
ANDI PENG: Right.
AUDIENCE: --which is
a pointer that we've
declared that tells us the
address of the integer x.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: And in this
one case, star ptr is
equal to the value of x which equals 5.
ANDI PENG: Correct.
AUDIENCE: Cool.
And that is a simpler way to get
that or is that the only way--
ANDI PENG: So right now it
doesn't seem very logical for us
to spend all of this time doing
this super complicated thing when
all we've done is just create two
integers with the value of 5, right?
It doesn't make sense.
But once we'll go over
memory allocation and-- we'll
go over why this may be
handy and useful later on.
Trust me when I say we don't just
create these arbitrary functions for you
guys to learn because we're
trying to mess with you.
There's actually uses for all of these
things and we will talk about them.
AUDIENCE: Awesome.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ANDI PENG: Good question.
ANDI PENG: It's not.
It really isn't.
AUDIENCE: --two variables
that also equal [INAUDIBLE].
OK.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
Before I move on, is everyone clear?
I know Taylor, you got in a bit late.
It's OK.
It's online.
You'll watch the first 20
minutes and you'll be all good.
OK.
Cool.
All right.
So this is essentially kind of a
similar thing that we just did.
It's just in a graphical form.
If you were to track what
just happened, int x equals 5,
all we've done at this point is
create a variable named x of type int.
We're going to store the
value of 5 inside of it.
There's no pointer because we haven't
actually created a pointer yet, right?
And then in the next
line, int star pointer,
that's where we're actually
physically creating the pointer
and we're setting that
equal to, or referencing
the pointer, to ampersand x.
Which is where wherever in
memory this happened to be.
I didn't actually bother
making up a value this time.
But in this case, that point
you would be equal to that.
And then down there, the star
pointer is the dereferencing.
That's where we're
pulling the information.
So that value at x is actually
going to be equal to 35.
So at this point, we've essentially
just reinitialized x to 35
without actually touching x.
Just through the pointer
that was pointing to x,
we can actually change what x was.
I'm going to draw this out as well.
So here we've created
some random address here.
Let's just say 0x00 again.
Let's just say that's the address.
And we've created an integer named x
and the value I've assigned to it is 5.
In the second line, int
pointer-- so now we've
got this second thing
here called a pointer--
and we're going to-- let's just say
it's some other random memory address.
So we're going to set this
equal to whatever that was.
And this pointer is going to
point towards the value of x
And then, if we change
the-- if we do star pointer,
that's going to the
value of our pointer.
In this case, it's going to track
this arrow over to this value of x
and it's going to change it to 35.
Effectively, we just changed
x without touching x.
Through just referencing pointers,
we can go and change the value of x.
Does that make sense?
So in this way, we can actually rename
and rechange and reassign values
to things that we didn't
actually make ourselves.
Does that make sense to everybody?
Cool.
OK.
So complex graphic here.
Go line by line.
Essentially, just do the exact
same thing that I just did.
Before I move on, I
really want to just make
sure everyone's really clear on this.
So up here, the code that we have is
int a equals 3, b equals 4, c equals 5.
So we've created three integers named
a, b and c that are equal to 3, 4 and 5.
And then we're creating three pointers
that point to each of those variables.
And now we're going
to go over essentially
what happens when you operate on them.
So draw them out.
Take a sheet of paper-- I don't
know if you guys all have paper,
but those of you who don't, maybe
borrow from those of you who do.
Take sheets of paper
and go line by line.
And at every operation that you do,
I want you guys to actually write out
what is a, b and c at this point.
And what are the addresses, what are
the pointers that point to a, b and c
at this point?
And then hopefully this
will kind of step you guys
through how to think about pointers.
We're not going to go
through all of them.
Maybe I'll give you five--
like, three minutes.
Get started on the first few.
Oh.
Oops.
AUDIENCE: In the second line, why
isn't the star [INAUDIBLE] variable?
ANDI PENG: Remember in
operators, in the first week,
we talked about how
if you do plus equals,
that just means a equals a plus c.
In this case-- so this is another
way in which the star could be used.
In addition to referencing
and declaring pointers,
remember that it also
means multiplication.
So in this case, it'd just
be a equals a times c.
That's just as different
way of writing that.
AUDIENCE: a equals a times c.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: What does it mean if
it says an ampersand letter?
ANDI PENG: Ampersand means
you're going to that-- you're
going to the place the pointer is
pointing and pulling the address.
So ampersand gives you the address,
star gives you the actual value there.
AUDIENCE: Are we
building on line by line?
ANDI PENG: You're
building on line by line.
So just go one line at
a time and then-- you
don't have to worry about
finishing the whole thing.
Let's try to get through
maybe two, three lines
and then we'll convene and finish this.
It's totally OK if you guys are lost.
This is a really hard concept.
If you guys are worried that the class
goes like this like David was saying,
it doesn't.
We're reaching the
conceptual peak of difficulty
and then it's going to
be downward sloping.
So you guys are almost there.
We have lots of candy to get
you guys through the hump.
I think pretty much after fall
break we'll be over the hump
and life will be fine again.
So no worries at all.
All right.
I'll give you guys 20
more seconds to wrap up.
OK.
All right.
Let's take a stab at this.
As you guys give me answers,
I'm just going to type them in.
And hopefully we-- can I?
I actually can't type it in.
I'll draw it on the board.
So here in this first line
we have a equals b star c.
Also Elliot brought up a
really, really good point.
Because I forgot that in addition to
the two ways we can use the star symbol,
there's actually a third way.
Multiplication.
And so just don't get confused because
that is the first way of using a star.
It's just telling the computer
that I'm about to create a pointer.
The second way by doing
star of your pointer,
that tells the pointer that you want
to access the data at that pointer.
And then, of course, there's
just simple multiplication
between two numbers that tells you
that I want to multiply the two.
So there's a lot of ways
we can use the star symbol.
Don't get confused.
Just make sure that you guys understand
exactly what all three of them
are doing.
So in this first line,
a equals b times c.
So let's go through what
is a, what is b, what is c?
And what is the pointer of a, the
pointer to b, and the pointer to c?
What are those all equaling?
OK.
So we start off with a equals 3,
b equals 4, and c equals 5, right?
So after that first line, can
somebody tell me what a is?
Yeah.
Feel free to just shout out answers.
20.
Good.
What's b?
AUDIENCE: 4.
ANDI PENG: What's c?
AUDIENCE: 5.
ANDI PENG: Yay.
Good.
What are pa, pb, and pc?
AUDIENCE: 000001 and 002?
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So kind of a trick question
but not really because here I
drew out actual memories.
But because, for an example, we don't
actually know what those numbers are,
we can just say ampersand.
I don't even know if I
can draw an ampersand.
It's like-- how do you do it?
AUDIENCE: Like drawing an eight.
ANDI PENG: Like an eight.
Like that.
OK.
AUDIENCE: Bingo.
ANDI PENG: Killing it.
So ampersand a, you can just do that.
Because we don't actually
care what the value of that
is, and it's some long
ass value anyways,
we're using just giong
to say ampersand a.
Then what's pb?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
Cool.
All right.
Easy first line.
We got this.
Pointers are easy.
It's OK.
Second line.
And so star equals is the same
thing as saying a equals a times c.
It's just an easier way of writing.
So we're not trying to make
a point or anything here.
So done with the first line.
What is a on the second line
after you do a equals a times c?
AUDIENCE: 100?
ANDI PENG: It's 100.
Good.
How about b?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ANDI PENG: How about c?
ANDI PENG: And how about pointers?
Are they-- the same, right?
OK.
Now third line.
Little trickier.
b equals star pa.
Can someone tell me, first,
what does star pa equal?
AUDIENCE: It's the value
that's stored at a.
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
And what is the value
that's stored at a?
AUDIENCE: 100.
ANDI PENG: OK.
So what would a be after
executing that line of code?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ANDI PENG: What about b?
AUDIENCE: 100.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
And then everything else is
pretty much unchanged, right?
Because we didn't touch it.
Cool.
Fourth line.
Slightly more complex.
So pc-- once again, pc is the pointer
that pointed to c-- equals pa.
What is a?
AUDIENCE: 100.
ANDI PENG: What is b?
ANDI PENG: What is c?
AUDIENCE: 5.
ANDI PENG: What's pa?
AUDIENCE: Ampersand a.
ANDI PENG: pb?
AUDIENCE: Ampersand b.
ANDI PENG: And tricky, what is pc now?
AUDIENCE: Ampersand a.
ANDI PENG: Yay.
Woo hoo.
You guys see?
This is all right.
It's not too bad.
We have more candy if it's not all
right, but I think it's all right.
And we're going to go over just one
more before we hit the harder ones.
The answers I have up here.
Essentially, know that this is
just like math at this point.
When you have simple equations like a
plus b, a times c, that's easy to do.
And when you start expanding upon
it, just go order of operations.
Same thing as before.
Keep track of if your
star is before something.
That tells you the value.
If you have an and before
something, it tells you the address.
And you should assign either
pointers or that value.
So let's go over this
last one real quick.
Not this last one, sorry.
Actually, you guys can pick.
Which one do you guys want to go
over out of the remaining three
that we have?
I don't think we can just do that
because we can't just jump to the line.
OK.
You guys don't have a choice,
it's just the third to last one.
Star pc equals b times c.
AUDIENCE: Star pb?
AUDIENCE: Star pb.
ANDI PENG: Sorry?
ANDI PENG: Star pb.
Oh, my bad.
Star pb equals b times c.
I'm going to give you guys 10 seconds.
Just quickly think.
This is that we have so
far, what happens after we
execute that fifth line right there?
OK.
What is a?
AUDIENCE: 100.
ANDI PENG: 100.
What is b now?
AUDIENCE: 500.
ANDI PENG: Good.
Does somebody want to explain
to me why this is 500?
I don't feel like we
actually ever touched b.
How did we manage to change the
value of b without touching b?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Because star pb
means the value at pb--
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
AUDIENCE: --which is b.
So here in our diagram, our pointer
pb is actually pointing to this right
here, which is the actual physical b.
And so if you go and
you do star pb, that's
following your arrow of your pointer
and physically changing the value of b.
So that's why we have b changed to
500 without actually touching b.
And then everything else remains the
same because we didn't touch that.
That's b.
Cool.
And then--
AUDIENCE: I just have a question.
ANDI PENG: Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Since we've--
there's no longer ampersand c,
does that mean ampersand a
redirect to the same thing now?
ANDI PENG: Yep.
So--
AUDIENCE: So the arrow
kind of just moves and--
ANDI PENG: So essentially--
AUDIENCE: --now we can't access--
ANDI PENG: --when we
dereference c on-- I forger.
What was that?
The third line?
Fourth.
Fourth line.
All we did was, essentially,
change this arrow
and have it pointed towards a instead.
AUDIENCE: So we can't access c anymore.
ANDI PENG: If you had this exact
number, you could access it.
But, no.
We don't have a pointer
pointing towards c anymore.
I think if you wanted
to re-access it, you
would create another
pointer that re-pointed to c
or dereferenced this and pointed back.
So, no, as of right now, the three
pointers, none of them point to c.
Everyone good?
Answers are online.
Feel free to, after section, go over
the last two and test yourselves.
Same concepts, just a
little bit trickier.
Just follow through the logic of
why things are different things.
And hint, pointers are
a topic that we love
to cover on quizzes because they're
conceptually very challenging.
So I would suggest that you
guys all review this chart
or slash similar concepts to
this before your quiz next week.
AUDIENCE: Excuse me.
ANDI PENG: Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
final one-- [INAUDIBLE].
ANDI PENG: 50,000?
I would need to follow it back down.
But somewhere-- I think the line
before, you created giant c value.
c equals this giant thing
which is 100 times 500.
No.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ANDI PENG: Yes.
100 times 100 which is 10,000.
Which is 10,000.
So back down there you're
multiplying b and c.
So the pointer that points to b--
which is the value of 500-- times a--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ANDI PENG: Maybe that's wrong.
AUDIENCE: No, no, it's not. [INAUDIBLE]
pointer at c is now pointing at a--
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
He's right.
AUDIENCE: --it's at its at a equals
a times-- it's the value of c.
ANDI PENG: Can you say that a little
bit louder so everybody can hear you?
AUDIENCE: So pointer at c now points
to what the pointer of a used to point
to-- and still does-- but they point to
the same thing which is the a, right?
The value a, however
it's been newly defined.
And at the beginning of that you're
saying a was previously 100 times
the value at b which is 500.
And so that's however much that is.
50,000.
They you're reassigning that to what the
memory space at c is-- the pointer at c
is pointing to which is a.
So you're redefining a to be 50,000.
ANDI PENG: She could
teach section for me.
Next time it's all yours.
Here.
Here's more candy for that.
You deserve candy for that.
AUDIENCE: I almost caught that.
ANDI PENG: You almost caught that.
That's all right.
Yeah.
But she was exactly right.
So what you have to do
is that-- I think we
have to follow the fact
that the pointers are now
pointing to different values.
So the value-- sorry, the
pointer of c repointed to a.
And so that shifted all of our numbers.
And that's why, when you access the
value stored there, it's different.
Does that make sense?
OK.
Cool.
Everyone good, before I move on?
AUDIENCE: Does the-- when you're going
down the rows in the left column,
does the first row affect the second row
and then the second-- like, it's all--
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So imagine it's code where I just typed
in a equals b times c, a star equals c.
Just imagine that I've
just ran this code
and I didn't print out what
all of these things were.
If I were just to print the first
thing at the top, it would be here.
If after I ran all of
those lines of code,
what these values should
be at the end are that.
So I've actually written a program here.
I haven't done all of
the multiplication.
But just imagine.
So here I just have a
program called pointers.
I'm going to zoom in if you guys-- OK.
So I've created variables a, b, and c.
I've set them equal to
3, 4, and 5 and I've
created their corresponding pointers.
And then here I'm just going
to print out what that is.
So let me run that.
Do you guys see-- crap.
Do you guys see how a,
b and c are those values
but their pointers are this giant
garbage value that we don't care about?
So if I were to actually plug
in all the multiplication
and then reprint all of
this, it would execute out
to what that is at the bottom.
So if you guys want to play around
with actually physically coding,
you guys can just plug all of those in.
The code will be online and then your
values should print to that afterwards.
And then you'll see how the pointer
addresses have actually reassigned.
So you'll see how the
address of c actually becomes
to equal whatever the address of a was.
And they'll match whatever
that large number is.
Good question.
Everyone all right?
One last call for questions.
OK.
All right.
So prepare to have your mind
blown a slightly bit more.
Arrays are actually just pointers.
That's all they are.
And remember, what are strings?
They're also arrays.
So what are strings really?
They're like pointers to the
beginning of a char of more chars.
So it's just concepts that start
to build on top of each other.
So that's why-- you
remember in lecture, David,
when he had that comparison
of int string mom
is something and then
another string mom and you
try to equate the two to each other,
they give you different values.
It's because strings
themselves aren't values.
All they are are memory addresses char--
they are arrays of chars and arrays
are just pointers.
So, in essence, when
David was comparing--
is it OK if I erase all of this?
So in lecture when David
had mom equals equals mom,
to us that seems to be the same thing.
Right?
But, in the computer underneath the
hood, what is actually happening
is that this string,
all that is is an array.
With an ampersand-- or, sorry,
with a null terminator at the end.
Right?
Backslash 0.
Wrong backslash.
So all they were-- all
these two strings were--
are array of size fours with
the letters of mom and mom.
But what arrays really are are just
pointers to a specific place in memory
that tells you to start your array.
So in this case, all this was
was just some garbage value,
some random pointer.
And all this was was
some other garbage value.
Let's just say 0x200.
And so when you try to equal
them two to each other,
they evaluate to false because
the addresses-- the pointers
that they were-- were different.
Whereas it's different if you're
trying to compare actual integers.
Like if you wanted to compare--
in the last example-- int a to b,
they would evaluate
to true as Elliot said
because they were
integers that were stored
and you're evaluating just the values.
Here, because strings are arrays
and all arrays are pointers,
that's why they aren't
equal to each other.
So kind of confusing, that graphic.
But let's just imagine.
We've create an array of size
3 with index from 0 to 2-- 0,
1, 2 with the values of 1,
2, and 3 stored in them.
All the array really
does-- here, let's just
say I'm creating a pointer
to that array that's
accessing the value at the
first index of this array.
So here it would be 0.
Right?
Does everyone understand how
that first line evaluated?
Great.
And so if you wanted to initialize
the additional values after that,
all we're doing is reassigning.
So 0, 1, 2, 1.
So this pointer that was once
pointing to here, all we're doing
is moving it down.
That's what the plus 1 is doing.
And then we can put 2 there.
If we wanted to put 3 in the one
after, we would erase this pointer,
put 3 in there.
Does that make sense everyone?
Yeah.
Did you have a question?
AUDIENCE: It's [INAUDIBLE] have
a question, I'll say it anyway.
I don't think it's actually a
question but-- in English, array
equals 1 makes sense.
We're like, OK, the first thing.
But things are 0 index
[INAUDIBLE] the array equals 0
to indicate the first spot.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So actually what I'm doing here is
I'm not accessing the first index.
All I was doing-- so first of all,
tell me what does star array do?
What does a star before a pointer do?
AUDIENCE: It indicates a pointer.
That you're declaring a pointer.
It de--
ANDI PENG: It dereferences which means
it goes and actually gets the value.
Right?
So in this case, you want to get
the value here and set that to 1.
Yeah?
So I'm not actually-- I don't
really care about the index of this,
all I'm doing is just iterating down
by moving my pointer down the array.
And then eventually I
have to stop it, right?
And the way that I stop
is when I hit, in the case
of a string, a null terminator.
I know, oh, if I hit a back-- if I see
backslash 0, I know I'm done with this
and I know that I can just
stop iterating through.
Really good question.
And we'll really go farther
in depth in this next week
because the piece that's going to
involve a lot of usage of pointers.
But just know that right now,
that's just a different more--
that's just a different way for
the computer to write, essentially,
what we've been doing.
Like David said in
lecture, the way that we
access an array is just by doing
array 0, bracket 0, if we just
wanted to access the first value.
All the computer is doing is turning
that into that and iterating itself.
So we call it syntactic
sugar which is just
a fancy way of saying user friendly
ways of us knowing how to program.
But the computer
underneath, what it's doing,
it's actually just having
a pointer that's adjusting.
But the way that we write it,
because it's easier for us
to think about things in terms of
boxes and how to move down boxes,
is by having the brackets.
Sorry, that was really,
really poorly but-- yeah.
AUDIENCE: So how would
you compare two strings
to see if they're equal to each other?
ANDI PENG: So David wrote
this program in lecture
so I'm just going to go
over quickly and briefly.
The way you would do that
is that you would actually
need to go and compare the
addresses-- or the values
obtained from the pointers.
So remember, how do you
obtain the value here?
I don't care about the address here.
How do I actually get the
value of whatever's here?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
So you compare the star
here versus the star here.
Are those equal.
And then you go down.
Are the star here and
the star here equal?
OK.
They're equal.
And you just keep going down
until you've hit the end of both.
And if all of them are equal, then
you know your string is equal.
And C actually has a
function written called
String Comp which actually just
does that for you so you dont'
have to write it yourself.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: I think in lecture
is when we do the compare.
We don't really need a
counter like pi, right?
ANDI PENG: You don't
because we don't really care
how many boxes we've iterated through.
All we care is that we're going to
keep going until I know to stop.
And you know to stop when
there's some sort of indication
that you're at a null terminator.
Yeah.
So--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So in the case of comparing
strings, I don't really
care how many letters
are-- I need to compare
if they're true or false if
they're equal to each other.
I don't care how many letters
are in each of them, right?
I just care that this
matches with this and the one
after matches and the one after
matches all the way up until the end.
Right?
Does that make sense?
So I don't really care how many letters,
I just care that all of the letters
match.
Yeah.
OK.
Can I move on from this?
Great.
We're running a little short on
time so I'm going to just allow you
guys to briefly look at this.
Run it into your ID if
you guys are curious.
And you guys can see what
this will be printing out.
OK.
So something that we'll also touch on a
bit is the idea of pointer arithmetic.
Which, all it is, is
rather than adjusting
the values of what is stored
at the address of your pointer,
it's just actually changing
the address itself.
So if you as the human wanted
to adjust your pointer manually,
the way you would do that is just
do n times the size of the pointer.
Right?
So an int.
An int-- how many bytes
in memory is an int?
It's four, right?
So if I know I have an array of all
ints and I want it to point to the one
afterwards, I'd know I just have to
move my pointer down four bytes, right?
And so n times the size
of the pointer bytes
is however many bytes you're just
going to move your pointer down by.
So for example, if we have an array of
ints, the first one, let's just say,
is stored as 0x00.
You know the next one is going to be at
0x04 because that's four bytes later.
And the one after that's going to
be 0x08 and so on and so forth.
And so, guys, take a look.
All you're doing here is
that you have a pointer y
and you're adding that to your
memory so that you can move down
the blocks of memory allocated.
Kind of a higher level concept.
You guys won't need
to know for this week,
but that's all it's doing down there.
OK.
Another joke time.
Two strings walk into a bar.
One says, I'd like a rum
and Coke garbage values.
The other says, you'll have to excuse
my friend, he's not null terminated.
You guys get it.
Sorry.
This is how I keep myself
going when I prep for section
is I insert a couple joke slides.
Anyways.
OK.
Before I move on--
so, essentially, we've
covered all the conceptual
issues related to pointers.
And then we're going to talk-- moving
more, talk about why that's important
and how that fits into the
idea of memory management.
But before I move on,
does anyone have questions
about pointer use, what's going
on when you're creating pointers,
how are the referencing each
other, how are they dereferencing?
Any questions about
that before I move on?
OK.
Great.
So this brings us into this
larger higher level concept
of memory management as a whole.
So, essentially, in
your computer, there's
two basic types of memory or
regions in which memory is stored.
You have here what's called
the heap and you have down here
what's called the stack.
And we're going to talk about
the stack first because it's
the more finagley one that you
have to kind of conceptually
understand what's going on.
So all the stack is-- think of
it as a physical stack of memory
where you have a block of memory
that's set aside for your program
while it's running.
And this is where, essentially, all
of your local variables are stored.
So this is just a zoomed
in picture of that stack.
The stack down there, I'm
just zooming in a bit more.
So, essentially, in a stack you have
a bunch of function in your program.
So let's just go back
to the week two example
where we had our main function
as well as a cube function
where we tried to create a function that
cubed-- that took parameters as input,
cubed them and returned
them back to main.
So the way that that's stored in memory
is that you have your main function
here at the bottom.
And then with each additional function
that you call and add on top of that,
the memory just stacks on top.
Think of it as a physical stack.
And so you have all of you main
variables of your main functions,
everything that's going on here, stored.
And then when you called
cube, it goes and it
creates copies of all those
parameters and it stores them
above in a different place.
And so why do we care?
The reason we care is that we can't just
use the parameters here-- the variables
here-- and we change them, we expect
them to also be changed here, right?
The idea is that they're saved
in different places in memory
so that, when you're accessing different
functions, what you think is happening
isn't actually happening because the
memory bits aren't interconnected.
And so the question that's really
important for us to kind of understand
is, what if, when we're running
a program, the size of a function
stack frame-- so physically, how
much memory do we have to give it?
Maybe it's a giant function so we
have to give it that much memory.
But if it were smaller we'd
need a tiny little bit.
So the idea is that when we're running
a program the size of that function
is dependent upon how many
variables and the type of variables
that we want to give it.
But what if the number of
variables-- and their sizes,
that's determined not
by you the encoder but
is determined by the actual
user of your program.
So if I wanted to create a function
that took strings from the user,
but I don't actually know how large
those strings are, it's hard for me
to allot the specific
amount of memory needed.
Right?
Because if this function-- if
this user inputs a giant string,
it's going to create an error
of what's called essentially
stack overflow where you go beyond the
bounds of the memory that you have.
And so then what do we do?
If we can't just create this giant
stack that can save everything,
what do we do to solve that problem?
So we are going to move on and talk
about this second type of memory
and then we can talk about how
we can use the two together
to solve that question.
So now we're going to move up
to a different part of memory
in our computer.
That's called the heap.
So all the heap is is a pool
of available memory that
can be allocated dynamically.
So that can change while
your program is running.
And so a region of
unused memory that can
be allowed-- that can be
allotted with the function
called malloc, or memory allocation.
So, essentially, when
you're running a program,
you can dynamically create memory from
the heap and use that all down here.
And so then, all of your functions
here can access the heap.
And so malloc, this idea that David
kind of quickly, briefly glossed over
in lecture, is just a way for
you to control your memory.
Like, when you're just creating
stack functions, when you're just
having your main function
with your random functions,
you think of them as children that just
ran away when you were done with them.
They were really bad children.
You create them, you
teach them something,
and then when you want to
access them again they're
not there because your
memory just ran away.
But malloc, or the heap, is a way
of having better children, where
you can kind of create
them, assign them values,
use them-- that sounded really
bad-- use them however you wanted,
but then be able to control
them and then free up memory
whenever you need them.
So then, when you're done with your
function, the children come back to you
and you still have that data there.
So the way that we malloc, or create,
memory is by the function void star
malloc size in bytes.
So that's just the prototype
for why we do that.
So an example is we create a pointer
of type int-- int star pointer-- equals
malloc size of int.
So the reason why we do size
of and not just a number--
because we all know that
an int is four bytes,
right-- but an int is only four
bytes on certain operating systems.
The idea for us as
programmers is that we
want to create code that can
run on all computers, not just
our simple computers.
And so that's why we like to use
size of and not just the number four.
Does that make sense to everyone?
So size of-- all it is a C
function or operator that
tells you how many bytes of memory does
a certain type of variable take up.
So in this case, size of an int is four.
Four bytes.
And malloc is going to free
up four bytes in your heap,
then you can then use in your main
function to be able to store memory.
Is everyone clear on that so far?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: I'm clear but
just to be over clear--
ANDI PENG: OK.
Totally fine.
AUDIENCE: --size of is [INAUDIBLE]
can actually [INAUDIBLE]
and it will actually do the
thing that we want it to.
It's not some pseudocode.
ANDI PENG: No.
AUDIENCE: It's like a real thing--
ANDI PENG: This is real code.
AUDIENCE: --we can use it.
It's actual.
Cool.
ANDI PENG: Size of comes with C.
AUDIENCE: That makes my life happier.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So if you're a lazy programmer
like I kind of am sometimes,
I don't like memorizing
what size of an int
is, I don't like memorizing
with the size of a float is.
Size of just tells you what
it is and that's a lot easier.
All right.
So an important thing
that you guys all want
to keep in mind when you're
using malloc is that you always
have to check to see if it's null.
So like I said, back to
that picture of the heap.
The heap is just this giant
stack of memory that you've got.
And you want to be able to take chunks
of memory from it and use it, right?
But what if you have no
more memory in that heap?
What if I've already used all
of it and I try to malloc more?
That doesn't exist.
Well, that's why you're
going to get an error.
You're going to seg fault. You're going
to have a segmentation fault where you
try to access things that aren't there.
And so the way we do
that and the way that we
prevent that is that we check
to see if the pointer's null.
So if I were to malloc something
and I had no more memory,
that would print an error because the
pointer returned to you is just null.
And so the way we do this--
this is just great design,
just memorize this-- is that any
time you try to malloc anything,
you're going to need to
check to see if it's null.
Because whenever you try to
obtain memory from the heap,
you always have to make
sure that you have memory.
That's all it is.
So pretty much those three
lines of code, memorize.
Every time you malloc, plop them in.
You're going to need them.
Because I guarantee you, we're going
to test you on a case and your computer
is going to explode because you're
going to try to access memory that's
not there and things are going to
crash and it's not going to be good.
So just drill that into your brain.
Malloc, null.
Good.
All right.
Then this begets the
question of what happens
after we're done using that memory.
Because the whole idea
of having malloc was
that we have this heap that we can take
memory from and then we can use it.
Right?
And then what we have to remember
is that, after we're done with it,
we can then free it.
Let it go.
We can let it go.
Or else you're also going to leak
memory and more bad things will happen.
Essentially, whenever
you're touching memory,
bad things will happen if you
don't do things correctly.
So you have to check to see, first,
if you have the memory available.
And then after you're done, you want to
free it and allow your operating system
to take it back.
So the way we do that is just that
function, void free, and the pointer
to that heap of memory.
So the example is free pointer.
It's pretty easy, simple,
don't want to forget it.
So check to see if it's null, free.
Everyone good?
So once again, code that you guys
can kind of quickly take a glance at.
I know it's a lot of new syntax and
it's all right if you're like, ah,
what does that mean again?
No worries.
All this was meant to be is displaying
an action, how all of these things
can be used together.
So that is put together
like a bunch of the past
slides we just went
through into one program.
AUDIENCE: In a way
that we can actually--
ANDI PENG: In a way that
we can actually use.
You could plop that into your ID,
you can run it and it would work.
AUDIENCE: OK.
So that's real?
ANDI PENG: That's real.
Yeah.
I try to make it so the
fonts are different so
that whenever I type real
code the font is font code
and that my note code is different, but
I don't know if that actually works.
AUDIENCE: No.
I think that--
ANDI PENG: OK.
AUDIENCE: --sometimes
[INAUDIBLE] and I'm
like, that would be really cute
if it was actually a usable thing
but then it's not a usable thing.
I like that this is a usable thing.
ANDI PENG: OK.
Yeah.
I'll pass that along.
Be like, David, kids are really
sad when you write fake code.
All right.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So the ptr here
is not actually a pointer,
it's a block of memory?
ANDI PENG: So are you talking about
the first line or the one down here?
Are you talking about this one here?
AUDIENCE: The ptr is
different things in--
ANDI PENG: Well, so up here
what I'm doing-- actually,
let's just go through here.
This kind of ties in
nicely all of the concepts.
So here we have int star ptr.
So int pointer, that's where
we're actually creating
a pointer that points to an integer.
Well, it's going to point to an integer.
And we're going to malloc, or
give it, enough memory allotted
to store an integer.
So four bytes in this case.
And then if that equals null-- equals
equals null-- we're going to print.
Oh, you have an error because
you're out of memory, right?
Otherwise the returning one,
that just tells your program
that you've got an error.
And then if you do
have that memory, it's
going to store whatever get
int gives you into the location
and set it as the value of the pointer.
So it's actually going to
physically erase this value
and put whatever get int returns.
And then you're going to
print whatever they entered.
AUDIENCE: And that's
going to be in the heap?
ANDI PENG: That's going
to be in the heap.
AUDIENCE: And so that
will be accessible.
ANDI PENG: Exactly.
Nice.
Good.
AUDIENCE: So when we free ptr at this
final step, we are freeing the pointer
or we're freeing the block?
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So we're freeing the pointer--
well, freeing the block of memory.
So the only way we can even access
the memory is by having the pointer.
If you don't have the pointer, you're
like, oh, I don't know where it is,
right?
So if you free it, you're essentially
freeing that entire block.
Then your computer knows, oh,
there's nothing usable here,
I can just put garbage
values back into it again.
AUDIENCE: So integers do exist on that?
ANDI PENG: Do integers exist?
Sorry.
Can you rephrase your question?
AUDIENCE: I meant, after you free the
pointer, the integer that you get,
will that still exist?
ANDI PENG: No, it won't.
Or at least it'll exist in your
memory before your computer does
whatever with it, but there's
no way for you to get that.
Because you freed the pointer.
You don't know where it is anymore.
Yeah.
I'm going to move on here.
Phew.
So we're through a lot of the conceptual
difficulties of memory management
and we're just going
to essentially spend
5, 10 minutes going
over syntax things that
will be usable and useful for you guys,
but nothing too conceptually out there.
OK.
So we're completely changing gears here.
Memory management, difficult.
Pointers, difficult. Yes.
It's really, really hard.
Totally fine.
That's why your piece is
going to be really hard.
But if you go and do
the things that we're
supposed to do, make
sure things are null,
make sure to check if things are
null, make sure to free memory,
make sure things aren't
leaking, you'll be good.
You will be set.
All right.
So we're going to move into this
completely new concept of redirection.
And so before now, the
main way that we've
been interacting with our
programs is through standard input
and standard output.
Right?
We as the user input
things and the computer
spits it back to us in the terminal.
But there are other
ways for us to interact
with the computer with our
programs that aren't just me
physically typing things
in when I'm prompted.
And the way we do that is
through the greater than carrot
and the pipe symbol.
So we can also read and
write to files using that.
So the way that we do this is the
greater than carrot, all that is doing
is writing whatever your
file has to a separate file.
So for example, if I
wanted to run hello world
and I wanted the output to
be saved in another file
and not just printed out to me, I
can just do greater than carrot,
output.txt.
So all that's doing is taking
my hello.world program,
and whatever the output is, it's
saving in a file called output.txt.
So the way that David did the
.csv with names of students,
it's the same that you guys can do.
And what's especially
useful here are the greater
than-- the two greater than carrot
signs which you can append to an output
file, which means that you
can just add on top of it.
You can just keep adding to
output.txt of each additional thing
that you're doing.
Or, if you start getting into more
complicated programs, the two greater
than carrot, that just prints
out the error messages.
So say you have a giant
amount of error messages
and you want to read
through all of them and you
don't want to have to scroll
through your terminal,
you can actually just do
greater than output.txt
and it's going to save
all of your errors
in a file called output.txt that
you can go through and read.
AUDIENCE: Where is the text file saved?
ANDI PENG: It's saved in the same
directory that your program is.
So you just go back and look for it.
And the same thing we
can do for input is
that we can actually take
the contents of some file
and we can input that into our program.
So rather than having to do command
line arguments of where you physically
have to type things
every single time, you
can actually just have a file called
input.txt that just puts it all in.
And then pipe is specially cool because
it can take the output of one program
and use it as the input
of another program.
So for example, in your guys' Vigenere,
there is this line of code that you
guys are running that you maybe perhaps
didn't really know what it was doing--
this ./generate 1000 pipe ./42.
Right?
So all that's doing, if we just
take a look at this step by step,
the ./generate, that means I'm
running my program generate.
That is taking in 1,000 at its input.
So I want to generate 1,000 random
numbers and I'm going to pipe that--
or I'm going to use that-- output
as input for my program called find.
And I'm going to try to find 42 out of
the numbers generated from those 1,000
numbers.
Does that line of code makes
sense to everyone else?
So in this way we're saving
ourselves a ton of steps.
We don't have to run generate, save
the file and then put it into find.
We can just do it all in one line.
So whatever generate is outputting,
plop it right back in to find.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: And in terms of command
line arguments, is that-- that's
three command line arguments?
It's generate, find-- no, four--
generate, 1,000, find and 42?
Or is the--
ANDI PENG: So the pipe doesn't really
count as a command line argument
because the compiler or the
terminal knows that pipe,
oh, I know that I must look before
the pipe because that's my output
and I must look after the
pipe because that's my input.
So it knows that-- the
./generate and 1,000,
those are two command then arguments
just for the first program.
And then the ./find 42 are two command
line arguments for the second program.
Yeah.
Everyone good on this?
So just real quick, what do
these three lines of code do?
Fairly simple.
Anyone want to tell me
what the first line does?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ANDI PENG: Think of it as just--
what does the greater than carrot do?
AUDIENCE: It puts something
into the next line.
ANDI PENG: So what is
the opposite of that?
AUDIENCE: It puts the next
thing into the first thing.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So all that's doing is you're
running a program .hello--
you're running a program named hello.
You're going to give it
an input called input.txt.
Right?
Because think of it as just
physically going into hello.
And then you're going to save the
output in a file called output.txt.
How about the second line?
Want to tell me what
the second line does?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ANDI PENG: Sorry.
Say that again.
Elliot.
AUDIENCE: So it puts a
list of numbers into find.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
So find, remember, in
order to run find you
need to know where you're searching.
And so all that it's doing
here is that it's giving you
a pre assigned set of
numbers, then find is going
to search those for the number of 42.
And then 15.
Remember, you guys ran this
when you tested your code.
Now do you understand what it was doing?
AUDIENCE: It's putting in
the set of instructions
to [INAUDIBLE] through a three by
three to get the-- to win the game.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: It inputs those
instructions into the program.
ANDI PENG: Pretty much.
So the tilde CS50./pset3/3x3, all that
was doing was that we created a text
file that had all the
titles ready for you guys.
And so for your game to play, you just--
we just put that into your program.
So we had created this
board and then we're
putting that board into your program
that ran it and created a tile of three
by three.
That's all that it was doing.
And so there was actually magic
going on behind the scenes
that you guys didn't
program that we programmed.
But now you guys understand why
we did that so it's all good.
All right.
So while redirection is a very
useful, C has a general mechanism
for reading and writing
files of its own.
Nothing conceptually
difficult here so I'm
just going to go through
really, really quick.
All it is is some memorization
and making sure you guys
are syntactically using it correctly.
The way that we'd do that is
create a reference to the file,
we'd open the file, and then we
would do all the reading and writing
and then close the file.
When thing you guys
want to keep in mind is
that while doing this, because
we are closing and opening files,
all of those commands are included
in the standard-- the standard I/O
library.
So make sure whenever you're
doing this that you've included--
#included-- standard I/O dot h.
So real quickly.
Step one, you want to create
a reference to that file.
And now that we've done pointers, you
guys can tell me what that line of code
is doing.
Right?
All that it's doing is creating a
pointer named file of type file.
Because you know that it's going
to point to a file and you're
going to open the file.
Then you're f open-- all
it does is open the file.
This is the file name.
And there's three things you can do.
You can read, write or append.
Most generally, you guys
will be reading or writing
because you're either going to be
inputting a file or outputting one.
So pretty much r and w are the two
things you're going to be using most.
So in this case, all I've done is
create a pointer to a file called file.
I'm opening it and I'm reading-- I'm
opening this file called file.txt
and I'm reading it.
That's all I'm doing at this point.
And then these are just functions in
which you can read different things
or write different things
or skip to different places
where you want to look.
All of these are online.
All of these you can just Google.
No need to memorize them.
They're just there,
disposable for your use
if you would like to
be able to use them.
So if I wanted to just read
in one character at a time,
I would do file fgetc.
Or if I wanted to read in a line of
text at a time, I would do fgets.
And so on and so forth.
All of these just do different
things you guys can use.
And then lastly, after I'm
done reading or writing,
I'm just going to fclose that file.
And remember, this is one
of those, remember, please
do this or else your file
is not going to work.
Always open a file before
reading or reading,
you have to always
close it if you open it.
Same thing with memory, right?
You have to always take
memory and free it.
Here you have to always open a
file before trying to read it
and you always have to
close it after you open it.
So this is also online.
I'm going to challenge you guys to
kind of write a program that prints
hello.world to a file.
It's really simple.
It essentially just involves
the few lines of code
that were just written previously.
You're going to put them
together and write that.
So some important things to keep in mind
while you guys are trying to use this.
If this is all very useful
for your pset this week,
is that fopen creates a file pointer.
It's not actually the physical file.
All it is pointing to the
file you want to open.
And you're essentially, whenever
you're using any of the other functions
like fread or fwrite
or fgetc or fgets, is
that you're just passing around this
pointer to all of those functions.
So you're not actually taking that
file and using it for your functions,
you're just taking the pointer
and putting it to those functions
so that you can use.
And if you forget to close
your file after you use it,
your program is going to leak memory.
Essentially, all that means
is that bad things will happen
and your program will
not function correctly.
And so on the pset in
the beginning, I think
there's a short where he explained--
Nate explained-- what Valgrind was.
All Valgrind is is a way for you to
make sure you're not leaking memory.
So you guys want to make
sure you watch that short
because that explains it
really well what happens.
OK.
So I went through that really,
really quickly because I really
want to get to talking about
the pset before you guys leave.
Does anyone have questions conceptually?
Mostly all this is just syntax that
you can use to read or write files.
Finally, everyone's favorite.
We're going to talk about the pset now.
So, show of hands, how many of
you guys read the spec this week?
Oh, that's half.
That's good.
So this is actually a really,
really fun pset in the sense
that you feel like a
detective because you're
doing all these really cool things
that you didn't know that you could do
but now it's really cool
that you can do them.
And it's actually a lot
simpler than you guys think.
So the basic halves of
this program are you're
going to download source code or
distribution code written by us.
And you're going to have one folder
called BMP and another folder
called JPG.
Within your BMP, you're
going to have three programs.
One of them is already written for you.
So copy.c is a program
we've already written
for you that you're going to download.
All that does is take as input a picture
and makes a copy of it as output.
That's all that file is doing.
But what you want to do for
whodunit-- so how many of you
guys remember in fifth grade or maybe--
you're younger-- maybe third grade,
when you guys had secret messages and
you had to put a piece of paper over it
to decode the message?
Yeah?
So that's all we're doing
except this time for a computer.
So we've given you this lovely image.
Doesn't look like
anything but underneath
it is a clue that's going to help you
with answering the question we ask you.
Essentially what you want
to do is input that file,
tweak some things around,
maybe adjust the colors,
shift things, so that whatever
the message is can come through.
So inside there are hidden
pixels and information
that if you write your code correctly
is going to decode and tell you
what this clue is.
And so some helpful hints as to how
you'd go about approaching this.
You really want to familiarize
yourself with file I/O
because we're reading from
files and writing to files.
Right?
And so whenever we do
that, that involves
file I/O. You're going to
have to familiarize yourself
with, how do you open up pictures files?
How do you write to files as pictures?
How do you do all of those things?
That's going to be really useful.
Secondly, how are you
going to be able to change
the colors that clear up this picture?
It's probably going to involve
adjusting your pixels or your RGB values
somewhere in there, essentially.
There's no right way of
solving this as long as you
can-- as long as you can kind of
adjust those pixels to make it
look like something that you care about.
That's all we care about as well.
So there's many ways to do this.
Just play around with it until
you get something that works.
And you would be really
surprised how few lines of code
you need to actually do this.
I'm talking like three
lines of code total
that you need to write
in order to do this.
So if you find yourself
writing 40, 30 lines of code,
you're probably doing it wrong.
All you have to do is kind of
play around with the colors
and see how that works out.
So then we head into a bit
to harder of a problem.
Here we have resize
where we're asking you
to-- we're giving you as input
a picture and your resizing
this image into something
larger or something smaller
depending on the dimensions we give you.
So remember in lecture
that David quickly
glanced over how information
is detected by your computers
to mean it's a type of file.
So a Word file has special
characters in front of that
tell your computer it's a Word file.
Same thing with a JPEG.
In this case we're going
to give you a JPEG file.
All we know is that JPEG
file is a picture, right?
But the computer distinguishes
it in very specific ways.
So at the beginning of
any JPEG file, you're
going to have what's called the bitmap
info header and the bitmap file header.
All those are are
different pieces of data
that tell your computer, hey,
listen up, a JPEGs coming up
and these are the dimensions or
characteristics of that JPEG.
So you guys really want to know
what information is stored inside
of those headers and
what is the size of them.
Because when you're running
through your program,
you're going to want to
skip over that amount.
Right?
Because you don't care
about modifying the header,
you care about modifying what's after.
Right?
So make sure you guys know
how large those things are.
Secondly, before you begin
trying to resize your image,
you're probably going to want to
save the dimensions of the original.
Right?
Because if I tell you this picture
is 100 pixels by 100 pixels,
and I want you to make
it four times bigger,
you know that you have to
multiply those dimensions by four.
So then you want an output file
400 by 400 pixels, for example.
So it's really useful for you guys to
save the dimensions of the original.
And then afterwards, after
you're done resizing,
you can write new headers with
those new dimensions after resizing.
And the way that you physically
can create in large pixels
is that you can write
new RGB-- remember, RGB,
all that stands for is red, green,
and blue-- pixels to an out file.
And you're going to want to
have different amounts of what
we call padding.
All padding is are spaces
before and after pictures
that tell your-- essentially that
tell your picture how large it
should be taking up.
This is very abstract for a lot of
you if you haven't read the pset spec,
but it's going to be
very useful for when
you're actually reading through it.
You're like, oh, yeah, that makes sense.
Why do I have to do this?
Makes sense.
Lastly, this is probably one of
the most frustrating programs
ever just because you can't
tell if it's working or not.
All this program, recover, is
doing is that, if run properly,
it should be able to suddenly
recover 50 images that
were lost on our hard drive.
And so the problem with this program
is that you can't really test it
because either you recovered
them or you didn't.
And so you kind of just
have to play around with it,
and if your program is
working properly, you'll
suddenly see that in
your directory you've
got a giant amount of
pictures that are now there.
So how I would approach
this problem is, we're
going to give you what's
called a card.raw file.
Essentially, that's
just a corrupted file
with all the pictures stored that
you're going to need to recover from.
So you're probably going to want
to input your card.raw, or open,
your card.raw file and you're
going to want to manipulate
it to be able to store JPEGs.
So I would start by tracking and storing
each individual JPEG as you find it.
You're not going to individually all
of a sudden just create all 50 JPEGs.
You're going to want to keep
track of how many you're opening.
And then you want to
make sure, when you're
writing to a buffer-- you guys
will know what I'm talking about
once you read the spec-- you want to
make sure that you're using an unsigned
char buffer.
And then you want to ask
yourself the question of,
how many bytes are in a
CF-- are in a card file?
That's how many you're going to
want to read into your buffer.
You're going to want to make sure
the two align because then you
won't have random memory leaking out.
You know exactly how many
bytes you need and how many
bytes that you want them to have.
And then finally, you want to
use a function called sprint--
s print f-- to generate custom file
names for every new JPEG that you find.
So as you create and
find JPEGs in your card,
you're going to want to
store them and name them.
Right?
And so you're going to
want to use that function
to create the names that
can store all of your JPEGs.
And lastly, don't forget to close
each JPEG after you're done.
Because what you're
going to do is you're
going to probably have
some sort of a loop that
iterates through all of your JPEGs.
You're going to write a JPEG
and rename it as you find it.
But after you're done
with every single JPEG,
you need to close it so you can start
over and move on to the next picture.
And so something that's
really fun that we like to do,
because this is such a weird problem set
but also a weirdly satisfying problem
set, is that all of the pictures we
have for you, if you recover properly,
all the pictures are pictures of
your wonderful teaching staff, both
of Harvard, at here-- and here at Yale.
And if you happen to
recover all these pictures
and identify the staff
members in those cards,
and take selfies with us if
you find us around campus,
for every photo you submit to us, we'll
give you a gigabyte of Dropbox space.
So let's do the math here.
If there's 50 pictures and
50 teaching staff members,
if you happen to find all 50 of
us, that's 50 gigabytes of Dropbox,
basically, we'll be giving you guys.
So some extra added incentives
if you guys didn't just
care about recovering lost images.
There's also some added incentives.
It's a fun problem set.
It really is.
It's kind of frustrating but then it
becomes really fun when you realize,
wow, it's working and now I
have all of these pictures
that I've just created by myself.
Any questions on the pset?
For anyone who's already
started, if you have questions,
I'll be here for a couple minutes after
section if you want to talk to me.
Well done, guys.
I'm sorry, I information
dumped on you guys.
Pointers are really, really
challenging and frustrating.
And I'm really glad that
you guys stayed with me.
We'll talk more in depth
about the next week
as we start doing hash tables and
more functions that involve them.
Yeah.
So if anyone has any
questions, I'll be around.
Thanks for coming and take more
candy because there's more candy.
Cool.