>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DOUG LLOYD: Selection sort is an
algorithm that, as you might expect,
sorts a set of elements.
And algorithm recall
is a step-by-step set
of instructions for completing a task.
>> In selection sort the
basic idea is this,
find the smallest unsorted element and
add it to the end of the sorted list.
Effectively what this does is build
a sorted list, one element at a time.
Breaking it down to pseudocode
we could state this algorithm
as follows, repeat this until
no unsorted elements remain.
Search through the unsorted
data to find the smallest value,
then swap the smallest value with the
first element of the unsorted part.
>> It may help to visualize this,
so let's take a look at this.
So this, I contend, is an
unsorted array and I've
indicated it by indicating that all
of the elements are colored red,
they are not yet sorted.
This is the entire
unsorted part of the array.
>> So let's go through the steps of
selection sort to sort this array.
So again, we're gonna repeat
until no unsorted elements remain.
We're gonna search through the
data to find the smallest value,
and then swap that value with the
first element of the unsorted part.
>> Right now, again, the entire
array is the unsorted part.
All of the red elements are unsorted.
So we search through and
we find the smallest value.
We start at the beginning,
we go to the end,
we find the smallest value is, one.
So that's part one.
And then part two, swap that value with
the first element of the unsorted part,
or the first red element.
>> In this case that would be
five, so we swap one and five.
When we do this, we can
visually see that we've
moved the smallest valued element
of the array, to the very beginning.
Effectively sorting that element.
>> And so we can indeed confirm
and state that one, is sorted.
And so we'll indicate the sorted portion
of our array, by coloring it blue.
>> Now we just repeat the process again.
We search through the unsorted part of
the array to find the smallest element.
In this case, it's two.
>> We swap that with the first
element of the unsorted part.
In this case two also happens to be
the first element of the unsorted part.
So we swap two with itself,
which really just leaves two
where it is, and it's sorted.
Continuing on, we search through
to find the smallest element.
It's three.
We swap it with the first
element, which is five.
And now three is sorted.
>> We search through again, and we
find the smallest element is four.
We swap it with the first element of the
unsorted part, and now four is sorted.
>> We find that five is
the smallest element.
We swap it with the first
element of the unsorted part.
And now five is sorted.
>> And then lastly, our
unsorted part consists
of just a single element,
so we search through
and we find that six is the
smallest, and in fact, only element.
And then we can state that it is sorted.
And now we've switched our array
from being completely unsorted
in red, to completely sorted
in blue, using selection sort.
>> So what's the worst case scenario here?
Well in the absolute worst
case, we have to look over
all of the elements of the array to
find the smallest unsorted element,
and we have to repeat
this process n times.
Once for each element of the array
because we only, in this algorithm,
sort one element at time.
>> What's the best case scenario?
Well it's exactly the same, right?
We actually have to still step through
every single element of the array
in order to confirm that it is,
in fact, the smallest element.
>> So the worst case runtime, we
have to repeat a process n times,
once for each of n elements.
And in the best case scenario,
we have to do the same.
>> So thinking back to our
computational complexity toolbox,
what do you think is the worst
case runtime for selection sort?
What do you think is the best
>> Did you guess Big O of n squared,
and Big Omega of n squared?
You'd be right.
Those are, in fact, the
worst case and best case run
times, for selection sort.
>> I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.