>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DOUG LLOYD: In our videos
on web development topics,
we've mentioned the concept of
a database a few times, right?
So a database you're
probably familiar with from
say using Microsoft Excel
or Google Spreadsheets.
It's really just an organized
set of tables, rows, and columns.
>> And a database is where
our website stores
information that is important
for our website to work properly.
Again, a really common example here
is storing usernames and passwords
in a database, so that when
a user logs into our website,
the database can be queried to see
if that user exists in the database.
And if they are, checking that
their password is correct.
And if their password is correct,
then we can give them whatever page
they're requesting.
>> So you're probably, again, familiar
with this idea from Excel or Google
Spreadsheets.
We have databases,
tables, rows, and columns.
And that's really sort
of the fundamental set
of hierarchical breakdown here.
So here's an Excel spreadsheet.
And if you've ever opened this
or another similar program
you know that these here are
rows-- 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
These are columns.
>> Maybe down here, although you may
not use this feature terribly much--
I'll zoom in-- we have
this idea of a sheet.
So maybe these sheets, if
I alternate back and forth,
are different tables that
exist in my database.
And if we continue the example all
the way, the name of this database
is Book 1.
Maybe I have Book 2 and Book 3.
So each Excel file is a
database, each sheet is a table,
and inside of each table I have
this idea of rows and columns.
>> So how do I work with this database?
How do I get information from it?
Well there's a language called SQL--
which I usually just call Sequel--
and it stands for the
Structured Query Language.
And it is a programming language,
but it's a fairly limited programming
language.
It's not quite like others
that we have worked with.
But the purpose of this
programming language
is to query a database, to
ask information of a database,
find information in a
database, and so on.
>> We also, in CS50-- and it's a very
common platform, it's called MySQL.
That's what we use in the course.
It's an open source
platform that establishes
a so-called relational database--
a database, effectively.
We don't need to get
into too much detail
on what a relational database is.
But the SQL language is
very adept at working
with MySQL and other similar
styles of relational databases.
>> And many installations of
MySQL come with something
called phpMyAdmin, which
is a graphical user
interface-- a GUI-- that
makes it a little more
user friendly to execute
database queries,
because databases are not just used
by advanced programmers, right?
Sometimes there are
these small businesses,
and they can't afford to
hire a team of programmers,
but they still need to store
information in a database.
>> Something like phpMyAdmin
makes it very easy for somebody
who's never programmed before to
pick up and become familiar with how
to work with a database.
The problem is, phpMyAdmin, while
it's a fantastic tool for learning
about databases, it is manual.
You're going to have to log into
it and execute commands and type
things in manually.
>> And as we know from our
example on PHP web programming,
having to manually do
things on our website,
if we want a dynamic, active responsive
website, perhaps not the best approach.
We would like to find a way to
perhaps automate this somehow.
And SQL will enable us to do this.
So when we're going to
start working with SQL,
we first need to have a
database to work with.
Creating a database is
something you probably
will do in phpMyAdmin, because
you'll only need to do it once,
and the syntax for doing so
is a lot more straightforward.
It's a lot easier to do it
in a graphic user interface
than typing it out as a command.
The command can get a little cumbersome.
Similarly, creating a table can
get quite a bit cumbersome as well.
And so things like creating a database
and creating a table, which you're
probably only going to do once--
once per table, once per database--
it's OK to do that in
a graphical interface.
In the process of
creating a table, you'll
also have to specify all of the
columns that will be in that table.
What sort of information do
you want to store in the table?
Maybe a user's name and date of birth,
password, user ID number, and maybe
city and state, right?
>> And for every time we want to add a user
to the database, we want to get all six
of those pieces of information.
And we do that by adding
rows to the table.
So we first create a database,
then we create a table.
As part of creating
a table, we are asked
to specify every column that
we would like in this table.
And then as we start to add
information to the database
and query the database more
generally-- not just adding,
but everything else we
do-- we'll be dealing
with rows of the table, which is one
user's information from the entire set.
>> So every SQL column is capable of
holding data of a particular data type.
So we sort of eliminated this
idea of data types in PHP,
but they're back here in SQL.
And there's a lot of data types.
Here's just 20 of them, but
it's not even all of them.
So we have ideas like INTs--
Integers-- we probably know
that this column can hold integers.
And there are variations thereon--
SMALLINT, TINYINT, MEDIUMINT, BIGINT.
Maybe we don't always need four bites.
Maybe we need eight bytes, and so we
can use these variations on integers
to be a bit more space efficient.
We can do decimal numbers, we
can do floating point numbers.
These are pretty similar.
There are some differences,
and if you would
like to look up the
SQL sort of guide, you
can see what the slight
differences are between them.
>> Maybe we want to store
information about date and time.
Maybe we're keeping track of
when the user joined our website,
and so maybe we want
to have a column that's
a date time or a timestamp that
indicates when the user actually
signed up.
We can do geometries and linestrings.
This is actually pretty cool.
We could map out a
geographical area using
GIS coordinates to plot out an area.
So can actually store that sort
of information in a SQL column.
>> TEXT is just giant blobs of text, maybe.
ENUMs are kind of interesting.
They actually exist in C. We don't
talk about them because they're not
terribly commonly used, at least CS50.
But it's an enumerated data type, which
is capable of holding limited values.
>> A really good example here would be
to create an enum where the seven
possible values are Sunday, Monday,
Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, Friday,
Saturday, right?
That data type Day of
Week does not exist,
but we could create an
enumerated data type such
that that column can only ever hold
one of those seven possible values.
We've enumerated all
of the possible values.
>> Then we have CHAR and VARCHAR,
and I've color these green
because we're actually
going to take a second
to talk about the difference
between these two things.
So CHAR, unlike C where
CHAR was a single character,
in SQL a CHAR refers to
a fixed length string.
And when we create this
column, we actually
can specify the length of the string.
>> So in this example,
we might say CHAR(10).
That means that every
element of that column
will consist of 10 bytes of information.
No more, no less.
So if we try and put in a 15
bit or a 15 character element
or value into this column,
we're only get the first 10.
If we put in the two
character long value,
we're going to have the two
characters, and then eight null bites.
We'll never be more efficient than that.
>> A VARCHAR is kind of like
our notion of a string
that we're familiar
with from C or from PHP.
It's a variable length string.
And when you create
this column, you just
specify the maximum possible lengths.
So maybe 99, or commonly 255.
That would be the maximum length.
And so if we were storing
15 character string,
we would use 15 bytes, maybe 16
bytes for the null terminator.
If we were storing a
three character string,
we would use three or four bytes.
But we wouldn't use the full 99.
>> So why would we have both?
Well, if we need to figure out how
long something is with a VARCHAR,
we have to kind of iterate
across it just like we did in C
and figure out where it stops.
Whereas if we know that everything
in this column is 10 bytes, maybe
we know that information, we can jump
10 bytes, 10 bytes, 10 bytes, 10 bytes,
and always find the
beginning of the string.
>> So we may have some
wasted space with a CHAR,
but maybe there's a trade
off of having better speed
in navigating the database.
But maybe we want the
flexibility of a VARCHAR
instead of having-- If our CHAR
was 255, but most of our users
were only inputting three or four bytes
worth of information or three or four
characters worth of information.
>> But some users were using
the whole 255, maybe
VARCHAR would be more appropriate there.
It's sort of a trade off, and
generally for purposes of CS50,
you don't need to worry too much about
whether you use a CHAR or a VARCHAR.
But in the real world, these things
do matter because all of these columns
take up actual physical space.
And physical space, in the
real world, comes at a premium.
>> So one other consideration
when you're building a table
is to pick one column to be
what's called a primary key.
And a primary key is a column
where every single value is unique.
And that means that you can easily
pick out a single row just by looking
at the primary key of that row.
So for example, you
generally, with users,
don't want two users who
have the same user ID number.
And so maybe you have
lots of information,
and maybe two users can
have the same name--
you have John Smith and John Smith.
That's not necessarily a problem,
because there are multiple people
in the world named John Smith.
But we only have one user ID number
10, one user ID number 11, 12, 13.
We don't have two users
with the same number,
and so maybe user ID numbers
would be a good primary key.
>> We don't have any duplication,
and we can now uniquely
identify every single row just
by looking at that column.
Choosing primary keys can actually
make subsequent table operations
a lot easier because you can leverage
the fact that certain rows will
be unique, or a certain column
of your database or table
will be unique to pick
out particular rows.
>> You can also have a joint primary
key, which you may find occasion
to use, which is just a
combination of two columns that
is guaranteed to be unique.
So maybe you have one
column that's As and Bs,
one column that's one, two,
and three, but you'll only ever
have a single A1, a single
A2, and so on and so on.
But you might have a B2, a
C2, or an A1, A2, A3, A4.
So you might have multiple As, multiple
Bs, multiple ones, multiple twos,
but you can only ever have a
single A1, B2, C3, and so on.
So as I said, SQL is a
programming language,
but it has a fairly limited vocabulary.
It's not quite as expansive as
C and PHP and other languages
that we talk in the course.
It is more verbose a
language than what we're
going to talk about in this
video, because in this video
we're going to talk about
four operations that we
can perform on a table.
>> There are more than this.
We can do more than this,
but for our purposes,
we're generally going to be using
just four operations-- insert,
select, update, and delete.
And you can probably intuitively guess
what all four of these things do.
But we'll go into a bit
of detail on each one.
>> So for purposes of this
video, let's assume
we have the following two
tables in a single database.
We have a table called Users that has
four columns-- ID number, username,
password, and full name.
And we have a second
table in the same database
called Moms that just stores information
about a username and a mother.
So for all of examples
in this video, we'll
be using this database and
subsequent updates to it.
So let's say we want to
add information to a table.
That's what the insert operation does.
In explaining all of
these commands, I'm going
to give you a general skeleton to use.
Because basically, the queries
are going look pretty similar,
we're just going to be changing
slightly different pieces of information
to do different things with the table.
>> So for INSERT, the skeleton
looks kind of like this.
We want to insert into
a particular table.
Then we have an open parenthesis
and a list of columns
that we want to put values into.
Close parentheses, the
following values, and then
again, we list out the values
we want to put in the table.
>> So an example of this
would be the following.
I want to insert into the table
users the following columns--
username, password, and fullname.
So a new row where I'm putting
in those three columns and we're
going to put in the values
Newman, USMAIL, and Newman.
So in this case, I'm
putting the lowercase newman
into the username column, the password
USMAIL, and the full name capital N
Newman into the fullname column.
>> So here's what the database
looked like before.
Here's what the users table on the
top looked like before we did this.
After we execute this
query, we get this.
We've added a new row to the table.
But notice this one thing
that I didn't specify,
but somehow I've got a value
for, which is this 12 right here.
I didn't say I wanted to
put ID number in there.
I wanted to put username,
password, fullname.
And I did that, that's fine.
>> But I also got this 12.
Why did I get this 12?
Well, it turns out that
when you are defining
a column that is going to be your
primary key, which is usually,
like I said, an ID number.
It's not always necessarily
going to be an ID number,
but it's usually a good idea to
be some sort of integer value.
You have an option in phpMyAdmin
when you're creating your database
or your table to set that
column as auto incrementing.
>> Which is a really good idea when
you're working with a primary key,
because you want every value
in that column to be unique.
And if you forget to specify
it for more than one person,
you now have a situation where
that column's no longer unique.
You have two blanks, so you can no
longer uniquely identify a column--
or you can no longer uniquely
identify a row based on that column.
It's lost all of its
value as a primary key.
>> And so apparently what I have done
here is configured the user ID
column to auto increment so that every
time I add information to the table,
it will automatically give me
a value for the primary key.
So I can never forget to do it because
the database will do it for me.
So that's kind of nice.
And so that's why we get
12 in there, because I've
set that column up to auto increment.
If I added somebody else
it'd be 13, if I added
somebody else it'd be 14, and so on.
>> So let's just do one more insertion.
We'll insert into the moms table, in
particular, the username and mother
column, the values
kramer and Babs Kramer.
And so we had this before.
After we execute that
SQL query, we have this.
We've added Kramer and Babs
Kramer to the moms table.
>> So that's inserting.
SELECT is what we use to extract
information from the table.
So this is how we get
information out of the database.
And so SELECT commands are going to be
very frequently used in programming.
The general framework-- the
general skeleton looks like this.
Select a set of columns from
a table, and then optionally
you can specify a condition-- or
what we typically call a predicate,
is usually the term we use in SQL.
>> But it's basically what
particular rows you want to get.
If you want to, instead of getting
everything, narrow it down,
this is where you would do that.
And then optionally, you can also
order by a particular column.
So maybe you want to have things sorted
alphabetically based on one column
or alphabetically based on another.
>> Again, WHERE and ORDER BY are optional.
But they'll probably be
useful-- particularly
WHERE will be useful to
narrow down so you don't
get your entire database back and
have to process it, you just get
the pieces of it that you care about.
So for example, I might want to select
ID number and fullname from users.
So what might this look like?
So here's my users table.
I want to select idnum
and fullname from users.
What am I going to get?
I'm going to get this.
I didn't narrow it down, so I'm
getting the ID number for every row
and I'm getting the full
name from every row.
>> OK.
What if I want to select password
from users WHERE-- so now
I'm adding a condition, a predicate--
where idnum is less than 12.
So here's my database again,
my users table the top.
What am I going to get if I want to
select that information, the password,
where user ID or idnum is less than 12?
I'm going to get this
information back, right?
It happens that idnum is 10, less
than 12, ID number 11 less than 12.
I'm getting the password for those rows.
That's what I asked for.
What about this?
What if I want to select star from the
moms table where username equals Jerry?
OK, select star is the special
sort of wild card so-called
that we use to get everything.
So they're saying select
username comma mother, which
happened to be the only
two columns of this table,
I can just select star
and get everything
where the username equals Jerry.
And so that's what I would get
if I made that particular query.
>> Now, databases are
great because they allow
us to organize information perhaps
a bit more efficiently than we
might otherwise.
We don't necessarily to store
every relevant piece of information
about a user in the same table.
We had two tables there.
>> We need to store
everybody's mother's name,
and maybe we don't have social security
number, we have their date of birth.
That doesn't always need
to be in the same table.
As long as we can define
relationships between the tables--
and that's where that relational
database term kind of comes
into play-- as long as we can define
relationships between the tables,
we can sort of compartmentalize
or abstract things a way,
where we only have the
really important information
we care about in the user's table.
And then we have ancillary information
or extra information in other tables
that we can connect back to the main
users table in a particular way.
>> So here we have these two tables, but
there's a relationship between them,
right?
It seems like username
might be something
that exists in common between
these two different tables.
So what if we now have
a situation where we
want to get a user's full name from
the user's table, and their mother's
name from the mother table?
We don't have a way to get
that as it stands, right?
There's no single table that contains
both full name and mother's name.
We don't have that option
from what we've seen so far.
>> And so we have to introduce
the idea of a JOIN.
And JOINs are probably
the most complex--
it's really most complex operation
we're going to talk about in the video.
They're a little complicated,
but once you get the hang of it,
they're actually not too bad.
It's just a special case of a SELECT.
We're going to select a set of
columns from a table joining
in a second table on some predicate.
>> In this case, think about it like this--
table one is one circle over here,
table two is another circle over here.
And that predicate part
in the middle, it's
sort of like if you think
about as a Venn diagram, what
do they have in common?
We want to link these two tables
based on what they have in common
and create this hypothetical table
that is the merger of the two together.
So we'll see this in an
example and maybe that'll help
clear it up a little bit.
So maybe you want to select
user.fullname and moms.mother
from users joining in the
moms table in every situation
where the username column
is the same between them.
And this is a new
syntax here, this user.
and moms..
If I'm doing multiple tables
together, I can specify a table.
I can distinguish in particular on
that on at the very bottom there.
I can distinguish the username
column of the users table
from the username column of the
moms table, which are otherwise--
if we just said username equals
username, that doesn't really
mean anything.
We want to do it where they match.
>> So I can specify the table and the
column name in case of a situation
where it would be unclear
what I'm talking about.
So that's all I'm doing there is I'm
saying this column from this table,
and being very explicit.
So again, I'm selecting the
full name and the mother's name
from the users table linked together
with the moms table in every situation
where they share that column--
they share that username notion.
>> So here are the tables we had before.
This is the state of our
database as it exists right now.
The information we're extracting
is this to start with.
This is the new table we're going
to create combining these together.
And notice we're not highlighting
Newman's row in the user's table,
and we're not highlighting
Kramer's row in the moms table
because neither one exists in
both sets-- in both tables.
>> The only information that is in common
between them is Jerry is in both tables
and gcostanza is in both tables.
And so when we do the SQL JOIN, what we
get-- and we doing actually get this.
It's sort of a temporary variable.
It's like a hypothetical
merger of the two tables.
We actually get something
like this, where
we've merged together the tables on the
information that they have in common.
>> So notice that users.username
and moms.username column,
it's exactly the same.
That was the information that
was consistent from the users
table and the moms table.
And so we merged them together.
We discarded Kramer because he
didn't exist in the users table,
and we discarded Newman, because
he didn't exist in the moms table.
So this is the hypothetical merger
using the JOIN operation of SELECT.
>> And then we were looking for the
user's full name and the user's mother,
and so this is the information that
we would get from the overall query
that we made with SELECT.
So we joined the tables together
and we extracted those two columns,
and so that's what we would get.
But SQL JOINs a kind of complicated.
You probably won't do them too much,
but just have some idea of the skeleton
that you could use to merge two
tables together if you needed to.
The last two are a
bit simpler I promise.
So updating, we can use UPDATE
to change information in a table.
The general format is UPDATE some
table, SET some column to some value
WHERE some predicate is satisfied.
So for example, we might want
to update the users table
and set the password to yada
yada, where the ID number is 10.
>> So in this case, we're
updating the users table.
The ID number is 10 for
that first row there,
and we want to update the
password to yada yada.
And so that's what would happen.
It's pretty straightforward, right?
It's just a very simple
modification to the table.
>> DELETE is the operation we used to
remove information from a table.
DELETE FROM table WHERE
some predicate is satisfied.
We want to delete from the
users table for example
where the username is Newman.
You can probably guess what's going to
happen here after we execute that SQL
query, Newman is gone from the table.
>> So all these operations, as I've said,
are very easy to do in phpMyAdmin.
It's a very user friendly interface.
But it does require manual effort.
We don't want to employ manual effort.
We want our programs to
do this for us, right?
So we might want to do
this programmatically.
We want to incorporate SQL and have
something else to do this for us.
>> But what have we seen that allows
us to programmatically do something?
We've seen PHP, right?
It introduces some
dynamism into our programs.
And so fortunately, SQL and
PHP play very nicely together.
There's a function in PHP
called query, which can be used.
And you can pass as the
parameter or the argument
to query a SQL query that
you would like to execute.
And PHP will do it on your behalf.
>> So after you've connected
to your database with PHP,
there's two primaries you do this.
There's something called MySQLi
and something called PDO.
We won't go into a huge
amount detail there.
In CS50 we use PDO.
After you've connected
to your database, you
can then make queries your database
by passing the queries as arguments
to PHP functions.
And when you do that, you store the
result set in an associative array.
>> And we know how to work with
associative arrays in PHP .
So I might say something
like this-- $results--
this is in PHP-- equals query.
And then inside of the
query function that argument
that I'm passing to query
that looks like SQL.
And in fact that is SQL.
That's the query string that I would
like to execute on my database.
>> And so in red, this is PHP.
This is SQL that I'm
integrating into PHP by making
it the argument to the query function.
I want to select fullname from
users where ID number equals 10.
And then maybe after I've done that,
I might say something like this.
I want to print out the
message Thanks for logging in.
>> And I want it interpolate-- I want
to interpolate $results fullname.
And so that's how I work with that
associative array that I got back.
$results fullname would
basically end up printing out,
thanks for logging in, Jerry Seinfeld.
That was the full name
where idnum equals 10.
>> And so all I'm doing
is I'm now-- I stored
my query, the results of my query
and results in an associative array,
and fullname is the name of
the column I was getting for.
So that's my key into the results
associative array that I want.
So Thanks for logging in, $results,
fullname will print out, will stick
right in between those curly
braces, Jerry Seinfeld.
And I'll like to print out the message
Thanks for logging in Jerry Seinfeld.
>> Now, we probably don't want to hard
code things like that in, right?
We might want to do something like print
f, where we can substitute and maybe
collect different information,
or maybe have the query process
different information.
And so query, the query function has
this notion of sort of substitutions
very similar to print f percent s
and percent c, is question marks.
>> And we can use question
marks very analogously
to print f to substitute variables.
So maybe your user logged in earlier,
and you saved their user ID number
in $_session of PHP super
global in the key ID.
So maybe after they logged in,
you set $_session ID equals 10,
extrapolating from the example
we just saw a second ago.
>> And so when we actually execute
this query the results now,
it would plug in 10, or whatever
the $_session ID value is.
And so that allows us to
be a bit more dynamic.
We're not hard coding things in anymore.
We're saving information
somewhere and then
we can use that information again to
sort of generalize what we want to do,
and just plug-in and change
the behavior of our page
based on what the user's ID number
actually is after they've logged in.
It's also possible, though,
that your results set
might consist of multiple rows.
In which case, you have
an array of arrays--
an array of associative arrays.
And you just need to iterate through it.
And we know how to iterate
through an array in PHP, right?
So here is probably the most
complex thing we've seen so far.
It actually integrates
three languages together.
>> Here in red, this is some HTML.
I'm apparently starting-- this is
a snippet of some HTML that I have.
I'm starting a new paragraph that
says the moms of TV's Seinfeld.
And then immediately afterwards
I'm starting a table.
And then after that, I
have some PHP, right?
I have all of this PHP code in there.
I'm apparently going make a query.
And to make the query, I'm going to
be using SELECT mothers FROM moms.
>> So this is getting-- this is SQL.
So the the blue is SQL.
The red we saw a second ago was HTML.
And the green here is PHP.
So I'm making a query
to my database, I'm
selecting all of the
mothers in the moms table.
Not just narrowing it down to particular
row, I'm asking for all of them.
>> Then I check if result is
not equals equals false.
This is just my way of checking sort
of if results is not equal to null,
that we would see c for example.
Basically this is just checking to make
sure that it actually got data back.
Because I don't want to start printing
out data if I didn't get any data.
Then for each results as a result the
foreach syntax from PHP, all I'm doing
is printing out $result mothers.
And so I'm going to get a set
of all of the mothers of each--
it's an array of associative
arrays-- and I'm printing out
each one as its own row of a table.
And that's really pretty
much all there is to it.
I know there's a little
bit going on here
in this last example with arrays of
arrays-- arrays of associative arrays.
But it really does just boil
down in SQL to making a query,
usually selecting after we've already
put information into the table,
and then just pulling it out.
>> And this is we would pull it
out in this particular case.
We would extract all of the individual
mothers from the moms table.
We got a whole set of them, and we
want to iterate through and print out
each one.
So again, this is probably
the most complicated example
we've seen because we're mixing three
different languages together, right?
>> Again, we have HTML here in red,
mixed with some SQL here in blue,
mixed with some PHP in green.
But all of these play
nicely together, it's
just a matter of developing
good habits so that you can get
them to work together the way you want.
And the only way to really do that
is to practice, practice, practice.
I'm Doug Lloyd, this is CS50.