>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Hello.
Let's take a walk through
Problem Set 8 Mashup,
which is going to challenge you to
draw upon elements for Google Maps
with elements from Google News and mash
them together into a web applet that
allows a user to search
a map for news local
to specific towns,
cities, and zip codes.
To do this, we're going to
integrate some HTML, CSS, PHP, SQL,
JavaScript, and a technique
generally known as AJAX in order
to create this immersive
user experience.
>> Let's first for Google Maps itself.
This, of course, is perhaps
a familiar interface.
But it turns out that Google Maps
also provides an API-- application
programming interface-- via which
you can take elements of Google Maps
and integrate them into
your own applications.
Indeed, throughout this
process, you're going
to find a couple of URLs
particularly helpful that
are mentioned in the
specification for Problem Set 8,
specifically this Getting Started
Guide or the Developer's Guide
for Google Maps API Version 3 as well
as the Google Maps JavaScript API
v3 reference, which is a
bit more arcane to read
but actually has all of the lower level
details about what functions or methods
and objects and properties and
events actually come with the API,
very similar in spirit
to [INAUDIBLE] pages.
>> Now if we take a look
at Google News, you'll
perhaps see a familiar interface here.
But it turns out you can also search
Google News for specific geographies
via an HTTP parameter called geo.
In fact, if I zoom in
up here, you'll see that
I'm at
news.google.com/news/section?geo=02138.
And, indeed, if I zoom
out, you'll see that I'm
looking at a page with a whole bunch of
views about Cambridge, Massachusetts.
>> Meanwhile, if I actually change the
URL not to be a zip code like this,
but something a little messier
like Cambridge, +Massachusetts,
where the plus is the way you encode a
space character in a URL and hit Enter,
you'll see that I actually
see almost the same news.
Perhaps it's a little bit different
because Cambridge actually
has multiple zip codes.
Now how would I know that and,
in fact, how could I somehow
tie cities and towns
to zip codes in case I
want to allow the user
to look up either?
Well, it turns out that there's
a website out there called
geonames.org which is
an initiative to have
a freely available database of all
sorts of geographic information,
not only for the US, but also
for other countries as well.
In fact, if I go to this URL here, which
is also mentioned in the problem set
specification, you'll see it three
listing of a whole bunch of zip files
any of which can be downloaded by you.
In fact, for this problem set
you're going to download us.zip.
Now within this file, is a whole
bunch of data in text format.
The files is very similar to a
CSV-- Comma Separated Values file--
but it actually uses
tabs to demarcate fields.
Now, meanwhile, if you look
here at what I've highlighted,
the fields in this file are going
to be things like country codes,
postal codes, place names,
and then, in some form
or other, states and counties,
communities, and more.
In fact, I've already
downloaded this file in advance.
Let me go ahead and open it here--
us.text-- and, indeed, you'll
see if I scroll down to line 16,792
you'll see a few records for Cambridge,
Massachusetts and its various zip codes.
What you also see there is the county,
some numbers that I don't really
understand, but also all
the way on the right,
some GPS coordinates--
latitude and longitude.
This is great because one of
the features of Google Maps API
is the ability to detect
where you are geographically
in terms of GPS coordinates.
>> Now let's begin to figure out how to
start tying these things together.
We've given you a whole
bunch of distribution code,
as well as MySQL database.
In fact, if I pull a phpMyAdmin having
already imported, as you soon will,
pset8.SQL, you'll see a MySQL table that
looks like this, an ID field, country
code, postal code, place name and more.
The types of all of those
columns I derived simply
by reading the readme.text
file here that specified
whether a field is an integer,
or varchar or the like.
>> So we've created that table for
you and given you the SQL commands
to execute to create that
table in your own database,
but there's actually no data in it yet.
Rather, you're going to have to
download us.zip or any country's zip
file from that URL there.
And then you're going to have to write
a command line script in PHP that's
going to open up that text
file, iterate over its lines,
and then for each of
those lines do an insert
into that places table
in your MySQL database.
So at the end of this process, you'll
have run that script ultimately
just once in theory.
In reality you'll probably
run it a bunch of times
while trying to fix various bugs.
>> Ultimately, you're going to have a
really big database with thousands
and thousands of geographic rows.
Then you're going to put that import
script aside once it's working
and your database is nice
and correct, and then
you're going to move on to actually
implementing the mashup itself.
The mashup is going to look
a little something like this.
At mashup.cs50.net, we
have a staff solution
that looks a little something like this.
Indeed, if I click on this newspaper
icon for Cambridge, Massachusetts,
you'll see a spinning
icon briefly and then
an ordered list, a
bulleted list of articles
related to Cambridge, Massachusetts.
If I click on Charlestown,
Massachusetts,
I'll see the same for that town.
And If I click on
Watertown, Massachusetts,
there might not be any
news of from Watertown,
so you'll see something
like slow news day.
>> Now, meanwhile, at top left are
some familiar Google Maps controls
to let you zoom out, pan
up, down, left, and right,
but also a search box that we put there.
So if I search for, frankly,
the only other zip code I know,
90210, we'll actually see
Beverly Hills, California.
When clicked it leads me to
California and a whole bunch
of news about Beverly Hills.
Now notice, too, what happened there.
If I this time search for 02138 or even
Cambridge comma Massachusetts or some
variant thereof, you get a
little autocomplete dropdown.
Now this is using a plugin
for a library called jQuery,
and that plugin is called typeahead.
We simply read through
the documentation,
downloaded the .js file integrated
into the distribution code so that you
ultimately can write the code that
fills that dropdown menu with the auto
selections or the auto suggestions.
>> Now the distribution code, though, that
you received doesn't do nearly as much.
You get the Google Map embedded, and
you get the controls the top left,
and you get the search box.
But if I type something like
02138, no places are found yet.
So that's going to be
one of our goals here.
Moreover, if you take a step
back and look at the map itself,
there's no news whatsoever.
Even if I click and
drag, no markers actually
appear for news because that
challenge is left for you as well.
>> Let's take a look then
at the distribution code.
Once you've downloaded
pset8.zip and unzipped it
into your vhost directory
in the CS50 Appliance,
you'll see these
directories here inside.
Bin-- which generally stands for
binary for executable programs--
includes, as in pset7, some PHP
files that other files include,
then public, which is
the files that need
to be publicly accessible
to a user with a browser.
Let's take a look in the
bin directory, and we'll
see that there's a file
there already called Import.
If we open this with gedit, we'll see
that, unfortunately, there's not much
there.
All that is there, though,
is a shebang at top
which specifies which
interpreter-- in this case PHP--
should be used to actually
execute this file.
But then where it says
TODO is where you're
going to need to write some code
that probably requires the config
file that's in the includes directory
as we've done before with PHP files.
And then you're going to
have to somehow open up
us.text which you presumably
have unzipped already.
Then you're going to have to
iterate over the lines in that file,
perhaps using some of the functions
suggested in the specification.
Then insert each of those
lines into MySQL database
by using the query function, which
we've again provided you with--
or at least a variant
thereof in functions.php,
which we'll see in just a moment.
>> Now let's close import and go back to
our directory and this time go into
includes.
And if I do ls there, you'll see
three files quite like Problem Set 7.
And let's take a quick look,
for instance, at config.php.
In there, is fewer lines
than before, and it
seems this file includes
constants.php and functions.php.
We're using a slightly different
technique this time around to actually
specify that these files are relative
to the current directory __ DIR__
represents whatever directory this
file, config.php, is itself in.
So this is a more
explicit way of specifying
what other files you want to require.
>> Now if I close this file and
open up constants.php instead,
you'll see a file very reminiscent
to Problem Set 7's as well, albeit
with a different database called pset8.
Finally, in functions.php,
we'll see just one function
this time called query.
This is almost the same except we handle
errors this time around a little bit
differently, but it's usage is
the same as in problem set seven.
>> Now let's go back into our pset8
directory, go into public, and in there
if I do ls, you'll see this--
articles.php, index.html, search.php,
and update.php-- all files.
And then the css fonts, img, and
js directory quite like pset7.
>> Let's take a look at
index.html, which is
going to be really the
entry point to the smashup.
Now in index.html, you'll see a whole
bunch of link elements in the head,
specifically, for bootstrap for our own
CSS followed by a whole bunch of script
tags for things like the maps, API
itself, a special marker with label
utility that we mentioned in the
specification is available to you,
jQuery itself, bootstrap
itself, and another library
called underscore which
we talk about in the spec.
Underscore.js like jquery.js
is a JavaScript library
that has a whole bunch of functionality
that a lot of people in the world wish
existed in JavaScript itself.
So all of these are
actually quite popular.
We've also mentioned typeahead
which is the library that
does that autocomplete dropdown and
finally a link to our own JavaScript.
>> Meanwhile, and perhaps
thankfully, this mashup
is driven by relatively little
HTML down here at the bottom.
Notice that we've specified a div in
our body of class-container fluid.
This, per bootstrap's
documentation, just
means that this div is going to fill the
viewport or the browser's window fully.
>> Meanwhile, below that we have a div
that's opened and immediately closed
with the unique ID of map canvas.
This now is from Google
Maps documentation
for its API, whereby I simply need to
have an empty div into which to inject,
ultimately, an actual Google Maps.
But more on that in just a bit.
>> Finally, there's a form
inside of here which
implements the text box up top left
in our interface for searching.
Notice that we've used
a bit of bootstrap
here too-- things like
form-inline and form-group.
We've given the former
unique ID of form.
And then, ultimately, I actually have
an input type, which is pretty familiar,
whose ID is q.
Just a convention.
Q for query-- could have
been called anything.
And then the placeholder,
meanwhile, is city, state,
and postal code which you might recall
seeing in our mashup demo earlier.
Let's close this file.
>> Now take a look at the PHP files that
await and then the JavaScript files.
In our PHP files, we've
already implemented for you,
for instance, updates.
Update.php-- we won't spend a huge
amount of time on here-- in a nutshell
is the file that our
JavaScript code is going
to contact via AJAX that
asynchronous technique that's
built into JavaScript these days that's
going to allow us to ask update.php
for more information.
>> Specifically, anytime
the user drags the map
or performs a search that jumps
the user to another location,
our JavaScript code,
as we'll soon see, is
going to call update.php
and ask for 10 or so markers
within the viewport based
on the GPS coordinates
of the top and bottom
corners of that map.
We can then repopulate the map now that
the user has moved the screen in order
to see 10 probably new
markers for different towns.
Meanwhile, this file is ultimately
going to execute a SQL query
against our database
table called places which
is going to return those
10 or fewer locations.
>> Meanwhile, in articles.php, is another
file we've written in its entirety.
It is very similar in spirit to
Problem Set 7's LOOKUP function,
which contacted Yahoo Finance for you.
This file contacts Google News
for you, ultimately grabbing
a machine-readable
version-- in something
called RSS format-- of the news
for Cambridge or Beverly Hills
or whatever town you've searched
for based on that geoparameter.
We parse that RSS, which is just a
type of markup language called XML,
and then we actually
return it to your browser
and to your JavaScript code,
specifically, in a format called
JSON, JavaScript Object Notation.
Now you'll see in the
specification-- we point you
at how you can actually see
some of the JSON coming back--
that this functionality ultimately
lets you populate those popup menus so
that when you click
on a marker in the map
you actually see a whole bunch
of bullets, each of which
links to an article.
>> Now let's take a look at one last
PHP file which, fortunately, doesn't
have much going on--
just a pretty big TODO.
Right now this file declares
an array called places.
And then ultimately prints
that array in JSON format--
pretty-printing it just so that
things are easier to debug.
Unfortunately, in the
middle there is this TODO,
which calls for you to search the
database for places matching a geo HTTP
parameter.
>> And, indeed, this is going to
be one of your challenges--
to implement this functionality here
so that when you contact this file with
a URL like search. php?geo= something,
your code will ultimately return a JSON
array of all of the places in your
database table that match that input.
So if the user types in Cambridge,
your file here search.php
should ultimately return a JSON array
for all of the matches for Cambridge,
which might be in Massachusetts
but could be even anywhere else.
>> Lastly, let's take a look at two
files that are static ultimately--
your CSS file and your JavaScript file.
If I go into our CSS directory,
there's a whole bunch of files there,
but most of them are libraries.
I'm going to take a look,
specifically, at styles.css,
which is our own global CSS that's
going to stylize this whole mashup.
I'll leave it to you to read through
the comments herein, but, in a nutshell,
this is the CSS that ensures that our
mashup, by default out of the box,
looks exactly the way we want it--
with the map filling the view port
and with the search
box up at the top left.
We've also taken the liberty of
stylizing that typeahead dropdown
menu a little bit as well.
>> The most important file
perhaps for this problem set
is this last one, scripts.js.
Inside of your JS directory
is even more files.
All of them are library files
except for this one, scripts.js.
If we open this up, let's take our
final tour through the functions that
are built into this file
for you and call attention
to the TODOs that lie ahead.
>> At the top of this file,
are three global variables.
One for a map, which is going to
be a reference to our Google map.
You can think of it
sort of as a pointer.
Meanwhile, we have
another global variable
called info, which appears to be
storing the return value of a call
to new google.maps.InfoWindow.
JavaScript supports objects which
are very similar in spirit to Struts.
And what this line for
our purposes is doing
is creating a new info
window in memory and then
keeping around a reference
thereto in a variable called Info.
And in between those,
meanwhile, is what appears
to be an empty JavaScript
array called markers.
All of those newspaper icons, or you
might choose another icon altogether,
are going to be stored
ultimately in this array
so that we can very easily add to
the map and remove them from the map.
>> Now let's scroll down
a little bit and whiz
through the code that's going to be
executed as soon as the DOM or document
object model or the
page itself is ready.
Recall that this syntax
here simply specifies
that the following code
should be executed only
when the browser has finished
loading everything else.
>> We first declare a
whole bunch of styles,
which end up stylizing
the map as per the spec.
We then declare a
whole bunch of options,
which further customize the Google
map that we're about to embed.
We then use a bit of jQuery code,
which is explained in a bit more detail
in the spec, to grab
that element, map-canvas
that we so uniquely identified.
And then this line here is
what seems to magically give us
a Google map inside of
our own application,
storing a reference thereto
in that variable called map.
>> Finally, down here we register
what's called a listener.
Think back-- way, way
back-- to week zero in CS50
when we looked at Scratch and
its support through a walk
through for things called
events and broadcasts.
You might not have used
it yourself, but it's
a mechanism whereby a
browser in this case
can get our attention when it's
ready to actually execute some code.
In this case, it's going to listen
to the map for an event called idle.
This means that the browser has
finished loading the Google map.
At this point a function called
configure should ultimately
be executed.
That function, configure,
we'll see, is written by us.
>> Now down here is a function
that, unfortunately,
is just a TODO add marker.
Per the spec. you're going to need
to write the code that actually
adds a marker-- whether it looks
like a newspaper, or a thumb tack,
or something else-- to the Google map.
Here now is that function
called configure.
I'll leave it to you to read
through this in more detail,
but realize that we add
a bunch more Listeners
so that we can execute code when the
user clicks on and drags the map.
We also have code in here that
initializes that typeahead plugin
so that the dropdown
menu actually works.
>> But let's focus on just a
couple of places herein.
Specifically, this to do here.
I'll defer to the online
documentation and the specification
for how to fill in this TODO.
But in a nutshell, this library
typeahead allows you to pass
in what's generally known as a template,
which has some variable placeholders
very similar in spirit to printf's %.*s.
But in this case, the
template per the spec
allows you to specify
what variables you want
to inject from data that's come
back from something like the PHP
files that you've written
that are emitting JSON output.
>> Now down here realize that we are
listening for typeahead selections
when the user actually conducts
a search and selects a value.
This is how we're actually
going to listen for that
and execute some code as a result.
Then we continue to configure
the mashup just a little bit.
And, ultimately, we call
this function update.
It updates the markers on the screen.
More on that in just a moment.
Meanwhile, there's a few
small functions in here.
One of which is hideInfo which
simply closes the InfoWindow.
Another function here, which ultimately
won't be too long, remove markers.
That's going to undo whatever
your add marker function does.
And then down here is search.
And this one is interesting because we
have written the JavaScript code that's
going to talk to search.php on the
server and get back some response.
>> You, of course, will still
need to implement search.php,
but we've implemented the
JavaScript code that's
going to handle actually performing
searches from that text box.
In particular, notice
that this function here,
search, does call search.php
by a method called
get JSON, which we saw in lecture.
And the syntax here
is a little different
from lecture in that we're using
jQuery so-called promise interface.
More on that in the spec.
This simply means for our
purposes now that there
are two special functions we
need to call with dot notation
here immediately after calling get JSON.
One is called done.
One is called fail.
You can think of these
as the success handler
and the failure handler just
in case something goes wrong.
>> Now let's look at the last
couple of functions in this file.
Down here is a function
called showInfo, which
shows info in one of those
little info windows that
pops up when the user clicks a marker.
Down here further is
that update function
that we have implemented for you.
It determines the bounds of the map.
What are the GPS coordinates of its
northeast and southwest corners here.
We've prepared some HDP parameters
here and then passed them ultimately
to update.php, which we've
also implemented for you.
That ultimately gets back some JSON
from the file called update.php
and then removes any
markers on the screen
and then iterates over
the data that's come back
from update.php, which
again is just a JSON array.
And then it ultimately adds a marker for
each of those places, handling failure
or errors which might very well happen.
>> Now just to give you a taste of how you
might go about debugging this project,
realize that I've opened in
advance this tab here to this URL,
pset8/articles.php?geo=02138.
Now, again, articles about
PHP we implemented for you
so this isn't so much
what you'll be using
to debug, but rather the technique.
Notice that I've searched for
Cambridge's zip code here,
and I've gotten back, indeed, a JSON
array of JSON objects inside of which
are two keys-- link and title.
>> So this functionality
works already for you.
But this technique of manually going
to a URL like this for something like
search.php?geo=cambridge or 02138 or
whatever the user has typed in should
prove invaluable as you, yourself, try
to figure out exactly whether or why
search.php is working or not.
>> Ultimately then, you have
a few TODOs ahead of you.
You're going to first implements
that import script that
reads in us.text into your database.
You're then going to need
to implement search.php
so that it behaves exactly as specified.
You're then going to want
to focus on scripts.js
and ultimately implements
those couple of TODOs,
including for configure
and that template,
add markers, remove markers, and
then last, but not least, one
personal touch.
>> Once you have your mashup working
quite like ours, the goal at hand
is for you to add a personal
touch to your mashup,
whether it's aesthetic or functional.
Take the mashup ever so
slightly to the next level.
So long as you push yourself beyond
your familiarity with the spec itself
and pick up one technique
new, even if it's just
something aesthetic like changing the
layout of the map that you're using,
the scope that we expect
will be satisfied.
That then is Problem Set 8 Mashup.
Stay tuned for more in the
specification and best of luck
tackling this, your last
CS50 problem set ever.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]