ANSEL: Hi.
My name's Ansel for CS50
[? R and D. ?] Today,
we're going to walk through some of the
basics of mechanical part manufacture.
So let's jump right into
it at kind of a high level,
I'll just over the basics
of what we're doing.
I'm going to CAT up which stands
for-- it's just like Computer Aided
Drafting, which is just a medium
of designing a part in a computer
program called SolidWorks.
>> And then from there,
we'll be able to 3D print
our part, which is a different
medium for manufacture.
If we wanted to make it
out of maybe metal perhaps,
we could machine it out of
maybe aluminum or steel.
But 3D printing is kind of a nicer
way to do that for simple parts
that are not subjected to really
precise or intense stresses and strains,
just because it's a really quick
medium by which we can prototype.
Like I said, we're going to
be using SolidWorks today.
So let's go into SolidWorks, and
I'll kind of walk through the basics
to make a new part and walk
through some of the subtleties that
are easy to gloss over.
If we go into SolidWorks here, and we
go to our file, let's open up a New.
And we'll just click Part and select OK.
>> We have this blank canvas by
which we're able to draw our part.
And first, we're going to
kind of create the skeleton,
and then build it up, and then add in
some of the more intricate features.
At first, let's just
go to Sketch, which is
a kind of in the upper
left-hand column over here.
And we click Sketch, Sketch.
And then, it will give us a
choice of different planes
that we can sketch it on.
>> I'm going to build this part,
which is this little iPhone dock,
from the ground up.
It's almost as if we're
looking down on it.
And then, we'll build it up.
Naturally, we'll select
the top plane over here.
And it will highlight itself in orange.
And then, SolidWorks kind
of does the rest for us.
>> SolidWorks is nice in that it
does a lot of the heavy lifting.
If you give it a geometry,
it'll just figure it out.
That'll become more apparent
as we walk through the design.
>> At a high level, the dock
is just a rectangular base.
And then it has kind
of this lofted feature
here, that's just an extruded
base which holds the phone.
And then, it's tilted at an angle.
Some of the dimensions
are kind of arbitrary.
I think I chose in this
specific model to make the tilt
something like 15 degrees.
But that's all up to you.
One thing we do need
to take into account
is that when the phone is sitting in
the stand, it has some center of gravity
or some center of mass that
needs to hang over the stand.
For example, if we did not include
this part right here, then when
we put the phone in it, the center
of mass would extend beyond the base.
And it would just fall over.
>> What we can do is make this base
a bit wider in the back such
that the center of mass of
the phone is over the base,
with some extra kind of comfort
that's built in there such
that when you put your phone
in it, it won't fall over.
That's just something that
we need to take into account.
That's pretty simple physics.
>> Let's start out with the base.
And so we're already
in our sketch plane.
If we go over here and we select the
rectangle-- it's a little bit small,
so I'll just point to it--
select the rectangle here.
And I'm going to start it at the
origin, which is kind of arbitrary.
But that's just how I'm going to do it.
And we draw a rectangle.
Now we have this rectangle.
And SolidWorks knows that for
instance, the bottom and the top lines
are parallel.
And the side lines are parallel.
And they're all horizontal and vertical,
as denoted by these green boxes.
These green boxes a really important.
And I we'll kind of
talk through them a lot
as we continue through
the design process.
But essentially, they're just
saying that there is some relation.
For example on this
line right here, there's
a green box with a
vertical line next to it.
That's saying that
this line is vertical.
It's constrained to being vertical.
We can move it around and
drag it, but it will never
be at an angle that's not vertical.
>> Those green lines will
make your life a lot easier
because it will allow you
to make relations and not
have to do is much work.
SolidWorks will figure it out for you.
And I'll kind of talk
through that as we get to it.
>> What I just did to kind
of enlarge that sketch is
I just hit F on my keyboard, which fits
your current sketch to your screen.
For example, if you're
maybe really far away
and you just want to make it fit
nicely, just hit F on your keyboard.
>> Now that we're here, we can
start to add dimensions.
One of the most important
themes in designing a part
is that you can do all this CADing
and make a really pretty looking part,
but it needs to be physically
applicable to something.
That something in this case is a phone.
Our dock needs to physically
adapt to the phone.
>> The way that we do that
is we measure the phone.
And then, we had a
little bit of a boundary
in And there will be some
tolerance to its manufacture.
The tolerance concept is just
saying that when we manufacture it
or when we print it, the
printing head is not exactly
at the location that we want.
>> It's going to be off by some
very, very small amount.
And that small amount is the tolerance.
And we design in that tolerance if we're
making a really sophisticated part.
But in our case, it
doesn't really matter.
And I'll get to that a little bit later.
>> Let's add some dimensions.
And you can do that by
clicking this button, which
just says Smart Dimension.
To Smart Dimension a line, we just
click on it and up pops this dimension.
You can move it around,
place where you want.
We'll place it up here for now.
>> And then when we click, this box pops
up and allows us to enter a number.
Just as kind of a
higher-level theme, it's
important when you're
dimensioning a line
to not have your dimension for this
line cross over other dimensions,
as it makes your drawing
or sketch pretty cloudy.
So we want to make it
as clear as possible.
>> Luckily, this dock is
a really simple part.
And we can design it pretty readily
with not that many dimensions.
But just kind of at higher level
when we're adding in more dimensions,
we don't want to cloud up the sketch.
We add this in here.
>> We have no idea how wide to make it.
So the first step is
where I'm just going
to grab my phone, which
is a pretty simple kind
of rectangular prismatic shape
with the corners rounded off.
And let's measure it.
>> This tool is called a pair of calipers.
This is a digital pair of calipers.
And I'm just going to turn
it on with the on/off button.
I'm just going to clean the inside
faces of any dirt or grease,
and then, zero it.
It's already zeroed.
>> It's in millimeters,
which we don't want.
We want it to be in inches.
Our whole part is being
designed in inches.
And if you don't know what your
current units are, in the dimension box
it says 4.4329 whatever inches.
>> You could design in any units and
still have a beautiful part at the end.
But I'm just choosing to
design this in inches.
That's the standard in America.
I'm just going to change
the units up here to inches.
And wha-la.
>> Let's measure the width of our phone.
And that'll give us an idea
of how wide to make the base.
I'm just opening up the calipers here.
And I'm just going to
close it down on the phone.
And we see that it is 2.30.
Kind of wiggle it around
a little bit to get
the smallest dimension--
2.305 inches wide.
We want to make the base
a bit wider than that.
So let's say we make it, I don't
know, maybe 2 and 3/4 inches
wide-- so 2.75 inches wide.
That seems about reasonable.
Just as kind of maybe a sanity check,
we can open up the calipers to 2.75
or pretty close to it,
and see that there's
kind of enough wiggle room outside
of between the phone and the calipers
to add material to support the phone.
So 2.75 inches sounds reasonable.
>> Hit Enter.
And our dimension is constrained there.
Now we need to do the same
thing on the vertical line here.
This is kind of the tricky part that
requires-- I guess it's not tricky,
but it's a little bit more sophisticated
than just guessing a number.
This dimension that we're
adding is this distance.
Like I was saying before, we
can't make this too short.
We need to make it long enough such
that the middle of the phone, the center
of gravity of the
phone, is over the base.
You could do this by drawing
out like a free-body diagram,
finding the center of mass, and
then just kind of drawing this out
and using geometry to find it.
That will certainly work.
>> I'm just going to
ballpark it and say we can
make it two inches, as that seems
to be just by eyeing it, plenty.
You're welcome to draw it out
and figure out the geometry.
It's pretty simple.
And it won't take you too long.
Two inches sounds like
there'll be plenty there.
>> I guess as a sanity check, this is
a dock that I had made a while ago.
And if we place our phone in there,
we see that it doesn't tip over.
And this width is 1.8 inches.
So two inches will be plenty.
Cool.
>> Again, we hit Enter.
And now, here's something
that is really important.
We see that all of our lines are
black and all of the points are black.
The line and then the points or
the nodes where they intersect,
are all black.
>> When everything in the sketch is black,
that means it's completely constrained.
By that, I mean that you
can't drag anything around.
Every point in this
sketch has been defined.
We can't change its location because
there are no degrees of freedom.
If I click on this dot here, this
intersection of these two lines,
and try to drag it and move
it around, it doesn't move.
>> Whereas if I kind of delete
one of these dimensions,
I'll just do this for the
purpose of this example.
If I delete this top dimension,
notice that this line is now blue.
So I can move it if I just
maybe click on this point.
It's no longer completely defined.
I'm just going to undo that.
And our sketch returns to black.
Great.
>> I'm now going to exit the sketch.
And we will create an extrusion from it.
There's this theme in
SolidWorks of creating
sketch is to design at a high level what
you want to do, and then extrude it,
which means to kind of create
material out of your sketch.
In this case, we've
sketched a rectangle.
Now we're going to extrude it,
which means create a prism out
of the base of that rectangle.
>> You can do more sophisticated things,
but we'll get to those a little bit
later.
There's no need to do
anything tricky right now.
It's pretty straightforward.
>> The next parts of these
designs will incorporate
a lot of relational geometry
and relational symmetry.
And what that means is when you create
a feature of your part or really
anything, you want to relate
everything in your sketch
to something else--
something that's defined.
In this specific case, we have the
origin, which is where I started.
There are these two
small red vectors here.
>> Everything is defined in
relation to our origin.
So we don't have to worry about it.
But if we wanted to define a
feature that was symmetric,
we wouldn't have to draw it twice.
We could draw it once, and then
define the mirror image of it
to just be based off of the
symmetry from the first part.
That might sound a little bit confusing.
It'll become clearer as we
walk through the design.
>> I'm hitting Exit Sketch in the upper
left-hand part of the screen here.
Now we have some sketch,
which is this kind of gray.
We'll go to Features.
We're going to click on the sketch.
And it's highlighted in blue.
The dimensions pop up.
And now, I'm in this Features
tab up here in the top left.
You'll see that there are
a lot of them on my screen.
We go to Extrude Boss/Base.
And now our sketch has become a prism.
I'm going to make this-- and you
can kind of choose a side somewhat
arbitrarily-- let's say we're going
to make this 0.15 inches thick.
I'll say 0.150 inches thick.
>> And I'm entering that into
this box here that says D1,
or that's just the thickness.
That's the box that
SolidWorks defaults to.
I'm just going to turn
my sound off there.
And we hit the check mark.
And great.
Now we have the base
of our sketch defined.
Cool.
We hit that green
arrow and it goes away.
I said that you can choose the
thickness somewhat arbitrarily
because the stresses and strains that
the phone is imparting on this part
are minimal.
The phone is really light and there
is plenty of support at the base.
If we were defining this for a phone
that was maybe were incredibly heavy,
we would have to run some more
sophisticated analysis on this
to ensure that the base wouldn't like
buckle, or crack, or deform, or deflect
under the stresses and strains.
>> But I think for the context
of what we are doing here
and kind of anything that's
associated with 3D printing,
that analysis isn't really required.
You just can kind of assume that
it'll be strong enough, because we're
really not putting much force on it.
That's just kind of side note.
>> We have our base here.
You can notice that I may be
panning around a little bit.
The way that I'm doing that is
I'm holding down the jog wheel
on my mouse so it can jog
but you can also push down it
and physically hear it click.
I'm pushing down on that.
And then, I'm just
moving the mouse around.
Push down the middle of the
jog wheel, and we see it
we can manipulate our
part in three dimensions.
>> Now we want to sketch
this side feature here,
which is actually going to
end up holding the phone.
And I said that that'll
be at a 15 degree angle.
The way we do that is we can
define a sketch on the side
here and then extrude it down.
We want to kind of look
at this face of the base,
sketch this, all of these curves and
everything, and then extrude that up.
Let's do that.
>> We want to look at just this side.
Well, we can tell SolidWorks
that we want our view
to be kind of normal to this plane.
If I click on this plane, you'll
notice that this little box pops up
with all these options.
And of these options, there's
a little blue rectangle
with a normal vector popping out of it.
If we just hit that, now are
looking at the normal to this plane.
We're looking down on this side
plane, which is what we want to do.
>> As this is still
selected, we go back over
here to Sketch which is in
this View tab over here.
And we'll hit Sketch.
And now we're sketching on this plane.
Great.
Now we're sketching on this plane.
>> We will add-- this is not going
to be kind of a standard rectangle
because the top line and the
bottom line are no longer parallel,
because we decided to put
the phone at an angle.
You don't need to put
your phone at an angle.
If it were vertical,
that would still work,
though it might not hurt
have kind of tab in front.
>> That would look kind of silly.
Having it pointed at an
angle is just a nicer design.
Also, if somebody's walking
up to your table or your booth
and your phone is on display displaying
an app, it's just kind of visually more
pleasing to have your phone
tilted back a little bit, kind
of in the way that your computer
screen is tilted back a little bit.
>> Let's see.
How did I design is the first time?
Let's go like this.
We're going to go to
this bottom corner here.
And I'm just going to
draw a line up here.
And I'm just kind of
roughing out the shape here.
Don't worry about the relations.
We'll take care of those in the second.
>> To exit the line drawing, I just double
click and that gets you out of there.
If you hit this green arrow
in the left pane over here,
that means that we can
exit drawing a line.
Now we have something that
kind of resembles what we need.
>> But here is an important part, and
this is what I was saying before.
We need to add a
relations to everything.
The analogy could be drawn to
when you're writing a script
and you're using a
constant pretty frequently,
you might define the constant
at the beginning of your file,
and then use it kind of
throughout your code, such
that if you need to change this number,
you only need to change it one time.
And then, it will kind of
propagate through your code.
>> It's a very similar case here.
If we define all of
these relations, we only
need to add the dimension one
time because everything else is
going to be redundant.
So that later on if we want to go
back and tweak the design maybe,
you only need to change one dimension.
For example, this line and
this line need be parallel.
But they're not right now.
So let's make them parallel.
>> We click on one.
Now I'm holding Control on my keyboard
and I'm clicking on the other one.
And now, they're both selected.
And this little box pops up.
And there, one of these
options is Make Parallel.
We select that, and now
these two lines are parallel.
Cool.
>> We want this line, and
again holding down Control
to select both at the same time,
this line to be perpendicular.
One of these options
is Make Perpendicular.
If you select these two lines and
maybe you're not seeing this box,
you can hover over to
this left panel over here
and it has all of the same options--
perpendicular, parallel, equal.
Equal means equal in length.
>> We're going to again do this.
Just by induction because I made these
two perpendicular and just by geometry,
these two have to be perpendicular.
But it can't hurt to add
in that second relation.
>> Now let's make this point
and this line coincident.
Again, I'm just hitting
this option Make Coincident.
Now we have the general
shape of the structure
that's actually going
to hold the phone up.
I'm going to just hit F there
to kind of center this out.
Looks pretty good.
>> I'm just going to go back here to
viewing this plane at a Normal .
If that box is not popping
up for you, there is a panel
up again here at the top
of your sketching field
where there's kind of
this like box outline.
You can hit that, and
this little menu pops up.
And again, you have the Normal
to operation available to you.
>> Now let's define that 15 degree
tilt that I was saying before.
We're going to go to Smart Dimension.
Smart Dimension is just that smart.
It can dimension the length of lines.
It can dimension angles
between two lines.
It just figures it out.
>> If we select this vertical line
and then select this angled line,
it shows us kind of
the angle between them.
If we click on that, this is in degrees.
I guess you could do it in radians.
Degrees I think is more natural.
I'm just going to 15.0
degrees, hit Enter.
Cool.
And now, it's completely constrained.
>> We can also define the length of this
line, again using Smart Dimension.
And we can say, I'm just ball
parking this kind of by eye,
seems like maybe 5/8 of
an inch would be enough.
I'll just say 5 divided by 8.
You can do operations in
the Smart Dimension field
like addition,
multiplication, subtraction.
>> And we hit that.
And now, we have these dimensions.
You might say oh no,
two of these dimensions,
the angle dimension and the
length dimension, are crossing.
That's not too pretty, which
I would definitely agree with.
You can bring that in
here to eliminate that.
>> We'll notice though that one
of our lines are still blue.
We want everything in
this sketch to be black
before we do any type of extruding.
We need to constrain this.
If you look at this, it
might not be obvious to you
where the degree of freedom is.
If we want to figure that out,
we can exit Smart Dimension--
which I do by just clicking it
again to turn it off-- and then drag
one of these points.
>> We notice that this can move
along this degree of freedom,
which we can prevent by describing
the length of this line.
We'll go back to Smart Dimension.
And we're going to
dimension this line here.
And we'll call that the
thickness of the phone
plus the thickness of our material.
I don't know how thick that should be.
We can pretty simply measure it.
I'll just go grab our calipers here.
And I'm just going to
measure the thickness
of the phone It's showing
here 0.303 inches.
I have a screen protector on my phone.
It's probably not going to
make too much of a difference.
0.303 inches plus two times
the thickness of the wall-- we
can kind of I guess at
the thickness of the wall.
>> Like I said, this structure
will be plenty strong.
We don't really need to worry
about making the walls too thin,
unless your paper thin.
So let's say 0.303 inches
plus parens two times
the wall thickness, which I'm going
to say is-- I'm just guessing here--
I'll say 0.15 inches, which is the
thickness that I made the base.
It seemed to work.
Cool.
>> SolidWorks does all the math.
We can kind of drag this dimension to
make it look a little bit prettier.
Nice.
Hit our green arrow and
we are completely defined.
Everything is black.
This is great.
>> One thing, and this is
just an aesthetic point,
is there's this little triangle here.
Well we don't want that triangle to
be sticking out when we extrude it,
because it'll look like
a hump in the front face.
We want it to be smooth.
To eliminate that, we can do
what's called an extrusion.
There are two types of extrusions.
There's kind of extruding
to create material
and extruding to remove material.
We'll extrude to create material
in making this feature here
that will hold the phone.
And then, we can remove material here.
And I'll get to that in a second.
>> Let's first exit our sketch.
We have the sketch here defined.
We can go over here
and click our sketch.
One thing that I will note
is this list of things
on the left-hand panel is
called the Feature Tree.
Just like when you're maybe
creating variables in your code,
you want to label them in a way
that's pretty self explanatory.
We should label everything
in our Feature Tree
to also be pretty self explanatory here.
>> This Boss Extrude 1,
if we click on that,
it highlights in blue what the
feature is, which is the base.
But just glancing at the Feature
Tree, if I saw Boss Extrude 1,
that's not at all illustrative
to what it does functionally.
We can rename that.
And the way to do that is just
once it's highlighted in blue, just
click and hold.
And now, you'll see that you
have the ability to rename it.
Let's call that Base.
>> Now if we click on Base,
again the base will highlight.
And I think that's just
a lot more helpful.
It might not really make a difference
in a simple design like this,
but for a really complicated part
or one that has a lot of features,
it will help you.
>> Let's now extrude this part.
We're going to click
on our sketch, go back
to Features in this
tab display pane here.
And we are going to go
Extrude Boss/Base again.
It's asking us reverse
direction to sketch.
Well, that might not
initially be obvious to us
which direction that is, so we can
hit Yes and kind of correct it later.
>> We're going to click
on our feature here.
And oh no, we see that it is
extruding in the wrong direction.
That's a pretty easy thing to correct.
We just need to tell the extrusion to
extrude it in the opposite direction.
>> In our left pane over here, you'll
notice that there are these two arrows.
And when we hover over it,
it says Reverse Direction.
So if we click on that, now
we notice that it is now
extruding in the correct direction.
>> Right next to that is
kind of a drop down.
And there a bunch of options in
here-- Blind, Through All, Up To Next.
We want to, I guess we could
enter the thickness of our base
as the dimension for
how deep to extrude it.
But that's kind of
sketchy-- no pun intended.
Let's go to Up To Next.
Oops, sorry.
I believe it iis-- I
thought it was Up To Next.
You can just click on
the surface here if you
don't know which one it
is, like I did not just.
SolidWorks will figure it out for you.
We'll hit our green arrow.
And now we have the feature that
will be actually holding the phone.
It's now starting to resemble what it
will look like in the final product.
>> You might think at this point
well, in the finished product
there's this kind of curve here.
And it's curved on the back I don't
know if you can really see that.
And we didn't sketch that in.
Those features are what
are called fillets.
Fillets are something that we
use in mechanical engineering
to eliminate stress concentrations.
>> You can imagine if you have a part
that has two lines coming together
at a really shallow angle, they'll
create kind of a really sharp point.
And if that part is subjected to any
stresses and strains in that plane,
all of those stresses will concentrate
at the vertex of that point.
So to eliminate that,
we add a fillet, which
just rounds that surface off
and smooths everything out.
>> If you're interested in kind of the
logic and the material science by that,
just Google "stress concentrations."
But at a high level, fillets
make it look nicer too.
So we'll add those in.
We'll do that kind of at the
end, as that's pretty quick.
>> You'll notice though that there's
this hump that I was talking about.
And it does not look good at all.
So let's get rid of that.
We're going to just
highlight this face here.
Oops, I did not mean to do that.
Highlight this face here
and go Normal to it.
And we're just going
to add a sketch here
that will get rid of
this little triangle.
>> Let's relabel this Boss Extrude 2
to be, let's just say Phone Support.
And if we hit the little
Plus button right here,
you'll see that there is a sketch here.
By default, SolidWorks kind of
hides the sketches away from you
once you're done with them, as it
will kind of cloud how the part looks.
But we need to reference some
of the geometry that's in it.
>> If we just kind of hover over
it, this little box pops up.
And there are these I guess
they're little glasses.
We can hit that button.
And now the sketch is visible to us.
Or at least, it should be.
Yeah.
If I just hit F here to zoom
in, you'll notice that now
that we have access to all of
these lines and their dimensions.
>> The cool thing about this is we can
create another sketch that actually
references the geometry
of a different sketch.
If we sketch on this plane, which
we can do by just highlighting it,
hitting Sketch in this upper toolbar
over here, and then Sketch again,
now we're sketching on this plane.
And we're actually just going
to create a little triangle here
that references all of these
points that we made before.
And then, we're just going to
extrude that away or cut it away.
>> Let's just go create lines
are here, zoom in a little bit
so this is clearer.
Start at the vertex down here,
you can see I'm drawing a line.
I'm going to bring it to this
point, bring it to this point,
and make it closed.
And you'll see that all
of the lines are black.
And we didn't even need
to add in any dimensions.
That's because we've already defined
those dimensions in a previous sketch.
And now, we're referencing
those geometries.
>> We hit Green Check,
Insert Line, Green Check.
Now that's completely defined.
We'll exit this sketch.
And we're going to cut that
little triangle that we made away,
and down the arrow or I
guess in this orientation,
down the direction of our support.
Cool.
>> I'm just going to go here.
Now, we're not going
to Extrude Boss/Base.
We're not going to create material.
We want to cut material away.
A few options over, there's
this option to Extrude Cut.
Let's hit that.
And you'll notice now, that SolidWorks
is going to take material away
from this triangle that we've defined.
Let's go and let's just
click this surface.
No.
And you can select the option
Through All in this drop down.
All that does is it will
extrude this forever.
Our part doesn't exist forever.
It only exists for a couple of inches.
It will take everything
that we need off.
>> That's typically a pretty
easy way to do cuts.
You just kind of cut all
of that material away.
Whereas in extrusions,
you want to define
how much material you want to create.
We'll hit our green check mark.
>> And all of that material goes away.
And now, we're left
with this smooth face.
We don't really need this
sketch anymore, so we go back
and hide it, which we can just do
again by right clicking and now hitting
the Hide button.
And it has disappeared.
>> I guess we can label this cut by just
saying Front Face Cut, hitting Enter.
We'll just make it a little bit clearer.
Cool.
We're getting there.
We just have a couple
of things left to do.
>> What we're going to now do is add.
You'll notice that there is
a rectangular cut in here.
It's what the phone
actually slides into.
And then I just made
a little cut here so
that you can access the Home
button of this particular phone
while it's sitting in the dock.
Let's add those two features in.
And we'll add a couple of finishing
details and we'll be done.
This is, you might think, well,
how are we going to sketch on this?
We don't want to sketch on this face.
We can just sketch on this face.
We're going to hit Normal to.
And now we have access to
sketching on this face.
And we're looking down it.
>> It's kind of the same process here.
There's kind of this
rhythm where we select
a face that we're going to sketch on.
We look at it at the normal, so
that we're looking down on it.
And then, we create some sketch.
And then, we do something
with that sketch.
Maybe we make a cut or we create
some material with Extrude Boss/Base.
>> Same thing again here as we've
done the previous two iterations.
We're looking down on it.
We want to select it
as a sketch surface.
It's highlighted in blue.
So again, we hit Sketch, Sketch
just as we've done before.
And now we've created our
sketch and we'll make that cut.
One thing that we need
to be aware of though,
and this will come into
play in just little bit,
is that the corners of
our phone are rounded.
If we just make this kind of a prismatic
cut, the phone will still fit inside,
but it might kind of wiggle around.
It might not be as secure.
>> We can add little complements
in here to complement
the rounded corners of our phone.
It's kind of a small detail.
And it won't make too much
a difference, but it's
nice to kind of design
the part in its entirety.
>> Let's go here.
We're going to just draw a
rectangle on our surface here.
And cool.
Now let's define it.
We're going to go to
Smart Dimension here.
Let's define it to be the width of our
phone, which I've already forgotten.
I'm just measuring it
here-- 2.305 inches.
>> And we're going to kind of add
a little comfort zone to that
so that you can easily take the
phone in and out of the dock
without having to kind
of pull them apart.
That would be kind of what we call
that is that they're interfering.
And we don't want that here.
We want it to be easy
to take it in and out.
>> We said 2.305 inches is the width.
And then, we'll add kind
of a comfort spacing
or a buffer spacing on each side.
So let's say two times some thickness.
What is that thickness going to be?
We can just kind of guess
arbitrarily here at some thickness.
If you have calipers
with you, you can maybe
open them up to say,
I don't know, 25 thou.
25 thou is 25 thousandths of
an inch or 25 times 0.001.
I'm just kind of guessing here, but
I think that'll be enough spacing.
We'll do that on each side-- say
20 thou-- two times 0.020 inches.
>> That is now the width that needs to be.
And we'll define its height.
This will be the thickness of
our phone plus that same buffer.
I think it was 0.303
inches, but I'm not sure.
0.303 inch is the
thickness of the phone.
>> Let's say 0.303 plus two times 0.020.
| at 20 thousandths thick
buffer on each side.
And I just multiplied it
by two because, there's
a buffer inside, the front and
the back and side and side.
Hit Enter.
Cool.
>> Now you might be
thinking, oh my gosh, why
is this all blue when we have just
defined the width and the height?
That's because we haven't
located it on this plane.
We can do this pretty easily though.
We don't need to add dimensions in
because we want it to be centered.
>> We don't need to add
dimensions in to say
this line should be so and so
inches away from this line.
We don't need to do that.
We can have SolidWorks
figure that out for us.
And one way to do that-- and this is
kind of I think one of the easier ways
to do it-- is to add lines and
then add relations to them.
And these can be called
construction geometries.
A construction geometry
is just a line that you
don't plan on doing anything with
as far as extrusions are concerned.
You're not going to cut
with it or you're not
going to create material with it.
You're just going to
use it as a reference.
That might sound kind of lofty.
I'll nail that down here.
We're still in Sketch mode.
If we go the Line and hit
this little arrow next to it,
this drop down will come.
And we have a Normal line option,
which is what we've been using before,
or a Center line, which will
create a construction geometry.
Let's hit that.
And this will create a dashed line.
>> Let's draw a line between
this side and here like so.
Zoom in and you can
see that it's dashed.
And then, let's do it again over here.
If we make these two lines
equal, our smaller rectangle
will be centered at least horizontally
inside the bigger rectangle.
They don't need to
necessarily be co-linear,
meaning that they don't
need to be on the same line.
But they do necessarily need to be
perpendicular to both of these faces.
>> Let's hit OK and let's
start adding relations.
SolidWorks is smart enough
to know that just by the way
I drew it they are
both horizontal, as you
can see by these horizontal lines
here-- this little green box.
So we don't even need to
do anything with that.
All we need to do now is equate them.
And SolidWorks will now center the box.
>> We highlight one, go over here
and highlight the other-- again,
holding down Control and clicking on it.
And say, make them equal.
And like that, SolidWorks
has centered the box.
Again, I'm just zooming out by
rolling on the jog wheel on the mouse.
And we could, if we
wanted to, pan around
by again holding down on the jog wheel.
Let's do the same process
to center it vertically.
I'm just going to go down here.
I'll go a little bit faster this
time, create this vertical line,
create another vertical line.
Again, I'm double clicking
to get out of Line mode.
And then, we hit our green arrow now.
>> And let's equate them-- click one,
Control click, highlight the other,
and then Make Equal.
Now everything's black,
and we're going to go.
Exit the Sketch, kind of the same thing.
Now we're going to make
an extruded cut down here.
And it's up to us now how
thick we want to make that cut.
>> This doesn't so much matter.
It's kind of up to us.
I'll say just based
on the geometry maybe
it'll be double what it is right now.
Right now, it's at 0.15 inches thick.
If we make it 0.3 inches
thick, that looks pretty good.
We can probably go a little bit
deeper-- maybe 0.40 inches thick.
Yeah.
That looks good.
Hit the green arrow.
And now we have this slot
that the phone will sit in.
>> Now, we need to add kind of this
little cut out for the Home button.
I guess this is not
completely necessary if you
don't need to use your phone
while it's in the dock.
But it's a nice feature to have.
And it takes little effort on our
end, so we may as well add it in.
Same thing.
Let's highlight this
face, go Normal to it.
And we're just going to sketch
on this face and we'll be done.
Again, his Sketch, Sketch.
Now, we're going to draw a circle.
We can just kind of go up here into
our shapes menu and click Circle.
And let's just draw a circle
kind of in the middle of nowhere.
And we'll start to add relations to it.
>> We're going to create a vertical
line that the center of the circle
will be coincident with.
And that way, our circle
is centered on the phone.
And when we slip the
phone into the dock,
the Home button will line up with
the cut out for the Home button,
because we know that the Home button
on our phone is in the center of it.
>> We're going to go here
and create a center line.
And I'm just going to find the
midpoint of this bottom line.
If I try to start a line
on this bottom line,
you'll notice that there
is a little yellow button.
And when we hover over that, this
little icon pops up next our pencil.
And that icon is aligned with a
green dot in the middle of it.
>> When you see that icon, that means that
that's the center point of that line.
So if we draw off of that,
we click and draw upwards,
we've just drawn a vertical
line from that midpoint.
I did that kind of quickly,
so I'll just do it again.
And let's say that I don't see that.
It's not popping up for me.
We can do it even a simpler way.
>> We'll go to center line.
And we'll draw.
We have this line here.
But it's not at the center point.
It's not centered against here.
So what we can do is, we can draw a
point, which we go to our Shapes menu,
see a Point, find the midpoint here.
You see that it pops up when we get
close to it-- drop point there, here.
The one thing you may notice that's
different about all the other shapes is
the point thing is
still highlighted, even
after you click the green check mark.
Just hit it again to unhighlight it.
And that will make this point and
the base of our line be coincident.
It accomplishes the same task.
>> Now we're going to take the
center of our Home button,
Control click our vertical line,
highlight the both of them,
and make them coincident.
Now our Home button is centered.
We can't move it left to right.
We can only move it up and down.
And we can change its diameter.
>> How big should we make it?
I don't know.
Let's measure it.
If we look on our phone
here, we take our calipers,
and we can measure the
diameter of the Home button.
And it's nice to give it kind
of a little bit of wiggle room,
so we'll make it a little bit
bigger than it needs to be.
>> That's because when your
phone is sitting in the dock,
if it were exactly the
size of the Home button,
you kind of have to stick your
finger like perpendicularly in
to be able to access the Home button.
Whereas, if we make it bigger,
you can kind of hit it at an angle
and see all the snapshots
that you have missed.
>> Let's go here and we'll
measure on the phone.
And I'm just eyeing it again here.
That looks to be
comfortable. it says 0.674.
We'll make a round number.
Let's say 0.65.
Yeah.
That seems comfortable.
Some of this is kind of
guesswork because we're not
designing a really kind
of nailed-down part.
This part's not
accomplishing any real task.
It's just holding something.
So it's OK to do a
little bit of guesswork.
>> Let's Smart Dimension this diameter.
We just said it was
going to be 0.65 inches.
We go up in our menu up in the top left.
Again, hit Smart Dimension.
If you just click
anywhere on the circle,
it's smart enough to know that
we're talking about the diameter.
Whether you kind of drag
it off to the side here
and it gives you that little phi
symbol or you hold it directly above,
it's the same thing.
You're defining its diameter.
>> Let's click here and
we're going to say 0.650.
Hit Enter.
And now, the diameter is defined.
And what we need to do now is
define the height from the bottom.
This is probably the trickiest
part of this whole operation.
>> In doing so, we want
the center of our circle
to line up with the
center of the Home button.
Just by kind of eyeing it
again with a pair of calipers,
we can measure the distance between
the center of our Home button
at the bottom of the phone.
Ideally, we would have a really
detailed spec sheet of our phone
and we could just look at the
spec sheet and figure out oh,
the center of this button
is so and so inches
from the bottom plane of the phone.
>> But we don't have access to
that, so we'll just measure it.
And it'll be pretty accurate.
I'm just kind of eyeing
it here, the center
of the Home button to
the bottom of the phone.
It looks to be about 0.329
inches, maybe a little bigger.
Let's call it 0.348 inches.
>> We now know that the
bottom plane of our phone
is 0.348 inches away
from the center line.
But the bottom plane of
the phone is at some angle,
so how are we going to figure this out?
I don't know.
Let's go to our Cut Extrusion
here, which I notice now
that I did not label,
so we can do that now.
We'll call this Phone Slots.
And there are a couple different
ways that we can do this.
We can say, we can Smart Dimension
it in a couple of different ways.
By this angle-- and this gets into
of this is a little bit more tricky--
let's look at it at an angle where
we have access visually to the plane
where the phone is going to be
sitting on and our Home button.
>> We go into Smart Dimension, and I'm
going to dimension from this line
to the center of our hole
here, which gets highlighted.
And now, I don't even
remember what the number.
I'm just going to quickly remeasure it.
I think it was 0.348.
Yeah, 0.348 sounds good.
Now we'll add that 0.348 in-- 0.348.
Hit Enter.
And our phone is defined.
Our button is defined.
Hit the check mark.
>> And here's kind of a subtle point
that would be kind of easy to miss.
You'll notice that the center of our
circle actually sits below this line.
That means that if we
extrude through the sides
where the Home button cut out is made,
we'll actually start to curve back up.
We can just eliminate that by drawing
kind of a rectangle above the phone.
>> If we go to our square thing here.
And we go to this point, just kind of
draw a rectangle randomly in the sky,
and then make the other edge of it
be-- I'll just click over here--
make this point be
coincident with the circle.
Now when we extrude, we
can extrude the circle.
And by extrude, I mean extrude
cut-- extrude cut the circle
and this little sliver in here.
That might be a subtle point.
And in our case, it wouldn't
make a huge difference.
But it's nice to add all
these finishing details in it.
It distinguishes kind of a
quickly, hastily made product
and one that had a lot
of thought into it.
>> We'll click our green check mark here.
And we're good to go.
You'll notice that this is blue.
This is kind of an exception.
We don't really need to
define it here, because it
doesn't matter how
tall our rectangle is.
It will still accomplish the same task.
>> This is pretty rare that you don't
need to define something in a sketch.
In 99.9% of cases, you
need the whole sketch
to be black like I had mentioned before.
In this case, it doesn't matter.
We'll exit the sketch, again go to
Features, kind of this common theme
here, find the plane, Sketch, Extrude.
And we'll go to Extrude Cut.
>> And now, SolidWorks prompts us
to pick what we want to cut.
Let's select these bottom pieces.
And now, let's get these little slivers.
We'll do it on the other side too.
Again, just zooming by
scrolling on the mouse.
Now we have everything we need.
>> We don't want to do Blind.
I guess we could do Blind, but it
doesn't really accomplish what we want.
Let's do Up To Next,
and that will only cut
through the first layer of material.
When we say we want to
cut up to next, that's
meaning we want to cut
everything up to the next face.
>> Well, the next face is
the layer behind here.
We don't want this Home cut
to go all the way through.
You don't need it to
go all the way through.
There's no Home button
on the back of the phone.
If we just hit the green check
here, now we have the phone cut out.
Now we can start to add in the finishing
details, because we're almost done.
I mentioned before that
we can add in fillets,
which make everything
look a little bit nicer.
These are super easy to do.
This is probably the easiest part
of this whole CADing process.
>> In our Feature Tree up here,
in this kind of tab pane,
we go to Features where we were hitting
Extrude Boss/Base and Extrude Cut
before.
A couple of options over, we have
this option to Fillet something.
Let's click on that.
All Fillet wants is an edge.
You can give it a face,
and it'll figure it out.
But it really is looking for edges
to which it can add a fillet.
>> I'd mentioned before that we want
to add a fillet to the back here.
If we just click on this edge,
it sketches out the fillet here,
which is pretty cool.
That required minimal work on our part.
SolidWorks just defaults
to some arbitrary value
for the radius of this fillet.
It looks good.
We can make it a little bit bigger.
I just think it's
aesthetically more pleasing.
>> This is when it becomes kind of
less scientific and more aesthetic.
The radius here is set to 0.10 inches.
We could probably set it
to I don't know 0.15 maybe.
That makes it a little bit bigger.
That looks nicer, I think.
This is up to you.
This is kind of customization.
So we hit the check mark there.
It adds in the fillet.
Looking good.
Now let's fillet this back edge here.
And what this is doing is that
first fillet that I added in
was this one right here.
We can also add in a fillet
to smooth this edge down.
>> Let's select again Fillet
and this back edge here.
And it does the same thing.
It's again defaulting to
0.15 inches, because that's
what I'd entered last time.
That seems a little excessive
here-- maybe 0.075, half that.
That looks a little bit nicer.
Again, this is totally
up to the designer.
>> That looks a little better.
Maybe we can actually make
that a little bit larger.
I'm going to show you now how to
make an existing fillet larger.
And this is kind of
a theme in SolidWorks
where when you've
already made a feature,
you can change it pretty
easily, pretty painlessly.
>> Let's go through and label some
things that we have not labeled.
Cut Extrude 3, we don't know what
that is, so we just click on it.
And we see that it was the
cut for our Home button.
Let's just label that Home Button Hole.
The fillets are kind of a
tertiary feature, so to speak.
Labeling them is not as crucial.
>> But you're looking at this and
you say oh my god, Ansel, my life
is falling apart.
What do I do about that?
And I say you need to change
the radius of this fillet.
Let's click on it.
And we're going to right click on it.
And now, this option pops up.
We have all of these options.
We can hide it, suppress it.
>> The top left option is
this Edit Feature option.
If we click on that, now we
return to the Feature pane
which we had access to before.
And we can change everything.
>> We had set it to 0.075 inches before.
Let's now maybe bump
that up a little bit.
I think it will just look nicer-- 0.10.
I accidentally added in a
zero in the wrong place.
That looks pretty good, maybe 0.120.
I think that looks pretty nice.
This part is effectively done.
It will do everything
that we want it to.
It will hold the phone.
It looks good.
Yeah, it has a spot for the Home button.
This is pretty much what
we wanted to accomplish.
>> Some things that we
can think about are we
need to be sure that the
center of the phone, the center
mass of the phone, if looking vertically
will hover over this base and not
kind of beyond it.
As I had mentioned before, if that's
the case, the phone will fall over.
I just kind of eyed it.
It might not hurt to just sketch it out
on paper using pretty simple geometry.
It's a super simple problem.
>> I chose in this specific example to
add the letters CS50 in the front.
You're welcome to add whatever
you want on the front.
But one thing that I
will caution you with
is that some 3D printers don't have
infinitely granular resolution.
>> And by that I mean that if you write
really small text with a really
small font, it's going to look
really kind of cloudy or blotchy.
If you make a really big text,
the letters are really large,
and it doesn't require a whole lot
of resolution on the 3D printer side,
so it'll just look way better.
So if you're printing
in text into something,
definitely make it as large as possible.
>> I'll just briefly show
you how to do that.
If we highlight this face here,
you'll notice that we can,
we'll sketch on it again.
Let's look Normal to it.
Hit Sketch, Sketch again.
Instead of drawing a line or a
circle, there is this big A here.
Some people call me Big A.
>> We can hit that.
And now we have the option
to add text on to something.
Let's type in CS.
You might be able to fit
CS50 all on one side.
It certainly wouldn't be symmetric.
I don't think it would be
aesthetically appealing.
So I did CS on one side
and 50 on the other.
That was just a decision that
seemed to work at the time.
>> We will hit the green arrow.
Now we'll notice that
these letters are blue.
And that's because they are
just floating around in space.
They are kind of free to move wherever.
What we want to do is, I'm actually
going to delete them by right clicking,
just hitting Cancel.
I'm sorry, right clicking
when you're not in a feature.
And then hit Delete.
>> We can do a nicer job in defining them.
When you write text, and text is kind
of something that's a little bit weaker,
you want to create a line that
the text will sit on, and then
define the text to be kind
of adhering to that line.
We do that by just
drawing a center line.
>> Make sure that it is horizontal here.
Double click to get out
of drawing the line.
And then hit the green arrow.
This line is just floating around here.
We have freedom to move it.
Let's not define it just yet.
Let's add the text in before
we set where it lives.
>> Again, we'll go to this big A here.
We'll hit CS.
And then, it defaulted to this
Line 1 as where it will live on.
But if that didn't exist,
we'll just delete this.
You can kind of select the
line by just clicking on it.
And SolidWorks knows
that you mean to put
the text on the line
with the green arrow.
Cool.
>> Now the text is really
small so we can actually
just double click on
it and edit the font.
And we do that.
It defaults using the document
font, which we don't want to use,
so we uncheck that.
And now, this font box
becomes un-grayed out.
It's at 12 point right now.
Let's maybe bump it up to like 48.
That looks pretty good.
And you can hit the green arrow.
>> And by moving where the line begins
around, you can move the text around.
For example, you should be able to--
I'm just going to zoom in a little bit,
select this point.
You should be able to move that.
And you can see that
the text moves with it.
>> You can do this, put the
text wherever you want.
You can define it by
fixing this point, like so.
And then, now our baseline
becomes blacked out, Exit that.
The sketch still exists.
You can go into the sketch like
I did before and extrude it.
We don't want it to go
all the way through.
We only want it to go maybe,
I don't know, 0.05 inches in.
You don't want it to
go all the way through,
just because it won't look nice.
Hit the green check.
And now CS50 or the CS
part of CS50 is in there.
Cool.
Then you can do 50 on the other side.
>> That's your total freedom as
to what you want to do there.
You'll notice that I just
suppressed it in the Feature Tree.
If you have a feature
that's kind of causing
problems with dimensions or something
is awry, you can suppress it.
And it will kind of get rid of
that feature and everything that's
referencing it or everything
associated with it.
Just kind of a side note.
Let's save this part, which I should
have done a long time ago in case
my computer crashed.
We can just go to File, Save As.
I'll just save it on my desktop.
We'll call this iPhone Dock.
And it saves is a part.
>> Once that you have created
a part, we encourage
you to use 3D printing as a means by
which you're able to manufacture it.
If you're interested in more
sophisticated methods of manufacture,
do look into ES51, which is Computer
Aided Machine Design, because that's
kind of a more exhaustive course
long, semester long introduction
to more sophisticated
manufacture methods,
like using a mill to
make it out of metal.
But we're not as concerned
about that right now.
This is a pretty simple part.
And it's going to be plenty
strong by 3D printing it.
>> Now, before it can be
given to the 3D printer,
we need to do a little bit of handiwork
that makes it in a file format
that the 3D printer will play with.
We can do that by using
MakerBot's own software,
and just import this and then
create it into a dot MakerBot file.
And we do that by exporting
this as a dot STL file.
>> If we go over here, we
can hit File, Save As.
The default is to save it as SolidWorks'
own extension, which for [INAUDIBLE]
is dot-- I don't even know-- SLDPRT.
We don't want that.
If we had this drop down, we
can change the format to STL.
And we'll say again, we'll
save it on the desktop.
>> Let's go-- I'm actually just
going to save in my Dropbox
so that I can easily access it in
my Mac partition on my computer.
But you're welcome to do
whatever-- iPhone Doc.
We'll hit Save.
It'll give us this little prompt box.
It's like, do you want
to save it as an STL?
And you're like, hell,
yeah, so you hit Yes.
>> Then I'm going to just jump over
to Mac here and go into my Dropbox.
I'm going to [INAUDIBLE] my CSP set
up that I'm diligently working on,
go to Dropbox, and I should see it here.
Cool-- iphonedoc.stl.
Just drag it on my desktop.
>> I'm going to fire up
the MakerBot software.
And by doing so, I will
just import the file
that we just made in a dot STL format.
And then from there, we'll create
the dot MakerBot file format.
It kind of gives you what the
printing stage looks like.
>> Let's just that are
part file to it, which
we do by saying Add File, kind of in the
upper-right menu over here, Add File.
I'm going to put it on
my desktop-- iPhone Doc.
Hit Open.
Do you want to put the
object on the platform?
Yes, I do.
So it says, I say move to platform.
This is in a really weird configuration.
We don't want it to print like this.
It'll take forever and it
will be really unstable.
We want to print in a
really stable configuration.
And by that I mean, we
want to have it print
with kind of this face on the bottom.
And then, start it from the
bottom, work our way to the top.
We'll do that by rotating
this part 90 degrees.
If we select the part,
and you can know that it's
selected because it's outlined
in yellow, hit Turn here.
A little menu will pop up.
And I believe we want to turn
it-- nope, that's not right--
turn it 90 degrees in
I guess it's the x way.
You can just play around
until you get it right.
Then hit Lay Flat,
and that will bring it
down to the bottom of
the build platform.
I don't need to rotate it.
>> And now, we are actually ready to print.
It was that simple.
If you want to kind of in a
more sophisticated setting,
you can adjust some of
the print parameters.
Infill just means how much of what's
being printed is actual filament
and how much is air.
>> For example, 100% infill mean that
this is a completely solid part.
Whereas 10% infill, which I guess is
MakerBot's default, means that only 10%
of this volume is going to be filament,
and the remaining 90% will be air.
And it's able to maintain most
of the structural integrity
by creating a honeycomb that
MakerBot figures out on their own.
They have an algorithm built into
this program that takes care of that.
We'll just leave all these settings.
I'll say Save Settings.
And now, we're going
to Export Print File.
Cool.
And it's ready to go.
It says it'll take about an
hour and a half for it to print.
You can probably a little bit of
work done while it's printing.
>> We can hit this Print Preview.
It's just kind of a cool feature.
And this allows us to get an
idea of how it will print.
3D printing is done by kind of
adding one layer on top of another.
So if we see over on the
left side of our window here,
there it says Layer 83.
>> There's a little slider that allows
us to kind of scan through our part.
If we scan through
here, you can actually
see the honeycomb that it prints.
You can kind of see that's
kind of hard to see here.
It may be a little
better if we look on top.
MakerBot figured all
that out on their own.
They have an algorithm
that took care of that.
We didn't design that honeycomb in.
That just makes it a more
efficient print process.
>> The high-level takeaways for this
are you design the part, prepare it,
in this case, where you can
print on a MakerBot 3D printer,
but you're welcome to use something
of the like that is not MakerBot.
Prepare it in their
software, and then give it
to the 3D printer on maybe the network
or on a flash drive in the correct file
format.
And then from there, you have
your part and you're ready to go.
The way that you can do
this, and you'll notice
that I use kind of a lot of
different software packages on here,
I happen to have SolidWorks
installed on my computer.
But it's not a free product.
Definitely if you're a
member of the college,
you might not want to go
through the strain of it
runs on Windows, kind
of downloading Windows,
having to get your hands on the
software, which can be a pain.
>> If you want to do something like
this or pursue a mechanical component
to your project, definitely
utilize the computer workstations
in the basement of Pierce
Hall in G11 specifically,
as they are open nearly
around the clock.
And they have all of the
software that you need.
They have SolidWorks and they are
very powerful with fun large monitors,
so it will make [INAUDIBLE]
pretty easy for you.
They're very quick.
>> Once you're done with that, you can
actually download the MakerBot software
package on your own computer.
It's free.
And I believe they do have both
Mac and Windows versions of it.
And then from there, you're good to go.
Utilize Pierce, SolidWorks,
export it, MakerBot, print it.
>> Try to add in relations
as much as you can,
so that you don't have to
add redundant dimensions.
That's important.
It might not be a big player in
a pretty simple part like this,
but it's just kind of a
good practice definitely.
And if interested in doing this on
kind of a more intricate level, a more
granular level, definitely
look into taking ES51.
>> That about concludes it.
I hope you have enjoyed listening to me.
And if you have any questions,
don't hesitate to shoot me an email.
I believe that my email is
attached to the invitation
of this event in some way.
Thank you.