>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DUSTIN TRAN: Hi.
My name's Dustin.
So I'll be presenting
Data Analysis in R.
Just a little bit about myself.
I'm currently a graduate student in
the Engineering and Applied Sciences.
I study an intersection of
machine learning and statistics
so Data Analysis in R is
really fundamental to what
I do on a daily basis.
>> And R is especially
good for data analysis
because it's very good for prototyping.
And usually, when you're doing some sort
of data analysis, a lot of the problems
are going to cognitive.
And so you just want to have
some really good language that
is just good for doing
built-in functions, as opposed
to having to deal with low level things.
So in the beginning, I'm just going
to introduce what is R, why would
you want to use it, and
then go over into some demo,
and just go on from there.
>> So what is R?
R is just a language developed
for statistical computing
and visualization.
So what this means is that
it's a very excellent language
for any sort of thing that deals with
uncertainty or data visualization.
So you have all these
probability distributions.
There are going to be
built-in functions.
You'll also have excellent
plotting packages.
>> Python is another competing
language for data.
And one thing that I find that R
is much better at is visualization.
So what you'll see in the demo as
well is just a very intuitive language
that just works extremely well.
It is also free and open source, as
is any other good language I guess.
>> And here, a bunch of just
keywords thrown at you.
It's dynamic, meaning if you have a
specific type assigned to an object
than it'll just change it on the fly.
It's lazy so it's smart about
how it does calculations.
Functional meaning it can really operate
based off of functions so anything--
any sort of manipulation you're
doing, it will be based off functions.
>> So binary operators, for example,
are just inherently functions.
And everything that
you're going to do is
going to be run off functions itself.
And then object oriented as well.
>> So here is an XKCD plot.
Not only because I feel like
XKCD is fundamental to any sort
of presentation, but because
I feel like this really
hammers the point that a lot of the
time when you're doing some sort of data
analysis, the problem is not
so much how fast it runs,
but how long it's going to
take you to program the task.
So here is just analyzing whether
strategy a or b is more efficient.
This is going to be
something that you're
going to deal a lot with in
sort of low-level languages
where you're dealing with seg faults,
memory allocation, initializations,
even making the built-in functions.
And this stuff is all handled
very, very elegantly in R.
>> So just to hammer this
point, the biggest bottleneck
is going to be cognitive.
So data analysis is a very hard problem.
Whether you are doing
machine learning or you're
doing just some sort of
basic data exploration,
you don't want to have
to take a document
and then compile
something every time you
want to see what a column looks like,
what particular entries in a matrix
looks like.
So you just want to have
some really nice interface
you can run a simple function
that indexes to whatever
you'd like and just run it from there.
And you need domain
specific languages for this.
And R will really help you define the
problem and solve it in this manner.
>> So here is a plot showing programming
popularity of R as it's gone over time.
So as you can see, like 2013 or
so it just blown up tremendously.
And this has been just because of that
huge trend in the technology industry
about big data.
Also, not just the technology
industry, but really
any industry that-- because
a lot of the industries
are sort of fundamental to
trying to solve these problems.
And usually, you can have some good
way of measuring these problems
or even defining them or
solving them using data.
So I think right now R is the 11th
most popular language on TIOBE
and it's been growing since then.
>> So here's some more
features of R. It has
an enormous number of packages and
for all these different things.
So any time you have a
certain problem, most
the time R will have
that function for you.
So whether you want to
build some sort of machine
learning algorithm called
Random Forest or Decision Trees,
or even trying to take the mean of
a function or any of this stuff,
R will have that.
>> And if you do you care about
optimization, one thing that's common
is that after you're done prototyping
some sort of high-level language,
you will throw that in--
you will just port that over
to some low-level language.
What's good about R is that once you're
done prototyping it, you can run C++,
or Fortran, or any of these
lower level ones directly into R.
So that's one really
cool feature about R,
if you really care about
the optimization point.
>> And it's also really good
for web visualizations.
So D3.js, for example, is
I guess another seminar
that we presented today.
And this is really awesome for
doing interactive visualizations.
And D3.js assumes that you have
some sort of data to be plotted
and R is a great way of being able to do
the data analysis before you export it
over to D3.js or even just run
D3.js commands into R itself,
as well as all these
other libraries as well.
>> So that was just the introduction of
what is R and why you might use it.
So hopefully, I've
convinced you something
about just trying to see what it's like.
So I'm going to go ahead and go through
some fundamentals about R objects
and what you can really do.
>> So here is just a
bunch of math commands.
So say you're-- you want to build
language yourself and you just want
to have a bunch of different tools.
Any sort of operation you think you'd
want is pretty much going to be in R.
>> So here is 2 plus 2.
Here is 2 times pi.
R has a bunch of built-in constants
that you'll frequently use like pi, e.
>> And then, here's 7 plus
runif, so runif of 1.
This is a function that's generates
one random uniform from 0 to 1.
And then there's 3 to the power of 4.
There's square roots.
>> There's log.
So log will do base
exponential by itself.
And then, if you specify a base, then
you can do whatever base you want.
And then here are some other commands.
So you have 23 mod 2.
Then you have the remainder.
Then you have scientific
notation if you also
want to do just more and
more complicated things.
>> So here is assignment.
So typical assignments in
R is done with an arrow
so it's less than and then the hyphen.
So here I'm just assigning
3 to the variable val.
>> And then I'm printing out val
and then it prints out three.
By default in R interpreter, it
will print things out for you
so you don't have to specify print a val
any time you want to print something.
You can just do val and
then it'll do that for you.
>> Also, you can use equals technically
as an assignment operator.
There are slight subtleties
between using the arrow
operator and the equals
operator for assignments.
Mostly by convention, everyone
will just use the arrow operator.
>> And here, I'm assigning this
oblique notation called 1 colon 6.
This generates a vector from 1 to 6.
And this really nice because then
you just assign the vector to val
and that works by itself.
>> So this is already going from a
single-- a very intuitive data
structure of just a double of
some type of type into a vector
and which will collect all
the scalar values for you.
So after going from scalar, you
have R objects and this is a vector.
A vector is any sort of
collection of the same type.
So here are a bunch of vectors.
>> So this is numeric.
Numeric is R's way of saying double.
And so by default, any
number will be a double.
>> So if you have c of 1.1, 3,
negative 5.7, the c is a function.
This concatenates all three
numbers into a vector.
And this will be-- so if
you notice 3 by itself,
normally you would assume
that this is like an integer,
but because all vectors
are the same type,
this is a vector of doubles
or numeric in this case.
>> rnorm is a function that generates
standard normal variables--
or standard normal values.
And I'm specifying two of them.
So I'm doing rnorm 2, assigning that to
devs, and then I'm printing out devs.
So these are just two
random normal values.
>> And then ints if you do
you care about integers.
So this is just about memory
allocation and saving memory size.
So you would have to append
your numbers by the capital L.
>> In general, this is
R's historic notation
for something called long integer.
So most of the time, you'll
be dealing with doubles.
And if you ever will later
on optimize your code,
you can just add these L's
afterwards or during it
if you're like precognitive about what
you're going to do these variables.
>> So here is a character vector.
So, again, I'm concatenating
three strings this time.
Notice that double strings and
single strings are the same in R.
So I have arthur and marvin's and so
when I'm printing it out, all of them
are going to show double strings.
And if you also want to include
the double or single string
in your characters, then you can
either alternate your strings.
>> So marvin's for the
second element, this is
going to show-- you
just have double strings
and then a single string
so this is alternating.
Otherwise, if you want to use a double
string operator in a double string
when you're declaring it, then
you just use the escape operator.
So you do the backslash double string.
>> And finally, we also
have logical vectors.
So logical-- so TRUE
and FALSE, and they're
going to be all capital letters.
And then, again, I'm concatenating
them and then assigning them to bools.
So bools is going to show
you TRUE, FALSE, and TRUE.
>> So here is vectorized indexing.
So in the beginning, I
am taking a function--
this is called a sequence--
sequence from 2 to 12.
And I'm taking a sequence by 2.
So it's going to do
2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12.
And then, I'm indexing
to get the third element.
>> So one thing to keep in mind is
that R indexes by starting from 1.
So vals 3 is going to give
you the third element.
This is sort of different from other
languages where it starts from zero.
So in C or C++, for example, you're
going to get the fourth element.
>> And here is vals from 3 to 5.
So one thing that's
really cool is that you
can generate temporary variables inside
and then just use them on the fly.
So here is 3 to 5.
So I'm generating a vector
3, 4, and 5 and then
I'm indexing to get the third,
fourth, and fifth elements.
>> So similarly, you can
abstract this to just do
any sort of a vector
that gives you indexing.
So here is vals and then the
first, third, and sixth elements.
And then, if you want
to do a complement,
so you just do the minus
afterwards and that'll
give you everything that's not the
first, third, or sixth element.
So this will be 4, 8, and 10.
>> And if you want to get
even more advanced,
you can concatenate Boolean vectors.
So this index is going to give you
this Boolean vector of length 6.
So rep TRUE comma 3.
This will repeat TRUE three times.
So this will give you a
vector TRUE, TRUE, TRUE.
>> rep FALSE 4-- this is going to give you
a vector of FALSE, FALSE, FALSE, FALSE.
And then c is going to concatenate
those two Booleans together.
So you're going to get three
TRUEs and then four FALSEs.
>> So that when you index vals, you're
going to get the TRUE, TRUE, TRUE.
So that's going to say yes,
I want those three elements.
And then FALSE, FALSE,
FALSE, FALSE is going
to say no, I don't want those elements
so it's not going to return them.
>> And I guess there's actually a typo here
because this is saying repeat TRUE 3
and repeat FALSE 4, and technically, you
only have six elements so repeat FALSE,
it should be repeat FALSE 3.
I think R is also smart enough such
that if you just specify 4 here, then
it won't even error out.
It will just give you this value.
So it'll just ignore that fourth FALSE.
>> So here is vectorized assignment.
So set.seed-- this just sets the
seed for pseudorandom numbers.
So I'm setting the seed to
42, meaning that if I generate
three random normal
values, and then if you
run set.seed on your own
computer using the same value 42,
then you also get the
same three random normals.
>> So this is really good
for reproducibility.
Usually, when you're doing some
sort of scientific analysis,
you would want to set the seed.
That way other scientists can just
reproduce the exact same code you've
done because they'll have the exact
same random variables that-- or random
values that you've taken out as well.
>> And so the vectorized assignment
here is showing the vals 1 to 2.
So it takes the first two elements
of vals and then assigns them to 0.
And then, you can also just do the
similar thing with the Booleans.
>> So vals is not equal to 0-- this will
give you a vector FALSE, FALSE, TRUE
in this case.
And then, it's going to say any
of those indexes that were TRUE,
then it's going to assign that to 5.
So it takes the third element
here and then assigns it to 5.
>> And this is really nice
compared to low-level languages
where you have to use for loops
to do all of this vectorized stuff
because it's just very intuitive
and it's a single one-liner.
And what's great about
vectorized notation
is that in R, these are sort of
built-in so that they're almost as fast
as doing in a low-level language as
opposed to making a for loop in R
and then having it to do
the dynamic indexing itself.
And that'll be slower than doing
this sort of vectorized thing
where it can do it in parallel, where
it's doing it in threading basically.
>> So here is vectorized operations.
So I'm generating a value 1 to 3,
assigning that to vec1, 3 to 5, vec2,
adding them together.
It adds them component-wise so
it's 1 plus 3, 2 plus 4, and so on.
>> vec1 times vec2.
This multiplies the two
values component wise.
So it's 1 times 3, 2 times
4, and then 3 times 5.
>> And then, similarly you can also do
comparisons-- logical comparisons.
So it's FALSE FALSE TRUE in this
case because 1 is not greater than 3,
2 is not greater than 4.
This is, I guess, another typo, 3
is definitely not greater than 5.
Yeah.
And so you can just do all
these simple operations
because their inherited
from the classes themselves.
>> So that was just the vector.
And that's sort of the most fundamental
R object because given a vector,
you can construct more advanced objects.
>> So here's a matrix.
This is essentially the abstraction
of what a matrix is itself.
So in this case, it's three different
vectors, where each one is a column,
or you can consider it
as each one is a row.
>> So I'm storing a matrix from 1 to
9 and then I'm specifying 3 rows.
So 1 to 9 will give you a vector 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and all the way to 9.
>> One thing to also keep in mind is that
R stores values in column-major format.
So in other words, when you see 1
to 9, it's going to store them--
it's going to be 1, 2,
3 in the first column,
and then it'll do 4, 5,
6 in the second column,
and then 7, 8, 9 in the third column.
>> And here are some other
common functions you can use.
So dim mat, this will give you
the dimensions of the matrix.
It's going to return you
a vector of the dimension.
So in this case, because
our matrix is 3 by 3,
it's going to give you a
numeric vector that's 3 3.
>> And here is just showing
matrix multiplication.
So usually, if you just do
asterisk-- so mat asterisk mat--
this is going to be
component-wise operation
or what's called the Hadamard product.
So it's going to do each
element component-wise.
However, if you want
matrix multiplication--
so multiplying the first row times
the second matrix's first column
and so on-- you would use
this percent operation.
>> And t of mat is just an
operation for transpose.
So I'm saying take the transpose in
the matrix, multiply it by the matrix
itself.
And then it's going to
return to you another 3
by 3 matrix showing
the product you'd want.
>> And so that was matrix.
Here is what's called a data frame.
A data frame you can think of as
a matrix, but each column itself
is going to be of a different type.
>> So what's really cool about data
frames is that in data analysis itself,
you're going to have all this
heterogeneous data and all these really
messy things where each of the columns
themselves can be of different types.
So here I'm saying create a
data frame, do ints from 1 to 3,
and then also have a character vector.
So I can index through
each of these columns
and then I'll get the values themselves.
And you can also do some sort
of operations on data frames.
And most of the time when you're
doing data analysis or some sort
of preprocessing, you'll be
working with these data structures
where each column is going
to be of a different type.
>> Finally, so these are essentially just
the four essential objects in R. List
will just collect any
other objects you want.
So it will store this into one
variable that you can easily access.
>> So here, I'm taking a list.
I'm saying stuff equals 3.
So I'm going to have one element in
the list, and this is called stuff,
and it's going to have the value 3.
>> I can also create a matrix.
So this is 1 to 4 and end row
equals 2, so a 2 by 2 matrix.
Also in the list and it's called mat.
moreStuff, a character string,
and even another list in itself.
>> So this is a list that's 5 and bear .
So it has the value 5 and it
has the character string bear
and it's a list inside a list.
So you can have these
recursive things where
you have another-- a
type within the type.
So similarly, you can have a matrix
inside another matrix and so on.
And a list is just a good way
of collecting and aggregating
all these different objects.
>> And finally, here is just help in case
this was just gone over very quickly.
So anytime you're confused
about some sort of function,
you can do help of that function.
So you can do help matrix
or a question mark matrix.
And help and the question mark are
just shorthand for the same thing
so they're aliases.
>> lm is a function that
just does a linear model.
But if you just have no idea how that
works, you can just do help of lm
and that'll give you some
sort of documentation that
looks kind of like a
man page in Unix, where
you have a short description of what
it does, also what its arguments are,
what it returns, and just tips on how
to use it, and some examples as well.
>> So let me go ahead and show
some demo of using R. OK.
So I went over very
quickly just the data
structures and some sort of the
op-- some of the operations.
Here is some functions.
>> So here I'm just going
to define a function.
So I'm also using
assignment operator here,
and then I'm saying
declare it as a function.
And it takes the value x.
So this is any value you want
and I'm going to return x itself.
So this is the identity function.
>> And what's cool about this
compared to other languages
and another low-level
languages is that x
can be of any type itself
and it'll return that type.
So you can imagine-- so let
me just run this quickly.
Sorry.
>> So one thing I should also mention
is that this editor I'm using
is called rstudio.
This is what's called an IDE.
And one thing that's
really nice about this
is that it incorporates a lot of the
things you want to do in R by itself
just very intuitively.
>> So here is an interpreter console.
So similarly, you can also get this
console raw just by doing a capital R.
And this is exactly the
same thing as the console.
So I can just do id function x, x, x.
And then-- and then that
will be fine itself.
>> So rstudio is great
because it has the console.
It also has the documents
you'd like to run on.
And then it has some variables
that you can see in environments.
And then, if you have
to do plots, then you
can just see it here, as opposed to
managing all these different windows
by themselves.
>> I actually personally use Vim, but I
feel like rstudio is excellent just
for getting a good idea
of how to use R. Usually,
when you're trying to
learn some new task,
you don't want to handle
too many things at once.
So R is just a very-- rstudio
is a very good way of learning R
without having to deal with
all these other things.
>> So here I'm running id hello.
This returns hello.
id 123.
Here is a vector of integers.
So similarly, because you can
take any some sort of value,
you can do returning id of
x so it returns 1234 and 5.
>> And let me just show you that
this is indeed an integer.
And similarly, if you do class
id x, it's going to be integer.
And then, you can also
compare the two and it's TRUE.
So I'm checking if id of x
equals equals x and notice
that it gives you two TRUEs.
So this is not saying are
the two objects identical,
but are each of the entries
within the vectors identical.
>> Here is bounded.compare.
So this is slightly more complicated
in that it has an if condition and else
and then it takes two
arguments at a time.
So x is of any type.
And I'm saying this
second argument is a.
This can be anything as well.
But by default, it's going to take
5 if you don't specify anything.
>> So here I'm going to say
if x is greater than a.
So if I don't specify a, it
says if x is greater than 5,
then I'm going to return TRUE.
else, I'm going to return FALSE.
So let me go ahead and define this.
>> And now I'm going to
run bounded.compare 3.
So it says is 3 less
than-- is 3 greater than 5.
No, it's not so FALSE.
>> And bounded.compare 3 and I'm going
to compare it using a equals 2.
So now I'm saying yes, now I
want a to be something else.
So I'm going to say a, you should be 2.
>> I can either do this sort of
notation or I say a equals 2.
This is a more readable
in that when you're
looking at these really
complicated functions that
take multiple arguments-- and this
can be dozens oftentimes-- just saying
a equals 2 is more readable for
you so that later on in the future
you will know what you're doing.
>> So in this case, I'm
saying is 3 greater than 2.
Yes it is.
And similarly, I can just remove
this and say, is 3 greater than 2
where a equals 2.
And that's also TRUE.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Are you
executing line by line?
>> DUSTIN TRAN: Yes I am.
So what I'm doing here is
taking this text document--
and what's great about rstudio is that
I can just run a short-- a key shortcut.
So I'm doing Control-Enter.
>> And then, I'm taking the
line in the text document
and then putting in the console.
So here I'm saying, bounded.compare
and I'm doing Control-X.
So I can just do run here as well.
And then that'll take the
line and then put it here.
And then similarly, I can do run here.
And then it will just keep defining
the lines into the console like that.
>> And if you also notice the curly
braces are there just like in C syntax.
x-- if the if condition is also
going to use parentheses and then
you can use else.
Another one is else if.
So this is going to be x
equals equals a, for example.
And then I'm going to
return something here.
>> Notice that there are two different
things here that's going on.
One is that here I'm specifying
return the value TRUE.
Here I'm just saying x.
So R will usually by default
take the last arguments--
or take the last line of the code,
and that will be what it's returned.
So here this is the same
thing as doing return x.
>> And just to show you.
And then, it will work just like that.
So let me continue with this.
>> So else if.
And really, I can return
anything I'd like.
So I don't even have to
return Booleans all the time,
I can just return something else.
So I can do return bear.
>> So if x equals equals a,
it's going to return bear.
Otherwise, it's going to return TRUE.
I can also do a vector
or really anything.
>> And normally in statically
typed languages,
you'd have to specify a type here.
And notice that it can just be anything.
And R is intelligent enough that it
will just do this and it will work fine.
>> So let me define this.
Unexpected-- oh sorry.
It should be a curly brace here.
OK.
Cool.
All right.
So now let's compare 3 and a equals 3.
So it should return--
yeah-- the value bear.
>> So now a more general thing is like
what about other data structures.
So you have this function.
This is going to work on any sort
of value like 3 or any numeric,
in other words, double.
>> But what about something like a vector.
So what happens if you do-- so I'm
going to assign val to, say, 4 to 6.
So if I return this, this
is a vector from 4, 5, 6.
>> Now let's see what happens
if I do bounded.compare val.
So this is going to give you 15 1251.
So in other words, it's saying
if you look at this condition
so it says x is less
than a or something.
So this is slightly
confusing because now
you just don't know what's going on.
So I guess one thing that's really
good about just trying to debug
is that you can just do val is greater
than a and see what happens there.
>> So val-- a is by default 5 so
let's just do val greater than 5.
So this is a vector FALSE FALSE TRUE.
So now when you're looking at
this, it's going to say if,
and then it's going to give you this
is a vector of FALSE FALSE TRUE.
>> So when you pass this into R, R
has no idea what you're doing.
Because it expects one single
value, which is a Boolean, and now
you're giving it a vector of Booleans.
So by default, R is just
going to say what the heck,
I'm going to assume that you're
going to take the first element here.
So I'm going to say-- I'm going
to assume that this is FALSE.
So it's going to say
no, this is not right.
>> Similarly, it's going to
be val equals equals a.
No, sorry 5.
And it's also going to be false as well.
So it's going to say no,
it's not TRUE as well so it's
going to return this last one.
>> So this is either a good thing or a bad
thing, depending on how you view it.
Because when you're
creating these functions,
you don't actually know what's going on.
So sometimes you'd want an error,
or maybe you just want a warning.
In this case, R doesn't do that.
So it's really up to
you based off of what
you think the language
should do in this case
if you pass in a vector of Booleans
when you're doing an if condition.
>> So let's say that you had the original
one with if else return TRUE and you're
going to return FALSE.
So one way of abstracting
this is to say I
don't even need this conditional thing.
Another thing I can do is just
returning the values themselves.
So if you notice, if you
do val is greater than 5,
this is going to return a
vector FALSE FALSE TRUE.
>> Maybe this is what you
want for bounded.compare.
You want to return a vector of Booleans
where it compares each of the values
to themselves.
So you can just do bounded.compare
function x, a equals 5.
And then instead of doing
this if else condition,
I'm just going to return
x is greater than 5.
So if it's true, then
it's going to return TRUE.
And then if it's not, it's
going to return FALSE.
>> And this will work for
any of these structures.
So I can bounded.compare c 1 6 or 9
and then I'm going to say a equals 6,
for example.
And then it's going to
give you the right Boolean
vector that you're designing.
>> So those are just functions
and now let me just
show you some interactive visuals.
I don't think I actually have
Wi-Fi here so let me just go ahead
and skip this one I guess.
>> But one thing that's cool
though is that if you just
want to test a bunch of
different data commands,
there is a bunch of different datasets
that are already preloaded into R.
So one of them is
called the iris dataset.
This is one of the most well-known
ones in machine learning.
You'll usually just do some sort of
test cases to see if your code runs.
So let's just check what iris is.
>> So this thing is going
to be a data frame.
And it's kind of long because
I just printed out iris.
It's printing out the entire thing.
So it has all these different names.
So iris is a collection
of different flowers.
In this case, It's telling
you the species of it,
all these different widths and
lengths of the sepal and the petal.
>> And so normally, if
you want to print iris,
for example, you don't want to have it
do all this because that can take over
your entire console.
So one thing that's really
nice is the head function.
So if you just do head
iris, this will give you
the first five rows, or six I guess.
And then well, you
can just specify here.
So 20-- this will give
you the first 20 rows.
And I actually was kind
of surprised that this
gave me six so let me go ahead
and check iris-- or head, sorry.
And here it will give
you the documentation
of what the value head does.
So it returns the first
or last of an object.
And then I'm going to
look at the defaults.
And then it says the default
method head x and n equals 6L.
So this returns the first six elements.
And similarly if you notice here, I
didn't have to specify n equals 6.
By default it uses six, I guess.
And then, if I want to specify a certain
value, then I can view that as well.
>> So that is some simple commands and
here's another one that's just-- well,
I can-- this is actually
a little more complex,
but this will just take the class
of each column of the iris dataset.
So this will show you what each of these
columns are in terms of their types.
So sepal length is numeric,
sepal width is numeric.
All these values are just numeric
because you can tell from this data
structure these are
all going to numeric.
>> And the Species column
is going to be a factor.
So normally, you would think that
this is like a character string.
But if you just do irisSpecies,
and then I'm going to do head 5,
and this is going to print
out the first five values.
>> And then notice this levels.
So this is saying-- this is R's way
of having categorical variables.
So instead of just
having character strings,
it has levels specifying
which of these things are.
>> So let's say irisSpecies 1.
So what you want to do here is I'm
subsetting to this Species column.
So this takes the
Species column and then
it indexes to get the first element.
So this should give you setosa.
And it also gives you levels here.
>> So you can also compare
this to the character setosa
and this is not going
to be TRUE because one
is of a different type than the other.
Or I guess it is true because R
is more intelligent than that.
And it looks at this and then
says, maybe this is what you want.
So it's going to say the character
string setosa is the same as this one.
And then similarly, you can
also just grab these like so on.
>> So that is just some sort of
quick commands of the dataset.
So here's some data exploration.
So this is a little more
involved with the data analysis.
And this is taken from some
bootcamp in R for in Berkeley.
>> So library foreign.
So I'm going to load in a
library that's called foreign.
So this is going to give me read.dta
so assume that I have this dataset.
This is stored in the current
working directory of my console.
So let's just see what
the working directory is.
>> So here's my working directory.
And read dot data, this
thing, is saying this file
is located in the data folder of
this current working directory.
And read.dta this isn't
a default command.
I guess I loaded it in already.
IEI assumed I loaded this in already.
>> But so read.dta is not going
to be a default command.
And that's why you're going to have
to load in this library package--
this package called foreign.
And if you don't have
the package, I think
foreign is one of the built-in ones.
Otherwise, you can also
do install.packages
and this will install the package.
And this will give you R. Uh, no.
And then I'm just going to stop
this because I already have it.
>> But what's really nice about R
is that the package management
system is very elegant.
Because it will store everything
really nicely for you.
So in this case, it's going to store
it in, I believe, this library here.
>> So anytime you want to
install new packages,
it's just as simple as
doing install.packages
and R will manage all
the packages for you.
So you don't have to do something in
Python, where you have external package
managers like paper
Anaconda where you're
doing-- you install the
packages outside of Python
and then you try to run them yourself.
So this is really nice way.
>> And install.packages requires internet.
It takes it from a server
and the repository that
collects all the
packages is called CRAN.
And you can specify which sort of mirror
you want to download the packages from.
>> So here I am taking this dataset.
I'm reading it in using this function.
So let me go ahead and do that.
>> So let's assume that
you have this dataset
and you have absolutely
no idea what it is.
And this actually comes up
fairly often in the industry
where you just have these
tons and tons of messy things
and they're incredibly unlabeled.
So here I have this
dataset and I don't know
what it is so I'm just
showing to check it out.
>> So I'm going to do head first.
So I check the first six
columns of what this dataset is.
So this is state, pres04, and then
all these different sort of columns.
And what's interesting
here, I guess, is that you
would assume that this looks
like some sort of election.
And I guess just from
looking at the file
name this is some sort of collection
of data about candidates or voters
who voted for specific presidents
or president candidates
for the 2004 election.
>> So here is values 1, 2
so one way of storing
the president candidates
are their names.
In this case, it looks like
they're just integer values.
So 2004, it was Bush
versus Kerry I believe.
And now, let's say you just don't know
whether 1 corresponds to Bush or 2
corresponds to Kerry or and
so on and so forth, right?
>> And this is, just to me,
a fairly common problem.
So what can you do in this case?
So let's check all these other things.
>> state, I'm assuming this
comes from different states.
partyid, income.
Let's look at partyid.
So maybe one thing you can do is
look at each of the observations
that have a partyid of Republican
or Democrat or something.
So let's just look at what partyid is.
>> So I'm going to take
dat and then I'm going
to do this dollar sign
operator that I did previously
and this is going to
subset to that column.
And then I'm going to head this in
20, just to see what this looks like.
>> So this is just a bunch of NAs.
So in other words, you have
missing data about these guys.
But you also notice this
dat partyid is a factor
so this gives you different categories.
So in other words, partyid can take
Democrat, Republican, Independent,
or something else.
>> So let's go ahead and let's
see which of these is-- oh, OK.
So I'm going to subset
to partyid and then
look at which ones are
Democrat, for example.
This is going to give you a Boolean,
a huge Boolean of TRUEs and FALSEs.
>> And now, let's say I want
to subset to these guys.
So this is going to take my dat and
subset to whichever observations
have partyid equals equals Democrat.
And this is quite long because
there's so many of them.
So now, I'm going to head this in 20.
>> And as you notice, equals equals
is interesting in that you're
already-- you're also including the NAs.
So in this case, you still can't get
any information because now you have NAs
and you just want to see which of the
observation correspond to Democrat
and not these missing values themselves.
So how would you get rid of these NAs?
>> So here I'm just using the up key on my
cursor and then saying moving around.
And then here I'm just going
to say is.na datpartyid.
So this and and will take
two different Boolean vectors
and say it's going to be
TRUE and FALSE for example.
So it's going to do this component-wise.
So here I'm saying take
the data frame, subset
to the ones that correspond to Democrat,
and remove any of them that are not NA.
>> So this will-- should
give you something.
Let's see is.na.
Let's try is.na datpartyid.
And this should give you--
sorry-- just a Boolean vector.
And then, because it's so long,
I'm going to subset to 20.
OK.
So this should work.
>> And this one will also be TRUEs.
Ah, so my error here is that I'm-- I
use C++ and R interchangeably so I make
this mistake all the time.
The and operator is
actually the one you want.
You don't want to use two
ampersands, just a single one.
OK.
>> So let's see.
So we subsetted to the
partyid where they're Democrat
and they're not missing values.
And now let's look at
which ones they voted for.
So it seems like most
of them voted for 1.
So I'm going to go ahead
and say that is Kerry.
>> And similarly, you can
also go to Republican
and hopefully, this should give you 2.
It's just a bunch of different columns.
And indeed, it's 2.
So partyid all Republican,
most of them are voting for 2.
>> So it seems like, just
by looking at this,
Republican is going to be
a very-- or the partyid
is going to be a very
big factor in determining
which candidate they're
going to vote for.
And this is obviously true in general.
And this matches your
intuition, of course.
So it seems like I'm
running out of time so
let me just should go ahead
and show some quick images.
So here's something that's slightly
more complicated with visualization.
So in this case, this is a very
simple analysis of just checking what
the president of '04 is.
>> So in this case, let's say you
wanted to answer this question.
So suppose we wanted to know the voting
behavior in the 2004 president election
and how that varies by race.
So not only do you want to
see the voting behavior,
but you want to subset of each
race and sort of summarize that.
And you can only tell
by this complex notation
that this is kind of getting hazy.
>> So one of the more advanced R
packages that's also kind of recent
is called dplyr.
So it is this one right here.
And ggg-- ggplot2 is just a nice
way of doing better visualizations
than the built-in one.
>> So I'm going to load
these two libraries.
And then, I'm going to go
ahead and run this command.
You can just treat this as a black box.
>> What's happening is that this pipe
operator is passing in this argument
into here.
So I'm saying group by dat
race and then president 04.
And then, all these other commands
are filtering and then summarizing
where I'm doing count and
then I'm plotting it here.
OK cool.
So let's go ahead and
see what this looks like.
>> So what's happening here is that I
just plotted each of the races and then
which ones they voted for.
And these two different
values correspond to 2 and 1.
If you want to be more
elegant, you can also
just specify that 2 is Kerry-- or
2 is Bush, and then 1 is Kerry.
And you can also have
that in your legend.
>> And you can also split these bar graphs.
Because one thing is
that, if you notice,
this is not very easy to identify
which of these two values are larger.
So one thing you'd want to
do is take this blue area
and just move it over here so you
can compare these two side by side.
And I guess that's something I
don't have time to do right now,
but that's also very easy to do.
You can just look into
the man pages of ggplot.
So you can just do ggplot like
that and read into this man page.
>> So let me just quickly
show you some cool things.
Let's go ahead and go to-- just an
application of machine learning.
So let's say we have these three
packages so I'm going to load these in.
So this just prints out some
information after I loaded in the thing.
So I am saying this read.csv,
this dataset, and now
I'm going to go ahead and look and
see what's inside this dataset.
>> So the first 20 observations.
So I just have X1, X2, and Y. So it
seems like a bunch of these values
are ranging from maybe 20 to 80 or so.
And then similarly for X2 and then
this Y seems to be labels 0 and 1.
>> To verify this, I can
just do summary data X1.
And then similarly for
all these other columns.
So summary is a quick way of
just showing you quick values.
Oh, sorry.
This one should be Y.
>> So in this case, gives the
quantiles, medians, maxes as well.
In this case, dataY, you can see
that it's just going to be 0 and 1.
Also the mean is saying
0.6, just means that it
seems like I have more 1s than 0s.
>> So let me go ahead and show
you what this looks like.
So I'm just going to plot this.
Let's see how to clear this.
Oh OK.
OK.
>> So this is what it looks like.
So it seems like yellows I specified
as 0, and then red I specified as 1s.
So here it looks like
label points and it
seems like you just wanted some
sort of clustering on this.
>> And let me just go ahead and show
you some of these built-in functions.
So here is lm.
So this is just trying
to fit a line to this.
So what is the best way
that I can fit a line such
that it will best separate
this sort of clustering.
And ideally, you can just see
that I just run all these commands
and then, I'm going
ahead and add the line.
>> So this seems like the best guess.
It's taking the best one that minimizes
the error in trying to fit this line.
Obviously, this looks kind of
good, but it's not the best.
And linear models, in
general, are going to be
really great for theory and just sort
of building fundamentals of machine
learning.
But in practice, you're going to
want to do something more general.
>> So you can just try running
something called a neural network.
These things are
increasingly more common.
And they just work fantastically
for large datasets.
So in this case, we only have--
let's see-- we have nrow.
So nrow is just saying number of rows.
So in this case, I
have 100 observations.
>> So let me go ahead and
make a neural network.
So this is really nice
because I can just say nnet
and then I'm regressing Y.
So the Y is that column.
And then regressing it on
the other two variables.
So this is shorter
notation for X1 and X2.
>> So let's go ahead and run this.
Oh, sorry.
I need to run this whole thing.
And this is just printing notation
for how quickly or not quickly it
converged.
So it looks like it did converge.
So let me go ahead and print
out what this looks like.
>> See here's the picture and here is
a contour showing how well it fits.
And this is just-- you can see
this that this is very, very nice.
It could even be
overfitting, but you can also
account for this with other
techniques like cross-validation.
And these are also built into R.
>> And let me just show you
support vector machine.
This is another really common
technique in machine learning.
It is very similar to linear models, but
it uses what's called a kernel method.
And let's see how well that does.
So this one is very similar to how
well a neural network performs,
but it's much more smoother.
And this is based off
of what-- how SVMs work.
>> So this is just a very
quick overview of some
of the built-in functions you can do
and also some of the data exploration.
So let me just go ahead
and go back to the slides.
>> So obviously, this is
not very comprehensive.
And this is really just a teaser
showing you what you can really do in R.
So if you'd just like
to learn more, here
are a bunch of different resources.
>> So if you're fond of textbooks or you're
just fond of reading things online,
then this is a fantastic
one by Hadley Wickham,
who also created all these
really cool packages.
If you're fond of videos, then
Berkeley has an awesome bootcamp
that's several-- that's kind of long.
And it will teach you almost
everything you'd like to know about R.
>> And similarly, there's Codeacademy
and all these other sort
of interactive websites.
They are also getting
common-- more and more common.
So this is very similar to Codeacademy.
And finally, if you just
want Community and help,
these are a bunch of
things you can go to.
Obviously, we still
use mailing lists, just
like almost every other
programming language community.
And #rstats, this is
our community Twitter.
That's actually quite common.
And then useR!
Is just our conference.
>> And then, of course, you can
use all these other Q&A things,
like Stack Overflow,
Google, and then GitHub.
Because most of these packages
and a lot of the community
will be centered around developing
code because it's open source.
And it's just really nice on GitHub.
And finally, you can contact me if
you just have any quick questions.
So you can find me on Twitter here,
my website, and just my email.
So hopefully, that was
something-- just a short teaser
of what R is really capable of doing.
And hopefully, you just
check out these three links
and see what you can do more.
And I guess that's just about it.
Thanks.
>> [APPLAUSE]