DAN ARMENDARIZ: Hello, everyone.
I'm Dan Armendariz, preceptor
in computer science for [? Cs ?]
and today I'm going to be talking
to you about digital photography.
Now, in particular we're going to
do a crash course in just 60 minutes
on a number of topics
in digital photography.
Unfortunately, we have
a packed house here
to sort of like choose
your own adventure,
and we will try to get
through as much as possible.
>> So without further
delay-- unless you happen
to be hiding under a rock--
humanity has for the very first time
put a lander on a comet,
which is a pretty cool thing.
Phi-lay or Phil-y or some
way of actually pronouncing
this-- I've heard it
pronounced a variety of ways,
but of course this lander
and the associated satellite
that actually brought the
lender to the comet each
have some digital cameras
attached and associated with them.
So this is the view of Philae from
Rosetta's OSIRIS narrow angle camera,
so Rosetta is the machine that actually
brought Philae over to the comet.
>> Philae is the lander itself and as
Philae was its way landing on a comet,
it snapped some photos.
And so there's something interesting
about this that I want to point out,
and first of all, this
is just the lander,
of course, but if you notice surrounding
that there seems to be no stars.
So I added a little bit extra black
just sort of design of the slide,
but the very center, the
very corner of this slide
is in fact original, the original image
that came from Rosetta's OSIRIS camera.
So just sort of give
that some consideration--
why, if this is in fact
in deep space, is it
the case that there are no
stars in this photograph.
>> So just a couple of other
things to take a look at-- this
was a photo that came back from
Philae, this was yesterday I think,
after it had actually landed.
And unfortunately, it was the case
where the very first that Philae landed
it bounced a couple times, and so
it's not actually the proper position
that they expected, but
still it has this kind
of neat look of the comet itself.
And one of things that's really neat
about this is that you realize that
Rosetta has been travelling for
about 10 years through space,
so this means that the digital camera
technology that's contained within
Philae and Rosetta is
least 10 years old,
but if you go back through the records
there's actually a scientific paper
that was published back in 1998
that talked about the specifics
of the specifications of the
cameras on each of these satellites.
>> And this is 1988,
that's a long time ago.
Do you have any idea what kind
of digital camera technology
was available back then?
There happen to be a digital
camera called the Canon EOS d2000
and it was really the
first digital camera
that came out that people considered to
be serious and usable digital cameras,
so was it the case
that back in 1998 when
there were creating the
specifications that they simply
duct taped one of these Canon
EOS d2000s to this lander?
Well, of course not.
>> This is meant to be a
scientific instrument
and so there's a lot of detail
that actually went into this,
but just to give you some context,
this top of the line d2000 camera
had two megapixel sensor and could take
photos at about 3.5 frames per second.
So two megapixels is
pretty abysmal, if you
have a modern smartphone such as
an iPhone or Android phone it might
be that the camera on
the front of your device
actually has one or two megapixels,
about the same number of pixels
as the Rosetta camera itself--
that's sort of the high quality one.
The Philae lander
actually has other cameras
that are only one megapixels each.
I think there's an array
of six for panoramas
and then there's another
for some scientific studies
and so basically the photo
that we were just looking at
was taken essentially with
a one megapixel camera.
>> Now of course, this is kind
of not a very fair comparison,
because when we're talking
about the scientific aspect
of digital photography then there's
a lot to of additional work that
has to go into making sure that
it's actually going to be correct
and that they can actually get
some usable data out of this.
And there's some interesting
things about the Rosetta camera
that we can actually learn from the
paper that was published back in '98.
In particular, it had a four megapixel
camera, which was pretty impressive.
It actually had a very
large sensor size--
we'll talk more about sensor size.
That was pretty well equivalent
to a standard 35 millimeter frame.
We'll talk more about that in
just a little bit, hopefully
if we actually get to it.
>> And the maximum shutter
speed, so in other words,
the maximum amount of time that, rather
than the fastest amount of time that
the sensor was actually able to
capture data and to capture the lights
for the exposure was
one 1/100 of a second,
which is frankly pretty abysmal compared
to this digital camera that actually
that came out in 1998, which operated
about 1/4,000 or maybe 1/8,000
of a second.
So let's take a look at
another image from space.
>> This came out of JAXA, which
is Japan's space agency
and this is a picture of they released
a satellite that went around the moon
and took some photographs, and
this was I believe a moon rise that
came over that, and
it's a fantastic image,
but again you have to
wonder what is going on.
Why are there no stars in this scene?
So realize that we we're talking
about digital photography, one
of the most important aspects of
it is to consider the exposure.
And of course, exposure is
not something that we actually
deal with solely in
digital photography, this
applies to film photography
as well and also videography
and a variety of other fields where
we're actually capturing images,
but there's really four major
things that impact the exposure.
>> One of the most important things
is the amount of available light.
Now sometimes you can control
this, if you're in a studio,
for example, or in this room we
can control the amount of light
by turning some lights on,
turning the lights off,
but in the case of the
satellites they really
don't have any control over this.
It is the amount of sunlight
that exist in the sky
or rather in space that reflects
off of each of these objects
and can be collected by this sensor.
So the amount available
light, we may or may not
have control over depending
on the circumstance,
but notice that we also
have three other settings
as well-- shutter speed, ISO, an
aperture through which any camera
actually uses to manipulate to try to
capture the amount of available light
that exist in the environment.
So another way to think
about this is that you
have a sensor in a digital camera, it
can collect a certain amount of light,
there's a range of amount of light
that it can actually collect,
too little light and it won't
register, so it'll look totally dark.
Too much light and it will
actually overwhelm the sensor
and it will look totally white.
So we have these settings
to try to compensate
for the amount available
light that exists in the scene
and fit that amount of light
in the scene to the range
that our sensor can actually capture.
>> So let's take a step back and
talk a little bit about light.
So you might recall from
high school physics,
light is of course is photons that has
properties of both the wave and matter,
and because of its
properties of a wave it
operates in various wavelengths
and we as humans can only
interpret and understand
and receive through our eyes
a small spectrum of the
electromagnetic spectrum, which
represents the color
that we're able to see.
Now, it's interesting to note
of course that our visual system
is a rather complex system that is made
up of a wide variety of parts, not only
just our eyes, but even all of
the sub parts within the eyes,
including the lens,
the iris and the retina
in the very back with all the
cells associated with that,
but also the pathway to the brain
and the visual cortex itself.
>> And this can lead to some very
interesting phenomenon that actually
impact us as photographers,
and perhaps more
correctly impact the design of
cameras and digital cameras.
So this you may or may
not have seen if you've
been trolling around on the
internet for long enough.
It's just an optical
illusion where there
are two tiles that are labeled-- tile A
at the top of this illusion and tile B
at the center, and it
just so happens that they
are in fact exactly the same color.
So even if you know this
fact, you look at it
and it still doesn't look quite right.
This is in fact a very
strong visual perception
that our brain is playing on us.
Just to try to prove
this to you a little bit,
>> I'm going to bring up the
same image in Photoshop
and I'm going to bring up the eyedropper
tool, select the color in the A tile,
and I'm going to draw a little
color bridge between A and B
and hopefully now you can
sort of see what is going on,
or you can at least convince
yourself that this color is
in fact the same in these two tiles.
So let me digress a little bit, because
I really am showing you this just
to make clear the fact that we have a
visual system that complicates matters.
Our eyes do not operate scientifically
like the Philae lander would
and like a digital
camera would, and this
causes some problems that actually
impact us as digital photographers.
So if we take a look at
the structure of the eye
we don't have to really
worry about too much of it,
but there is of course the iris
and the lens that actually focuses
the light into the back of
the eye, which has the retina.
The retina has a variety of cells,
and in the very center of our vision
there exists a structure
called the fovea where
we have a very high concentration
of detail cells that
allow us to see color vision
and a variety of other things.
Now the retina is made up of
a variety of types of cells.
There's two major types that
we're really concerned with.
There's rods and cones,
and each of these
have different properties,
so the rods for example
are primarily associated
with night vision,
whereas cones give us our day vision.
What this means is that rod cells
are more sensitive to light.
They're the ones that
are activated and that
are in use when you're outside in
the middle of the night, for example.
And cones tend to be in use when
you have high detailed vision
or when you're actually in daylight.
So just like we were saying,
rods have more light sensitivity,
cones have less.
In the fovea, which was that
structure that I mentioned
that's in the very middle of the retina
in the center of your field of view
you have a high concentration of
cones and a low concentration of rods.
In fact, the relative presence of
rods overall in your entire retina
is very high.
You have far more rods than you have
cones, which is pretty interesting
and sort of eludes a little bit to the
fact that the greatest amount of detail
that we have and the
greatest amount of day vision
that we have is in the
very center of our vision.
>> When we go outside at night if you've
been to a planetarium for example,
you might have heard
the host actually say
that when you want to look
at something up in the sky
actually look at it in
the corner of your eye.
The reason for that is you have
more rods in your periphery
than you do in the
center, and this means
that you can perhaps see that
detail a little bit better
with that more sensitive cell.
>> Now, the primary stimulus
for cones is trichomatic,
that means that the cones are
really the ones that provide to us
our color vision, so among other
reasons this in combination
is why in broad daylight we can
actually perceive far more colors
than we can in the middle of the night.
You might have noticed if you go
outside in the middle of the night
the colors don't seem to be as bright.
One of the reasons for
that is that the cones
are the ones that provide
to us our color vision,
and the cones are what
become inactive at night.
>> Now similarly, rods
actually detect motion
and this is another reason why
it's very useful in the periphery
and why we can detect motion more in
the periphery than when we're actually
looking directly at something.
Now, the reason that we are able to
actually have trichromatic vision out
of these cones cells is because
we have different types of cones
that respond to different wavelengths
of light, and it's not an exact science.
We don't say that one
specific type of cone cell
responds precisely to some
specific wavelengths of light,
know there's a response curve
that's associated with these.
And that implies that some of them
there's some overlap in this element,
so we might actually have
sort of a non-linear stimulus
to various types of colors.
>> And in fact, this is precisely what
happens, if we take a look at this
we have three different types of
cells-- The s-type cell, which
is for short wavelengths, the
MDL types, which are absolutely
the most prevalent types
of cones within our eye,
and you notice that those are
very high up in this spectrum,
much closer to the green spectrum.
And this actually is
very, very important to us
as digital photographers and in
the construction of digital cameras
because this is one of the primary
reasons why-- well, there's
a lot of things that this
impacts and hopefully we'll
get a chance to get to them.
But the result of this
is that we actually
respond better to green wavelengths
than we do to red or to blue,
and in fact our response curve
is very different for that.
>> And if you sort of close
your eyes for just a minute
and imagine that you have three
similar rooms that are all
totally dark except in the very
center there is a light bulb.
And in one room, you
have a green light bulb,
in one room you have a red light bulb,
in another you have a blue light bulb,
and that's all you have in
this room for illumination.
And if you imagine the relative
brightness of these rooms based
purely on this single light
source, try to imagine
which one might feel brighter,
and the correct answer is green.
Generally what happens is that because
we respond, because our cone cells are
stimulated much more by the green
wavelengths than by any others,
we respond much more to that
light, and so that is actually
very important for our perception
of brightness and luminous,
as opposed to some of
these other colors.
>> Now, if we take a look again at
this, the eye structure that we had,
we had course light that comes in
on the left side of this diagram
through the iris, focused by the lens
and onto this so-called "censor,"
our retina at the very back of
the eye, and this is very similar
to the structure of a digital
camera as well in some ways.
We have a lens, which is actually
used the focus the light.
And that light is then
focused onto the very back
of the camera, which has the sensor.
>> Now this is a diagram of a digital
SLR-- a single lens reflex camera, which
for those of you that
are unfamiliar are sort
of the more professional looking ones.
They're the ones that
allow you to change lenses,
they're the ones that have a hump
on the top of the camera where
the prism and the viewfinder is so
you can actually look through it.
The reason that it works
that way that it does
is that the pentaprism actually
reflects the light that
has come in through the
lens and reflected off
a mirror that operates that
sits at a 45 degree angle.
It goes up through the pentaprism
and then out through the viewfinder
where you are able to see the image.
>> When you actually take the exposure,
the mirror moves up and out of the way,
the shutter is opened, and that allows
the light to pass all the way back
through and directly hit the sensor,
which causes the exposure to happen.
So in the typical configuration you
cannot actually see the image through
the viewfinder in a proper digital
SLR, you cannot actually see the image
through the viewfinder and
also capture the image.
If you happen to have
one of these cameras
you might say well I
have a preview mode,
but what that essentially does it
lifts the mirror out of the way.
It turns off, essentially disables,
the optical viewfinder and it
uses the screen on the back of
the camera based on the light
that the sensor is receiving.
>> Now there's an important aspect of
light to recognize beyond the fact
that it is made up of wavelengths,
that it is made up of colors, that
as a result of the various
wavelengths, and that
is that the individual
photons that make up the light
have a direct correlation
to the relative brightness,
or to the intensity of that light.
So every time that we
double the number of photons
at any particular wavelength
of that light then
we're essentially
doubling the intensity,
we're doubling the
brightness of that light,
and this has a very important
name in photography.
It's called stops.
So when we're talking about exposure,
we talk about stops in this way.
We generally want to try to manipulate
this is quantized notion of photons
that are actually
entering into our camera
by either having or doubling the
amount of light that is allowed in.
So it's very, very
frequent that you'll see
numbers related to this idea of stops.
So for example, the idea
of exposure compensation,
which we'll talk more
about in just a minute,
operates in this notion of
stops where a single stop
is a doubling or halving
depending on the direction
you're going of the amount of
light that's being entered.
>> Now of course, when we're talking about
a number of stops, so for example,
let's say we're talking about a change
of two stops as opposed to one stop.
This means we are not just doubling
it, but we're doubling it again,
so a changing two stops
results in a four times
difference in the
intensity of the light.
Likewise, a three stop
differences is eight,
four stops is 16, so on and so forth.
>> So even a low number
of stops can represent
a wide variety of different
intensities in light.
And in fact, when we're talking
about daylight versus the brightest
day versus the darkest night we're
really talking about 20 stops perhaps
at the absolute most.
That's probably something
closer to 15 stops or so,
but that'll be important
in just a minute as we
keep talking about exposure.
>> So we talked a little bit about
light and so let's talk about some
of these other exposure
settings that actually
allow us to capture the
light that exists in a scene.
There's shutter speed,
there's ISO and aperture,
and we alluded a little bit
to shutter speed before,
but I do have a video that sort
of shows the anatomy of a camera
and also will illuminate this
idea of the shutter itself.
So I have here this
high speed photo which
I happened to find on the
internet, and what you will see
is this action of actually
capturing an exposure
on this particular digital SLR.
>> So as I'm talking I want you to pay
attention to a couple of things.
First, notice that the mirror
moves up out of the way,
recall that we talked about
this in a digital SLR.
Now notice that the thing that
we're seeing it behind that
is not the raw sensor itself, but
it is in fact a piece of plastic
or Kevlar depending on the
quality of the camera that
operates as the shutter.
It's a mechanical shutter
actually move out of the way
and exposes the sensor underneath.
So let's take a look
at this one more time
so you can sort of watch
the action of the shutter.
The mirror moves up by the
way, notice shutter opens
and then very quickly there is
another curtain that closes behind it.
This is a very typical set up for
digital SLRs with mechanical shutters.
We'll have two curtains that
operates either horizontally
or vertically depending
on the particular camera
and it will move across
the entire plane.
First the first curtain will open,
exposing the sensor underneath,
and the second curtain will close
thereby stopping the exposure.
>> Now there are other types of shutters
as well, and really for our purposes
we don't have to worry about them too
much except for the electronic shutter.
So this is a mechanical
shutter, and you'll typically
find this on digital SLR.
And the whole combination
of these movements,
including the mirror
moving up, out of the way,
the shutter opening, and then the
second curtain closing behind it,
results in that characteristic
click that we hear in cameras.
But for cameras that don't
actually make that physical noise,
such as camera phones and
compact cameras and smart phones
and a variety of others is that
they have an electronic shutter.
An electronic shattered doesn't
operate in the same way,
but rather it starts to read data off
the sensor and then immediately stops,
or rather it allows the sensor to
accumulate the data of the changes
in the voltage caused by
photons hitting the sensor
and then it will actually clear it
once the exposure is actually complete.
>> So this is sort of the most rigid
definition of shutter speed,
but what ultimately this means is that
this is defining how much light we
are actually receiving
on the sensor plane,
and ultimately this means
that we can change the shutter
speed in terms of stops.
We might have the shutter
open for a single second,
for example, and so we would say that
our shutter speed is then one second.
And what that means in the mechanical
terms is that the first curtain opens,
the sensor is then exposed
to light for one second,
and then the second
curtain closes behind it.
>> Then of course, we can
change this by a stop
if we go a stop brighter
this means that we then
have to keep the
shutter open for longer,
so that we can collect more photons.
So a stop brighter would result
in two second shutter speed.
Likewise, a stop darker, which would
mean that we have to have the shutter
open for less amount of time so we would
have half a second of a shutter speed.
We can keep going in either
direction, but if you play around
with the settings on
your camera, you probably
will notice that it seems
to approximately double
or halve depending on the
direction of your tuning.
>> Now, the shutter speed because we
can have it open for some arbitrary
amount of time does have
some impact on our image.
In particular, imagine
what happens if you're
capturing all of the photons
in a particular scene
over a couple of seconds.
You might imagine if there's
some movement within this scene,
so for example there's a ball
that moves across the scene,
or in the case of this
photograph there's
a wave that moves across the scene.
>> I'm capturing the photons
from that entire movement,
so this is causing a
motion blur that becomes
very visible within the photograph
and sometimes this is intentional.
Sometimes you actually want to get
some motion blur so you can smooth out
the motion of the waves,
for example, or perhaps you
want to actually capture
movement of a fast moving
car, you want to actually capture the
movement of fireworks, for example.
By the way, many people love to go
outside and take pictures of fireworks
and have very high, fast shutter
speeds, which just looks abysmal,
because it's just the brief moment of
explosion or a couple of seconds after
and then they're all chimping.
>> Do you know what chimping is?
It's like you take a picture, right, and
then you're hunched over your camera,
and you show your friends
and you're like, " oh,oh,oh."
Chimping, right?
OK.
>> So come back, so you have this
idea of fireworks where it's really
the movements of these fireworks
that's really interesting, so
try experimenting with
your shutter speed
and capturing the movement
using a very long shutter speed,
rather than a very short one.
Of course, this means
that you can get motion
blur due to a wide variety of factors.
It might not just be the object in
this scene that's moving quickly,
as is the case in the fireworks here,
or the other car or the environment
in this photo on the
left, but instead imagine
if you're trying to hold of the
phone or your camera for that long.
No matter how much you
actually brace yourself,
you will have a small amount of
movement that translates to some motion
blur within your camera.
>> So if you're try to
counteract that, you either
have to increase the shutter speed so
that it decreases the amount of time
that the shutters actually open
and thereby freezing that motion,
or you need to stabilize
the camera in some way.
In which, case you might
want to use a tripod
or to set the camera down on some stable
table or something along those lines
to actually freeze
that particular motion.
So this is an artistic
question that you have
to ask yourself is in which direction
do I actually want to take this,
do I want to try to capture the motion
by having this intentional motion blur,
or do I want to freeze
the motion, and sometimes
freezing the motion is precisely what
you want, in the example of sports
photography for example.
>> You really want to capture that precise
moment that something is happening,
or perhaps rather than get this smooth
motion of the entirety of some ways
you really want to capture
the sort of instant moment
that a wave crashes or
breaks against the rock
and you want to capture that moment.
You certainly will want to capture this.
By the way, this is what it looks like,
my camera got soaked, I got soaked,
it was totally fine.
Don't worry about it,
a lot of cameras are
a lot stronger than you would imagine.
The buttons on the camera
were a little gritty
from the sand stuff--
ended up being fine.
>> Now sometimes you actually want to mix
both motion and still in one camera.
So imagine what happens if
you have a moving object
and you pan your camera with that object
keeping some part of that object still
totally still relative to
some portion on your sensor,
if you're able to have a long shutter
speed that actually captures movement
of the environment but you keep
that one part of the object
still relative to some portion on
your sensor you can mix both and get
a sort of neat effect where you are
able to get something in sharp focus
and without any motion
blur, but sort of blur
everything else in the environment.
And sometimes this is actually
what you want also for sports,
sometimes you do you want to convey
this motion of the motion itself
or the idea of speed.
So for example, in a
car race you might not
want to totally freeze the
motion of the car and the wheels,
because then it will look
like it's not going anywhere.
It's just standing on
the track, providing
some of that can actually give
some amount of drama to the scene.
So let's take a step back from
the shutter speed a little bit
and talk about some of these
other settings as well.
One of them is ISO, and
you might have heard
of the term in the
context of sensitivity,
but that's not really an accurate
way of thinking about it, at least
in terms of digital cameras.
We're not actually changing
the sensitivity of the camera,
there's actually some other
electronic trickery that's
happening underneath the hood,
but for our purposes for now,
thinking of it as
sensitivity is an OK way
to think about it, especially
In terms of exposure value.
>> So ISO starts generally
at a round value of 100.
It's just sort of an
arbitrary value, and if we
are to think of it in our
simplified terms as sensitivity,
increasing the ISO means that
the sensor become slightly more
sensitive to light,
which would then allow
us to change the shutter
speed to be faster.
So, in other words because we're
trying to get the amount of light
in our scene to match the
specific range of our camera
we have to play with these
settings, so these two settings
that we've mentioned and also aperture
that we'll talk about in just a moment,
in order to really get that precise
range of photons within our sensor.
So one of the ways that we're able
to do this one, and one of the ways
that we're able to
alter our shutter speed
is to also change the
ISO for a given scene.
So by increasing the ISO we
increase the so-called sensitivity,
which allows us to make
the shutter speed faster,
or likewise perhaps we actually want
to make the shutter speed longer.
Perhaps we actually
want to have a lower ISO
and increase the time that the
shutter is open to capture our motion
or to capture that motion blur
for some artistic purpose.
>> Now the downside to ISO of
course, is that we actually
get a fair amount of noise as a result.
And these are some examples
from relatively old cameras,
but generally this shows an
interesting general trend
that larger cameras tend to do slightly
better in combating issues of noise.
And it's not really the case
that larger cameras are doing it,
there's a lot of factors that play
into this-- the age of the sensor
is one important distinction,
but also the size of the pixel,
so it's not really the
size of the camera,
but the size of the pixels itself can
make a huge difference because larger
pixels can capture more light,
there's more area through which you
can actually capture more photons.
And also the electronics
are a little bit bigger
and they cant hold
more voltage, perhaps,
and be able to give us a
better signal to noise ratio.
So there's a variety of reasons why,
but generally speaking, bigger sensors
or bigger pixels more specifically
allow us to get better quality out
of our higher ISO settings.
If you're really struggling with getting
a lot of noise out of your images,
perhaps you are using, for
example, a smartphone that
has a sensor that's really,
really small and because it
has a very high megapixel
count, the pixels also
have to be very small, which results in
a relatively noisy image at high ISOs.
>> So one of things that we've noticed is
that ISO noise improvements has just
been enormous, especially
in recent years.
The sensors essentially a technology
very similar to that of our computers
and over time it's
really, really improved,
and nowadays the noise that we see
in digital cameras really greatly
exceeds the noise capabilities of film.
So in other words, the digital
cameras with digital cameras
we can take images that are far
less grainy, far cleaner than film,
and this is maybe good or bad
depending on how you look at it.
Sometimes you like having that
additional texture for that,
but you can of course add
that later in software.
>> So let's take these two into
combination in these two ideas
and combine them to realize how we
can alter one to impact the other.
So in the context of
ISO and shutter speed,
imagine that I'm taking
this photograph, which
I did many years ago back
in 2007 in New Hampshire.
I was on a dock at the
edge of Lake Winnipesaukee
and there was some cool stars
whose trails I wanted to capture.
So I set my camera
outside, changed the modes
so that I could have several
minutes worth of exposure time,
and just waited outside in the cold
for 15 minutes and got this picture.
>> And so there's a variety of stars
here, it's an OK photograph,
but at the very center I've
highlighted one particular star, which
I think I asked an astronomer friend
and they said it was big at the time.
One of the interesting
things to notice is
that you can of course see the
Earth's rotation in the star trails,
but notice that the
radius of the circle seems
to get smaller as you get
to the upper right portion.
That's because I was pointing
the camera towards the north,
and this appeared just of
the slide just little bit
was the North star through
which the Earth was rotating.
OK.
So anyway, we have this star
that I want to point out.
Vega, it has a specific
length, and realized
that if I wanted to make the
star trail longer the thing
that I would need to do is
to change the shutter speed.
I would have to have the shutter
open for a longer amount of time,
but the amount of light
in this scene is fixed,
I can't actually change the shutter
speed without changing something
else so that the amount of
light that enters into my camera
continues to be correct, and I continue
to get a properly exposed photograph.
>> So I can of course
change the sensitivity,
and if you're able to look at this
relatively small text below each
of these images you'll
see the change that
happened is that I changed the ISO by
one stop, so changing it from ISO 800
to ISO 400, which then allowed
me to increase the shutter
speed approximately by a value of 2.
And that is how we were
able to get precisely
this star trail that was twice as long.
>> All right, so then let's talk
about this third idea of aperture.
Now aperture, unlike
shutter speed and ISO,
doesn't have a very
nice doubling or halving
to represent a single
stop change in exposure.
The reason for that is that
aperture or f-number is really
a ratio of some things
that are related to a lens.
Now this icon is actually from
the now defunct apple Aperture
software, which is too bad.
It was a fantastic software, but one
of the things that this icon has which
is representative of a lot of
lenses that you have on cameras
is the data on the lower
right of this lens.
You notice that it says 50 millimeters,
which is the focal length of the lens,
and it also has this 1:1.4, I know
it's upside down, but you can read it,
it's 1:1.4 and that is
actually this aperture.
This is actually the f-number, the
maximum possible aperture of this lens.
And this is important
because this tells us
quite a few properties about this
particular lens-- the focal length
tells us how zoomed in or zoomed out it
is, 50 millimeters on a typical camera
is a very stand sort of field of
view, it's not too zoomed out,
it's not too zoomed in,
it's perhaps somewhat
equal to how it would look to
our eye, but there's definitely
some changes in the field of view.
>> Let's take a look now at this aperture.
The ratio here is precisely the
ratio of the focal length divided
by the apertures effective diameter,
so what does this actually mean?
So let's keep in mind this
division for just a minute.
The f-number from this previous
slide was in fact this 1.4 value,
the 1 colon just represents
the fact that this is a ratio,
and the focal length
is this 50 millimeters.
So this is important and we'll be
able to find out why in just a second.
>> So here's an oversimplified view of
a lens, it's a side view of the lens.
On the very far right of this image
we have an imaginary sensor plane.
Notice this symbol here, there's
a vertical line with a circle.
That represents a
sensor plane, and if you
happen to have a digital SLR or
some sort of other advanced camera
take a look on the body of that camera,
you might actually find the symbol
and that represents the plane
through which your sensor actually
exist somewhere within
that camera, but anyway we
can measure the focal length from
the nodal point of the lens, which
in this oversimplified
thing just happens
to be in a single lens element, all
the way to the focal plane itself.
And there's an effective
diameter of that lens.
>> The diameter is the maximum
aperture through which
the photons enter and are
focused on to the sensor.
But imagine what might
happen for just a minute
if we had this amount of
light that was actually
able to enter through our lens,
but we actually restricted this,
so we have some sort of device that
actually reduced the amount of light
on the outside from
coming into this lens--
very similar to the iris in our eyes.
When you go outside,
for example, and it's
bright daylight you might actually
notice that your iris constricts
to let in less light, likewise when
you go inside into a very darkroom,
your iris expands to allow more light.
It's precisely am analogous
situation to what we have here.
>> And so what this actually
means is that the f-number has
some indication of precisely how
much light this lens is actually
able to accumulate through this
diameter and the focal length,
because as we actually
increase the focal length,
the diameter would need to increase
to allow the same amount of photons
to enter into the lens
and fall onto the sensor.
So there's some math that we
can do to actually figure out
precisely what a stop difference
is between the various f-numbers.
So I'll hopefully be
able to post a handout
next to the slides that will
actually show you that math.
>> That goes through this and
takes all this into account,
but you can also sort of
figure it out yourself
through this ratio that
we were just talking about
and imagine that the way that
we are able to restrict light
through this mechanism is to
have different amounts of areas
through which the light is able to flow.
So if we have a circular
lens that has an aperture
that's this large that means that
photons are flowing through that area,
but imagine how this might change
if we actually restrict that area.
So because we're actually talking
about a difference in area
rather than some sort of linear
change, such as shutter speed,
this is actually what causes
the very strange numbers
that we see out of f-numbers.
>> So there's an easy way to
remember the differences
in one stop between
all of the f-numbers.
First remember two numbers-- f1 and f1.2
and double each one to get a subsequent
number.
So for example, you would
double f1, we get f2,
so now the string of aperture values
that we have are f1, f1.4, f2.
Now we take that second
number, 1.4 and double that.
So now we have 2 and 2.8, and we
can continue along in this fashion.
4, 5.6, 8 and so on and so forth.
This breaks down after about
the 32 or something like that,
but it's close enough
approximation for our purposes.
>> So just like shutter speed
and ISO, the aperture
does have an impact on our images,
and one of the biggest impacts
that it actually has
beyond the fact that it's
allowing more or less light depending
on whether we have constricted
our aperture or increased it's size,
the biggest change perhaps that it has
is the amount of background
blur that you might actually
have within your image.
The larger the aperture,
the more background blur
you'll actually have in your image.
So you can reduce the size of the
aperture, thereby letting in lets light
and get more of your
scene in focus, or you
can try to increase the size of the
aperture by decreasing the f-number
and you will get less of
the scene in proper focus.
And this can be an
effective tool as well
if you want to isolate your subject from
the background, for example, or perhaps
you actually have a landscape shot
and you want to do the opposite.
You want to try to get as much
of that as possible in focus,
and so what you might actually do is
then decrease the size of the aperture
by increasing your f-number and
altering the other shutter values,
or the other exposure values as
appropriate to actually capture as much
of your scene and focus
as you might like.
>> So this is the big four.
We talked about the amount of
available light, the shutter speed
that's actually there, ISO, and aperture
and how the amount of available light
is we're sort of at the mercy of the
scene that we happen to be capturing,
unless we happen to have an
indoor setup or some other way
that we can impact that
amount of light, and how
we can use the three values--
shutter speed, ISO, and aperture,
to vary the amount of light
that enters to our sensor
and captures our exposure.
And so there's this
discussion of stops and how
I mentioned earlier on how
there's this distinction.
>> There's about 20 stops
difference perhaps
between the brightest bright day and
the darkest dark night without any moon
shining or anything
like that, and cameras
tend to operate in a dynamic
range, so the possible range
of light that they can actually
capture tends to be much lower.
Perhaps along the lines of about 10
stops, or maybe at a maximum 12 stops,
and we're talking about some
really high end cameras here.
You might recall from our discussion
earlier of the Philae lander
that had some phenomenal
technology-- well,
the Rosetta camera had some phenomenal
technology for the time period, 1998,
and that actually has possible
14 stops of dynamic range.
>> But this really implies
something about this
that if we have some object, such
as the moon or a comet that's
illuminated full on by
sunlight with any atmosphere
especially to reflect some of that
light, then anything in the background
is just going to be so
completely dark that we're not
going to be able to see it.
So this is sort of the primary reason
why a lot of these photographs have
such harsh lighting is that there's
no atmosphere to reflect it and sort
of fill in the gaps in the
crevices of the moon, for example,
or the crevices of the comet, but also
because the stars that are actually
within the night sky are so dark
relative to the ground that's being
illuminated by the sun that they fall
away in exposure and we cannot actually
see them whatsoever.
>> So some terminology here,
there's underexposure,
overexposure, sometimes
there's both, underexposure
is when something's a
little bit too dark,
you actually need to
increase the exposure
to actually get all the details.
Underexposure-- the hallmarks of it
is everything just looks way too dark,
the shadow areas have
absolutely no detail.
This one isn't horrendously
underexposed, but it's pretty bad.
>> Overexposure is the opposite.
You have overexposed
portions of your image
and you've lost detail because it's
simply too bright for your sensor.
You might need to change your exposure
values to compensate for that.
And if you have both, we'll
you're just sort of out of luck.
>> So one way to overcome these
issues, because frequently you
will come into a compromise between
the capabilities of your camera
and the amount that you can
actually vary these three exposure
values and the amount of light that
exists in the scene so one of the best
powers that you have, especially if
you're taking photographs outside
is to just wait a little
while for better light.
Generally midday light is really
harsh, it casts very harsh shadows,
there's less atmosphere to actually
reflect and scatter some of the light
and so it just tends to be
not a very good situation.
If you're able to wait
even just a few hours,
wait until dusk or if you're
able to do so, get up at dawn
and you'll be rewarded
with wonderfully soft light
that has a lot of color--
warm colors and tone
that results from the light passing
through more of the atmosphere.
>> Now very quickly, there's
this concept of metering,
which is what the camera
actually does on our behalf
to alter each of these
three exposure values
and try to capture an appropriate image.
And generally what the camera does
is it tries to take the entire scene
and look at it in the
sort of middle gray.
It tries to figure out what is the
middle tones, the middle brightness
of the scene, and it will try to
expose your photograph for it.
>> And typically there's some
additional fantastic goes into this,
it will divide it into
a variety of zones
and it will try to figure out in
which zone you've actually focused,
and say OK that's probably
a very important zone
and so it will apply some extra
weighting or priority to that zone
and all that stuff is
fine, but this will still
have the problem that even though
you might have some images that
are being exposed to this middle
gray, the scene may not actually
be appropriate for that.
And so unless you're using
the absolute most manual mode
available on your camera, you're
probably relying on your cameras meter
to some degree to try to help
you pick these exposure values.
And this means that
occasionally you need
to do something called
exposure compensation to notify
the camera that the scene
is actually a little bit
different than its assumption.
So in particular, if you have a
scene where there's a lot of snow,
or a lot of white sand as
in the case of this image
or it has a lot of dark areas, it's
a very shadowy, very dark alleyway
or something like that, dark
at night and you actually
need to notify the camera
that it needs to not
expose for the very middle
you can apply some exposure
compensation to overcome this issue.
>> So in this example, the original
exposure that the camera wanted
was on the left.
Notice how it looks sort of dull
gray, it's not precisely what you want
and I would suggest that this is
actually one of the best things
that you can do to
improve your photography
is to pay more attention to the exposure
compensation setting on your camera
because most likely if you are taking a
scene in the snow, which is especially
relevant for those of
us here in Cambridge,
very soon it's going to start
to snow, or if you're outside
and it's dark at night
then you actually have
to apply some exposure compensation.
>> So you apply exposure
compensation in stops
and what you do is you tell the
camera to either increase or decrease
the exposure compensation based
on its assumption of middle gray,
in this case, I know that because
the scene was going to be brighter
than the camera was
expecting it I needed
to actually tell it to increase
the exposure compensation,
so by adding a positive 1 stop of
exposure value of exposure compensation
I told the camera that it's actually
brighter than it was anticipating
and would then take a
properly exposed photograph.
Likewise, we might have a
scene that was too dark.
For example, if you are trying
to take an image of someone who's
wearing a dark coat for example then
it might actually confuse the camera
into making everything
little bit too bright,
you might need to dial in some
negative exposure compensation
to overcome this issue.
>> Now many cameras have a wide
variety of metering modes.
In fact, what you will find is
that the simpler the camera,
the cheaper the camera
the more modes it has
and this is just ridiculous
what they've gone through.
I've seen cameras now of course
there is like a self portrait mode,
but they have a party mode, candlelight
mode, a sunset mode, fireworks mode,
beach mode, snow mode.
I saw one camera that had a beach
mode and the beach two mode,
so I have no idea what the
difference between those two was,
but it doesn't matter.
You don't really need
any of those modes,
because the vast majority of the time
they do nothing special to the camera,
to the settings in the camera, other
than altering these three exposure
values.
So if you just sort of think
about what you might want out
of that particular image, you
could overcome those issues
and use one of the simpler, one
of the more raw metering modes
so that you can actually take photos
with a great deal more control.
So for example, in a
portrait you might actually
want to isolate your subject
from the background, which
would mean decreasing the f-number
or having a very large aperture,
so you get very nice background
blur from them or within that shot,
and so that would be your priority.
And that's precisely what the
portrait modes in these cameras do,
is it tries to make the
apertures as large as possible
and alters the other
settings as a result.
>> OK.
So let's go into a completely different
direction and talk a little bit more
about the digital aspect
of digital cameras
and just talk very quickly
about sensors and some
of the different technologies
and some of the things
that actually impact
us as photographers.
I'd alluded to dynamic range
before and we can think of sensors
as being an array of bucket that
capture light in the form of raindrops.
>> So imagine we set out an
array of buckets outside
and they're going to capture rain, and
we can then measure the amount of rain
in each of those buckets
and that is our image,
so-called, and we can take
this analogy quite far
and it's actually a
relatively good analogy
because it alludes to a number of
things within the digital camera.
Imagine a couple of scenarios.
First of all, imagine what might happen
if we allow rain or photons to actually
fall into our bucket and not
a lot to actually falls there.
Now imagine that we have some
sort of way of measuring this,
if we have some measurement
that's not accurate enough
to measure the small amount of water
that we've actually collected then
it's indistinguishable from
noise, we're not actually
going to be able to measure
that as any sort of signal.
>> And so we'll perhaps guess as
to the value that is actually
appropriate for that
small amount of white.
This alludes to this problem of sensors
that do not collect enough photons
and it's just too dark
and so there's noise
in these dark regions of the image.
Likewise, if we allow too much to
collect into this bucket it might fill
up and actually overflow
and so beyond that point
we have no way of measuring or
knowing how much rain has precisely
fallen within this bucket, we just
know that it's beyond the maximum.
That's precisely what happens in these
buckets as well, or in these pixels
as well, is that once we've
gotten to their maximum of voltage
then it's not actually possible
to get any more detail out of that
and we would get an overexposure.
>> We can actually take this
analogy just a little bit further
if you imagine again
this array of buckets
that are sitting next to each other.
One of these buckets
fills up with water.
You can imagine it might spill
over into neighboring buckets,
and this concept is known as
blooming within a digital camera
and we actually see this in a wide
variety of circumstances where
a very, very bright section of the
scene that is extremely overexposed
will actually bleed some of its data
over to the neighboring pixels as well
and cause those to become
overexposed as well, which
is kind of an interesting phenomenon.
>> Now imagine that we're
actually able to take
a division between the
maximum amount of volume
that we're actually
able to measure here,
our full well capacity,
our full bucket capacity,
divided by the smallest possible signal.
This would be our dynamic
range and one of the ways,
there's variety of ways that we can
improve the dynamic range for a camera
and what this essentially says is the
possible range, this range that we were
alluding to before, that allows us to
specify how much or how little light
we can actually capture with our camera.
So there's a variety of ways
to improve this dynamic range
as you might imagine.
One of them is to have a
bigger bucket-- actually
allow us to capture a fuller signal.
Another way to do this is to
minimize the detectable signal,
to actually decrease the
amount of noise that we get out
of the electronics of
this particular sensor,
and some of the
advancements in recent years
have, in fact, been to
decrease the smallest
detectable signal within
the sensor and then
we are able to improve our
dynamic range and get improvements
within our photographs.
>> Now one of the other really important
things to realize with digital cameras
is that they come in a
variety of sensor sizes
and so there's a wide variety of sizes.
One of the great things
of modern digital cameras
is that we are seeing larger and larger
sensors in smaller and smaller cameras,
but there's a wide variety of
things that this actually impacts,
not the least of which is the way
that focal length will actually
change the field of view depending
on the size of the sensor.
So imagine, just for minutes, and sort
of a teaser for what you should look
into after this seminar
is actually over--
imagine that we have a lens that
because it's circular projects
this circular image on to
some location and imagine
we have a sensor that's relatively
large and captures as much
of this area as possible, in
this case our red sensor here.
>> Now imagine we have a smaller
sensor, this blue sensor that
captures the center
portion of this image.
If you blow both up to be
approximately the same size you'll
notice at the blue sensor
seems to be a crop,
it seems to be this
center portion and it
makes it look like you're
using a larger focal length
lens than you actually are.
So for this reason, as we
shrink the size of sensors
we also have to shrink the size
and the focal length of our lenses
in order to compensate for that
change in the field of view.
And as you might recall from
our discussion about aperture
just a few minutes ago,
this means that we also
have to change the diameter of our
aperture to maintain the same f-number.
>> So we can go on and on to a wide variety
of topics in sensor sizes and all
these things, but this is really
just a teaser for some of the things
that you might actually
start looking into.
When we start talking about
this a little bit more
we start talking about 35
millimeter equivalency.
We might have some sort of
reference size of a digital sensor
that we're able to compare
other sensors to in order
to discuss our focal lengths
in a more meaningful way
and so I certainly suggest that you
start doing your research in that area
if you're interested in
doing that, but for now it
seems like I've run out of time
and we'll have to sign off.
>> So I want to thank you
all very much for viewing.
I'll post the slides that
we have here online and also
that handout that allows you
to understand a little bit
more the mathematics
behind the wacky f-numbers,
and I do encourage you
to take a look at that.
And so thank you very much for
watching and I hope to see you soon.
Oh.
Thank you, thank you.
The illustrious audiences enjoys it.