CHRISTOPHER BARTHOLOMEW: Good afternoon.
Thank you for coming to
the Google Glass-- Breaking
Through the Glass Ceiling
session, or seminar.
This specific seminar isn't really
based upon, like, coding examples.
It's essentially when
I taught this same--
or when I mentored students for CS50
last year on Google Glass projects,
it wasn't the coding that
really, really affected them.
It was the, well, how do I take all
these tools that Google has given me,
and use them to build
a specific application?
We're going go over a couple things.
We're going to go over design patterns.
We're going to go over applications.
We're going to go over exactly how
to take all the knowledge that Google
is going to give to you-- because Google
is extraordinary in the sense of giving
you all the samples you need.
They're going to give you all the
documentation you need to implement it.
But we're going to use
that knowledge that they've
given you to create
Glassware, Glass applications.
So let's get started here.
So a couple things that you should
just keep in the back of your head
whenever you're doing
Google Glass applications.
Because one of things
about Google Glass in
itself is that it's a
controversial piece of technology
that not many folks actually use.
So in the back of your
head, you should always
think about-- the ultimate
success of any wearable technology
depends on the applications
that are available for it.
If there's no good applications for a
specific device, then it's worthless.
>> Another thing is as Glass
developers, the challenge
is to create apps that are
more convenient and innovative
than our own mobile device apps.
And this doesn't actually
mean that you have
to create a whole brand new application.
I mean for example, I can just
simply go, OK Glass, take a picture,
share with.
And then I can just say, share.
OK Glass.
Share.
And I can share it to my circles just
like that on Google+ or something.
>> It's a lot quicker than me going
out here, taking a picture,
and then essentially
doing the same thing.
So it makes it more convenient.
It's an innovative way to do
things a little bit more quicker.
>> Now, another way to think about
a Google Glass application,
or any type of wearable technology
app, is that if you completely
wiped your mobile device,
what would be the first five
applications that you would
actually download, and why?
So just keep those in
the back of your head
when you're going to start designing
a Google Glass application.
>> So what's the agenda?
First thing that we're
going to do is we're
going to basically say, what is Glass?
We're going to talk about the Glass
timeline, basically the thing that
moves across the screen when you
use the controller along the side.
We're going to talk about
design patterns for Glassware.
>> We're going to talk about mirror
API versus the glass developer kit.
I'll throw that around
a lot, essentially,
because the mirror API was the
original application program
interface that was released by Google.
That's cloud based.
Whereas the GDK, the
Glass Development Kit,
was released later down the
road, essentially so that
you can actually use the hardware
capabilities in Google Glass.
We'll go over some professional tips,
and also, essentially, some resources.
>> So instead of explaining
exactly what is Glass overall,
I'm just going to use
the one minute video
that Google has provided
to kind of go over it,
because I think that's essentially the
best way to do it without me giving
Glass to every single person here.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-Here are the basics
of how to use Glass.
This is your touchpad.
It runs from your temple to your ear.
Tap the touchpad to wake up Glass.
You should see the display
above your line of sight.
Adjust it to see everything.
>> The home screen shows a clock.
This is your timeline.
It's a row of cards.
Things to the left are
happening now or coming up,
like the weather, an upcoming
flight, or an event in your calendar.
You can tap on any card to see more.
Swipe down anywhere to
go back to the timeline.
>> Cards to the right of the
home screen are from the past.
For example, messages,
videos, or photos.
Tap on a photo to share it,
and choose one of your friends.
Swipe down to go back to standby.
And have fun exploring.
>> [END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
CHRISTOPHER BARTHOLOMEW:
So that's the generic user
interface for Google Glass.
Essentially, it's a very
simple, timeline-focused UI
that allows the user to use not
only voice commands, but also
this bar along the right-hand
side to swipe really
quickly through different specific
dimensions of the different Glass time
cards.
>> So what's on Glass?
Well, the display is 640 by 360.
The camera in itself is a five megapixel
camera that does 720p video recording.
It has Wi-Fi and Bluetooth on it,
but it does not have cellular.
So in order use Glass
outside of a Wi-Fi network,
you'll have to essentially link
it to your phone using a hotspot.
>> The storage is about 12
gigabytes, and that's not
including the operating system.
It's 16 total essentially.
It has two gigabytes of RAM.
And there's some additional great
pieces of technology that are built in.
You have a gyroscope.
You have an accelerometer.
You have an ambient light
sensing and proximity
sensor, which is used
for, like, blinking.
For example, if I blink, it will take
a picture, which is kind of strange.
But it's one of those pieces that
you can leverage inside of the SDK.
>> And you also have a bone
conduction audio transducer.
So that allows me to really
kind of whisper, OK Glass.
And then it will access to my commands.
So that overall is what Google Glass is.
>> So let's get more into the nitty
gritty of what these time cards are,
and how we can use them
to do different things.
So there are three
types of timeline cards.
There's the static card, which
displays text, HTML, images, and video.
These things can also be used to
invoke these things called a live card,
or immersions.
And we'll talk about
that in a little bit.
>> A live card displays cards that are
important at the current moment--
stuff that's rendered, essentially.
Stopwatch is a good example for this.
>> And an immersion displays what
we call an Android activity that
basically takes over the entire screen.
So the idea here is you're able to
make a lot of good, clean, crisp,
and dynamic applications, whether
it's just a simple HTML CSS
template, whether something
that's going on and active.
This is an image of a game
called Zombies Run, which
is actually pretty fun.
We'll look at that.
And this is a game here that uses the
gyroscope-- I keep saying gyroscope--
yeah, it is gyroscope .
What am I doing?
The gyroscope, so that you can
actually balance things on your head.
>> So let's go more into timeline cards.
Static cards can also contain a bundle
of cards, for example, a photo album.
You could see that denoted by
this little page flap right here.
When you tap into it, you're given
another line of timeline cards.
And there you'll be able to kind of
scroll through using your scroll bar,
and you'll also be able
to share specific cards.
So now that you should be somewhat
familiar with the different types
of timeline cards,
what we're going to do
is we're going to talk
about the design patterns.
And this is probably the thing
that most students get caught up
with when they start diving
into Google Glass development.
>> So there are three design patterns.
The first design pattern
is periodic notifications.
And what that does it uses the mirror
API web services, or Android background
services to push
notifications onto a timeline.
For example, if you sign
up for cnn.com's app,
they would send you a notification when
there's a news event that had occurred.
>> The mirror API can be used to create
any language-- the mirror API can
use any language to create
a web service interaction.
So essentially, like if you are
not very familiar with Java,
which is what the GDK uses, and you're
more interested in PHP for example,
you can write a PHP service and
a Glassware application that
interacts with that,
as opposed to having
to dive deeper into
the Java parts of it.
The Android background services uses
Java per the Glass Development Kit.
>> So what we'll do is we'll switch
over to just an example on the Glass,
if we could.
Sorry for the screen.
It's tilted to the side here,
for people who are inside.
There we go.
Sorry about that.
Takes a little bit to load here.
>> So this is an example of something
that The New York Times would send.
It's a periodic notification that
contains multiple static cards that
has information about it.
So if I click into it-- and
this will load-- there we go.
If I click into it, then
what you'll get here
is you'll get information
about a headline or a story.
You can also attach things to it so
that you can actually read aloud.
And what read aloud does is it
will read it to you in your ear.
You can't really hear
it, but essentially it's
a bone connector that
will read in your head.
This is the best way to put it.
>> So that's what kind of periodic
notifications are about.
There's all different types of them.
If you use Twitter,
Twitter's another app
that kind of gives you an example
of what these periodic notification
apps are.
>> The second design pattern-- and
we'll go and go back to the thing.
The second design pattern
is the ongoing task.
And essentially, this is a card that's
constantly running in the background.
You can leave the card.
You can go do something
else in the timeline.
But essentially, what was happening
is that it's always running.
Something's always going
on, like a real application,
like a stopwatch for example.
>> This can only be implemented
using the Glass Developer Kit.
But you can take full advantage
of all of the Glass hardware.
The Android GDK is Java only.
So if you're familiar
with Java, that's great.
If you're familiar with Android
development specifically,
there's a great seminar, I believe.
I'm not sure what the exact time is.
But there's a seminar
on Android development.
If you are planning to do the
GDK, I recommend going to that one
specifically, because
it's going to overlap
exactly what you're
going to use for Glass.
>> So let's see.
Let's open up another app.
Could we switch over to the thing?
OK Glass.
Start a run.
So this is a game that I use
when I'm bored when I go running,
called Zombies Run.
And essentially what it does is
it tracks-- it's essentially,
you're running from
zombies the entire time.
But it's like if I run-- I know
this is going to be really awkward--
but if I run around here, it
should track or give me a pace.
It should update how far I've
run, or things such as that.
>> So this is like a-- this
app is essentially--
it's taking a second to update
on that side-- annoying.
But essentially, what's going on
here is that this is always running.
And you're interacting with it.
And you can just kind
of do different things.
And so there are many
apps that are like.
And there's apps that you can actually
create that do the same thing.
So that's it.
>> All right.
So the next design
pattern is an immersion.
Immersions will consume the entire
screen and the entire timeline.
So you actually can't just jump out
and go do other things if you want to.
It's like as if you're playing
a game on Glass in itself.
This can only be implemented
using also the GDK.
So once again, the
advantages of using the GDK
is that you basically take full
advantage of all the hardware that's
on Google Glass in itself.
>> So we're going to go up to
one more example on the Glass.
OK Glass.
Play a game of balance.
So this is a game I like to play when
I'm bored at work, just in a meeting.
Hopefully it'll show
up here any second now.
There we go.
All right.
So what it is is I'm
using the JavaScript
to balance these objects on
my head, things like that.
So this is kind of an
immersion application.
Level nine is like impossible.
>> OK, Glass.
There's also interactive game that
you can do, like-- not record a video.
Stop recording.
Why are you recording?
Sorry.
Glass is acting up.
OK, Glass.
Play a game of Clay Shooter.
So this is another one of
those weird interactive games
that you can mess around with.
This uses a lot of components
inside of Google Glass.
Fire.
I'm horrible at this game.
And essentially, you can just use the
word fire to actually go out and fire.
Fire.
Oh, it's never going to happen.
I'm going to miss it every time.
But it kind of gives
you more of an example
of using all the different
components to make these Glass games.
So the next thing you
want to think about here
is invocation methods, a fancy term
for, how do I start my application?
So there are different ways to
leverage different invocation methods.
Different design patterns, for
example the periodic notifications,
those won't use the OK, Glass menu.
So if you're wanting to do something
that had and sent notifications,
say you have an application that reminds
you about something that's happened,
you're not going to be able to
bring that up using the Glass menu.
That's only something
that you'll be able to do
through the Glass GDK in itself.
>> So I've been using these two
terms, mirror API and Glass GDK.
And so I'm going to go into
those a little bit more deeper.
So before the GDK,
mirror was used primarily
as the application interaction.
It uses backend web
services to accomplish
simple tasks, such as timeline
subscriptions, content sharing,
and voice text.
Glassware using the mirror API can
be written in almost any language.
Glassware that only
uses mirror API will not
have the ability to use
voice invocation methods,
nor the hardware goodies such as
the gyroscope and accelerometer.
>> You can create Glassware without
a physical device in hand.
So that is a nice thing.
So if you need to just create
Glassware that you don't really
need the actual device,
you can do that, especially
if it's hard to get an actual Google
Glass, or if you don't have one,
or something of this sort.
It requires knowledge of oAuth2.
And what open authentication
is if you ever
go onto a website that says
sign in with your Facebook,
or sign in with your Google account,
things like that, that's Open Auth.
And that is essentially going to be
used because the mirror API is a cloud
service.
>> As for the GDK, the Glass
Developer Kit is, in essence,
an extension to Android development.
It can only be used with Java.
Developers have full though
to all the native hardware
features, including the
gyroscope and accelerometer.
It's primarily used for
voice invocation abilities,
as you saw-- OK, Glass,
that whole menu thing--
live cards, and immersive applications.
This does require that you
have the device in hand,
because you always have to be constantly
loading the code up to your Glass
to test with.
>> So GDK versus mirror.
The pros are that its straightforward
for Android developers,
beginner or professional.
You've got the ability to
use all the native hardware.
It opens the door for
interactive Glassware,
offline functionality where
you don't need the internet,
and lots of documentation.
So it's well documented.
>> The cons are that it's only
available in one language, Java.
And the integrated development set up
can take actually a pretty long time
to do.
When I say long time, and I mean
like maybe a couple hours to get it
all configured.
There are a lot of
things, too, you'll have
to consider like battery
life and memory usage.
I mean, I was at 100% when
I started this presentation.
And I dropped 20% already.
>> So depending on the apps that you use,
and depending on what your app actually
does, you want to think about, OK, what
can I do with the most minimal battery
life consumption?
So those are the important things when
you start using all those goodies.
>> In terms of the mirror
API, you can pretty much
use almost any language
that has a web framework.
You can't use C, but for example,
you can use PHP, Java, Python, Ruby,
Go, other different languages.
And the cool thing is it just uses
straightforward web architecture.
You make a post request.
It inserts a card.
You make a get request.
It gets cards.
>> The cons is that you do need the
OAuth2 knowledge, i.e. the sign
in with your Google account.
And that can be sometimes
confusing for folks.
I believe that when the seminars
are posted that not only the slides,
but some other materials
are attached to it.
Is that correct?
And I have a big PDF,
like a nine page PDF,
on how to set all that up for people.
And it gives you an idea of
like a database structure
to hold the keys and the tokens.
So I'll hopefully be able to
shed some light on the OAuth
with going into that document
a little bit further.
>> One of the things that is a big con is
that there's no offline functionality.
You do need internet access.
If you can't decide, don't worry.
You can use both.
For example, let's say you create a
game using the immersion via the GDK.
You could also create a
leaderboard that's in the cloud.
Using the mirror API, you can send your
score to your leaderboard web service,
so it can be displayed.
>> So you essentially want to use what's
best for your application type.
Not necessarily-- you don't have
to go to one side or the other.
It's just that one's going to
be-- if you're going to use both,
you might have a need for that.
And it is a lot of work.
But it's definitely worth it
if you can get it through.
>> So I'll give you a quick example of
the mirror API and its capabilities.
So for example, one of
the things that-- this
is the Glass starter project that
comes with the Google samples.
It basically lays out
everything that you
can do with at least the mirror API.
>> Some of the stuff that I had
shown you earlier as well,
for example, the game, the
balance game and those,
those are actually sample
code that Google provides you.
So you see, Google has done
a lot of the work for you.
You just need to basically
figure out exactly how
to put your application
together to better utilize
those tools and those things
that they've given you.
>> This is the sample for the timeline.
But what we can do here is,
the code behind on this,
is you can see exactly how they
insert a message into a timeline,
or insert a picture, or insert
a card with paginated HTML.
Subscriptions-- a subscription is
something that you subscribe to.
For example, I subscribe
to The New York Times.
And so they send my Glass, my
specific Glass, updates periodically.
That's what really the mirror API is.
And on the Glass developer website,
they have all this here for you,
so that you can basically leverage this.
>> So one of the other
things that I wish I had
when I was developing Glass applications
before, and also my students last year,
is this cool thing.
And it's called the
Glassware flow designer.
And the Glassware flow designer
is basically a way for you
to build a Google Glass application,
so that you can actually
see what's going on.
>> So I built this kind of temporary
Google Glass application here.
OK, Glass.
And then I want it to do something.
Launch a CS50 app.
And then it'll say,
welcome to my CS50 app.
And then I can tap, as you can
see here, for more options.
And one, I can either do an automatic
A plus, or I can write my PSET for me.
So there's different things.
If you use the write my PSET option,
it says, warning, not recommended.
Don't want Glass to
write your PSET for you.
>> But essentially, this is a nice tool
that a lot of people have missed.
And it would be great
if you can help lay out
your application in one of these items.
And the cool thing too is that
there's this design review button.
And what this design review
button does, essentially,
is it allows the actual Google
Glass team to review your app
and give you comments on it beforehand.
So a lot of cool features that the Glass
team has done in order to build it,
to make it as easy as possible for
you to actually write Google Glass
applications.
Yeah?
>> SPEAKER 1: Is this only
design, or can you then
translate this-- does this automatically
translate into code that you can use?
CHRISTOPHER BARTHOLOMEW: So the question
was that, is this only for design,
and does it translate into
the actual code for you?
No, it doesn't.
But what it does is it does beat
a giant white board and tons
of white pieces of paper.
So you know exactly once
you apply a specific card,
you know it will apply-- when
you're writing your program,
oh, I want this specific card to
actually launch something else.
And so it lays it out very nicely.
And if you are planning to
do a Google Glass application
and you do one of these, I would submit
one of these as your pre-proposal.
And I'm sure your TF will be really
happy about that, because they'll
be like, oh this is what
your application does.
I know what I'm expecting from it.
Because sometimes, it's
really hard to keep
track of what's going on in a Glass app.
>> Let's go back to this.
Another cool thing is the utilize
of the Glassware playground
to review and create content that
is displaying on your application.
So what that is is a tool where you
can actually design how things look.
So for example, if I want to
make-- waiting for it to load here.
>> If I want to make a
specific template, I can
do that here using
this, essentially a tool
that they've given us,
to really customize
how your actual cards are going to look.
Hello.
This is great.
Thanks, Google.
So you can actually
see how your cards are
going to look when you
start building them
and then you start sending
them over to Google Glass.
>> The next thing is this
PDF handout that I've
created in order-- if you
were going to do notification
services, periodic notifications, or
work with the mirror API as opposed
to the GDK.
And let me get that out for you.
>> Taking a bit to load here, sorry.
Supposed to be already open.
There we go.
>> So for example, if you want to
set up using the mirror API,
I have full detailed instructions
on how to do that-- how
you access the Google's API
console, with what account,
how to create a specific--
enabling the mirror API,
working with open
authentication, and also
how to use the playground that
we just specifically looked at.
So good information here that will
come with the actual slide deck.
>> Otherwise, you can also
do other things here,
and specifically there's the
database structure that I've created,
or that I've done for
you, that you can look at
to see how to build an open
authentication table for users.
So something to also
understand ad keep track of,
especially if you're going to
be working with the mirror API.
There you are.
>> So, a ton of resources.
What I recommend doing is going to
developers.google.com/glass and read,
because there's a lot
of information there,
far too much to go over
the entire seminar.
But there's a lot information, that's
a lot of good information, that kind of
expands more on this, especially
on the code side of things.
I've also added a quick
start guide for the GDK,
so that if you need to
kind of jump into it,
you have the ability to do that as well.
>> I've added-- there's video
right here, Android Tutorials.
There's a YouTube video
that's included, that if you
want to start developing using
the Android operating system,
if you're a beginner, that video
will really help you do that.
Again, the Glass applications
that are using the GDK
are literally just Android applications.
They can port back and forth.
>> Finally I've added a Google
style guide for Java.
If there's anything specifically--
How do I do a-- you know,
what's the best way to do a
for loop, in terms of Google?
That style guide will
help you do those things.
>> And that's it.
So I hope you guys
have enough information
to go forward with jumping into
a Google Glass application.
But definitely visit the resources.
Definitely dive into the different types
of applications that are available,
especially the sample applications.
Look at some of the code
that they provided you.
And honestly, with your
experience in CS50,
it should not be a difficult
thing to break into and get in.
OK?
Thank you.