>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> ERIC OUYANG: Hey, everyone.
Welcome.
This is Building Dynamic
Web Apps with Laravel.
My name is Eric Ouyang.
I am a sophomore studying social studies
with a secondary in computer science,
and I live in Adams
House here at Harvard.
>> So Laravel, at its most core,
is a MVC web app framework.
So like what you guys have
been doing with CS50 Finance,
Laravel is a framework that allows
you to build dynamic web apps.
So you can think of it in some senses
as an extension of the type of stuff
you've been doing in CS50
Finance, but a system that's
a lot more robust, a lot
more elegant in some senses,
and provides a lot of
functionality for you
to build fairly complex
web applications.
So let's go through some
of the key features,
and then we'll dive into an
example of building a blog
application with Laravel.
>> So one of the first things that
differentiates it from MVC type of work
that you've been doing with CS50
is it includes a ORM engine.
So ORM stands for object
relational mapping.
So this allows you to build
a layer of abstraction
between the database
and your controllers.
So unlike in CS50 Finance where
you directly make queries,
the ORM layer allows you to
abstract that away and create
models that are more powerful than
you can directly with SQL queries.
>> Another thing that's really
helpful is inheritable templates.
So you'll notice in CS50 Finance,
you end up rewriting a lot of things,
where places you could potentially
reuse things, you're not able to.
So here in Laravel, you can use what's
known as the blade template engine
to create a master layout.
And from there, you can inherit
so that sub-templates can actually
include elements within
that larger base template.
>> Migration.
So this is a fairly standard features on
most modern web application frameworks.
So this allows you to represent
database schema changes in code.
So without going to say, phpMyAdmin,
you can actually create these migrations
where you represent the database
schema changes in code directly.
And this allows you to-- especially
if you have multiple people working
on the same web application--
track these changes,
say in GitHub, or some other repository.
>> So this is really helpful
and mitigates the need
to, say, pass around a lot of SQL dumps.
And finally, Composer is
something really, really useful
that allows you to use other
people's code to do awesome things.
So Laravel's structured as
several composer packages.
So say if you wanted to bring
in an authentication package
or if you wanted to bring in some
sort of generator script or an admin
interface, you can plug and play
those components with Composer.
>> So let's get started.
Any questions from you
guys before we get started?
No questions?
Cool.
So the first step is
installing Composer.
So Composer allows you to
manage these dependencies,
whether it's the Laravel framework
or some other third party extension.
The first command allows
you to download Composer,
and the second command allows you to
move it into your local bin folder
so that you can run Composer
directly through the terminal.
>> After that, go ahead and
create a new Laravel project.
We're actually going to
use some example code
that I've put together
to create this blog.
But if you're starting from
scratch, you would use this command
up here, composer create-project,
laravel slash laravel, and then
the name of your project.
And that will include
all the distribution code
for starting a new Laravel project.
So for your CS50 final projects, you'll
probably want to use that command.
>> But we're going to start with this.
So once you've done
that, you're going to get
a fairly extensive number
of files in blog50.
So let's just go through
some of these components.
You'll notice at this route
directory, there is an app folder.
Inside the app folder, there's
a couple helpful folders.
Of note to start with
is this config folder.
So this sets up how
your web application is
going to, say, authenticate people or
cash things or connect to the database.
>> And what's really
helpful is that Laravel
allows you to set up different
development environments.
So what we've done here is if
we go under the local folder,
there's a database.php file.
And you'll notice here that we
set up a MySQL connection that
allows individuals to connect
to the MySQL server that's
directly on the CS50 appliance.
And we're connecting to a database
that I set up called Blog50.
>> So let's actually go ahead and
run the working version of this,
just to get a sense of what the
application that we're building
looks like.
So I have a copy of
this Blog50 completed.
So Laravel actually
has built in a server
that you can run directly
from the command line.
So this is similar to the
PSet before when you actually
build your own server in C.
So they have one built in so
that you can run your Laravel apps
directly from the command line.
>> So if we do php artisan serve, this
will launch a development server
on port 8,000.
So if we go to local host
8,000, you'll notice that, hey.
We have our blog up and running.
So Laravel here is generating
the front page of our blog.
Very simple application.
But there's a couple
really nifty features
that it provides underneath the hood.
>> So the blog application's
straightforward.
If we wanted to create a post,
we can click on that button.
We can say, "Hey, everyone.
This is a really fun
seminar," for example.
And write something down here.
Text here.
If we click Submit, you'll
notice that our new blog
post has been added to the
front page of the blog.
If we go back here, you'll notice that
there have been some comments already
on the blog.
So if we scroll down, you'll
notice that Jonathan Tan says
that he was very intrigued by this post.
>> So we'll go into how object
relational mapping allows
you to do these relations in
a fairly seamless way as well.
Cool.
Any questions about functionality
of what we're going to build?
Cool.
So let's start out with actually
creating the database tables.
>> So recall that in CS50 Finance, you
put together a table for the users
as well as for the
stocks in your portfolio.
So as we mentioned earlier,
what we use in Laravel
is something known as migrations.
So if we go back to the
distribution code here,
the first command that is
helpful that Laravel provides you
is this migrate command.
So we can do php artisan migrate:make.
So this allows us to create a migration.
>> And then we'll want
to create a migration
called create_posts_table,
which is going
to be where we're going to
be storing our blog posts.
And you'll notice here that it runs
through some code that actually
generates a file with
a time stamp on it.
So if we go and look at Database,
we'll notice under Migrations
that it's created a
blank file for us which
has boilerplate code with the name
that we specified, create posts table.
>> And it has two functions in it.
Up is what we want to run when the
migration is applied to the database.
And down is what we're going to do
when we want to reverse a migration.
So here let's start out
with writing this migration.
So there's a helpful class
in Laravel called Schema.
>> So we're going to run Schema::create.
And we're going to create
a table called posts.
And here we apply this using a function.
And within here, we're going to actually
specify the contents of our table.
We're going to create a ID,
which is auto-incrementing.
>> In addition, we're going
to create a field that
represents the title of our blog post.
We're also going to create a field
for storing the text of our blog post.
And finally, we're going
to store some timestamps
for when our post was created
and when it was updated.
And for down, it's fairly simple.
All we want to do is drop
the table that we've created.
>> Great.
Any questions?
So now if we go ahead
and-- actually, local host,
let me delete what we had earlier.
Go to Databases.
I'm going to delete what we had earlier.
Drop this and create
a new database Blog50.
So now what the magical
part is here that we
can apply these migrations directly
to the database using the command line
tool.
So if we do php artisan migrate,
you'll notice that, hey.
It's created the migration table,
which we'll take a look at in a bit,
and it's applied this first migration.
>> So we look at Blog50, you'll notice
that it's created two tables for us.
First is this migrations table.
So if we browse this, you'll notice that
this table is fairly straightforward.
It's just said that, hey.
We've applied this migration.
We go back and look at posts.
You'll notice that the structure
is exactly what we had asked it.
We have an auto-incrementing ID.
We have a string for storing
the title, and a text field
for storing the content.
Great.
Cool.
Any questions about migrations
work, how we can apply them?
No?
Cool.
So now we're going to go ahead
and actually create the model.
So we want to create a posts model that
stores an abstraction of the database.
So rather than doing MySQL queries
directly, we're going to create.
So we have to create a
folder in here called models.
And inside here, we're going to
create a file called post.php.
>> Inside this PHP file,
we're going to create
a class post which extends eloquent.
Eloquent is the name of the ORM
engine that Laravel provides.
And in here, we might expect that
you actually need to write some code.
We're going to write some
helper functions later.
But out of the box, this will already
recognize what's in the database
and we can access, say, the text
of our blog post or the title,
and create stuff directly with
pretty much no code whatsoever.
>> So that's one of the magical components.
And wind once this class
is more fully fledged,
we'll include information about what
it's related to, so the comments.
Also create a function
so we can actually
directly get the URL
of a blog post page.
Cool.
Any questions about that?
No.
Cool.
>> So now once we have our model, we
want to create a controller that's
able to interface with these models,
and subsequently the database.
So if we take a look at
BlogController, you'll
notice that there's not
much here right now.
All there is is an index function
that generates the home page,
but without anything
there to display yet.
>> So the first function
that we're going to create
is one that allows us
to create a blog post.
So we're going to declare a
new function called newPost.
And inside here simply, we're going
to set the layout of this page
to be a render version,
if you recall from CS50,
of this template called blog.new, which
we're going to create in a little bit.
>> You'll notice here on line six that
we specified this variable, layout.
And if we take a look
at the Views folder,
there is a Layouts folder, which
includes a very basic HTML file.
And of note, you'll notice
that we have this container
here that yields content.
So inside of our template
what we're going to do
is create what's going to be
substituted directly within this layout.
>> So we said that we want to render
a template called blog.new.
But inside of Blog, there's
not yet this new template.
So we're going to create a
file called new.blade.php.
This tells Laravel that
this PHP file should
be rendered with the
blade template engine.
So this is a fairly
straightforward file.
It's going to be the form by which
we actually add in a blog post.
>> So the magic here from the
inheritance is that, hey.
We want to specify that the
section, the content section
here, which is delineated
by @section and @stop.
So what's in between here is going to
be substituted into the master layout.
And here what we want to do is
very simply create a new HTML file.
Let's just add a quick title.
Add a blog post.
And within it, we're
going to create a form.
>> This form is going to have an action.
And this is going to be something
that we substitute in later,
and we'll see how
routing fits into here.
But we're just going to define for now
that this goes to a URL with the route
from createPost.
And then this is going
to have method post.
Within here, we're going
to have two fields.
Div class="form-group".
>> We're using the Bootstrap CSS library
graciously provided by Twitter.
So we're going to create two of these.
So this first input is
going to be the title.
So input name="title".
Class="formcontrol".
Type="text".
I'm going to add a placeholder="Title".
>> And then the second one is
going to be a text area.
Name="content".
Class="formcontrol".
And placeholder="Write here".
There we go.
Finally, we're going to
add a quick submit button.
Type="submit" class="btn btn-primary".
So these are all
features of Bootstrap so
that this can be laid
out in a way that's
prey to the user,
rather than naked HTML.
>> So we've defined the controller here.
We've defined a very simple view.
But what's missing is
the connective tissue.
So at this point,
Laravel has no idea how
we're going to actually
access this controller.
So this is defined in a
file called routes.php.
And right now, we have one route.
Which is when we go to the
home path for this website,
it's going to render
the index controller.
So here what we need do is implement
a new route for us to create a post.
>> So we use this method
get, which specifies
that when a user tries to
get this page-- specifically
the post slash new page--
what we're going to do
is use the controller called
BlogController new post.
The one that we just created.
And then we're going
to alias it as newPost.
We're going to create another
function in a little bit.
But what's here under
the key "as" is what
we can substitute within
our Blade templates.
So for now, let's
actually also say route.
So we're also going
to create a controller
so that we can create these posts.
So if a user posts to the page post
slash new, what we're going to do
is uses a controller that
we're going to create shortly
called BlogController at createPost.
And we're going to alias
this with as createPost.
Cool.
>> Any questions?
So let's run what we have so far.
So if we do php artisan serve,
we will see lots of errors.
So it looks like we have a
syntax error on routes line 27.
Ah.
Missing a semicolon.
So if we go to 8,000,
you'll see nothing here yet.
So this is the default home page.
>> But if we go to post slash new, hey.
It'll be the form that we just created.
Right now, we haven't
implemented the functionality
of when we press the Submit button.
So if we click on the Submit
button, it's going to run an error.
But we're going to code that
right now, precisely what we
want to do when a user
submits this form.
>> So let's do that.
Go back to the Controllers file.
What we're going to do is
implement this new function
that allows us to create a post.
Declare new function.
Public function createPost.
And this function is going to be a
little bit more sophisticated than what
we had before.
But you'll see here that we're not
going to actually write any SQL.
The ORM, the Eloquent
ORM, is going to allow
us to do this in some
ways a more elegant way.
>> So we're going to create a new post.
And here we're
instantiating a new object
from the model that we just
created, the post model.
And what we're going to do is set the
title attribute of this using something
that we get from the server.
So this is similar to what
we had before in CS50 Finance
where we would do, using the Super
Global Post looking for title.
>> So Laravel provides some sanitation
and whatnot using this helper function.
So we would prefer to use this instead
of this very basic raw form from PHP.
And then what we're going to do is set
the content of it to Input get content.
We're actually going to wrap
this in a helpful function
that PHP provides called nl2br, which
turns new lines, nls, into brs, breaks,
so that we can actually have
different paragraphs within it.
And finally what we're going
to do is save this post.
So we call the function
save on this model.
We're going to save the post.
And finally what we're going to do
is redirect the user specifically
to the route which we're going to
create shortly, alias by viewPost.
And we're going to pass in the arguments
id, being the id of this new post.
>> Great.
So now if we actually go and run this.
We're going to add a new post.
Let's say this is seminar 50.
And say, sure.
Asdl.
Whatever.
Some sort of content.
And Submit it.
And we'll notice that,
hey. routes not defined.
But if we take a look at phpMyAdmin and
look for whether or not our function
did anything.
Look at Blog50 posts.
We'll notice that, hey.
In fact, we did just create that blog
post with the timestamps as specified.
>> So now let's go back and actually create
this other function in our controller,
specifically the viewPost controller.
So public function viewPost.
So here what we'll do, instead
of having empty parentheses,
we'll want to pass in the ID of
the post that we're creating.
And from here what we're going to do
is actually query the database for it.
>> So if we do post,
there's a function called
Find that allows us to query it by ID.
Specifically, actually, we're going to
use an alternate version of this called
Find or Fail, which allows us
to quit out of this function,
throw an exception if the ID
we pass in does not exist.
And then we're going to do something
similar to what we did earlier
where we set the content
of this page to be
the rendered version of this new view
which we're going to create, blog.view.
>> And we're going to pass into
it-- just like in the CS50 render
function-- a dictionary of variables.
The keys of this associative array
become variables within the template.
So we're going to do post post.
So pass indirectly the post that
we've queried from the database. .
Now what we're going to
do is create this view
so that we can actually view
the blog posts that we've built.
>> So we're going to create a
file called view.blade.php.
So inside of this template,
what we're going to do
is put together a simple page that
allows us to display the content.
So we do section, that's before content.
Stop.
And what we're going
to do within here is
write some HTML to display this page.
>> So we're going to wrap it with a fancy
new HTML5 element called Article.
And in here, we're going
to have a header where
we're going to simply have an h1,
which includes the post title.
So here, if we look at this
double curly brace notation,
this will do essentially
PHP echo post title.
So it's a helpful shorthand
that Laravel provides us.
So we're going to use
this notation instead.
>> And here, we're going to also
print out the content of it.
And in here, we're going
to do post content.
And down at the bottom what we're
going to do is create a footer.
And in the footer, we're going to
first display when this was posted.
So this was posted at, created at.
>> And Laravel uses a really nice
date library called Carbon.
So we can actually do something called
difforHumans, which you saw earlier.
When we posted. it'll say,
like, five seconds ago.
So this is a really nice
functionality of Laravel.
And finally, we're going
to close this footer.
>> So now if we go back to
Home Page we're going
to see nothing here yet because
we haven't coded up the home page.
But if we go to post slash one,
we're going to see an exception.
Does anyone know why
we see an exception?
What are we missing?
Any ideas?
So what did we do
earlier for us actually
to define how we get to
particular controllers?
>> SPEAKER 1: The route?
ERIC OUYANG: Yeah.
So we still have to define the route.
So we go back here to routes.php.
You'll notice that we
haven't actually defined
how we're going to get
to this controller.
So now we're going to define this route.
It's fairly straightforward,
similar to what we did earlier.
But what we're going to notice here is
that we're going to have a placeholder.
>> So if we do route.get slash post ID.
So ID now is what's going to
be passed into the controller.
This is going to use the
controller that we just
created, BlogController at viewPost.
And we're going to
alias this as viewPost.
Great.
So now we're going to create this route.
>> So now if we go here
and refresh this page,
we in fact do have our new blog post.
So this is what we created earlier.
Very simple page, but displays the
blog post that we just created.
Cool.
And if we actually go through the whole
process of creating a new blog post,
we'll notice that everything
redirects properly.
If I say, "Hi.
I'm Jonathan Tan."
Say, "This is my blog post."
And Submit it, this will create
this new blog post with ID 2,
which increments from what we had
previously and displays it properly.
Awesome.
>> Any questions?
Yes?
>> SPEAKER 2: Does Laravel handle
sanitization and everything for you?
ERIC OUYANG: Yes.
So when we saw earlier when
we did input colon colon get,
that sanitates any SQL
injections and whatnot
that we might want to perform if
we're a malicious user of the website.
So Laravel handles a lot
of that behind the scenes.
Good question.
>> So let's take a look at the home page.
So if we first go back to the
controller for the home page,
you'll notice that it
doesn't do much here.
You'll notice that we're not
passing into this controller
anything particularly helpful.
It's just this index file.
>> So let's pass into
this something helpful.
And specifically, we're
going to pass in posts.
And Laravel allows us
to do post all, which
will allow us to get all the posts.
Now if we go back to
index.php, you'll see, hey.
Nothing here yet.
But what we want to do here
is actually iterate through,
do a foreach loop over the posts that
allows us to print out the posts.
>> So foreach posts as
post, what we want to do
is print out the content
of the blog post.
But one thing you'll notice is that
we actually wrote most of that code
already, in view.blade.php.
So what we're going to actually do is
use a nice helpful feature of Blade
and factor out this common code.
So we go here.
>> We're going to take this content
right here, and what we're going to do
is create a new folder.
Let's just call it Partials.
And in here, we're going
to create a post.blade.php.
So here, we factored out the way in
which we want to display these posts.
And here what we'll do instead of
actually having that HTML directly,
we're going to use this directive
called include blog.partials.post.
>> And what we're going to do here
is pass in the post of the page.
So now if we go back here, we'll
notice that the functionality is still
the same.
But now we have this
factored out code, this HTML.
So we can use it in Index.
So here, this is very straightforward.
All we do is include
blog.partials.post and array.
And somewhere to
before, we do post post.
>> So now if we go back to the
home page, we'll see that, hey.
We have a list of all the
blog posts that we had before.
We might want to add some "if"
conditions and "else" conditions
so that if we don't have
anything on the blog,
we want to display something helpful.
Like, hey.
There's no content yet on the blog.
And if you guys actually look at
the distribution code on GitHub,
you'll see an example of how we do that.
>> Cool.
Any questions?
Yes.
>> SPEAKER 2: I guess just
a fundamental question.
Back at the route.
ERIC OUYANG: Yeah.
If we take a look at routes.
>> SPEAKER 2: Where does the
uses.blogcontroller at create post,
what does that direct us to?
ERIC OUYANG: Yeah.
Yeah.
>> SPEAKER 2: Or what is that--
ERIC OUYANG: So, take a look, say
for example, this route right here.
The first part is the actual
URL that the user will go to.
And this array here,
associative array, defines
how we want to have the
application act in response to it.
So uses is the controller,
the function that we
want to call when a
user goes to this URL.
So viewPost right here was a
function that we defined inside
of BlogController--
>> SPEAKER 2: I see.
>> ERIC OUYANG: --so that we
can actually render a view,
perform some calculations,
interact with the SQL database.
>> SPEAKER 2: OK.
>> ERIC OUYANG: And then the other
part, "as" is an alias that we use.
So if we notice when
we created the form,
you'll notice that URL::routecreatePost.
So it substitutes in the actual
URL so that we're not hard
coding these in so we can change it
once, say if we wanted to rename.
Instead of post slash
new, we want to do like, p
slash new just to clean
up our URLs a bit.
We would change it in one spot rather
than across all the different files.
>> Cool.
That's good.
So now we have a very
basic blog platform.
We probably want to add in a button so
that we can actually create new posts.
So if we take a look
at the Layout Master,
we have a section called Header Right
that we've just defined up at the top.
So we can add buttons to
the top of the header.
>> So if we go to index.blade.php, actually
do is define what goes inside of here.
So this Header Right section,
what we're going to do
is add in a button to go to the
URL defined by the route new post.
Just to clean it up and make
it pretty and all Bootstrap,
we're going to make
this a default button.
Let's just make it large for fun.
>> And inside it, we could put some text.
But what Bootstrap
provides is glyphicons.
So we can actually add in that
nice pencil that we saw earlier.
Glyphicon.
Glyphicon-pencil.
So this will allow us to put
in an icon instead of text.
Now if we do stop, this
will define this section.
And, hey.
We have a nice button that links us
directly to the add a blog post page.
>> So we have a fairly simple blog.
We can add stuff to it.
But what we generally expect
from blogs is commenting.
So it's really important for us to have,
say, if someone else visits a website
and really likes the post that
they can engage in discussion
with other people who visit the page.
So we're going to go and create a
new database table and a new model
so that we can associate
comments with posts.
>> So the first step, just like before,
is that we need to run a migration.
So like before, we do
php artisan migrate:make.
And we're going to create one
called create_comments_table.
This will create a file
that has our new migration.
And we're going to, like
before, define a new table.
So Schema::create a
table called comments.
This function here.
And inside this table what
we're going to do is first,
like before, assign an ID.
Increments ID.
>> We're going to allow users to associate
their name with a particular comment.
We're going to have some content that
goes along with this, text content.
And here what we're going to
do is something different.
We're going to create an integer
that's called post_id which
is going to signify what post
a particular comment goes with.
>> In addition, we're actually going to
set a foreign key constraint on this.
So MySQL will enforce that.
We're not trying to
assign comment number
5 to post 5,000 if we haven't
had 5,000 posts on it.
So what we do here,
we do foreign post_id
is going to be associated with
the ID field from the table posts.
And we'll actually do something
else helpful, is onDelete.
>> So if we delete some
post from the database,
that we want to cascade the
deletes for comments as well.
Because it's not very helpful
for us to have comments on posts
that don't exist.
And finally, like before, we're
going to set time stamps on this.
And like before, we're going to
have the reverse migration be
dropping the comments table.
>> So now if we go back
to here, we're going
to run this migration, artisan migrate.
And now it's applied this
migration that we just created.
So if we a look at phpMyAdmin,
we do, in fact, now
have a comments table that has the
structure that we just specified.
So like before, we're
going to create a new model
to abstract the SQL table
that we just created.
>> So let's Add a new file.
We're going to call it comment.php.
And this is actually going to be fairly
straightforward with a slight change
from what we had before.
So class Comment extends Eloquent.
And what we're going
to do here is define
a function that is the
relationship with other models.
So we're going to have a post function
here that returns this relationship.
So we're specifying that
this belongs to post,
saying that there is one post
that this comment belongs to.
>> This actually has to be
capital P for the model.
And now just on the other flip
side, we have to say that, hey.
Posts have comments.
So what we're going to do is
define public function comments.
And here is returned
this has many Comment.
So now magically when we have a post,
we can get the attribute comments
and it'll populate it with the
information from the database.
>> So let's actually go through and
add a new feature to our view file
so that we can both display
and create comments.
So we're going to define a new section.
Let's just separate it
with a horizontal rule.
Section id="comments".
What we're going to do
here is, like before,
iterate through all the comments.
So actually how we do this is,
as I mentioned, fairly magical.
>> We do post comments.
And then we can do this for each
loop over each of the comments.
And what we're going to
do is div class comment,
and we're going to actually
print out this comment.
So display that hey,
comment name-- the person
who posted this comment--
says dot dot dot.
We're going to put this in a block
quote, just to make it look nice.
And then comment content block quote.
And foreach.
So now this is going to loop
through all the comments
that is associated
with each of the posts
and display each of those comments.
I'm going to add another section down
here, which allows us to add a comment.
So h3 class.
Put a title here.
Add a comment.
And we're going to define a new form.
>> So like before, we're
going to do form action.
And here, the new action is we're
going to define a new controller that
allows us to respond to post
requests for creating comments.
So URL::route createComment.
I'm going to pass in the parameter here.
The ID of the post that
we're creating comment on.
And then the method of this
form is going to be post.
>> Now we're going to add in
a two fields, form group.
This is going to be an input with the
name "name" and class="form-control",
type="text", and with the
placeholder="Your name."
We're also going to define
another form field, which
is going to be a text
area as we had before.
Just like before, call it content.
Class="form-control."
Placeholder="Write here."
>> And just so that we
can actually submit it,
submit type and class="btn btn-primary."
Close the form.
Close this action.
So now if we refresh this page where
we have, say, a particular post.
We have to reboot the server.
PHP artisan serve.
Reboot this.
We have to define the route.
But for now, let's just take this
out so that we can actually show you
what the page looks like, and then
we'll actually create that route.
So, hey.
We have this new form down here
so that we can create comments.
So let's actually define a
function within the controller
so that we can add comments.
Let's go back.
And within blogcontroller.php,
what we're going to do
is create a new function
called create comment.
>> Public function createComment.
This is going to have a single
parameter, the ID of the posts
that we're commenting on.
And like before, we're
going to first get the post.
So post, findOrfail id.
Afterwards, we're going
to create a new comment.
So comment = new Comment.
Comment name = Input::get name.
Comment content = the same new line
into breaks of Input::get content.
>> And finally, we're going to have to
associate this comment with the post.
So we're going to use
this function, comments,
that allows us to save
this relationship.
So now this comment will have
automatically the post ID.
We could also set it
manually, but this is
more easy to read as far
as the function goes.
And after we perform
this, what we want to do
is redirect the user to the
route specified by viewPost
with the array with the
parameter of the post ID.
>> And now so that this actually
functions, we need to define this route.
Route::post.
And now we're going to call this
post slash ID slash comment.
Array uses the new function
that we just created.
BlogController.
CreateComment as createComment.
Great.
>> So now hopefully if we refresh this page
and add in a comment, say, David Malan.
"Hopefully this works."
Submit.
We do, in fact, have a
comment on this blog post.
Cool.
So now we have a fairly
functional blog post.
We're just going to
add a couple tweaks so
that we have some more useful
information on these posts.
>> So if we go back to the
front page, we have no sense
of how many comments are
on each of these posts.
So what we're actually going
to do is, inside our model,
define a helper function that allows
us to specify the number of comments
that go with a particular post.
So we're going to create
a helper function.
>> Public function.
GetNumCommentsStr.
So a string that specifies the number
of comments that go along with it.
And what we're going to do is say
that num = this comments count.
So we're going to count
the number of comments.
And if this number equals 1, we're
just going to return 1 comment.
And then otherwise, we want to return
the concatenation of num and comments,
so we get the pluralization correct.
Just make this a single quote.
One comment.
>> And now we can use this function
directly inside of our view.
So if we go back to the
partial posts that we created,
now we want to actually
display the number of comments.
So what we can do is
post, use this function
that we just created to
display the number of comments.
So if we now refresh, it
does, in fact, display
the number comments
that go along with it.
>> If we wanted to be fancy if you
actually look at the distribution code,
we can actually link
this to the comments.
If you recall, we defined within the
view that this has section ID comments.
So if we actually wanted to link
directly to the comments section, what
we would do here is a href
URL of the route viewPost.
Pass in the array ID of post ID.
And then we want to go to
specifically the comments section.
>> Here let's close the A tag.
So now if we refresh this
page, we click on this.
We'll go directly to
the comments section.
If we had a longer post, you can
actually see this bounce down.
But you'll notice that it's
not at the top of the page.
Cool.
Great.
So that's a fairly straightforward
example of something simple
that you can do with Laravel.
>> But you can notice here that
we've done a lot of things
with fairly little amount of code.
Laravel allows us to do the
SQL queries behind the scenes.
It does the sanitation
for us behind the scenes.
Allows us to do these relationships
very easily without us needing
to do any SQL join statements to
combine comments with what the posts.
Allows us to do this
inheritance of templates
so that we can define these nesting
files so we're not repeating ourselves,
just like when we had that
display of the blog posts
that we don't have to
copy and paste the code.
>> And from here you can build
increasingly complicated applications.
You can imagine if we
wanted to implement log-in,
we could say, bring in a third party
framework that allows us to do that.
There's a bunch of them
that are really, really
great that can do like,
password recovery.
And it'll send you a
reset password email.
We can implement permission
so that I can create a post,
but someone else can't edit it.
We can implement
functionality to delete posts.
>> But you can see here that we have pretty
much all the rudimentary components
to build some really, really,
dynamic and exciting web apps.
So with that, I think we're good.
Do you guys have any questions?
Yes?
>> SPEAKER 3: How do you
get static content?
>> ERIC OUYANG: Static content.
So you saw before that when we had
this right here, this layout content,
view make, we had this
without this array afterwards.
Blog.index, we had this
as just a static file.
So if we don't pass
anything along to it,
it'll just render the HTML directly.
But if we pass in this associative
array of posts, which is dynamically
pulled from the database, we
can make the page dynamic.
Cool.
Any other questions?
SPEAKER 3: How would you compare
Laravel to maybe some other options?
ERIC OUYANG: Sure.
Yeah.
So Laravel is-- that's
a great question--
one of many options for web frameworks.
So Ruby on Rails is one that's popular.
I believe Twitter used to be
implemented with Ruby on Rails.
I think they've since switched.
There's another one called FuelPHP.
>> So Ruby on Rails uses the Ruby language
and implements a lot of the MVC stuff
that we see here.
FuelPHP is another PHP framework.
Django is one of my favorites.
It's a web framework for Python.
So you can write your web app in Python.
So there's a ton of these options.
>> Laravel, I think, by and
large is my favorite right
now for PHP just because
of the components
that we talked about earlier.
It's Composer enabled.
It includes a really, really
expressive ORM system.
Also has a really awesome templating
language that some of the others
just don't provide.
And migrations.
Migrations are awesome as well.
Cool?
Awesome.
Well, thanks so much for
watching this seminar,
and good luck on your final projects.