[MUSIC PLAYING]
ROGER ZURAWICKI: Hi, my
name is Roger Zurawicki,
and I will be covering
the CS50 Meteor seminar.
Meteor is a new framework
devoted to the new kind of web,
not the PHP making requests
back and forth kind
of web we saw in the PHPP set,
but the more dynamic JavaScript
parts of the web.
Things Meteor can do
includes Live Updating
and immediately communicating
between users of the same website.
>> For this seminar, we have
code hosted at my GitHub.
You can go to this URL and download it.
If you know how to use Git,
you can clone the repository.
If you don't know how to use
Git or have not used GitHub,
that's completely fine.
I will show you really quickly
how we can go to GitHub,
and there's an option to
download a zip right there.
Once you download this directory, you
can get started playing with our code.
>> More information about Meteor
can be found at meteor.com.
In the Seminar folder, I actually
have some Meteor projects we can use.
One of the folders we have in our
seminar project is the todos app.
So if I go into it I,
have Meteor installed.
So to run it, I just need to type
Meteor, and Meteor will install.
As you can see, we have to
make sure we installed Meteor.
So I'm just going to
run it one more time
to make sure that Meteor
is properly installed.
>> While I have Meteor
installing, I can show you
some live demos of Meteor sites
going live right now on the internet.
I have a demo of our app.
You can access it at the following URL.
This is the to do app that we
have in our seminar directory.
The URL for this is
rozu-rabbit.meteor.com.
You'll see that Meteor will actually
host your Meteor projects for free.
And at the end of the seminar,
you'll be able to do this as well.
>> This is a to do list app.
And you can sign in, create
accounts, and add tasks.
You can create an account like so.
And now, once you have an
account, you can add tasks.
For example, one of the tasks I
might need to go pick up my laundry.
And if you're on this
site online, you'll
actually see this task on
your computer in real time.
>> I can show you a quick demo
of this by opening rozu-rabbit
in another tab with the same URL.
And we see that the same data comes up.
We can also run it in
a different browser.
Say I run it in Safari.
That way we're not logged in.
So we have the same Meteor
app, and once it loads,
we'll see the same data
we did in the first one.
As you can see, I'm not logged in here.
And when the audience checks data,
it updates on all the browsers
simultaneously.
This is one of the really
cool features about Meteor.
With almost no work, you
have a live updating app
that changes on all of
your devices at once.
>> If I check the check box here
in my to do list, we will have,
in my other Chrome browser,
the item checked off.
And this happens instantaneously.
All right.
So it looks like Meteor
installation is ready now.
So now let's go back to the
todos app and run this locally.
>> If you have a Meteor project, you can
just run it with the command Meteor.
Once you do this, Meteor
will do some preparation
to make sure all of
your code is in check.
And then it'll tell you that the
project is ready to be served.
You might need to allow your
firewall, if your computer blocks you.
>> So what Meteor is telling me
right now is that at this website
local to my computer, I can see
what this Meteor project is.
Note that right now, my app is
not accessible to the internet.
We'll cover how to bring your Meteor
app to a live site a bit later on.
So I'm just going to copy this
URL now and go into Google Chrome.
>> And this is the to do
list from the example.
You can see they implemented
a few more features here.
We have different tabs, we
have the same account features,
and we can add new lists.
Now, one of the really
cool feature about Meteor
is that not only can this
work on your web browser,
but you can also create
native iPhone and Android
apps through a tool called PhoneGap.
>> So some projects will come
pre-configured for running
on iOS, like this todos app.
So all I need to do to run it in iOS
is type Meteor, run, and then iOS.
And when I do that, Meteor
will prepare the package again.
And then, once it's ready, it'll
load the iOS simulator on my command.
Note you can only run iOS apps
if you have a Mac computer.
You can run your apps on
Android on all platforms.
>> So now you can see that my iPhone
simulator came up on my screen.
And in just a moment,
it'll load with the app.
If we make it just a bit
smaller to fit on the screen,
we see we have our iPhone app.
And just so we don't
get confused, let's make
sure we are on the same
website, the local host 3000.
>> So right here is an example
of the Meteor app I have,
the todos app, running both on
a phone and on a web browser.
And when I change stuff
in the web browser,
it immediately goes to the phone.
And I can delete something on the phone,
and it changes in the web browser.
>> Now, normally to create native
phone app for iOS or Android,
you need to know either Java or
Objective C. The technology Meteor uses
to allow JavaScript to run as
your app is called PhoneGap.
What your app essentially
is is a web browser.
And Meteor handles all
the tricky parts involved
for bringing that web browser to
your iPhone or your Android device.
You can see that the
user interface is smooth,
and it looks and feels very
much like a native app.
Notice that if I go to the home
screen now, I also get an icon.
This isn't a website like
you'd find in Safari.
This is its own app.
You can install and
delete it if you'd like.
>> We can briefly show you what the code
for this kind of todos app looks like.
If you look in the todos folder,
you will see there are many folders.
But over the course
of the seminar, we'll
understand what each folder is used for.
Let's go into the terminal so we
can see the files a bit better.
>> I'm going to press Control
C to stop the server,
and now I'm back in the todos app.
I have different folders here, like
the client folder, the server folder.
And these folders simply mean that
everything in the client folder
gets executed on your web browser.
Everything in a server folder
gets executed on a server.
>> What I want to point
out is that what we had
when we had our phone running and
our web browser, these were clients.
But what's running in a
terminal, that's the server.
We have other folders, like
lib, which is library code,
like your helper
functions, which you can
use on both the client and the server.
And then you have a public
folder and resources
folder necessary for getting
your images and other CSS loaded.
>> If you have Meteor installed, we will
continue with the tutorial for Meteor.
You can go to this URL,
meteor.com/install,
to get the command line that I
showed you that installs Meteor.
We will go through the first
few steps to get a better
feel about how to install Meteor.
>> But first, I think it's important that
we review a little bit of JavaScript.
To show you some examples of how
our C knowledge can be translated
to JavaScript, I've
created a few examples.
They are in the js directory.
So if in the seminars folder you
look, there's a folder called js.
And in here, we have a few examples.
>> Let's open up the first
example and see very quickly.
What we see is your standard
hello world command.
You notice in C that you
have quite a few lines.
And as CS50 students know,
we need a main function,
and we have to include the standard
I/O library in order to call printf.
>> Let's look at how JavaScript compares.
I'm going to open ex1.js.
Commented out is what the
C code would look like,
and the line below is all
you need to run in Node.
You don't need a main function, you
don't need to include any files,
and you don't need to return.
You just call console.log.
This is the equivalent of your printf.
>> And it takes the same
arguments printf would.
And in order to run it,
instead of running make ex1,
you would just call Node ex1.js.
You write Node and then
the file, and it gets run.
It does not get compiled.
JavaScript is a interpreted language.
So it doesn't need to be
compiled before it's run.
If I wanted to run ex1.c,
I have to make it first,
and then I can run the executable
to get the same output.
>> Let's quickly cover some
other JavaScript concepts.
Let's look at example two.
In ex2.js, in ex2.c, we can
see that we have some code.
Let me quickly go to
a better text editor
that will show these
new lines a bit better.
All right.
Here we have example 2.c.
Here we have different types
that we're printing out.
And as we know, printf takes
different percent arguments
to access different pieces of data.
If we want to print
a string, we call %s.
If we want to call a floating
point number, we called %f.
And there's no easy way to call a
Boolean by its true or false value.
But if you use %d, you can get
a 0 or a 1 for false and true.
>> JavaScript is a bit nicer for us.
In JavaScript, let's look at the few
differences we have in this file.
First, you notice that in C we have to
initialize every variable with a type.
S is a char star.
It's a string, and it
cannot be any other type.
N is a float.
B is a Bool.
>> But in JavaScript,
there are dynamic types.
That means that you don't
need to tell JavaScript
what types your variables will be.
You just say var for variable, the name
of the variable, and then its value.
So a var can be anything really.
It can be a string.
It can be a floating point number.
It can be a character.
It can be a Boolean.
And console log works a bit differently.
If you want to print
a number, you call %d.
But most values can be
printed as strings just fine.
>> Let's run this in Node
to see what would happen.
I can call Node ex2.js,
and we get printf
with the values CS50, N as
the floating point number,
and then B as the Boolean
converted to a string true.
What about if we made example 2.c?
Well, we still have some
more annoyances with printf.
Notice that the floating point
number has to be formatted correctly,
and that the Boolean can't simply
be displayed as true or false.
All right.
Now let's look at example three.
In example three, we are showing
how you would use a for loop.
In fact, it's very simple.
One of the nice things about
JavaScript is that it is C based.
That means that a lot of your
code will look very similar
and feel very much the same.
In a for loop, the only thing
that has really changed here
is instead of int i, we have var i.
We can still assign it to value
zero, check that it's less than five,
and increment it by one
with the ++ operator.
We call console.log on i, and that
will print us a number with each line.
Let's run it really quickly
to see what it outputs.
We get a new number in each line.
Another thing I want you
to notice with console.log
is you didn't have to write
backslash n for the new line.
Console.log will print
everything on its own line.
That's a nice feature
that JavaScript gives us.
>> Now let's open up example four.
In example four, first in the C,
we are calling a few functions.
Notice that we have to declare the
functions before we use them in main.
If we had main first and
then add and then high, make,
clang, or GCC would
give us an error saying
that it doesn't know what high is.
It doesn't know what add is.
So in C, you have to be picky about the
order in which you call your functions.
>> Let's look at how you can
do this in JavaScript.
We have different files because there
are a few different ways to do this.
One way is pretty much
a direct translation.
Because functions in C
return types, and JavaScript
doesn't really know or care
about what type you return,
you don't write a type.
Instead, you just need
to write function,
and everything is pretty
much the same as before.
>> When you have a variable, like in
add, we just need to write x and y.
We don't need to say x is an int.
We don't need to say y is an int.
We return with the same syntax.
For high, we declare it with
function instead of void.
Notice that whether
it's void or non-void,
it's still all the same function.
And we simply don't put
anything in parentheses,
and it looks very much like the C code.
And below, we can call it below.
>> If we look at example 4b, we notice
that I've changed a few things.
The only thing I've changed
really though is the order.
We have the same
functions, but now they're
declared after they're used in
console.log and high on lines 18, 19.
If you did this in C,
make would throw an error.
Here, this works just fine.
And I can show this to you by
calling Node on 4b example.
>> Another way we can call functions
is by saving functions as variables.
Like I said, a variable
can have any type.
One of the types a variable
can have is a function.
So if you look at example
4c, what I've changed
here is var add instead of function add.
And now add equals a function.
This function here is anonymous.
It has no name, so it's just
function and then the parentheses.
The syntax after that
doesn't change, but you
do have to keep in mind that
you have a variable that you're
storing the function into add, and a
variable that you're storing into high.
>> Because add and high are now variables
and not functions, something changes.
This is a common bug I see in
a lot of people's JavaScripts,
and something to keep in mind.
When I run this, let's see what happens.
I get an error.
It's saying undefined at this point.
So it's saying it
doesn't know what add is.
>> Because now add is not a
function, add is a variable.
And you haven't actually given
add a value yet when you used it.
That brings us to example 4d, where if
you want to use variables as functions,
you just need to make sure they
get the value before they're used.
>> Let's move on to example five then.
Here, we talk about
structs in C. In C, structs
have this fixed structure to them
because you have to declare them
before you use it, and
you say I have a student,
and every student has exactly
one name, one year, one gender.
It has to have all of them.
It can't have any other values,
and they have to be specific types.
>> Then we can initialize the
struct in this nice syntax
because it knows the order.
So it knows that Roger is a name.
It knows that 2016 is a
year and M is a gender
because we told it this
list is a struct student.
And then you can print
it, accessing s.name.
Let's see how we would
convert that to JavaScript.
Notice that s is now a
variable, and there's no type.
It's just a var again.
Because it doesn't matter if the
type of this variable is a pointer,
it's a struct, or anything else.
We have a slightly different syntax.
This syntax is the object syntax.
>> You might have seen it in JSON.
JSON actually stands for the
JavaScript Object Notation.
This is how you define
objects in JavaScript.
We have a key, which is
the value, like name.
And we give it values on
the other side of the colon.
And one thing to keep in mind is you
don't need to have a name and a year
and a gender for an object.
An object can have no values.
It can have as many as you'd like.
>> We can use these objects in just the
same way we would use a struct, s.name.
We can run it really quickly
by doing node example 5.c.
We can't actually run a C file in Node.
It doesn't know what C is.
It only knows JavaScript.
When we run the ex5.js, we get
the value, which we expected.
>> Let's move on to example six.
Here I just want to talk a little
bit more about JavaScript arrays
because they're a bit
different than what you're
used to in C. Arrays are notated,
not with the brackets like in C,
with the curly braces, but brackets.
You can have an empty array,
like arr in line four.
You can have arrays
with multiple values.
And you access them
just the same way in C.
>> Up to line seven, everything
seems pretty straightforward.
One minor difference is here at line 10.
The way you get a length of an
array is just by calling .length.
An array can actually be
treated like an object,
and this object has a length property
that you call to get the length of it.
Notice that this is different
in C because in C you
have to know the length of
your object ahead of time.
>> So another nice thing about arrays
is that you can have different types.
If you have an array in C, there
are arrays of a specific value,
either a struct pointer
or floats or [INAUDIBLE].
Here, you can have different values.
I first had a floating point number,
then a Boolean, then another integer.
And actually, they can change types too.
Look at line 16.
Array two is changing from being
a number, an integer, to a string.
>> Another nice thing about arrays is here
at line 19, they have infinite size.
You can just say I want the hundredth
element to be the string legit.
And this doesn't seem to make
sense because the array only
has space for three elements,
so the end should be two.
But when you do this, let's
see what array three becomes.
We would run this quickly
with node example six.js.
We get this really long
array, and what happens
is we have the first few elements
and then a bunch of blanks
until we get our string.
JavaScript fills in the
array as it's needed.
>> Let's finally go to our last example.
Here we have a list
of different students.
I want to talk a little
bit about some nice aspects
of for loops in JavaScript.
In C, for loops are kind of limited.
They have a fixed structure, where you
have a variable, you have a condition,
and then you do something
at the end of the loop.
And of course this works in JavaScript,
as we saw in the previous examples.
But we also have nicer ways
of doing this in JavaScript.
This is called a foreach loop.
>> Sorry, let's go back
to example seven here.
We can also say section is a list.
So give me every i or
every index in that list.
Then we can get the student
by just calling section of i.
So all of the code of setting i
equal to zero and making sure i
is less than the length and
adding one to i every time, that's
taking care of you rather
nicely with this foreach loop.
>> Not only do foreach loops
work in lists or arrays,
they also work in objects,
which is also nice.
You can get the name of
every property by just taking
a dictionary or an object, like student,
and then just saying give me every key.
A key would be these
properties, name or house.
So what's going to happen here is that
we print out first the name and then
the house of every student.
>> I can run this in Node
really quickly to show you.
We get first the C style for loop, where
we get every object being printed out.
And then we have the JavaScript
style, where you can just
print out every key
and value individually.
>> All right.
Now that we've covered Node.js, I think
we're ready to get started with Meteor.
Like I said, Meteor did a great job
of writing some ready-made examples
for you that you can explore through
this tutorial or in the seminar folder.
But here I want to
start more from scratch.
>> Let's create a simple to do application.
This is kind of the base of what the to
do application I showed you earlier is.
In this tutorial, you
will see that there's
a command Meteor create to
create a new Meteor project.
You need to call this in order
to run Meteor projects because it
will run the commands
to create the Meteor
files necessary for your project.
>> If you go into the terminal, we can
go into the folder called step one.
And step one will correspond with
the first step in the tutorial.
Notice there are folders, step
one, step two, all the way to five.
And each one is corresponding
to a step in this tutorial.
I'm going to open it
in my text editor here
so we can see a bit of what was created.
We notice that there
are four main parts.
There's a Meteor directory, .meteor.
And that you usually
don't need to touch.
Meteor takes care of
that folder, and it just
makes sure that your
project will work correctly.
>> We also have three files, a HTML file,
a JavaScript file, and a CSS file.
Let's first start with the HTML file.
At first glance, this looks
like a normal HTML document.
But notice that there
are a few differences.
One, this isn't actually
a complete HTML document.
We're missing the HTML tags.
This is normal.
In Meteor, you're not expected
to create these HTML tags.
That's done for you.
You want to begin-- if you
want to create a website,
you just need to start
with the head tag,
define that, and then
define the body tag.
>> But if you notice in this
HTML file, we have a new tag.
We have the template tag.
This is not normal HTML.
This is a special version of HTML
that Meteor makes available to you.
It's called space bars.
You can define templates as little
modules, kind of like helper functions,
in your C or JavaScript code.
This template would
have a name called task.
And you can see right here on line
13 that you can call these templates.
And what Meteor will do is just
fill in these tasks for you.
>> Another thing you might notice is a
bit different is this each function.
Each will take the variable
tasks and kind of go through it
in that foreach loop we
saw in example seven.
This each can take a dictionary
or a list, an object or a list,
and it'll just go through all of the
values like a foreach loop would.
So if we have a bunch of tasks, this
will call the template on each task.
>> Let's run the Meteor project
just to see that this happens.
I run the Meteor project with
just Meteor or Meteor run.
And now Meteor just will need
to quickly prepare the project,
start the database as necessary,
and then post the app locally.
We can go to our web browser now.
And we'll see that we
have a very simple app.
So what we saw showed up was actually
the step one, the step one file.
>> Let's move on to step two only because
I think it will serve the same purpose.
I'm just going to change
to the step two directory
and run Meteor again so we can see
the template we just worked with.
Yes, a question?
>> AUDIENCE: If we're getting permission
denied, is that-- what's it
called for that?
ROGER ZURAWICKI: If
you're running Meteor run,
and you have permission
denied, some of your files
might not have the right permission set.
So you have to check where
the permissions are off.
They could be off in
your Meteor project,
or they could be off in the
Meteor files themselves.
>> AUDIENCE: If I downloaded it just now
from your GitHub, then what should I do
[INAUDIBLE]?
>> ROGER ZURAWICKI: If you want
to make sure you can access it,
there's a command you can run.
Let me quickly write it out
so other people can see it.
I'm going to open a new tab here
and go into my seminar folder.
Chmod is the command
to change permissions,
and you can say r for do it
recursively for every file.
And permissions, you can try 0755
to make sure you have full access,
and everyone else can read.
And if you just run
this command, it'll make
sure the permissions are in
check for the whole directory.
Running ls-l can show you the
permissions in more detail.
This looks OK.
>> What's most Important is
that you have all three
rwx for all the files in
the seminar directory.
Did that solve the problem?
>> AUDIENCE: It says missing
operant [INAUDIBLE].
[INAUDIBLE]
ROGER ZURAWICKI: You
have to make sure you
have a dot at the end of your command.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ROGER ZURAWICKI: All right.
Let us quickly go back to the
local host, the app we have.
And you'll see that we have a
few tasks here, as expected.
We have a bunch of CSS, which
you don't need to worry about.
The Meteor tutorial
just gives this to you
to make your to do list look a
bit nicer than the plain HTML.
And we have the JavaScript file, which
I'll go into more detail a bit later,
but it just provides these tasks.
This is task one.
This is task two.
This is task three.
So this is the data Meteor's getting.
>> One of the cool things about Meteor is
that changes can happen automatically.
If I wanted to change the
name of the first task,
so it would say this is not
task one, and I save it,
then when I go to the web
browser, you can refresh it,
and it automatically says
this is not task one.
You can do the same thing
in any of these files.
Make a change, instead of to do
list, I will have it my to do list.
>> And one thing you just noticed,
that I didn't even have to refresh.
The idea of refreshing is kind
of solved for you with Meteor.
Whenever it detects the file changes,
it will load the changes for you.
This works on all files, whether
it's HTML, CSS, or JavaScript.
To show you what this app would look
like without CSS, I can remove it all.
And when it's reloaded, you now have
a not as nice-looking to do list.
Let's put that content back.
And surely enough, it
refreshes, and our CSS is back.
Great.
>> We can now move on with the tutorial.
Let's talk about step two, templates.
This is what we just saw
with the different tasks.
Meteor will explain to you what
templates and how this logic works.
But let's just look at the code to
see if we can make sense out of it.
>> In very simple applications,
like what we have in the simple
to do, step one, step two, step
three, step four, step five,
we don't have any folders.
We don't have the server
folder I mentioned.
We don't have the client
folder that was mentioned.
So Meteor will run all the files.
It'll run it both on the
client, both on the server.
>> And if you want parts of your JavaScript
code to run just on the client,
they need to make sure that you have
an if statement, kind of like what
we have in our JavaScript file here.
So Meteor, only if
it's the client, then I
want to define a template
helper called tasks.
What this code really
does is it says there's
a object called template
that Meteor provides.
And we're going to add a helper.
Helpers are these tasks,
these things like the tasks.
>> You'll see that if we go back to the
HTML file, we called each on tasks.
Tasks is not defined in the HTML.
It's defined in the JavaScript.
And Meteor needs to know what tasks is
when we go into the JavaScript here.
Tasks is this helper.
Helper, you can think of
it as a template variable.
And what does tasks do?
Well, it returns the list of values.
Because it's a list,
we can call each in it.
So that's why we call each on tasks.
And now we have task.
>> What does task do?
Well, it has this arrow
here after the curly braces.
That means task is a template.
It's not a helper,
like what we just saw.
It's a template we've defined.
And where have we defined it?
We've defined it below right here.
>> All this template does is render
a list item, and it calls text.
Now, text seems to be a
helper, but I'll show you
that this is actually still
a data member of tasks.
When you call each, it goes into
the data structure a little bit.
Like the foreach loop, it now just looks
at the first element in our object.
We see that text is
defined here in our object.
So Meteor is smart to know that
we're talking about this text,
not the helper called text.
It just gets the value of this
text here and displays it as HTML,
and that's how the data goes
from the JavaScript to the HTML.
>> Moving on though, in this example
we hard coded those values.
Meteor does two really
nice things for us.
Besides the live refresh that we
showed, it also manages our database.
If you had to work with PHP,
you had to configure phpMyAdmin.
You had to make sure your
tables were all in check.
You had to do a lot of work to make
sure your data was formatted correctly,
and PHP could communicate with it.
>> Now, Meteor uses a new paradigm.
This is a more modern way
of handling a database.
It's a technology called MongoDB.
Just like in JavaScript, we saw that it
didn't matter what types the data had.
Everything was a var.
It wasn't a charstar.
It wasn't an int.
It wasn't a struct.
It was just var this, var that.
>> MongoDB works kind of the same way.
You don't have to define your tables.
You don't have to say a table
has a name, which has an int.
It has, I don't know, a
dollar, which is a decimal.
It's just these JavaScript objects,
all these vars, essentially.
And this is a really powerful
way to prototype your app.
And that's why Meteor
takes advantage of this.
>> If we go to step three,
let's see what has changed.
If we look at the todos HTML, not much.
CSS hasn't changed at all.
But the small change we see in HTML
is we've changed how tasks is defined.
Tasks is now a function.
That means that every
time we want to get tasks,
we're going to run this function.
It doesn't return the
function as a value.
>> Meteor is smart to actually run the
function to see what we get out.
And it returns this thing called tasks.
We've defined tasks on line one,
and it's a Mongo collection.
Mongo is referring to
the database Meteor uses,
and this new just means let's make
a new collection, call it tasks.
In MySQL, this would be equivalent to
looking for the table called tasks.
Mongo has collections, not tables.
So this just looks for tasks.
>> Now, template in our
helper in the template, all
we have to do to get all the
tasks is this function, find
and this empty brace.
This is more particular to Mongo syntax.
There's plenty of
documentation online for how
you can make efficient and
really useful Mongo queries.
But something like this is good
enough for just finding all the data.
>> Now, one of the issues you might see
is that we never actually add data.
So what happens when we
actually run step three?
Let's quickly go into
step three and run Meteor.
Notice that I had another Meteor
project running somewhere else,
so Meteor doesn't like that.
I'm just going to quickly close to
the other Meteor with Control C,
go into step three,
and run Meteor again.
Notice it's starting
MongoDB because MongoDB
is a part of every Meteor project.
>> So it says my application has errors.
That's a nice feature Meteor has.
It makes sure your
HTML is well validated.
Let's quickly look at why this might be.
It seems I have accidentally
copied the wrong HTML code.
If I save it now, Meteor
automatically restarted the server,
and now the app is running as expected.
Notice to fix this, you can just run
the same HTML file from step two,
copy it into step three.
>> We can go back to our local host.
And now we see we have our to do list.
Great, but it's empty.
We don't actually have any
tasks in our Mongo database.
So let's talk about a
few ways we can do that.
If we go back to the terminal, we
can close it and run Meteor Mongo.
>> If you're familiar
with how Meteor works,
this actually gives you access
to the full MongoDB for Meteor.
Notice that you have to be running
Meteor first for this to work.
So if I run this in a new tab, I
can go back to the same directory.
And now Meteor works just fine.
This is a prompt.
Let me make it a bit
bigger so we can see.
This looks a bit different than
what you might be used to you
don't really need to use Mongo.
The whole point of me here is
so that you can use JavaScript.
But if you're curious,
the Mongo API doesn't
use SQL, the Structured Query Language.
It uses its own language that
looks a lot like JavaScript.
Very quickly, we can find
the table via db.tasks.
And it's telling me
turns out if we run find,
kind of similar to what we had with
Meteor, we can load all the elements.
The problem is, we don't
actually have any tasks defined.
So it can't get them.
>> We can insert, though.
So we can run insert
with command insert.
And we just give it
an object, and we just
make sure the format is what we expect.
If we looked at step two,
we saw that every task
was an object with a text
as the key and whatever
your to do item was as a variable.
So we can do something here.
>> We can have it insert a task
called I come from Mongo.
And we press Enter, and it runs.
We can run find again, and we
see that there is an object here.
Mongo assigns it an ID, which you
don't really need to worry about.
What's important to you is the data
you put in, is the data you get out.
>> Let's go back to our website,
and hey, our task loaded.
And you can see that
because Meteor is very smart
and always refreshes for you, I
didn't have to touch the page.
It automatically loaded.
>> Let's run some code in
JavaScript though to do this.
Like we have Node in the back
end to execute out JavaScript,
we can also run JavaScript
directly in our browsers.
You can do this by a feature
called Inspect Element.
If I right click on a
section of the page,
there's an option
called Inspect Element.
If you're running a
browser like Safari, you
may need to enable your developer
tools before you get this feature.
>> What we care about is the console.
So we will just go to the
console at the bottom.
Now we can run any JavaScript
here, like the JavaScript
files I showed in the js example.
But now let's look at tasks.
We can run our command.
And hopefully I'll be able to make
it a bit bigger so we can all see.
>> If we run tasks.find, and you'll
see that this is the exact same code
that the JavaScript file uses
in step three, this task.find.
We can run the same thing, and
now we get some weird stuff.
How do we actually get the data?
Well, we have to run this
command called fetch.
>> This is very useful for debugging.
What you get here is
a cursor, and this is
a nice way Meteor has
optimized fetching data.
This cursor has all the features for
live updating and refreshing the page
when something has changed.
But it won't get us the data.
We can get the data via fetch.
And you see we have an object, and
it's just like what we had in Mongo,
with an ID and the text we put in.
>> So how do we insert an item in Meteor?
Well, we just have tasks.
And then we can run the
same insert command,
giving a dictionary or a object
with the same format, text
and then I come from the console.
Take a look above because when I
do this, it shows up on the website
automatically.
>> Notice that you can put anything
you want in these items.
It doesn't have to
have a fixed structure.
I could have a equal to the
number three and b equal to false.
And it all works.
I can even choose not to
include a text at all.
This is just not recommended
though because then Meteor
will not know what to display.
But in each case, we
get an ID, and that's
the ID of the object you can use.
>> As we continue with
step four and step five,
the tutorial will show you ways that
you can create UI elements using
the HTML you know to
create different tasks.
Let's look at step four really quickly.
We'll see that we added
a section about events.
Templates can have
helpers, which get us data.
But it can also call events.
And this is where stuff
becomes useful, because events
are what happen when you click on
different things on your website.
>> Here, our code is telling
us to add this event.
Add it when you've submitted
something with the class new task.
What you have here is a CSS selector.
So this just looks for an HTML
element that has the class new task.
And it looks for the event, like submit.
Other events include
click, hover, double click,
similar to what you get in normal HTML.
>> What you give it here is now a function.
And you can have your
code in that function.
This function is what ends up getting
called when you submit this new task.
Let's look at the HTML just so we
understand what this new task is.
We've added a form here
with class new task.
And it has an input that takes text.
And this is where we
will add our new tasks.
>> Let's run step four in the
website to see what it looks like.
We can quit first out
of the MongoDB we had
from our previous
example with Control C.
And let's change it into
the step four directory.
We'll run Meteor again
to start the server.
And unfortunately, I had Meteor
running in another terminal.
So I'm just going to
make sure this closed.
Let's quit this and change
to part four, step four.
OK.
>> Now our Meteor code is running.
And you can see that it updated, without
us even having to refresh the page.
What has changed here is now
that we don't have any tasks,
but we have a form here, this
text box, to add our new tasks.
And we can type our task here.
I come from the HTML page.
When I press Enter, it got submitted.
>> We can see what happened as
defined by the JavaScript code.
What this function did was
take the text from the form,
and then just called tasks.insert,
like we did in the console.
They also chose to add a createdAt date.
This is how you would
specify the current time.
After that, it clears the form by making
sure the value is the empty string.
>> And then it calls return false to
make sure nothing else happens.
When you return false from a
form event, that stops execution.
Say a form has an action,
like submit to a PHP page.
If you had not returned
false, you'd return true.
It would end up making that request.
False intercepts it and
stops it right there.
>> So that was a little demo about
how Meteor works, and we've
been following the tutorial for a while.
And you can please feel
free to continue doing this.
There are plenty of resources,
and the tutorial is actually just
very good about explaining
what's going on.
I do want to show you now, in
the few minutes we have left,
what are some of the
cooler features of Meteor,
and what are some of the
more useful packages.
One of the great things about Meteor
is that you have a package system.
You can easily incorporate code
that many thousands of developers
have written worldwide
into your Meteor project.
One example of this is what you might
do in step nine of the tutorial, where
you are trying to add accounts
to your Meteor project.
If we have a CS50 PHP
project, we would have
to rely on the framework
or our own code to make
sure we securely handle
passwords and usernames
and storing the database
and all of that.
>> It turns out Meteor has some
packages to do that for you,
and to do it very easily.
What we can do is add a few packages.
So let's do that right
now in our console.
I'm going to quit the project and
right now go into simple-todos.
Now, simple-todos is
the project that you
will have after being done
with step 11 or step 12,
at the end of this tutorial.
And let's quickly look at it to see
what are the different features we have.
Let's just make sure it's running.
Sometimes it takes a while
to refresh, but here it is.
>> We have our option to hide
complete tasks, and we can sign in.
And this was done with
the Meteor package.
It's great.
We have now username
and password sign in.
But what if we wanted to add
another kind of login mechanism?
Let's say I wanted to log
in with my Meteor account.
I'm going to run meteor add, and this
is the syntax for adding packages.
I can say accounts, and accounts.meteor.
It's going to now find
the package and load it.
You can see that I have not
found the right package name.
>> So how do you find out about packages?
Well there's a great website, made
available by the Meteor people,
called atmospherejs.com.
Atmospherejs, one word, dot
com, is a great repository
for finding all of the Meteor
packages in the repository.
I can search accounts, and then
it'll show me all the relevant stuff,
all packages with the account's name.
>> While that loads, we can try
adding some other packages.
Maybe the Meteor package isn't working
right now, but I can add Facebook.
I can add the account and then
run the Meteor project again.
Once this starts, let's see
what's changed on the website.
You can see-- I might
have to refresh it here.
>> I have a button to
configure Facebook login.
And here, I have all
the instructions Meteor
has prepared for you for
setting up a Facebook app.
And you can use that
information to add your IDs.
Once that's done, you'll have
Facebook login working in your app.
>> I'm just going to get
an app ID and a secret,
just to show you how this might work.
You will need a Facebook account
to use Facebook developer options.
Let me just quickly find the
Meteor keys that are necessary.
I have another Meteor project
that I'm going to use,
and I'm just going to take
the keys from that file.
>> And once I find it, I'll just be able
to copy these keys into my Facebook.
So here is a key.
And this is secret.
You should not be
sharing this with people.
And then you give it your app secret.
And this is so Facebook
knows you are you.
And you save the configuration.
>> I think in the process I
have stopped my Meteor app.
So I just want to make
sure it's still there.
OK, let's make sure our Meteor server
is running so the web page is running.
Notice if we stop the Meteor
server, the page is still there.
It just won't update anymore.
The Meteor server is necessary
for making sure the page is live.
>> OK, I've submitted it, and now
I can sign in with Facebook.
Now it's just a matter of
having a Facebook pop up
and putting in your account
information and logging in.
Once you do that, Facebook might
nag you for some more security.
So we'll just stop there.
The point is that when you're done
with that, you'll have Facebook login.
>> Meteor has a bunch of
other packages as well.
You can log in with Google+.
You can log in with GitHub.
You can log in with Twitter.
Or if you search, you'll
find plenty of other things
like Meetup, LinkedIn,
and Meteor Developer.
So Meteor Developer was the
package I was looking for.
meteor add accounts-meteor-developer.
In the meantime, I
also want to recommend
some other packages for your projects.
It might prove useful to
include the jQuery package.
This allows you to use
jQuery in your clients.
You could just do it with one line, and
Meteor will make sure you're up to date
on jQuery.
I also recommend houston:admin.
>> This is kind of like a phpMyAdmin
kind of tool for your MongoDB.
This allows you to edit
your data quite easily
without having to go to the Mongo shell,
like I had done earlier in the seminar.
So now that that's running, let's run
Meteor again and see what we can do.
>> You notice that adding some packages
might have them present some warnings.
You won't need to worry
about that with houston.
So we can now have the option
to configure Meteor admin.
And they give you the directions
if you want to set that up.
>> We can also now go to /admin.
This is brought to you
by the houston package.
And this is Meteor admin interface.
You just create an
admin account, like so.
And if you refresh the page, you might
have some collections showing up.
>> It's a very useful tool,
and I strongly recommend it.
You can see that because
houston was giving some errors,
we don't have any collections
showing up right now.
The way you would use houston is
making sure this function gets
called in your simple-todos.
So houston doesn't
know what my tasks are.
>> We set up a Mongo
collection called tasks.
Let's go into simple-todos and just
make sure that in the JavaScript,
we have added tasks to our collections.
We've now saved, and it's building
the application, refreshing.
And let's see.
Now we have some tasks.
And we can add some new tasks.
But if we want to add tasks,
let's do it with the app itself.
>> Now we can add some data.
Hi, this is a task.
It seems kind of strange that
we're not seeing any tasks.
We might want to check if we got any
errors here, or maybe somewhere else.
If we go into admin, that seems strange.
If you pull the repository
after this seminar,
I will make sure that
simple-todos works with houston.
Unfortunately, it doesn't seem to
be working at this very moment.
>> Are there any other questions?
Houston normally is a
tool that works very well.
Houston specifically is a bit
buggier than the other ones,
but I do recommend it when it works.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: What can you do
with the Facebook package
once a user is logged
in with their Facebook?
>> ROGER ZURAWICKI: Once
a user's logged in,
you can make calls to the Facebook API.
A lot of that lies more in
how Facebook opens their API.
Meteor, make sure you
have the connection.
But everything after that is a matter
of learning how to use the Facebook API.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ROGER ZURAWICKI: All right.
Thank you very much for
this CS50 seminar in Meteor.
If you have any questions,
you can email me
at my email address
listed below the seminar.
And I'll be happy to
answer your questions.
I'll also be at the
CS50 Hackathon should
you need help with your Meteor projects.
Thank you for watching.