>> DANIEL ARMENDARIZ: Hello, everyone,
welcome to iOS app development
with swift.
I'm Dan Armendariz.
I'm precepter of computer
science here at the School
of Engineering and Applied Sciences.
And swift is actually kind
of a really neat language.
And I have some plans for today.
So over the next hour or so we're going
to look at iOS app development itself
using Xcode and actually creating some
very basic, very simple applications.
And looking at the way that you
actually take those applications,
and build them, and actually
put them on an iOS device.
Some of the things that
we're not going to look at
will include things like
actually taking an application
and putting it on the app store.
There's a lot of tutorials online that
will help you with that aspect of it.
But also because as
part of CS50, you get
to join the Apple development
team, CS50's app development team.
If you haven't done that yet and
you are affiliated with CS50,
I do recommend that you
do that because that
is how you're able to create
some programs in Xcode,
build them, and actually put
them on some of your iOS devices
if you actually have
a physical iOS device.
If you don't have a physical iOS
device that's more than fine.
You can actually develop for iOS.
And Xcode has a
simulator that allows you
to see your application in
action on your computer.
But it sort of is a neat thing
to actually play and interact
with your application
on an actual device.
So there's a couple of requirements to
actually do all of this development.
One of them is that
you have to have a Mac.
It has to be running 10.9.4 or later
in order to do development with swift.
>> You can use an earlier
version to develop
with Objective C for iOS and Mac.
But I recommend, and a lot of the
examples that we'll see today,
use 10.10 Yosemite.
So if you haven't yet upgraded,
it's a good excuse to do so.
Now Xcode 6.1 is the latest version of
the integrated development environment
that Apple provides for free that
you can download off the app store.
And I recommend that you
also run the latest version.
>> If you happen to be running an earlier
version, Xcode 5 and below just
simply do not support swift whatsoever.
And the beta versions of six, which
were released over the summer,
do support swift, but there's
been an enormous number
of changes in the language, enough
so that the code that you're
going to look at and that you
might find on the internet
will not actually compile properly
in these prior versions of Xcode.
So again, if you don't yet
have a developer account,
I recommend you go to
developer.apple.com.
Sign up, create a developer account,
and join the CS50 app development team.
That will provide to you an opportunity
to compile your applications
and put them on your device.
OK, so let's get started.
The very first thing
we're going to do is
to actually create a very
simple project in Xcode
that will allow you to
make an application.
>> So if you don't yet have Xcode
open, go ahead and open it
and create a new project.
A special splash screen
will open and will give you
some options about what
it is that you want to do.
Just say that you want to create
a new project, a new application.
This window will pop up,
assuming you're using Xcode 6.1.
Right now, and for the
duration of this seminar,
we're going to be using
single view applications, just
sort of a basic application
to get your feet wet.
And you can branch out
on your own from there.
>> Click Next at this point.
Now here there's a couple of things
that you might want to enter.
The product name is the
name of your project.
In this case, I'm just
going to call it Seminar1
because it's our first example.
Organization name, in
this case is just my name.
You can of course change it
to your own name, or to CS50.
Organization identifier, if you
happen to have a website just take
the domain name in
reverse, com.yourname.
and then the name of the product
should appear automatically
after that as the bundle identifier.
>> Obviously the language that we're
going to be using for today is swift.
You can, of course, use Objective C
for that, but today will be swift.
And we'll for now say
universal devices, so
that it works on both iPad and iPhone.
And we will leave core
data unchecked to keep
the project relatively
simple for the time being.
So let's go ahead and click Next.
And it's going to ask me
where I want to save it.
I'll just save it to my desktop for now.
>> All right, so now this is what will
happen when you actually open Xcode.
And notice that the
very first thing you see
is this exclamation point that
says no signing identity found.
I intentionally did this
on my computer and I'm
hoping that I'm going to
be able to actually fix it,
because I want you to see how this
will actually work on your own machine.
>> Go ahead and click fix issue.
It will ask you if you have an
existing apple developer account.
This is where joining the
CS50 app development team
is important so that you not
only have an app account,
but you also have the
capability to sign the apps
and put them on your iOS device.
This is not-- clicking
fix issue is not necessary
if you're just going to
build and develop locally,
entirely within the iOS simulator.
>> But for now I'm going
to develop and put them
on my iPad, which will be
able to broadcast as well.
So I do want to actually add this.
And it's going to ask
me for my apple ID.
So it's going to be this.
And I have to fetch my
password, which is over here.
So give me just one second to find that,
and copy that, and paste it over here.
>> Click Add.
It's going to ask me
which team I want to join.
I'm going to do school of engineering.
Click Join.
Whoops, that's the wrong one.
Let's do this one.
Hopefully that one will work.
That one still doesn't work.
We're running out of good ones here.
OK, this one should work.
Now close that.
Now let's do school of
engineering, click choose.
>> And now hopefully after a
couple of seconds you can-- OK,
I'll revoke and request.
Oh man, this is going to not work.
OK, I'll try a different one.
Let's do this one here.
Live demos are failing me.
We may have to revert to just
building entirely locally,
but that would be OK in this case.
>> So here, while this is actually
working, what we're going to do is just
create a very simple
Hello World application.
So this is Xcode.
And if you haven't seen it yet, it
can be a little intimidating at first.
There's a lot of panes, there's a
lot of doodads in various areas.
But just realize that there's
really several main components
to this development environment.
On the far left are all of the files
that are applicable to your program
or to your particular project.
We'll be clicking around
on some of them and we'll
point out the most
important ones over time.
On the far right, we
have a set of attributes.
And all of these attributes, there
are various panes for the attributes.
The panes will change depending on
the context of the main content, which
happens to be in the middle.
Now the middle can actually show
you a variety of things, for example
your code itself.
Or you might actually have-- when
you click on the storyboard which
is, by the way, just a graphical
representation of your user
interface for your application--
then the attributes pane
on the very far right
will actually change.
Now there's a couple of other
things that I want to point.
You can sort of explore around
in the environment on your own.
But one of the things
that has been very useful
is this button here, the
top right of the window.
There's this button that
looks like on the far
left it has a paragraph
followed by two circles and sort
of two arrows pointing
away from each other.
If you switch between the
standard editor, which
is the far left one, the one
that's selected by default,
and the two circles overlapping
each other, what you actually get
are a double pane view.
>> And this is actually
going to be useful for us
when we need to link items
in the UI to the code.
And we'll talk more about
that in just a moment.
But realize that if you get
even more panes like this,
you can simplify your view just
a little bit by clicking back
on your single editor.
So far so good.
So basically we have the code on
the left, attributes on the right,
and whatever it is we're working
on here in the very center.
>> So here I've clicked
on the main storyboard.
And the storyboard,
again, is a way in Xcode
that you can actually create your user
interface using just drag and drop
techniques.
And so for our very
first application this
is precisely what we're going to do.
We're going to go down to the
very far lower right portion
of the screen, which contains
a variety of user elements
that you can then click and drag
to create your user interface.
>> Now all of these
elements are called views
because they supply some sort of view.
There's an image view, for
example, to actually show
an image on the user interface.
There's a table view to
actually show a table.
So on and so forth.
There's a wide variety of
views that you can select here.
So just for now we're going
to search for a label.
You can just scroll through
all of the lists that's there.
But there's the search
bar at the very bottom
that makes it easier to identify
specific views that you actually
want to drag into your user interface.
>> Found my label.
I'm going to drag it here, directly
onto my sample application.
Right there in the middle looks good.
And I'm going to type "Hello World!"
Hit Enter.
Now I have a label.
It doesn't look like it's
centered quite properly.
So I can try to re-center it.
Fortunately it offers these
guides to make things much easier.
I'm going to try to compile it.
Hopefully it will actually work here.
And if it doesn't, in just a moment
it will in fact appear on my iPad.
It's right here.
There it is.
>> OK, so that's it.
We're done.
We've created our very
first application.
Now obviously this doesn't do anything.
It's just a label.
There's no connection between
the user interface and the code.
So if we actually wanted
to create this connection,
if we actually wanted to have some sort
of communication between the elements
that exist on the
screen and the code that
allows us to control
those elements, then
we actually need to
look at the code itself.
>> So this is what's called
ViewController.swift.
And for, especially for
your first few programs,
this is going to be sort of the
bulk of the code that you enter--
is going to be in this document here.
There's a lot of stuff
that's in here so far, right?
There's import UI kit class, override,
[? funk, ?] all these various things.
And it's not quite clear what
it is that all of this means.
So let's take a step back away
from Xcode for a little bit
and look at the language itself, swift.
>> So with swift, it was in
design and development
at Apple for about four
years to my understanding.
And there's a couple of features
about it that are really neat.
First of all, it's compiled
language, just like C.
So you first have to
compile it and then run it
before you can actually
execute the code that results.
But there is, unlike C, an interactive
prompt that you can actually run
and type arbitrary commands into.
And very much like a JavaScript console,
which you may be familiar with now,
it actually will evaluate those
commands and provide to you the output.
And they've even taken
that to the next level
and they've created something
called playgrounds in Xcode
that allow you to
visually work with code.
And we'll actually see some examples
of that in just a little bit.
It's based on C. C underlies
it, because all of the compilers
create code out of C and
create the object code from it.
But it really shares
relatively little syntax.
It will look fairly different.
There'll be some similarities.
But there are going to be
quite a few differences
compared to, say, JavaScript or PHP.
And we'll point these
out in just a moment.
>> Now one of the biggest things
about swift that's nice
is that, especially compared
to C, it's meant to be safe.
Everything in it is meant to
be very strongly typed in.
In fact it's almost annoying
at first, when you first
start working with swift, just how
much it enforces types everywhere.
Anything that's a string
has to remain a string.
It's very difficult to sort of convert
it or coerce it into some other form.
>> And again, we'll show examples of this.
But ultimately realize that
this is meant to protect you,
and by you I mean your code, from
crashing in some horrible way when
you have some sort of mismatched type.
And again, work with it.
Because it will be frustrating at first
as you try to figure out why exactly
you're getting this unusual
error dealing with types.
But it will be worth it in the end.
>> It does deal with automatic
memory management,
so no longer do you
have to deal with things
like malloc and free and all
of these sorts of things.
And it's also designed for generalities.
So while we can use an Xcode to
create iOS apps and Mac applications,
we can also just use it
as a scripting language.
And so we can use it sort
of instead of PHP or instead
of Python to actually
quickly parse and process
some data that we have on our computer.
>> It has a wide variety of modern
features, optionals, mutability,
generics, closures, and a lot of this
stuff you may or may not recognize.
And it's just sort of an unfortunate
part of the language that some of these
sort of futuristic, modern elements that
are contained within the elements are
so deeply ingrained that I actually will
have to teach you CS50.5 a little bit.
>> We have to learn a little bit more
about some of features in order
to really understand what's going
on and so that you can look at code
and not feel totally lost.
And you'll see what I mean
by that in just a minute.
OK, so let's-- enough of this
sort of theoretical stuff.
Let's actually look at our
very first swift program.
It's one line of code.
Line 14 right here, it
says print l n hello CS50.
>> So there's a couple of things that's
very different about this compared
to things that you might be
used to from C, for example.
One of them is that there's no
intmain, there's no include section,
there's none of this extra stuff.
The include, like standard
I/O, like the libraries
that actually provide the
standard features of the language,
are automatically included as
part of swift's standard library
and that are automatically imported.
You don't have to do
that import manually.
>> Intmain doesn't exist because
the main entry point for the code
is actually at the
beginning of the code.
So any code that you have
starting from the beginning
will actually be executed at the start.
So this really greatly simplifies.
Notice also, that there's no semicolon.
There's no semicolons in this language.
You put a statement
on an individual line
and then the next line
represents the other statement.
If you want to put
mulitiple statements online,
then you have separate it by semicolons.
But for the most part,
for good style, we're
never going to see semicolons for
the purposes of separating statements
in swift.
So how does this actually work?
Well very much like C we
actually have to compile this.
And so we can do that by using
swift c and then 1.swift.
And then after a couple
minutes this will compile
and then I can run item one.
And than it will just say "Hello CS50."
Awesome, so there we go.
There's our first hello world program.
Let's move on to number two.
>> Now in this-- this has changed
slightly, because whereas normally you
do-- in fact always do you have to
compile a swift application before you
actually run it-- one
of the great features
that I alluded to before was that
swift can actually be used in sort
of a pseudo-interpretive mode, there
is in fact like an interpreter.
But what this will do is there
is, in fact, a swift application
that you can run.
>> So for example if you just type
swift here, what will happen
is that you will get a prompt.
And you can type your swift
code, print hello, and run it.
And it will actually print--
well, it didn't print in this case
because it printed to centered
out, which is not visible here.
But it is actually able to function.
And so in this case, I'm just
going to use this as a script.
And I can actually run this code there.
So the way that I actually run
it will be slightly different,
but you'll see that in just a moment.
Now, in this case what we're going
to do is to first define a variable.
So this is how we define
a variable in swift,
is we use the let keyword, followed
by the name of the variable,
and then we provide some
initializing data optionally.
So this case we're defining
a constant called name,
and we're going to use that in
the output of our print line
at the very bottom, hello name.
>> Now notice that rather than using %s,
we can encapsulate the name of this
variable in /() and be able to
concatenate in the contents of this
string into this string.
Now unlike C, string is an
actual real type in swift.
And so it sits alongside
ints and alongside
doubles very easily
and naturally compared
to some of the other
languages that we've seen.
So this would actually function
just like you would expect.
>> I can run 2.swift.
And we see that my name is
actually spliced in, "Hello Dan."
OK, awesome.
Moving on to number three.
Now it was a little bit
of a white lie that I
said that the way that we declare
variables was to use the let keyword.
As many times as you possibly can you do
want to use let, because what that does
is it defines a constant.
And that tells swift that it can
optimize the speed of your application
because it knows that that
variable is not going to change.
>> So evaluate carefully
when you're going to use
a variable for the
purposes of changing it.
And when you're going to
create a variable just
to hold some data and that is
not actually going to change.
So this concept of immutability,
it's not actually going to change,
is an important one even as
far down as defining variables.
So here we've defined a name,
let name, and in this case
it's a constant, that is of type
string, and it is equal to Dan.
>> So whereas in the prior
version, it infers-- and by "it"
I mean swift-- swift
infers the type of data
that we've entered into the variable.
In this case, we can be explicit.
So let then the name of this
variable is name, then a colon.
And after the colon do we
specify the type of data.
So no longer is it int name or
string name or something like that.
But instead let label, we're
defining whether or not
it's constant or variable,
followed by the name,
followed by the type optionally.
>> So in this case we're defining
this name is a string.
We're saying is Dan.
And now I have another variable,
in this case it's called label.
But notice that it is
prefixed with the var keyword.
The var keyword means
that this variable can
be changed at a later point in
time, somewhere down in the code
can we actually change it and it
won't give us any particular error.
>> We can do standard concatenating
operator here using the plus symbol
to actually add our
name into this string.
And then we can print out
as we saw just a moment ago.
Now let's say that you
want to create a variable
but you don't want to initialize it yet.
You don't yet want to
put any data within it.
Well you have to tell
swift what the type of data
is going to be before you can
actually define it properly.
>> So in this case, when we've defined
a variable called grade we have to be
explicit about its type, because
it cannot infer just looking
at the initialized data
that you provide to it.
It will give us an error if you
just type var grade, for instance,
because it has no type therefore.
So grade=100.
So that 100 is an integer, it
fits very nicely into that.
It will continue to function.
We can see how then we
can concatenate this in.
Now you might be
tempted, if you actually
wanted to concatenate the
grade into another text string,
into another string, that you would just
use that same concatenating operator.
And that would normally be true.
But swift will not allow you to
implicitly change the type of data.
So in this case, this
line, 25, will fail
because grade is an
integer and not a string.
And so there's a mismatch set of types.
So you have to be explicit when
you want to change this data,
when you want to coerce this
data into a different type
and say, OK, I want to take
this grade, which is an integer,
and convert it to a string.
>> So I take a capital s String all of the
types, you'll notice, are capitalized,
Int, Double, String, so on and so forth.
All of them are capitalized
just to make things easier.
And we'll say capitalize
String pass into it grade.
And it will create a
string out of that integer.
And then we can concatenate
the two very nicely.
Any questions on this stuff so far?
All right, let's plow
through to number four.
>> Now let's talk about some more advanced
structures, like arrays and loops.
And unlike C, arrays in swift
are not represented by pointers.
Pointers in swift,
although they exist, called
like unsafe pointers or
some similar type like this,
they're not exposed to you normally.
So it becomes very difficult
for you to manipulate
the memory directly of your computer.
>> So arrays are just a data type.
And they're referenced using this sort
of now standard square bracket notation
that you've seen before.
But when you actually want to
define a type of a variable
as an array of some
particular type, then you
put that type in square brackets.
So what I'm saying here is that
I'm creating a variable called
grades of type int array.
And I'm setting that equal to some
initialized data, which in this case
is 100, 0, 90, 85, which is just a
collection of arbitrary grades here.
Now in this case I could,
remember, remove the type,
and it would be able to infer it
based on the initialized data.
But if I removed this and
I needed to set it later,
then I would have to make sure
that I have the type there.
All right, let's move along.
So we can-- arrays
provide to us a variety
of methods through that dot notation
at you are probably now familiar with.
So grades.count, for example,
tells us precisely the number
of elements that are
contained within this array.
>> If I want to add additional--
now notice that this is a var
and not-- this is a variable
and not a constant, which
means that I can change the contents
of this array, I can add objects to it.
But I can't just say grades
and then in square brackets
four, because that will be an
out of bounds error in this case.
If I want to actually change
the size of this array,
I have to use the dot append method to
add something on to the very end of it.
I can, however, change
individual indices.
>> So I could use grades
and then square brackets
zero to manipulate this first index and
so on, like you would normally expect.
And I can do the same to actually
receive the data from that as well.
Now there's also sort of a fancy method
of doing this, grades plus equals
and then another index,
which will append--
or not another index--
but another list which
will append that list
to the back of grades.
And the grades will
then contain all that.
But that's sort of an extra thing
that I'm just showing you for fun.
>> Now there's a for loop.
And this is the start of where
things start to change a little bit.
Notice how this for loop is
different from for loops in C.
Now I will note that
for loops in Swift can
be made to look like for loops in C, but
there's a lot of more useful constructs
that essentially eliminate the need
to have for var i equals 0 semicolon i
is less than some length,
so on and so forth, right?
And this construct is just one of them.
>> For index, index is new
variable, in this case, in range.
And what I'm saying is that there's
a range from 0 all the way up to
but not including grades.count.
So this dot dot less
than sign represents
a range of values starting from zero
all the way up to grades.count minus 1.
There is a separate
operator that exists,
which is dot dot dot, which would
mean that I want the range of zero
to grades count inclusive.
>> But in this case, because these
arrays are zero index, we of course
do not want to go to the
maximum number of grades.
I can sum the grades, as you might
expect, and output all of this stuff.
OK, moving on.
Now let's talk about functions.
In order to define a function
you use the funk keyword.
And again, in Swift you have to
be very careful with the types.
You provide to it parameters
by defining, for example,
the name of the parameter and
then in colin, the type of data
that you expect that
parameter to accept.
>> So in this case we have a
function called print grade count.
It accepts a variable called gradebook,
or rather a parameter called gradebook.
And we are expecting that gradebook
to be an array of integers.
If that gradebook is empty,
we'll print one thing.
Otherwise we will print out the number
of grades that this actually has.
>> Now if we want to return
some value, then the way
that we modify this definition is
to actually use this arrow keyword,
or to use this arrow signifier.
So here we're going to define
a function called average.
We're going to accept a list of numbers.
And we're going to return a
double, which will hopefully
be the average of this array.
And in order to do that, in order
to actually calculate this average,
we will take a sum and we will of
course sum up all of the objects
within this array.
>> Notice that there's a new
style of for loop here.
We don't have to be explicit about
iterating over every single element,
but we can instead say for
grade and gradebook, meaning
that for every single
item that we have in this,
provide that item in this
variable called grade.
And I want to do something with it.
So I'm going to sum all of this data
and actually return the double division.
>> Now notice again here there is the
concept of integer division in Swift.
If you want to double division
because you want decimals,
then you have to be explicit,
not just about one side,
because it's not going to allow you
to coerce data on either side of this,
you have to actually course
both sides into doubles
so that you're very
explicit about making sure
that you're doing double division.
>> Let's move on.
So if I actually want to accept--
so in this particular example,
this is still a command
line based application.
And we're starting to see some of
the limitations of the young language
in that although we can
access the arguments by using
this process.arguments, it's
still not necessarily the cleanest
thing that we've ever seen.
But basically I encourage you
to sort of look at this code
and try to figure out
what exactly is going on.
>> Essentially what's happening is that
we're taking a list of arguments
and were coercing them into
integers, and then we're
going to use that as a way to print
out the average of all of our grades.
Moving on.
Now there's another type of data--
another data type rather than arrays
called dictionaries, which are very
similar to hash tables or hash maps
and are similar also to
PHP's associative arrays.
So they have the notion
of keys and values.
>> And they're defined also with
this square bracket notation,
but the difference is
that dictionaries have
inside of the square bracket, a colon.
And the colon separates the data
type that is the key and the value.
So in this case, I'm going to create
a dictionary to accept some grades.
And it is going to be
of type string:int,
which means that all of the
keys are going to be strings,
and all of the values of those
keys are going to be integers.
>> What this means is that I can
then reference the specific data
that I want using those keys rather
than using numeric indices like I
would have for a standard array.
Now let's see, there's
one important thing
that I also want to mention about
this particular sequence of code.
And that is that there's
another type of data,
or rather there's this
idea of data that is
contained within Swift called optionals.
>> And what optionals means is
that it acknowledges the fact
that sometimes you're not going to
get the data that you actually expect.
And so what I mean by that is-- let's
take a look at this sequence of code
which iterates over all of the
arguments that were passed to this code
and tries to convert them, tries
to split into a variety of strings,
because it accepts a very
particular type of argument.
And then it is going to try to coerce
the strings that represent numbers
into integers that are grades,
that I can then compute.
>> So basically I'm going to
use this split function that
exists within the
Swift standard library.
I'm going to pass into it the
string that I want to split.
And then in using this
sort of funky syntax, which
I don't know if we'll
get to, but maybe, we
will actually specify the precise
character that we want to split at.
So what does this actually look like?
Let's take a look at
actually running this code.
>> So for example, let's say I have
a quiz and I got 50 on that.
And I have a PSETs and
I got a hundred on that.
And I got-- there's another
quiz and I got a 40 on that.
I hit Enter, and eventually what
will happen is that what it's doing
is taking these parameters, splitting
the strings at these colons,
recognizing that there's
two elements in each one,
and it's essentially
keeping track of each.
>> So I have in my dictionary a quiz, whose
value is represented by the number 50,
I have a PSET that has value of 100,
and a quiz one which has a value of 40.
Then later on in the code I
actually average all of those values
and list all of the keys of
that particular dictionary.
But this is important
so that you can notice
what is happening, is that what we
want to do is to take this string
and split it at this character,
which we can do again with this split
function using this sort of
interesting syntax that exists here.
>> Just for now assume that that's OK.
We'll look more at this
in just a little while.
But now there's an interesting
aspect that we actually
want to try to convert this
string into an integer.
But in other languages
what might happen is
that we would probably try
to do it and either get back
some sort of sentinel
value like negative one
or maybe a null or something like that.
Or maybe it would just caused an error.
And we would have to
then catch that error
and then try to do
something based on the fact
that this conversion
to an integer failed.
That's where this idea
of optionals comes in.
You can actually create a data type that
is an int question mark, for example.
That means that this integer
is, in fact, optional.
And what will happen is that it may
contain an integer, or it may not.
It may, in fact, be this other
idea, entirely called nill.
In which that means that there's
no value whatsoever in this.
It's not even zero,
there's just no value.
There's absolutely no value represented.
>> And that is what this line 71 is doing.
Is that it is saying that I
want to try to set a value,
a variable called grade, equal to the
conversion of this string into an int.
So I've taken this string,
this first components,
or rather the second
components, because this
is zero indexed, of this
string that I've split.
And I want to convert
that to an integer.
But it may not always proceed
normally, because imagine
what would happen if, rather than type
a number, I type of course like asdf.
>> It's going to fail.
It's not actually going to be
able to convert that to an integer
as I would expect.
So rather than kick off
some sort of an error,
we have this idea of an optional.
And that means that using
this question mark I can say,
OK, is it possible that I can take
this, converted it into an int,
and put it into a variable,
which will also be an int.
If so, then that means
that this was successful
and this first portion of
the block can continue.
>> Otherwise, it failed.
There is no value in grade-- or
rather there is no value in existing,
and I actually have to try to
handle this error condition.
You're going to see this
question mark all the time
in Swift and in example code for Swift.
And in fact the nill operator, this sort
of question mark, the optionals part,
is going to be probably one
of the more difficult things
to sort of wrap your head around
as you actually work with it.
>> It might make sense now.
And in fact, when I was
writing sample code for this,
certainly I understood
what was going on,
but still caught me by
surprise every so often
when I would find that
some data was actually
a nil version, an optional version
of the data that I was expecting.
So just realize that if you
have an optional version
you have to unpack that
data from this box.
>> So it's sort of like I-- imagine if you
have a box and it contains something.
And what you need to do
is to ask the question,
is it possible that this box actually
contains the data that I'm looking for?
If so, then pull that data out and
put it into this variable existing.
If not, then I just have to
disregard the contents of this box
altogether because it
literally contains nothing.
>> Any questions on this?
OK, let's move away from this
sort of command line based thing
and start looking at
some of the technology
that Xcode provides to us
in the form of playgrounds.
So there's a lot of
capability here with Swift.
And if you open up Xcode and it
asks you what you want to do,
you can open up the playground
and just play around
with a lot of different structures
and aspects of the language
before you even start touching
the iOS SDK or the Mac SDK.
>> So this case, let's say that I have--
I have a relatively contrived example
here, but bear with me as we sort
of work through this example.
Let's say that we have to do a lot
of exponents with a fixed value,
like we know that we're going to need to
do a lot of square powers, for example.
So we're going to take some value
x, we're going to square it,
we're going to take some value
y and we're going to square it.
So on and so forth.
>> Now we might actually just create a
power of 2 function for this, right?
So we'd create a power of 2 function.
We'll accept a double.
We'll output-- or we'll
return a double type.
We'll take this result
and then for twice
what we actually take the results, which
was the initialized to value of one,
and multiply it by x.
So in essence we have x times x here.
>> And so then I can then, as we might
expect, take this, run power of 2,
provide to it some data, I like 2.0.
And we get to see the results here 4.0.
Run power of 2 on 3.2 and we
get to see our result, 10.24.
So far so good, right?
Now we're thinking, well, OK.
Now I actually need to
do a lot of powers of 3.
So I'll copy paste all of this code,
change the name of the function from
power of 2 to power of 3, and everything
will be the same except for this value
here, this range, 1...2.
>> So rather than repeating
this loop twice,
I want to repeat this loop three times.
So I just change that value from
1 to 3-- or rather from 2 to 3.
So again, the same code,
that's the only change.
Now this also works.
Power of 3 provided in some value of 2.
We get 8.
So 2 cubed.
And 3.2 cubed is 32.768.
And so far so good, right?
But hopefully this is a little
bit of a red flag for you
in that we now have
some duplication of code
except for some very minor
change from one to the next.
So is there some way that
we might be able to simplify
this problem, where we can actually,
at run time, figure out some,
provide to us some function that has
precisely the power of that we want.
>> And there's this idea of
closures, which is really, really
important in the context of Swift,
and in many other languages as well.
But probably you will see
it used more so in Swift
because it's embedded
within the language
than you will in other
also modern languages.
So the idea of a closure
is this, is that we
can have a function that is meant to
be a generic function, a generic power
of function.
>> And this function is going to accept
this exponent that we actually
want to create.
So for example, the very first
instance, we wanted a power of 2.
So we would provide power of
and then in parentheses 2.
And now notice what
this actually returns.
This takes an input of a primer
called y that is an integer,
and it returns this crazy looking
thing in parentheses-- parentheses
double and then arrow double.
>> What this means is that I'm
going to return a function.
I'm not returning
another type of data, I'm
in fact returning a function
that has this parameter, that
accepts a double as input and
outputs a double as a return value.
And as a result, because now I've called
power of, passing in some value for y,
and I'm creating this other
function-- notice that there's
another function that's being created
inside of this-- what I am doing
is I can then change
that value, that one
value that I had changed
from 2 to 3, I now make it y.
>> And this persists.
So every time that I call power
of, essentially what happens
is that I get returned a function.
Notice that here I've defined
a new variable called square.
I've set it equal to power of,
provided this value 2 to power of.
And what this returned is the function.
So square, the variable
square, is now of type function
that has this-- oops, scroll up a
little bit-- that has this signature,
accept a double and output a double.
>> So now what I've done
is I've essentially
created a function called square that
accepts any value and will square it.
We can see what happens down here.
Square 3 for example, means I'm going
to take the value 3 and squared it.
So how exactly does this work?
When I pass power of 2-- when I
pass 2 into this power of function,
this variable y is
populated with that value 2.
And that is sort of held in memory.
That's sort of like held in
state somewhere in the computer,
we don't really care how
or where at this point.
>> But I return this function
called exponentiate.
And again, it doesn't really matter
what this function is called,
we can really call it anything, that
accepts a double and returns a double,
but uses this value y inside of it.
So even though it's this function,
this exponentiater function that's
been returned back to my
variable that I called square,
it has contained within it
this notion of what y was.
And it remembers that.
>> So every time I call that function that
is now called square, it uses that.
But this also means that I can
create another variable using
a different power of.
So I can create a cube variable, for
example, provide to it power of 3.
Now cube will actually take some
value and cube that and return it.
So we can see that I get
a value 8 out of that.
>> But that value y hasn't
changed because they're
held in sort of independent variables.
They are sort of held in
independent spaces in memory.
So cube will always have
x to the power of 3.
And square will always have
x to the power of 2, which
means that square will always
square numbers, as I expect.
And cube will always cubed
numbers, as I expect.
This also means that sometimes you can
get some sort of funky looking syntax
where you have power of at the very
bottom of the screen here, power of 5.
And you pass into the result.
You call that function that's
been returned with the number 4.
And so what essentially this
is 4 to the fifth power,
we can see the results there.
With me so far?
>> So this idea is called a closure,
because what we're basically doing
is we're encapsulating
some data into-- sort
of enclosing this data
into a function and we're
being able to reuse this function.
Now this syntax though can actually
be simplified a great amount.
And there's lots of possibility
in Swift for this simplification.
And that's what sort of the
subsequent ones actually look at.
So in 7b for example, we
take this exact same code.
>> But now rather than
actually define a function
inside of this power of
function and give it a name,
and then return the name
of that function, which
then is used as part of
this closure, instead we're
just going to simplify it.
We don't need this function to be named.
So this is the concept of an
anonymous function where we can then
accept as input, in parentheses here,
the variable x which is of type double.
>> We're going to return the type double.
And then the keyword, n, is
the beginning of this function.
So notice that all of this
is within curly brackets
and we're defining an
anonymous function here.
Just a simpler way of
defining the exact same thing.
OK?
But hold on, Swift actually allows us
to go further and simplify even more,
because really we don't
care that this parameter is
named any particular thing.
It can really be called anything and
we can still use that first parameter.
>> So in fact there is this special
type of data in anonymous functions,
there's this special name of
variables in anonymous functions
that start with the
dollar sign and represent
the parameter numbers, zero
indexed, for this function.
So there's a couple of things going on.
Here I'm going to return, and then a
curly brace representing a function,
right?
>> Notice that I don't have defined the
parameter types or the return type.
It can actually be inferred
because of the signature
of this original function.
So we can eliminate
that as a possibility.
But also I can use dollar sign zero to
represent this first parameter that's
passed into this anonymous function.
So simplifying it even more.
OK?
So far, so good?
>> Now it's this type-- do you
remember this dollar sign zero
that we saw in this curly brace
that we saw just a little while
ago in this Swift six example?
It was right here.
Notice that's exactly
what we're looking at,
is that we have passed
into this split function
an anonymous function that
checks the first parameter
to see if it equals the colon symbol.
And that's exactly what's
happening, is that all
we're doing-- the return
keyword is implied
in this case-- we're returning
this value where we're comparing
the first parameter against
this character colon.
And so that sort of demystifies this.
And you're going to see this construct
a lot in Swift syntax, so do keep that
in mind when you're
taking a look at this.
Now we can get off
the rails a little bit
and go really fancy that shows
even some more of Swift's power.
You might even see some
of these in sample codes.
So that's why I'm going
to show this to you.
>> Basically what we can do is that, first
of all, it was kind of needless for me
to implement all of that power of
code because if you import the Darwin
library, it actually includes a function
called pow that does this for you.
So we can simplify it even more and
have our power up function now just
be a wonderful one liner where we just
return this anonymous function that
accepts dollar sign 0 as its
base and y as its exponent.
>> But we can get really,
really fancy when we
realize that Swift has a
lot of power under the hood.
A lot of the operators that
we've been dealing with,
plus signs and division symbols and
all these things that you normally
operate with with data types
in a programming language,
are actually extensible in Swift.
So what that means in that we
can define our own operators.
>> So now I am tired of typing in all this
pow and then a parentheses and then
the base.
I don't want to do that.
I actually want to have an
operator that allows me to do that.
So I can tell Swift that I want
to create an operator, star
star-- by the way I can't use the carat
because the carat is an operator that
does something else entirely.
So I don't want to sort
of collide with that.
And so what you see in a variety
of languages, including Python,
is like star star operator
to represent exponents.
>> So that's the only reason
why I've done that.
And it's going to be
an infix type operator.
And I have to provide
to it some information
about the precedence of this
operator so it's left associative.
It's like relatively
high precedence compared
to summation or multiplication.
It's higher precedence
than all of those.
So on and so forth.
And then I define the
function that actually
dictates what this operator does.
So assuming that I have a left
hand side and right hand side,
which would be perhaps a
better variable name for this.
Left hand side and right hand side.
I can then take this power of the
left hand side to the right hand side
and return that value.
So now it's super sweet.
All we have to do is 2 star star 3
and that is 2 to the third power,
and we get a value of 8.
2 star star 10 is 2 to the
10th power, we get 1,024.
>> So now our power of function,
which again is different,
because the whole idea behind this
was that we have one function that
always takes some value and
multiplies it-- or rather
takes the exponent to the same power.
So now it's even simpler.
So now it's just dollar
sign 0 star star y.
We don't even have to use pow anymore.
>> OK, who's lost?
Are we doing OK?
Any questions on this stuff?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: When you-- [INAUDIBLE]
the funk power of y double.
So when you're returning a function.
DANIEL ARMENDARIZ:
Funk power of y double.
Oh yeah, I don't know
what the y numbers are.
Sorry about that.
>> AUDIENCE: Why are you returning
a function [INAUDIBLE] enclosure.
Isn't dollar zero star
star y [INAUDIBLE]
find that operator with that
returning double [INAUDIBLE] double?
>> DANIEL ARMENDARIZ: So let
me answer your question
how I understand it and you can tell me
if I didn't understand your question.
So this construct, the curly brace
dollar sign zero star star y,
is a function.
And it accepts a parameter that is
represented by this dollar sign zero.
The return keyword is implied in this
very short, anonymous function syntax.
>> Which means that essentially
what this is saying
is that I'm defining a
function-- and then I'll
just call it something--
where I have some value y.
I have y, which is double.
And I'm returning a double.
And I have within that return y-- sorry,
I shouldn't have called this y-- x.
Oh dear, oh dear, oh dear.
X-- nope-- star star y.
>> So this is just a
simplified version of this.
And so the reason that I have dollar
sign zero is that using this enclosure
means that I no longer have
to type pow, or no longer do
I have to do something
like 3 star star 2.
I can just have a single
function called square
that will always take
some value as input
and actually return the square of that.
>> So the whole purpose of the closure is
to just sort of encapsulate the fact
that I always want to use y whenever
I call that function as the power
when taking this exponent.
So returning then, a
function that accepts
a double, which is the base, and
returning the result of that exponent
is the key here.
And that's the major distinction.
There was just a bit of a flourish.
>> This is not any different
compared to the prior examples,
but it was just a bit of
a flourish we can actually
create an operator in Swift
and actually do stuff with it,
which is kind of a cool thing.
Did I answer your question?
Sweet.
Anything else before we move on?
OK.
>> Now this sort of begs the
question is that-- well OK,
now we have the ability for
functions to be returned.
Can we also pass functions as data
or as parameters to other functions?
And in fact we can.
So let's say that we have
all of the same code.
We have the square variable
that will square this code.
And we have the cube variable
that will cube some data.
And we actually want to apply
to a wide range of numbers.
>> So what we might be tempted to do,
of course, which is certainly valid,
is to iterate over this list of numbers
and apply my functions square and cube
and get two new lists as results
that are this original list squared
and cubed, respectively.
Perfectly acceptable.
But what's the thing that
we see here is that we have,
again, duplication of our code.
And there's perhaps an opportunity
for us to simplify this a little bit.
What if there was a way for us to
actually always iterate over some list
and just pass to this magical
function a variable that
represents a function
that we want to apply
to every single item in this list.
This brings up the concept of what
are called higher order functions.
And that is essentially what this
is, is that we can create a function.
>> And in this case it's called a
mapper, just to give it a name, just
mapping over every
single item in a list.
Where I take a list
and I take a function.
And that function, of course,
has a certain signature.
It accepts as a parameter double
and it will output is a double.
And the whole result of
this function is going
to be a new list that is of type double.
OK?
>> And what I'm going to do
is to apply this function f
to every element in my list.
And reply-- and rather return this new
list as a result, which is really cool.
Now I can pass functions around.
And this idea of higher order
functions is really important.
And this mapper is really just
the poor man's implementation
of a function that is built
into Swift called map.
And it does precisely this,
perhaps even a little bit better.
>> This is just sort of a generic,
simplified version that
allows us to see the
concept that applies here.
Now look at the way that I
can actually apply my square
and my cube functions
to this list of numbers.
I run my mapper.
I provide to it my list of numbers.
I provide to it the the
function that's going
to apply to each of those indices.
And it is going to be
output as a result.
And I will get to see that I've squared
and cubed my numbers as a result.
>> And of course the mapper will take
any sort of anonymous function.
We can even see that I've created
a new anonymous function that
just takes some parameter
and divides it by 2.
And we can see that I've, in fact,
divided my list by 2 instead.
Cool?
So far, so good?
All right, now let's
come back to this idea.
Let's implement this back in
the context of a gradebook.
>> And if I do that, we can see that I can
apply a wide variety of these options--
or a wide variety of these
higher order functions
to actually simplify my ability to do a
variety of things on lists of numbers.
So for example, if I
take a list of numbers,
one of the higher order functions
that exists is called reduce.
What reduce does rather
than map, is reduced will
take two elements in the list,
will take some function that
compares the two elements of
the list, and it will then
sort of output-- the
output of that function
will be another element that
you then compare to others.
>> So you could use this to actually
sum of the numbers in your list.
For example, if you had
a list of 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
you take the first elements, 1 and 2.
You can apply to it an addition
function that takes those two elements
and spits out one of those elements,
which would be the value 3.
Then we take that value 3 with the next
element of the list, sum those two,
and then keep going down the list.
>> We're reducing the
list to a single value.
And it just so happens
that the plus symbol
is an operator, just like we just saw.
This operator is
actually a function that
has precisely this list that we
would want, rather these properties
that we would want.
So I encourage you to
take a look at this.
I want to sort of move
on from some of this code
so that we can actually look at some
actual, real, true Swift in Xcode,
in iOS development.
But take a look at
this and see if you can
parse through what's going on
with some of these higher order
functions including filter,
reduce, and you'll even
see somewhere in here map as well.
It's right here.
Where it will take a sequence
of grades and it will actually
map them using the switch construct,
which you might recognize from C,
but actually it is a lot more
powerful than the switch construct
that we have in C.
>> And we'll apply that to
every element in the list
and actually provide
the letter grade of each
of those grades using all these concepts
that we've just talked about before.
Now let's sidestep for just a
minute and talk about structs.
And so structs are a wait in C that we
were able to define a new type of data.
Structs exist within Swift.
And so do a lot of other constructs
called enums and classes, that really
take this idea to a
whole different level.
>> And basically it's just a way
of defining a new type of data.
So if you get-- if you come
across class or structs or enums,
don't get confused by it.
It's just the way of defining
some new particular type of data.
And this is really important when
we're talking about iOS app development
because everything that
exists within the iOS app
is essentially an object of some kind.
And an object is basically a
class or an enum or a struct.
>> So in this case I'm
defining a new type of data
that I'm calling assessment
that's some properties, including
a name and a sequence of grades.
So one type of assessment
that I might have in mind
would be quizzes, for example.
I would want to have an
assessment that was a quiz
and that had a variety of grades
associated with that, for quiz one,
quiz two, so on and so forth.
>> Or I might have a different type
of assessment for problem sets.
And I can do things.
I can actually have
functions within this type
of data, which are now called methods.
So if you ever see the
word method, it really
is just a function that applies
to a very specific class,
or to a very specific type of data.
It allows us to modify the data within.
>> So in other words, if I want to
add a grade to my assessment,
then all I need to do is to
append the score that was input
to this function to
my internal property.
There's another neat construct here
in Swift, which is this dot dot dot
operator, which means that scores can
now accept any number of integers.
And scores will be an
array of integers that
have been passed to my function, which
means that I can do stuff like this.
>> I can do add grades and just provide
arbitrary numbers of integers into it
and actually be provided an array
of those values in my function
or in my method, as is the case.
Now this is important because
everything in Xcode, everything in iOS,
is in fact an object.
So keep that in mind
when we bust open Xcode
and skip ahead beyond iOS
versions two and three
and actually go on to version four.
>> And again, all of this will
be posted on the seminar page.
iOS four is sort of a full blown
implementation of a very basic app.
And what this app does is it
loads a UI, which looks like this.
Again, if we click on storyboard we can
see that this is what it looks like.
This is the UI.
It has a title at the very top.
I've called it web gallery.
>> In the middle there's an element
called the UI image view.
And at the bottom there's a
toolbar with a single button that
has stretchy spaces that allow it to
center in the middle of this toolbar.
And what happens is that when this
loads it downloads a JSON file that's
contained on a server elsewhere,
parses that JSON file,
and the JSON file looks a bit like this.
The JSON file looks like this.
There it is.
>> It has an album name and
it has an array of photos.
Each of those photos
have a name and also
a URL themselves that represent the
jpeg version of that individual photo.
So what happen is that when this program
loads, it downloads the JSON file,
parses it, puts all of this into
the equivalent of an array in iOS
app development, which is an nsarray.
And then I can then load
this data into an application
and load it on my screen.
>> There is an image that was loaded
with the button at the very bottom.
If I click Get Next Image, it then
pulls that image from the internet
and replaces that image
in the UI image view.
So you can download this and actually
take a look at it on your computer.
And build it and actually
compile it onto your device.
But essentially the process was
this, create the storyboard--
or rather not create--
but select the storyboard.
And actually we'll-- if you don't mind--
we'll take just a couple of seconds
to actually show you how this was done.
>> Just so that how we can actually
achieve this is made a little bit more
apparent.
Single view application, I'm
going to call this seminar
four representing this
particular number.
Save it on the desktop.
OK, going to click on the storyboard.
And what I'm going to do
is to find my image view,
drag it onto my user
interface and center it.
Now just centering it unfortunately
is not going to do a whole lot,
except for a screen
that is this exact size.
>> So we can convince ourselves of that by
clicking on this double circle thing,
bringing down this pop
up menu here and changing
to preview, where we'll actually
get a chance to preview how
this will actually
look on other devices.
As we can see, we don't even
see it on this particular case.
So I'm going to close this for now.
>> And I'm going to select
this icon down at the very
bottom portion of the screen.
It says Resolve Auto Layout Issues.
Sorry, it's cut off at the bottom.
But if I click on that, what I
get is this pop up-- go away.
What I get is this pop up that
allows me to add missing constraints.
And by doing that it
will then sort of lock it
into the center portion of the
screen like I might expect.
>> Now in order to get this button on
top of it, I need to go to the Editor.
Go to Embed In and click
Navigation Controller.
What that will do is that will add
this whole other component to it,
but it will actually link
it back to my original UI.
And the details, again, we don't
really need to care about right now.
But I do want to have a
toolbar at the very bottom.
So I'll check Shows Toolbar.
>> And this provides within my view,
which is now somewhere else,
we can see it's linked over here.
It now provides a toolbar
at the bottom of my UI.
So now, rather than selecting an
image view, I can find a label,
or rather a toolbar--
let's see, where is that?
What is it called?
A button-- item bar-- item--
sorry-- bar button item.
Plop that there and apply a couple
of flexible spaces on either side
to actually center that.
So now I've created my UI, basically.
And I can give it a name by
double clicking at the very top
here and saying web gallery and so on.
Now again, these are elements
that exist by themselves.
And I have to connect
them to my code which
I can do by again bringing
up this double circle icon,
changing from the preview.
Which, by the way, now we can see is
nicely centered and will look good
on a variety of devices.
>> Switch to automatic, which will
bring up the ViewController code.
And now this part is important.
In order for you to connect these
two elements, your code to the UI,
you select the item that
you want to connect.
So in this case, we
actually want to encode
change the image that's contained
within this UI image view.
So if you control click from
the image view and drag,
you'll notice that you get a little bar,
when you let go of everything this pop
up will occur.
>> And it says that we will
create a connection.
And from here I want to give it
a name, something like gallery.
Hit Enter.
And this actually provides
a variable called gallery
that I can then reference in my code
to change the image, for example.
So how does that code actually look?
Well again, I don't want to
spend too much time on it.
And I encourage you to
download it and take a look.
But one of the most
important aspect is the code
that actually fetches an image.
>> So in this case I want
to get within my photos
array, which is contained
within my class.
I want define the name and the URL
that's been parsed out of this JSON.
Actually ask the device to get the
URL, to fetch the URL from this,
and then fetch the data from
the contents of that URL.
Then convert that data into an image
by passing it into the UI image.
So again, these are all different types
of objects, different types of classes.
>> And then I can then set my
gallery.image equal to that data.
And that's sort of the meat
of it that actually is then
able to change the data from-- change
the picture from one to the next.
So again, hopefully now
a lot of the constructs
will make a little bit more sense.
Notice that there's some
exclamation points here.
The exclamation points are
essentially related to the optionals.
>> What I'm basically saying is
that without even checking
to see if there's data
within this optional,
I'm going to go ahead and assume
that there is and unwrap it.
Remember that we used the analogy of
sort of a package for the optionals
and we need to unwrap the
package and pull the data out.
The exclamation point
forces that actually happen.
>> But I know that this is
safe because I checked
to see if image data is equal
to nil, I've actually check
to see if that optional
was, in fact, failed.
If that had, in fact, failed already.
And so I'm sure that once I get to this
point I can safely unwrap that data.
You might also see it in
the form of a question mark.
So if we scroll down to where I
need to actually parse the data.
>> So don't be put off by
these sort of lengthy names.
You can find in the Apple
developer site a lot
of references to all of the
objects and all of the processes
that actually make this possible.
But notice that this is essentially
a function where I pass it some data.
And I get back some sort of data.
And I need to use this as keyword to
convert it into this nsdictionary?
Which is again, an
optional nsdictionary.
Which I then need to
check to see if it exists.
>> So I can use that if let
successful equals parsed,
then I know that that optional
actually contains some data.
Or what I did here was to
just assume that if there
were no errors that it is in fact safe.
All right, I want to thank
you all very much for coming.
I know this was a lot,
but it was only an hour
to talk about some
pretty advanced stuff.
And so hopefully you'll get a
chance to download all of the code
and take a better, more
thorough look at it.
Sort of convince yourself of all
of the stuff that's going on.
And I want to thank you
all, again, for coming.
And good luck with your final projects.
Have a great day.