SPEAKER: Now let's dive
into the distribution code
and take a look at the context
in which the code you write
is going to be operating.
At the end of the day,
you're going to implement
the entirety of the web server.
But we have provided
you with the skeleton
code that have some functionality,
particularly related to networking.
Let's take a look.
>> So up here toward the top
of the file is a bunch
of feature test macro requirements.
Now this is just a feature of c, whereby
according to a bunch of man pages
you have to define some of
these constants to be true
or to be even specific numbers so that
you have access to certain functions.
Otherwise they'll be undeclared
and you won't have access.
So I've done this by way
of reading the man pages.
Now down below, in
lines 15 through 17, we
have a whole bunch of limits declared.
>> And we've borrowed these from a
popular web server called Apache.
And these are just
numbers that are going
to cap the total number
of bytes that are allowed
in various contexts for the HTTP request
that a browser is allowed to send me.
Next, we define octets.
Now an octet is just a fancy way
of saying a byte, or eight bits.
Turns out in yesteryear a byte
wasn't necessarily eight bits,
so octet is always eight bits.
So in this case we've adopted
what's common in the networking
world of calling eight bytes an octet.
>> Here I've specified that octets will
be 512, so that much like in forensics
when we read a bunch of
bytes at a time, here too,
we're going to read a
bunch of octets at a time.
Next a whole bunch of header files.
How did I know to include these?
Well I simply read the man
pages for a number of functions
that we'll use in this distribution
code and include in the ones
I was instructed to.
>> And now we have a data type.
We've declared an octet to be a char.
And we'll see later that that's
used throughout the code.
And we've declared a
whole bunch of prototypes,
and we'll walk quickly through
each of those functions.
Lastly, and perhaps most
important to keep in
mind at this point in
the story, is that there
are, in fact a whole
bunch of global variables
at the top of the file, root,
CFD, SFD, request, file and body.
>> Now generally, using so many global
variables, or global variables at all,
isn't the back practice.
But it turns out we're also using a
technique called signal handling later
in the code, which allows us to
detect when the user hits something
like CTRL C and shut down
the server gracefully.
And in order to do that gracefully
and actually free up memory,
we need to have access to
these global variables.
>> And now let's take a look at main, which
drives the entirety of this program.
First, at the top here we
have an error number variable
that appears not to
have a type, but that's
because it's actually
defined in a file called
error errno.h which
is included higher up.
If you do man errno to actually
see the definition for this thing,
you'll see that this is a
special global variable that
is set by a whole bunch
of functions not written
by us, but by the authors of Linux
and other systems to actually set
a number to that variable when something
goes wrong so that you can globally
figure out what did go wrong.
>> Now down below you'll see a new
technique perhaps using getopt,
a function that helps parse command
line arguments so that we don't
have to bother wasting time figuring
out how to parse something like 8080,
or dash p, or dash h to get help.
getopt essentially does that for us.
See the man page for more.
>> Next, we do a bit of error
checking to make sure
that the port number is within
the specified range in the spec.
Next, we see a call to the function
start, whose definition we'll
look at in a moment, and as its name
suggests, this starts the web server.
Here we have a call to a function
called signal which says,
if and when you hear Control C from
the user's keyboard, go ahead and call
a function called handler that's going
to ultimately clean things up and stop
the server.
>> Below that is what appears to be an
infinite loop, the first line of which
effectively is a call
to a function called
reset, which we ourselves
implement later on in order
to free up some of our global states.
After that is a line of
code that conditionally
is checking the return
value of connected.
Now connected looks like a predicate,
something that returns true or false.
And it does, but there's
something special in connected
in that it's a blocking call.
It will sit there and wait
until a user's browser
tries to connect to this web
server and only then will it
return true or false so that we proceed
to the inside of this if statement.
>> Once there, notice this function to a
function called parse, which we wrote,
which parses all of the octets, all
of the bytes coming from a browser
to the server, so that we can hand
you back ultimately a value to one
of those global variables that
stores all of the bytes in just
the headers of that
request, not the body
if there were actually a body to it.
>> Now down below we begin to
parse those headers to extract
a subset of the information
that we care about.
Specifically, per the
specification, we first
wanted to request line, which is
just that very first line that
hopefully says something like get
slash or some path and then HTTP 1.1.
We're using this metaphor
of a needle in a haystack
to look for particular
chars or addresses.
And indeed, there's a number of
functions in our distribution code
that you, too, might find helpful
when looking for particular values.
>> Ultimately, we copy these bytes
into a variable called line,
which notice, too, we've
allocated on the stack
by way of a dynamically sized array.
And we're deliberately trying
to avoid calling malloc
because again, because
of Control C being
a potential feature of this program, we
don't want to have this code suddenly
interrupted by the user hitting
Control C, the result of which
is that I might not have a chance
for free something I've malloced.
So I'm trying to use as much
of the stack is I can here.
>> Next up, a whole bunch of to dos.
The specification will expound
on exactly what's expected here,
but the comments give you
a hint of what lies ahead.
You first need to
validate the request line
and make sure that it looks like the
specifications grammar, so to speak,
says it should.
You then need to extract something
called the query, the stuff out
after a question mark, like
we saw with our Google example
in passing in an HD parameter.
We then concatenate together
the root of the web server
with the path that's in
that request first line
and form the full path of
the file we want to look for.
>> Thereafter, we're going to make sure
that the file exists and is readable.
And then we're going to extract its
file extension, the .html or the .php,
or some such extension that's at the
very end of the string requested.
Next up is a whole
bunch of code we wrote
to actually generate PHP
generated content for you.
In a nutshell, this
code takes in the name
of the file you want PHP to interpret.
We pass it by something called
a pipe into PHP's interpreter.
Get back the response as though
the response were a file itself.
And then we iterate over that file's
bytes, pulling them all into one buffer
so that we can ultimately
print them out.
>> Indeed, all of these
calls here to dprintf
allows us to print something
called a file descriptor, which
is just an integer
that represents a file.
Very similar in spirit, but
fundamentally different from a file
star pointer.
Notice how you can use syntax like
printf here so that I can dynamically
insert something like the length
for the value of an HTTP header
called Content-Length.
And ultimately I used the
function right to actually write
the body to the request.
>> Unfortunately, we only implemented
support for dynamically
generated PHP files.
We did not implement support for
static files like gifs, and jpegs,
and CSS and HTML files.
That, unfortunately, is left to you
to respond to the client purpose
this to do.
So in there you'll find that there's
not much inspiration within that block,
but if you a little higher up at how
we went about interpreting PHP code,
the functions you'll use
are a little different.
>> In fact, you can borrow
some of the functionality
perhaps from the forensics
problem set, because
at the end of the day all you need to
do here is once you know what file open
and once you know it's so-called
MIME type or content type,
you need to read in those bytes
and somehow spit them back out.
>> And now a tour of this
file's other functions.
Up first is connected,
which simply returns true
when it finally hears a
connection from a user.
Next up is error.
Error, meanwhile, as a function we
wrote to handle all of the different 400
and 500 HTTP status
codes that you might want
to send back to the user,
along with a standard message.
>> Next up is load, a particularly
meaty function, whose purpose in life
is to read from a file star pointer the
contents of a file into a global buffer
that we declared globally
above [? main. ?]
This is a bit complex because we
have to read the bytes from the file
but check on each iteration
whether we've already
hit the end of the file or
something else has gone wrong.
And we use realloc to make sure that
whatever buffer we're using is growing
and growing and growing and always
staying ahead of the number of bytes
that we need to fit in there.
Handler, meanwhile, is
the function that gets
called by way of having
registered Control C as a signal
that we want to intercept.
Notice here in handler
that it ultimately
calls stop, which of course
stops the web server.
And unfortunately, lookup
is not implemented.
In spirit, this is a
fairly simple function.
Given a file extension, it needs
to return it's so-called MIME
type or content type.
And we specify in the specification
what that mapping must be.
But you need to translate
it ultimately to c code.
>> Next up is our similarly meaty function
called parse, whose purpose in life
is to read, not from a file,
but from a network connection.
Specifically, reading and parsing the
HTTP request that's come from a browser
to the server so that
ultimately we can parse
at just the headers in the request
line and return those to you
by way of a global buffer that
we declared above [? main. ?]
>> Reset, meanwhile, is a
function that we define
that gets called iteratively inside
of main every time you're about
ready to start listening
for a new connection
so that we always know
the state of our variables
and so that we've also
freed any memory that
might have been allocated for
a previous network connection.
Next up is start, the
function that we wrote
that contains a whole
lot of networking code
that ultimately starts the web server.
>> Last up is the function
called stop, which
does exactly that, it
stops the web server.
But first it frees up any memory
that still has been allocated.
But it ultimately calls exit
without even returning control
to our main function.
Ultimately, one of the
most important techniques
when implementing this web server is
going to be a bit of trial and error,
having one browser window open
at right and a terminal window at
left, the servers console
window, so that you
can see the messages that are
being displayed on the screen.
>> But better still would be a third
window, a second terminal window,
in which you use Telnet, the usage
for which is prescribed in the spec.
And Telnet is just a very
simple network program
that lets you to pretend to
be a browser in one window
while talking to the other window.
This way you can see
exactly the textual commands
that are coming back
from server to client
without having to poking
around chrome's developer
tools in an otherwise
clunkier interface.