>> ROB BOWDEN: This is the
more comfortable section,
but that doesn't mean that if you
feel like you're not more comfortable
you won't learn things here.
So let's get started.
Do you have slides
going right into things.
Am I about to just take it right now?
Switching laptops.
>> ALLISON: You don't want to
introduce yourself, Rob?
>> ROB BOWDEN: Oh, I'm Rob.
This is my fifth year TF-ing CS50.
>> GABRIEL: I'm Gabriel.
I'm head TF of CS50.
I was TF last year and this year.
ALLISON: And I'm Alison, and this
is my second year TF-ing CS50.
>> ROB BOWDEN: All right, so
this thing on the left,
hopefully you've seen it before.
If not because you
download it for yourself,
you should have seen it in lecture.
So this is the CS50 appliance, and he
did a somewhat of a description of it
in lecture.
But basically it's just you
are running an operating
system within your operating
system so that we can give you
programs without needing
to worry, oh is this
going to work on both Windows
and Mac, or if some of you
are already using Linux, Linux.
It's just supposed to
be a common playing
field so everyone has the
same exact environment.
>> So if you haven't
downloaded this already,
you should download it, because you're
going to need it for the problem set.
And it is a two gigabyte
download, so it might take awhile.
On the Harvard it'll go fast.
So CS50 appliance.
>> Now in the beginning, we're going to
talk about just a bunch of command line
stuff, and so by that, I mean working
in this little environment over here.
And notice all of things
I say right here right now
are going to work if you're inside of
a terminal inside of the appliance,
or if you are inside of
the gedit terminal window
inside of the appliance.
So those environments are identical.
>> But I'm going to go a third route.
And notice down here this
little IP address right here.
So you don't have to
do this, but this IP
address-- now if I-- except
it's blocked by this thing.
OK, so that IP address
over in a terminal
here-- so this terminal over
here is a terminal in my Mac.
So this is in no way currently
associated with the appliance at all.
And if you're on Windows, then you're
going to need to download something
specifically for this, in particular
people tend use Putty, P-U-T-T-Y.
>> So what I'm going to do is type
SSH and then that IP address.
Well, jharvard at that IP address.
So 192.168.24.220.
This scary message, ignore it.
Just type yes.
This is CS50 in a box.
It asks for your password.
>> And so in a lot of these contexts where
it asks for the password, [INAUDIBLE].
We've got a lot of questions where
it says it's not actually typing.
It doesn't show you the characters of
the password as you type, if anything,
for a security feature, because if
someone is looking over your shoulder
and they see star star
star star, then they
know that your password
is four characters.
So the idea is it will ask
you for your password, type.
It's not going to show
you the characters,
but it's actually accepting them.
In this case, any time you
ever see a password prompt
dealing with the appliance, the
password is going to be crimson.
So crimson.
>> And now here inside of this
window that is in my Mac,
I am basically having
the same exact view
as inside of a terminal
in the appliance.
So you don't have to do this.
You can do everything you
want inside of the appliance.
I almost never actually do
anything in the appliance.
I almost always minimize that and now
I'm working SSH into the appliance.
>> If anything, if you
have a slower computer,
you might notice a difference.
I do this because I prefer
this terminal window.
It has some features like
I can split the window,
and now I can SSH in
through the appliance.
I got two SSH's going on at once.
If your computer is particularly slow
and you're working in the appliance,
and you realize this is
really laggy, whatever.
Tends to be much faster
if you're SSH-ed in.
But otherwise you can work either way.
>> AUDIENCE: What does SSH mean?
>> ROB BOWDEN: Secure shells,
something like that?
What does SSH mean?
GABRIEL: Secure shell.
ALLISON: It's just secure shell.
ROB BOWDEN: Secure shell.
It's a protocol that you-- it's
a secure protocol, so encrypted.
People can't snoop the network and
see what you're saying to anything
you're SSH-ed to.
And in fact, in the olden
days of CS50, so in 2009
when I was a freshman, the way that
you worked on CS50 problem sets,
was you SSH-ed to some server
that we gave you access to,
and you worked on there.
So you didn't have this
graphical appliance.
You didn't have gedit.
You didn't have all these things that
you could visually point and click.
You had to work in this interface.
I prefer to work in this interface.
So part of what we're going
to be going to over right now
are a bunch of the
commands that you should
start to get familiar with as
you go along in the course.
And honestly, once you
get used to them, it
is so much faster to
work in this environment
than it is to work with finder,
dragging and clicking things.
>> So here we are.
Now I just SSH-ed in, and so
the default location-- you
saw some of these commands in class,
but we'll go over all of them again.
The default location we're
in is the home directory.
And directory, just
another word for folder.
So we're in the home directory.
Type ls, list the files
in this directory.
Evidently I created a blah.c earlier.
So we have a desktop directory.
You notice the syntax highlighting?
The light blue highlighting indicates
a directory and the straight white
indicates just a plain file.
So there are going to be
some other colors you see.
An executable file is probably going
to be green or something like that.
OK, so we are in the home directory.
>> Now if I want to go into a different
directory, cd is the command I want.
So change directory, and then you
pass the name of the directory
that you want to go into.
So here we have four options.
I can go into downloads, and now we see
here it has updated this parenthetical
to say I'm in ~/downloads.
>> So what is tilde?
It's a shorthand for
your home directory.
So almost everything you do is going to
be with respect to your home directory,
and pwd is just a command
I use once in a year that
just prints the current directory.
And so you see here that
~/downloads really resolves
to /home/jharvard/downloads.
So /home/jharvard is my home directory.
>> So we can cd dot dot.
Now dot dot is a special directory that
always refers to the one directory up.
So if I'm in ~/downloads, then cd dot
dot is going to bring me to tilde.
What do we think cd dot dot
is going to bring me to now?
It'll bring me to /home.
So tilde by print working directory,
I'm in now /home/jharvard.
one directory up from that,
now it says here /home.
>> Now cd dot dot.
Now I'm in the root directory,
and you can't do it again.
You'll just stay in the
root directory forever.
The root directory has a whole bunch of
things that, if you want to look into,
you can.
For example, if I go
into bin, that contains
all these binaries, such as ls,
and cd, and all of those things.
So these commands need to
exist somewhere in the system,
and it's in the /bin directory.
But almost everything you do is
going to be from your home directory.
And cd without any arguments whatsoever,
you could say cd ~, don't need to.
cd is going to bring you
back to your home directory.
>> One last one.
cd - is going to bring you back to
the last directory that you were in.
So I just cd'd twice in a row, so my
last directory was the home directory.
If I go to slash bin, and now
let's go up and into user.
User share.
Let's go to user share.
Now I'm now in user share.
cd -, back in bin.
So this gets particularly useful
when you have-- and it'll toggle.
So user share, back bin, share bin.
>> So this gets useful.
You may find yourself having many,
many, many nested directories.
And you want to do something
real quick in an upper directory.
You go to that directory, make
changes and stuff like that,
and now you want to go
back to where you were.
cd -.
I'm always frustrated
when I happen to go
to that directory I
wanted to do work in.
I always get frustrated when I did
it in two steps instead of one step,
because that means that cd - is going
to bring into that intermediate location
instead of where I want to go.
>> So we see all the list files.
We know how to get around so far.
So now let's talk about editing files.
So in this course, you're almost
always expected to use gedit.
If you want, you can take the next step
and start learning a command line text
editor.
So various options exist.
>> And the ones that are probably
going to be relevant to you,
we have Nano, Vim, and Emacs.
So Nano is the beginners
command line text editor.
So Nano let's go on
blah.c I created earlier.
It's just this standard C file.
And you see a whole bunch of stuff
going on at the bottom of the screen,
and apparently blah.c
contains this C code.
>> So in this particular editor,
what it's saying at the bottom--
now this caret symbol,
we see this ^G, ^X, ^O.
So that in almost all
context that you see,
you might see that caret symbol in
other places online, on Stack Overflow,
something like that.
It almost always refers to control.
So to exit I want to do
Control X. Control X, exits.
And I can use my arrow
keys to move around.
Notice I cannot point and click readily.
You need use your arrow
keys to move around.
There might be a setting
to point and click.
>> But let's make some changes.
Now Control X to go exit.
It's going to say save modified buffer.
Now the prompt, y for yes, n for no.
Control C for cancel.
I'll just say yes.
File name to write.
The default is the file
that it already is.
Hit Enter.
OK.
Now I've just edited that file,
saved it, and it is changed.
>> So Nano is the easiest
text editor get used to.
The alternatives are Vim and Emacs.
Those are higher level text editors
that have a very steep learning curve.
So my personal preference is Vim.
And it has a wide variety of options.
And once you get used
to it, you'll never
want to go to any other
text editor because you just
have so many things
available to you in these,
but it takes a really
long time to learn.
So maybe you just want to force
yourself right now to get used to it,
but I would say it's worth it.
But it is hard.
>> And then Emacs.
I always struggle in Emacs because
I know how to do absolutely nothing.
Apparently Emacs is not by default
installed on the appliance.
We will probably add that
as a default installations.
Once you learn one of
Vim or Emacs, there's
no compelling reason to
ever learn the other,
but it's a completely different style.
OK so that's editing text files.
>> AUDIENCE: If you were stuck
in Vim right now, how do we--
>> ROB BOWDEN: There are
multiple modes in Vim,
and there are entire
tutorials on learning Vim.
So if you happen to be
in insert mode in order
to type text, which you can
enter that in various ways,
but i is how you get into insert mode.
In or get out of any special
mode that you're in, just Escape.
And you just bash Escape to get
out of any nested modes your in.
Just OK, now I'm back in normal mode.
>> And so in normal mode, a colon.
You see it appear at the bottom.
And then q.
So q will quit if you've made changes,
which I-- have I made changes?
I have made changes apparently.
So if you've made changes, it'll
say you can put an exclamation mark.
I'm going to call it a bang.
So you can put a ban to just
quit without doing anything,
or colon wq will save and quit.
So w in general is write.
So write the file.
I can write and quit.
Or you could have just
qx slam, q bang just
to get out of there regardless
of any changes that you've made.
>> All right, so now let's
go-- we can create files.
Let's start removing files.
And I'll just throw in one
quick new command, touch.
So touch foo.
Touch bar.
Touch baz.
If I ls, now we see
that those files exist.
They're completely empty.
So touch is just an easy
way of one, [INAUDIBLE].
Two, technically just to state
it, it updates the timestamps.
So any file that you create has
a timestamp associated with it.
So baz was created on
September 14 at 16:21.
It's now 16:22, so if
I touch baz again, we
see that baz was most
recently modified at 16:22.
But otherwise I almost never
look at the timestamps on files.
So touch, here I'm just using
it to create some quick files.
>> All right, so now rm is the
command that we care about here.
And we can rm boo.
Say remove regular empty file boo.
And we can type y, and now it's removes.
rm baz.
Remove regular empty file
baz and type n for no.
Now it's not removed.
So bar and baz still exist.
Foo is gone.
GABRIEL: Keep talking.
ROB BOWDEN: Great.
So the annoying message
here, remove regular empty--
what are you doing down there?
Remove regular empty file.
So if we don't want to be
bothered by that message,
we can throw in this -f
flag, and so that's force.
And now if I rm -f, it's not going to
say do you want to remove this file.
It'll just do it.
And ls, I don't see bar there anymore.
>> Now that is a potentially
dangerous command.
It tends not to too bad.
We'll come back in a second how
it can get really dangerous.
And let's create some temp directory.
mkdir, another command.
So mkdir is a command
that makes a directory.
And now by ls we see this nice light
blue highlighted temp directory.
I can cd into temp.
And I can mkdir foo.
cd into foo. mkdir bar.
cd into bar.
>> So we see we can easily get
into some pretty deep nesting.
Now how do I remove a directory?
rmdir.
So if I just straight try to rm,
like we did with a regular file,
rm bar is going to
say cannot remove bar.
It is a directory.
There's a special command for
removing directories, kind of.
So rmdir bar.
Now bar is gone.
>> OK, so rmdir I pretty much never use.
The reason being-- now let's
make a regular file bar in here.
So rmdir boo.
rmdir.
Failed to remove foo.
Directory not empty.
So you cannot use remove dir on a
directory that has things in it.
>> So you have some options.
You can go into that directory, remove
everything manually, and then come out
and rmdir the directory.
That obviously sounds annoying.
What if there are thousands
of files in there?
Well, you could rm *.
We'll talk about * in a second.
It basically means all the things.
But better yet, so rm -r.
So rm -r-- in a lot of
contexts, -r means recursive,
which we'll talk about what
recursive means in several weeks.
But it basically means traverse
the entirety of this directory
and remove everything.
>> So rm -r foo is going to say
descend into directory foo?
Yes.
Remove regular empty file foo/bar?
Remove directory foo?
Yes.
So now foo and everything
within it has been removed.
>> Now that can get particularly annoying
when-- let's touch 1, touch 2, touch 3.
Could have a whole bunch of files.
If I wanted, I could create
thousands of files in here.
And rm -r foo is going
to be pretty annoying.
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
With a lot more files you
quickly see how many times
I would have to type yes.
Well, we just saw before how we can
get rid of needing to type yes, -f.
So mkdir foo cd foo touch 1 2 3.
OK, so rm -rf foo is going to
blindly remove foo entirely.
No prompt.
No anything.
Foo is gone.
>> So I tend to use this
command all the time.
That said, it is a
very dangerous command,
because if I do something like
this, it will not prompt you.
It will be gone.
And it happens pretty frequently,
and even in higher level CS courses.
Sometimes we'll see
something where someone
says I accidentally our rm rf-ed my home
directory and all of my P set is gone.
And it's devastating,
but there's no trash can.
There's no there's nothing
for you to retrieve.
It's just gone.
Even worse would be
something like rm -rf/.
So we just discussed
that root directory.
It holds all of the
files on your system.
Things tend to get pretty messy
when you remove things like ls,
and cd, and all of those.
>> AUDIENCE: What's the difference
between rm, rf, and rm*
ROB BOWDEN: So rm*--
>> ALLISON: Question was what's the
difference between rm, rf, and rm*.
>> ROB BOWDEN: So rm*.
Star in general means all of
the contents of this directory.
Trying to think of other
ways of showing star.
Well, star actually generally
means match any pattern.
So if I have a file called dog1,
touch dog2, touch cat1, touch cat2.
So ls*1 is going to print cat1 and
dog1, because that star can be filled
in with-- the one needs to be there,
but star can be either cat or dog.
It's a wild card.
That's the word I'm looking for.
Wild card.
Or I could ls dog*, and
I'm got to see dog1, dog2.
So those are listing the files
that match that particular pattern.
You can use ls in this way.
>> Ls* star matches anything.
So it's going to print all of
the contents of this directory
since all of them match.
It's not going to print anything
in upper level directories.
If I have a sub directory, foo, and
touch 1 2 3-- so now if rm* star,
remove cat1, cat2, dog1, dog2.
Cannot remove foo.
It is a directory.
>> So star expands to all the
files in the directory.
So technically rm* is like saying
rm cat1, cat2, dog1, dog2, foo.
Whereas rm -rf, technically star would
accomplish what we want, but rm -rf--
if I go out of this
directory, rm -rf temp,
that's going to go into temp and
recursively remove everything.
>> So star is separate in that that
is understood by-- so this thing
that I'm running in, this thing
that is prompting me for commands
and then executing and doing
them, I call this my shell.
And so this shell is itself a program.
And if I wanted, I
could run in /bin/bash.
The shell is called bash.
And now we notice something
has slightly changed,
and that's because my settings for
the shell are somewhat different.
>> But now I'm technically running
a shell within my original shell,
and I can exit that shell, and now
I'm back to my top level shell.
The purpose of saying
that is-- the star.
So the star is something
understood by bash.
So rm -rf, -rf flag is
understood by just rm.
It knows that when you
pass a -rf that you
want it to recursively remove
all files without prompting.
The star is something understood
by bash that when you say rm*,
bash isn't going to say
hey rm*, remove star.
Bash is going to say rm*
remove cat1, cat2, dog1, dog2.
It's automatically going to expand
all of the files in the directory.
>> And similarly tilde is another
symbol that bash understands.
When you say cd ~, bash expands
that to your home directory.
Other questions so far?
OK so we're going to start going quick.
>> Tab completion.
Just to throw it out there.
A lot of people don't
realize this exists.
So if I type cd dow, I
want to go into downloads.
I do not need to type nloads.
I can just hit Tab.
So it recognizes that
dow is a prefix that
doesn't match anything
else in this directory,
so it will complete that for you.
Now I can enter.
>> I also do that recursively.
So mkdir foo.
Let's go into foo.
mkdir bar.
So going back to my home
directory, I can see downloads.
Now hitting tab again,
automatically going to fill in foo.
It's the only directory.
Hitting tab again, automatically
going to fill in bar.
So now I'm in (~Downloads/foo/bar).
>> So this tab completion,
whenever I got to office hours,
and I'm standing over
someone's shoulder,
and they're going rm
D-O-W-N-L-O-A-D-S, I'm dying.
Just tab, tab, tab, tab.
So definitely used tab.
And similarly up and
down, a lot of people
just that happened to
never have hit up and down.
It'll go through the previous
commands, so if you just ran something,
and you want to run it again,
just hold up till you get to it.
OK.
>> So quick, some other things.
Let's go back into temp.
Let's create some files.
So in here, I'm just
going to list some words.
dog, cat, meow.
Let's do dog, fish.
So now rep is a very
useful commands that you
use to search throughout
files for a particular text,
and technically you can do really
complex expressions for it to match.
>> So here, if I grep, and what
do I want to search for?
Let's say I'm searching for cats, and
I want to search all of these files.
So how do I do all of these files?
Star.
So in file one, I have cat.
I probably could have
called it something better,
because that looks like
line numbers or something.
But in file one I have a line with cat.
In file two I have a line with cat.
So now I can look inside file one and
see oh yeah, that file did have cat.
Notice file three was not matched
because cat isn't in there.
I can grep for meow.
Only file two has meow.
>> So this you can combine,
again, with -r, which
as I said before
frequently means recursive.
And so I can come up here, grep -r
for any instance of-- let's edit
this one just to throw a cat in there.
So grep -r for any instance of
cat throughout this directory.
And it will recursively
search any subdirectories.
So in baz, there's cat.
In temp/2, there's cat.
And in temp/1 there's cat.
So that's searching within files.
>> Now you can also use a find.
And so find is specifically about
looking for files with a given name.
So let's make some more.
Let's go into downloads.
Touch dog1.
Touch cat2.
Touch cat_dog.
Touch catcat.
>> So I want to find all
files with dog in the name.
So find, and for the longest
time I never remembered
how find worked, until I finally
read something that made it so clear.
So find, automatically recursive.
You don't need to pass a -r.
So find dot.
We haven't talked about dot yet.
Whereas dot dot always
means one directory up.
Dot always means the current directory.
So I could rm -r dot in the
same way I can rm -rf *.
Ultimately they
accomplish the same thing.
rm -rf dot is going to remove
the entire current directory.
>> OK, which I don't want to do there.
But find dot.
So recursively search the current
directory, and now everything
after this are a bunch of flags that you
use to exclude things from the return.
So find dot returns everything that it
can find from the current directory.
Those are all the files
recursively searching.
We'll see some of those in a second.
>> But in case you're wondering how I do
that, so Command K, at the very least
in my terminal in the Mac clears it.
Control L generally clears
it for any sort of terminal.
You can also type clear.
And if you ever get
into a weird scenario--
it's happened to me a couple time--
where the colors of your prompts
are all messed up, or you
aren't able to see anything
being typed when you're typing, because
sometimes like background color is set
the same as the foreground color
and now you can't see the fonts.
Reset is something that just resets
you to the default black background,
white front, or whatever
you set them to.
>> So where were we?
Find dot.
So now everything past this
point restricts the results
to something that matches
the given pattern.
So here I want to search
everything with the name cat.
I got nothing.
Why is that the case?
Well, I'm just searching for
something with exactly the name cat.
If I want to search something
that has some pattern, and cat--
the quotes technically aren't necessary,
but I'm throwing them in there.
So now it finds catcat because
that's the only thing that
has some arbitrary
pattern followed by cat.
I can put cat*, and now
find catcat, cat_dog, cat2,
because those are all things with cat
at the beginning followed by anything.
You can combine this.
If you want to search for all C files
that you have, you might do *.c.
We have blah.c here.
So that's a find works.
You can search.
It has a whole bunch of flags
for further restrictions.
And one on them, let's say -d.
So deprecated.
Oh, that's not what I want.
Not -d.
Type d.
So find dot - type d.
So what that just did is I'm searching
for all files in the current directory
with a-- d stands for
directory-- directory type.
This returns all directories
in the current directory.
And type F is all regular
files, all non directories.
So that's just an
example of other ways you
can restrict the search other
than just the name of the file.
>> It's been 30 minutes.
Still going.
>> ALLISON: I'll breeze through.
It'll be fine.
>> ROB BOWDEN: So some other things.
Now bang, exclamation mark.
So that generally means--
well, let's see an example.
So !f, what is that going to do?
Well it seems to have
repeated find dot -type f.
What about !g?
That just grep -r cat*.
So bang you can use to repeat
a recently done command.
So if I type !gre, it's going to re-run
the commands that began with gre most
recently.
>> And you can see all these
commands with history.
So history.
These are all the
commands I've run today.
And well, it's not literally
restricted to today,
but I've only used this
appliance as of today.
It's your entirety of the
history of your bash shell,
except it cuts off at some point.
AUDIENCE: What happens if you do
history [INAUDIBLE] command and an error
in the result will still print the--
>> ROB BOWDEN: Yeah, if there is an
error in one of these commands--
so let's say, that is an
error command not found.
Still appears in the history.
All right.
Other questions on anything?
So that's bang.
>> Now, really useful command, man.
So that gives you the
manual for a given command.
So let's say man ls, so
this is showing me ls.
It lists directory contents.
And this is where I see that there
are these various flags that exist.
So we see that ls -l exists
if we were to read that. ls -l
gives me this full listing of the
directory with who owns the file,
the size of the file, the
the modified timestamp.
So ls -a is another one that you might
actually use somewhat frequently.
-al is my most common flag this past ls.
>> So -a, notice there's a lot
more files than just ls.
ls -a.
What's in common with all these files?
They start with a dot.
So this is a convention in Linux that
files that begin with a dot are hidden.
So it just means that
when we just straight ls,
or we're searching this directory using
the finder equivalent, or the Windows
Explorer equivalent, that we
don't want to see these dot files.
They just pollute the view of things.
So they are hidden
unless you specifically
request them with something like -a.
So I can cd into .local, and I see
that that is itself a directory with
a shared directory, and
applications, and blah blah blah.
So dot, files they're just hidden.
>> OK, so other important ones.
I have a couple I can skip.
Let's just real quick talk about
the file redirection things.
So there's a whole complex series
of things you can do with these,
but just to see them, let's say, echo.
Another command.
Really dumb command.
All it does is print what I tell it to.
So echo hello.
It just echoed hello to the screen.
Hello world.
Echoes hello world.
>> So one command or one
symbol that bash understands
is this greater than symbol, and
that is the output to a file symbol.
So if I output this to
foo, there's now a file
called foo, inside of
which is hello world.
So notice that when I echo
hello world pipe into foo,
it didn't echo hello world.
Instead it was put into file foo.
And another command just
to throw it at you, cat.
That's an easy way to just completely
list the contents of the file
so that I don't have to open
a text editor to view it.
So the contents of the
foo file are hello world.
And I could cat blah.c,
the contents are this.
>> Again, these are commands that, don't
expect you have them all memorized.
The idea is you've seen them.
Maybe you're working on
something, and you're
like I'm sick of opening this file.
I wish I could just look
at the contents real quick.
You could do that, then
look back and say oh I
remember something like
that exists, and it's cat.
>> So that is going to a file.
Now there isn't really any good
example of reading from a file yet.
What's something that takes
something from standard in?
Any simple Linux command?
When we get to it, in a couple
weeks all the piece-- well,
this week you have a piece where you
start taking input from the user.
And so usually you type
that input at the keyboard.
Instead of typing that
input at the keyboard,
you can instead pipe in from a file
so that when you do Mario, ./mario,
pipe in from any given file, and
that's going to run the mario program.
Not expecting input at
the keyboard, instead it's
just going to read the
lines from the foo file.
>> So greater than foo puts it into
the foo file, and less than foo
takes stuff from the foo file and
uses that as input to this program.
And just to see it, we could also echo
foo bar baz, and then instead of one
greater than, let's do two into foo.
What does that do?
It just appends to the file.
So instead notice if I do echo blah into
foo and then cat foo, it's just blah.
So when you output to a file, it
completely overwrites that file.
If you just want to append,
double [? grader. ?]
>> And last is pipe.
Pipe Gets much more complicated, where
it takes the output of one command
and feeds it into the next command.
So some common thing, history.
So, ugh, I don't want to look at this.
Show me all commands in my history
where I grep-ed for something.
No, that's confusing.
Show me all commands where I find.
All find commands I ever ran.
>> So history.
Now history outputs to the
screen this list of commands,
but I don't want to
output it to the screen.
Instead I'm going to pipe it into grep.
So let's grep for all instances of find.
So now instead of grep taking
the input, instead of--
grep is able to handle as input-- we're
using grep slightly differently here.
So instead of typing the list of
things we wanted to search for
and said grep is taking as input.
So if I do just grep find, it
waits for me to type things.
So cat hello find.
Hello.
Find.
Notice every time I type find
it recognizes that I typed find.
So instead of this, will
search files for find.
>> So history is now going to
output a list of all commands.
We're putting that output,
and we're feeding it to grep,
and so it's spitting out
all instances of find.
The reason I said it'd be confusing
is if I-- it's still confusing.
If I grep for grep.
Notice it's pretty much always
showing the command I just
ran because that command
itself has grep inside of it.
>> OK, so any questions on anything?
And I'll transfer it over at this point.
Hopefully this is a nice
overview of all commands
that you don't need to have
memorized, but these make up
a solid 95% of what I
do at the command line.
Also keep in mind that the command line
itself, bash is a programming language,
and so when you get down to it, you
might want to do really complex things.
And so it has things like
loops, and ifs, and all of those
that you're going to get used to
with your programming languages.
But that is beyond the
scope of this section.
OK, so no questions?
ALLISON: None?
GABRIEL: Are you going to--
ALLISON: I can do it
on mine if you want.
We can see what happens.
ROB BOWDEN: Off to Allison.
ALLISON: Woo.
You're a hard act to follow, Rob.
Do you want me to switch with you?
Or you got, OK.
I'm going to try and not
quite be as lengthy there.
Let's see if this will
work the way I want it to.
Maybe?
Haha!
Yes.
>> So I'm just going to very quickly go
through variables, loops, conditionals,
and a little bit on the compiler.
If you have questions at
any time, please stop me.
These guys will remind me to repeat
your question in case I forget,
but shouldn't be too bad.
>> So variables, yeah.
We have no one of your
Scratch pieces here.
I'm sure most of you, if
you had some sort of game
that you created with Scratch, you had
to keep track of something like score,
or time, or something like that.
So those bright orange
pieces that we see there
are just the Scratch form of
variables, and you will definitely
be using variables
throughout your programs.
If you're not, I'm not really
sure what you're doing.
>> But anyway, big thing,
defining variables.
With C every variable has
to have a type declared,
so I gave you a very
general one at the top.
So you'll have your
type and then whatever
you decide to call your variable.
So in this case, type
in your variable list.
>> We have three examples.
Char of some grade,
of an A, which is what
I'm sure you all want
to get in this class.
You can define multiple
variables on one line
as long as they're all the same type,
which is our second example there
where you have three
variables, x, y, and z.
They're all floats.
And then you can also, in this last
example with int score and number
of teams, you can
initialize them right there.
>> So in the middle example where we
just have float of x, y, and z,
those are not initialized yet.
They have no value.
Or they have garbage values.
And if you try and use them,
the compiler will yell at you.
You have to both declare and
initialize your variables.
So in this last one, we're doing both.
We are declaring variables
of score and number of teams,
and we are initializing them, giving
them their initial values of 7 and 4
respectively.
Cool.
Everyone good?
Awesome.
>> OK, so some conventions.
If you guys have read
through style 50, these
are just things that we'd like for
you to implement in your style.
So meaningful names.
If you start calling things
just x, y, and z, especially
as you get into lengthier
programs, you're
probably going to
confuse yourself and be
like what is this variable referring to.
I have no idea what this means.
>> So if it's meant to hold
a score, call it score.
If it's meant to hold some answer
or result, give it a name like that.
For loops, which we will
get into in the next slide,
single letter variables are fine.
ROB BOWDEN: I, j, and k are
just conventions for for loops
that everyone expects them
to be called i, j, and k.
You can call them-- I see row
column or row call sometimes
for two nested loops, and
that's also kind of standard.
But i and j is completely understood.
>> ALLISON: Yeah, i and
j you're totally fine.
For sake of clarity like
in some of your P sets,
it might make sense to have more
descriptive things in there just
to keep track of it.
But I think i, j, and k I think
the vast majority of us all use.
>> ROB BOWDEN: With these
conventions, so style is important.
It's one of the four axes
on which you're graded,
and it is so easy to just go over
your P set at the end and make sure
that there aren't stylistic mistakes.
So make sure you're tabbing correctly.
Make sure your variables are named.
Leave some comments.
It is very easy to get those points.
You don't have to think about
anything in order to get those points.
You don't have to figure anything out.
It's just making it look pretty.
>> ALLISON: In fact, we
have style 50, which
will tell you where you're messing
up if you're messing up on style
and will tell you exactly what you
need to fix and how you need to fix it.
It's also just good to mention
that it's course policy
that if you're at office
hours and your code is a mess,
we can decline to help
you until it looks nicer.
So start out right,
keep consistent style,
you're also just going to make
your lives a whole lot easier when
you're trying to go through debug.
If you're trying to figure out
where you're missing a curly brace
and they are all over the place, you're
just making your own life harder.
So be consistent with style.
I promise it'll make your life easier.
It'll make our lives easier.
Everyone will be much happier.
And that's what you want.
GABRIEL: Your grade will be higher.
ALLISON: Yes, and your grade.
If your TF's like you,
tends to be favorable.
All right, and then just
the second point here.
Consistent initializations.
So as we saw, you can declare
and initialize things.
Multiple variables on the same line.
One thing we would like you not
to do is to declare some variables
and not initialize them on the same
line that you are initializing others.
>> So in case that made
no sense whatsoever,
we have the example here
where we're declaring ints
in variables of quarters
dimes and pennies,
but quarters and pennies
have no initial value.
We haven't initialized them,
but right in the middle there
we already initialized dimes to 0.
So either do quarters, dimes, pennies.
Or do quarters equal 0.
Dimes equal 0.
Pennies equal 0, or whatever
those initial values are.
>> Big thing with style, be consistent.
When in doubt, be consistent.
But follow our style guide too.
Cool.
Everyone good there?
>> AUDIENCE: Where's the style guide?
ALLISON: The style guide
is on-- what's the website?
>> GABRIEL: I think it's manual.cs50.net/--
ALLISON: Style?
>> GABRIEL: Style.
Yep.
>> ALLISON: Yes.
So question, where is style 50.
manual.cs50.net/style.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: If we're defining
variables, is it OK
if we put like [INAUDIBLE] like
int score and then int goal.
So would you say that now we've
got to define them together?
>> ALLISON: So question, should
you have redundant code
when you are defining
variables such as int score and
on the next line int game?
ROB BOWDEN: There are definitely
cases where redundant code is bad.
I would not consider
that redundant code.
I almost never declare multiple
variables on the same line ever.
And if anything, it's because
usually I leave some sort of comment
explaining what the variable is for.
So I'll say int score slash slash.
Keeps track of whatever.
In total slash slash.
So it's much grosser in that way
to put them all on the same line.
I just never put them on the same line.
>> ALLISON: I feel like it's
personal preference at this point.
>> AUDIENCE: Does that go for
for loops and stuff too?
ROB BOWDEN: Like inside?
Like int i equals 0 comma
length equals something?
That you don't have a choice.
With for loops the initialization
part-- so you might have only seen
int i equals 0 semicolon i less
than whatever semicolon i plus plus.
That int i equals 0,
technically you can also
do what we saw before
with the comma syntax.
int i equals 0 comma j
equals 3 comma k equals 5.
You don't have a choice to split
that up into multiple lines,
and that's standard.
Seeing it there is fine.
ALLISON: Awesome.
Well, convenient segue into loops.
So yeah, here we have some examples
of loops that you guys saw in Scratch.
And of course all of these
can just be recreated in C.
And they basically allow you
to repeat some section of code
until a certain condition
is met, which we'll
get into right after talking
about loops with conditionals.
>> So we have three main types.
For, while, and do while, which
we will all go through right now.
So first one is for loops.
So for some condition,
execute this block of code.
We have this cool little
diagram here at the bottom.
But basically you have in
your for, that first line,
you're going to
initialize your variables.
>> So as we talked about, i is
equal to 0 or i is equal to 10.
Whatever you need that
variable to be it's
going to be initialized there,
declared and initialized to some value.
So then we have some
condition that's going
to be checking our
variable against something.
So in the case the typical case where
maybe you want this section of code
to execute five times.
So we'd have int i equals 0, and we
want it to be when i is less than 5.
So that condition is just
going to check that every time.
If that condition
evaluates to true, it's
going to run the code, which is exactly
what this little diagram is showing.
>> And so it executes it.
It updates a variable,
which is what we see
in the last part of our for
loop initialization there.
So it'll just keep doing this
until that condition is not met,
and then it will exit
the loop and continue
moving on with the rest of your program.
Everyone good there?
Cool.
>> So here's an example, very similar
to something I just talked about.
So we just want to print
this is CS50 10 times.
So you see here we have
our for, and then we
initialize the variable
i to be equal to 0.
Our condition is checking
that it's less than 10.
So evaluate to true when we first
start, and then updates our variable
each time that it actually executes
and prints out this is CS50.
And will terminate after 10 times.
Cool.
>> So while loops are up next.
And as you see here, we just have
some while this condition-- question?
>> AUDIENCE: How can I jump
actually just not one number,
but two numbers [INAUDIBLE]
i plus plus plus?
>> ALLISON: So the question was how can you
update your variable by more than one
at a time.
So i plus plus will
update by one each time.
If you wanted to update it by
two, you could do i plus equals 2.
>> ROB BOWDEN: Have you seen
plus equals in lecture yet?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> ALLISON: It's effectively the
same thing as i equals i plus 2.
So it's going to take it and
update it by two each time.
Plus equals is just something
we call syntactic sugar.
ROB BOWDEN: Yeah, those exist for
pretty much all arithmetic operators.
So i times equal to
would double the number.
j divide equals 3 is the same
as j equals j divided by 3.
>> ALLISON: Or minus equals 2 would
decrement i by two each time.
ROB BOWDEN: Even mod equals.
You haven't seen bitwise operators,
but caret equals and ampersand equals,
all of those exist.
>> ALLISON: So a lot of times, especially
with your first couple of P sets,
you'll be probably incrementing by
one, so i plus plus, j plus plus
are all things you're going
to typically be using.
But that update condition is
fully within your control.
You can update it by whatever increments
or in whatever way you decide to.
Maybe you even want it to be
a random number sometimes.
But yes, there are lots of
things you can do with that.
You're not restricted to i plus plus.
>> ROB BOWDEN: Just so you
know it exists, it also
exists in another form, plus plus i.
So if you're ever searching online
and happen to see plus plus i,
pretty much means the same thing.
ALLISON: Cool.
Good?
Awesome.
So while loops.
Very similar.
You have some condition.
The main thing to notice
here is instead of having
three different parts
to set up, we have one.
We just have some condition
that's being checked.
And in the same way, as long as
that condition evaluates to true,
your code is going to run.
And if it's false, it
will terminate, move
onto the next part of your program.
So this is kind of like-- what's
a good example of checking
for some normal condition?
GABRIEL: While true.
ALLISON: You could do while true.
Well, 1 is equal to 1.
>> ROB BOWDEN: You can do while--
just instead of using a for loop,
you can always code a
for loop in a while loop,
so i greater than 0 or
while i less than 10.
>> ALLISON: Awesome.
And then we have do while loops, which
is great for user validation, where
you want to get something from
your user, see if it's valid,
and then continue from there.
So one of the things to know is with a
do while is that it's going to execute,
and then it will re-execute
if this condition is met.
>> So probably the best way to do this
is just to see an example here.
So as I just mentioned, user
validation is really useful--
or do whiles are really
useful with user validation.
So this is just going
to re-prompt some user
until they enter a positive number,
which might be useful for your P set
this week.
And so in this case, when we
initially run this program,
it's going to print
enter a positive number.
It's going to get some
input from the user,
and then it's going to check
that input against the condition
that you've set for it.
>> So in this case it's going to check.
It's going to say, OK,
is our input negative,
or is it 0 or negative,
which would be invalid.
So then it would re-prompt.
Question?
>> AUDIENCE: Is this the same then as a
while loop if you just copied that code
and put it [INAUDIBLE] while loop?
>> ALLISON: So question was would
this be the same as just a while
loop if we were to just
copy the while loop above.
So in this case, your while loop is
going to check the condition first.
So in this case, if we tried
to write as just a while loop,
it would say while
input is less than one.
But we don't have an input for it.
>> AUDIENCE: If you [INAUDIBLE]
while loop including this code,
but then you coped the code
above the while loop also.
You just had this code
[INAUDIBLE] while loop.
ALLISON: It would be
the same thing, yes.
So you could just write--
instead of having a do-- yes.
GABRIEL: But that's more elegant.
ALLISON: Yeah, that's more elegant.
You can get into design and whatnot,
but yes, you can totally do that.
Any other questions?
OK, cool.
>> So we've talked a lot about conditions
with all these loops that we have,
so we're actually getting into
conditions in Boolean expressions.
Again, you use these in C,
so just kind of transitioning
from more graphic interface
to actually coding.
>> Cool, so big one, if.
Basically just allows us to introduce
some logic into our program and check
sys conditions.
So in this case, OK,
is n greater than 0?
Yes it is, so you can execute this.
It's just checking some
condition that you've
set, which I think we're all
comfortable with checking conditions.
Cool.
So if else is your other one,
you can say OK, if this is true,
do this first thing.
Otherwise I want you to
default and do something else.
Like in this case, you either pick a
positive number or a negative number.
You only have two options.
You need it to execute regardless
of what your user inputs.
So you can say well,
is it greater than 0?
Cool.
Print a positive number.
If it's not, print a negative.
Everyone good?
>> And then one thing to recognize is
that if the if condition is met,
the else will never also execute.
Only one of these will
execute at a time.
So it's a trade off.
You don't get to have both.
You either have the first condition.
You either have the if
or the else, not both.
Which then can make things
even more complicated,
because you can do if,
else it, and then else.
So in this case, we
have three conditions.
And again, only one of these is
going to end up being executed.
So you might be wondering
well, what if you
have something that
can meet two of these.
Maybe whatever you're inputting
meets both the condition
for if and the else if.
Only thing that's going to run
>> ALLISON: As soon as it finds something
that it meets the condition for that
evaluates to true, that's what
it's going to run and nothing else.
So if you had is this number
between 0 and 5 for your first one,
or is this number between 3
and 5 for the else if part,
and you input the number--
I said 0 and 5 and-- 4.
It's going to hit the first one.
It's going to say OK, this
number is between 0 and 5.
Execute and leave.
It will never hit that second option.
Cool?
Awesome.
>> OK we also have switch statements if
you want to get even more-- or sorry,
switch is next.
I'm getting ahead of myself here.
Again, multiple if blocks
where as I just said
is as soon as you find a condition
that's met and an if else if else,
it leaves.
If you need to check
multiple things, you're
going to want to use this because
it will check every time here.
So this will run through and if
it's greater than or equal to 90,
it's going to print that.
And it will run through and
check every single one of these.
>> AUDIENCE: So this would be
more buggy than [INAUDIBLE].
Would this be like [INAUDIBLE]?
>> ALLISON: The question is would this be
buggy or does this do what you want.
It really depends on what
you want from your program.
>> AUDIENCE: I mean like if you put 90 in.
ALLISON: If you put 90--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
GABRIEL: You're going to get two things.
ALLISON: You're going to get two things.
Yes, two.
>> ROB BOWDEN: Two?
>> ALLISON: No.
>> ROB BOWDEN: Four.
If you put 90, it's going to say you
got an A, you got a B, you got a C,
you got a D.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ALLISON: Right.
So I depends on what you
want from you program.
Sometimes you need to
check multiple things.
You'll get much deeper into what
good design is as you go forward.
The important thing to
realize is that this
will check all four conditions here.
Whereas if this were an if else if else
if else, it would hit that first case,
it would print you got an A and be done.
>> ROB BOWDEN: Even if we
decided to change this to if
and greater than or equal to 90,
if and greater than or equal to 80,
and less than or equal to 89, if
n greater than or equal to 70,
and n less than or equal to
79, so that will be correct.
That will do what we want, but
it still checks every single it.
>> So whereas in the first scenario, if we
enter 90 with just if else if else if,
and we enter 90, then
it's going to correct.
It will check the first
one, print you got an A,
skip everything, because it
already found one that works.
All cases are mutually exclusive
based on if else if else if.
So it'll execute the
first if, then it's done.
It'll go to the end.
>> Whereas if we change
this to be what I was
saying with less than or equal to 89.
It's going to check the first one.
It'll print.
It'll check the second one.
It's not going to print.
Check the third one.
Not going to print.
Check the fourth one.
Now going to print.
So in that case, the else if
version, since these cases
are mutually exclusive, it's
better use if else if else if,
because that is going to have
fewer checks of the conditions
than this version.
ALLISON: Awesome.
So another thing we can
do is switch statements.
Basically a switch statement
takes in some variable,
in this case it's n, and
determines which case to execute.
So this is also one where your cases
should be kind of mutually exclusive.
So in this case, if
we we get a one, it's
going to match whatever that
variable-- whatever the value of n
is to one of these cases, so 1, 2, or
3, and print out the corresponding line.
>> And then if you notice here,
we also have a default,
which you can of think of as your else.
So if you pick any other number
besides 1, 2, and 3 in this case
it's just going to print invalid.
Deciding when to use ifs versus
if elses versus switches is going
to be something that you guys will
see design wise as you start writing
more complicated programs, and
there's no hard and fast rules
of when to use them.
It really depends on your context.
>> ROB BOWDEN: And just
to throw it out there
since it is more comfortable section.
Switches, they tend to
be-- so you're limited
in the number of ways you
can use them, because ifs,
the condition can be pretty
much anything you want.
With switches the cases
have to be numbers,
or technically they can be chars, but
chars, as we'll see, are just numbers.
So they have to be numbers, but switches
are really more efficient than if
else if else if, because even
taking the example before-- well,
the grade example seems good.
>> Well let's say here, we instead do
this as an if else if else if scenario.
So if n equals equals 1,
print you picked a low number.
If else if n equals equals 2,
you picked a medium number.
Else if equals equals 3, high.
Else invalid.
>> So let's say that was our scenario.
So let's say we enter
4, so we expect invalid.
The way that if else if else
if approach is going to work is
checks the first condition.
It's not satisfied.
So we check the second condition.
Check the third condition.
Not satisfied.
So we go to the else and print invalid.
>> The way the switch works
is it compiles down
into what we're going
to call a jump table.
The main idea being
that when you enter 4,
it can immediately go to the default.
It doesn't need to check am I case 1?
Nope that's not it.
Case 2?
Nope.
Case 3?
Default.
OK, this must be where I
want, and then execute that.
No, it immediately jumps to the default.
Or it I enter 2, it's
immediately going to go to the 2
without needing to go through case 1.
>> So in that way,
realistically nowadays that's
not that much of an efficiency gain.
Usually computers are pretty
fast, and that's not that great.
But it is the case that
switches are faster.
If you're really trying
to optimize, use a switch.
>> ALLISON: Cool.
And then we have ternary operator.
So I know I mentioned earlier
the word syntactic sugar.
So it's just things that make
your code much more concise.
So this is one of those cases.
>> So ternary operator is question mark
colon as we see in the line string
s equals n greater than 100
question mark high colon low.
So basically how this works is it's
the n greater than 100 is a condition.
So I think it can make sense.
It's like asking a question.
It's saying oh, is n greater than 100.
Who knows?
And if it evaluates to
true, it's going to give you
the first thing that's
listed there, which is high.
Otherwise it's going to give you low.
So this is just a really simple and
efficient way to do like an if else.
That's all this is.
>> And if we were to write this
as an if else conditional,
it would be if n is greater
than 100, return high.
Else, return low.
This is just a much more
concise way of writing it.
>> ROB BOWDEN: So this particular example
is whenever you're doing something
like this, this is the pattern
where I use ternary very frequently.
So we haven't talked about scope yet,
but I hate seeing string s semicolon.
If n greater than 100, s equals high.
Else, s equals low.
So that pattern, those five lines
of code literally 100% of the time
can be transferred into what
was up there with a ternary.
So the ternary, one line of code.
The if else, five.
That's an example I point
out every single time.
This would great place
for a ternary operator.
It's so clean.
But people tend to never use it.
>> ALLISON: Take it away Gabe.
>> GABRIEL: So now you guys all
learned in lecture this week
that everything in a
computer is binary, right?
Just like the lamps here.
You can be either turned on and off.
And by everything, I mean
literally everything.
Some numbers, and chars, and strings,
and even the code that you write when
it gets compiled to machine
code and stuff like that,
so it all boils down to 0's and 1'.
>> And so when we're dealing
with integers, which
is something that's technically very
simple, we should be able to do stuff
like adding them, which is
probably one of the simplest things
you can do to two integers, right?
So addition and subtraction works just
like it works in decimal notation,
except here it's binary, right?
So it's in base two.
So add 1 plus 1.
That gives 0, and 1 carries over.
And just keep doing that, So now
comes the more interesting question.
>> We know how to represent all
positive integers in the computer,
but let's make this an exercise.
Pretend you guys are all in 1960 or
something trying to create a computer,
and you have to come up of
a way of storing minus 1,
for example, or minus any
integer for that matter.
How would you do that?
Any ideas?
Just throw anything at me.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] designate
a special if your [INAUDIBLE].
>> GABRIEL: You can designate a
special bit, which will be 0 or 1.
Let's say one if it's positive
and 0 if it's negative.
And then the rest of the bit
is just to store the number.
Cool.
So that's a very good idea.
We have, I don't know, 200.
And if the first bit is
turned on, then it's plus 200.
If it's turned off, it is minus 200.
Cool.
>> There is only one small
problem with this,
which is if we try to sum things up.
So imagine we have 11111 here, and
we're summing this with 00100 whatever.
If those two are positive, that's fine.
But then if one of
them is negative, like
let's say that this bit here
is the one that's responsible
for-- I'm going to make a separate--
so this one means that this number here
is positive.
This one means that this
number here is negative, right?
>> But then when you're
going to sum them, you
need an if statement
saying oh if this is 0,
then my sum will be
something different, right?
So there's a slightly
more clever way to do
that, which is called two's complement.
So basically what we
do is we define minus 1
to be the thing that if
we add up to 1 gives us 0.
Let me repeat that.
So let's say that this here is 1.
What is the thing that
naturally in positive integers
added to that gives us 0?
What if we try to add it to this number?
We're going to have-- OK, so let's add.
We're going to have 1 plus 1
is 0, and then it carries over.
And then we're going to get 0 again.
I'm getting confused.
And you're going to get 0 and
0 and 0 and 0 and 0 and 0.
Lots of 0's.
>> At the very last one, we're not
going to be able to carry it over,
because let's say we're only dealing
with one byte, so only 8 bits.
So what the computer does by default
is just forgets about that [INAUDIBLE],
OK?
So this is what is called
the two's complement.
We simply define minus 1 to be the
thing here that if you add that to 1
would give you 0.
And that's pretty cool
because we don't really
need late to implement
a different type of sum
depending on whether that's a
negative or a positive number.
Does that make sense?
>> So one thing that we do
here in order to convert
between a positive and a negative
integer is then we flip everything,
and then we add 1 to that number.
If you try to do it yourself
on a piece of paper,
you're going to see that makes sense.
But if I take this number
here, this is five.
So if I flip everything
here, so 1, 1, 1, 1, 1.
Flip, flip, flip.
And then I add 1 to it.
I'm going to have exactly minus 5.
OK?
>> This kind of makes sense because if
you try to sum this with the number
that we had before, which
was-- let's flip this again.
It was 101 and lots of 0's.
If you try to add these
two numbers together,
you're going to have exactly 0.
OK.
Any questions?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> GABRIEL: What do you mean?
>> AUDIENCE: Negative to
positive [INAUDIBLE].
>> GABRIEL: No, you flip
and you add 1 always.
Yeah.
OK, so characters also encoded binaries.
We have ASCII table, as you
also saw in lecture, right?
So it's basically a mapping of things.
And here I can't emphasize enough
that for a computer, a and 65
are literally the same thing.
So if I write something like char c
equals a, I could at the same time
just write 65 here, and it
would be exactly the same, OK?
There's no difference whatsoever.
>> We usually tend to put
characters in variables of type.
Char, not because they're essentially
made for that, but because
of human convention.
But you can just deal with integers
instead of variables of type char,
and you'll be fine.
The only actual difference
between a char c and an int i
is that an int has four bytes in most
systems, while a char has one byte.
They're essentially the
same thing in terms of data.
So what will print here?
Here we're printing a digit using printf
with a plus 1, and just like integers,
chars can be summed, so
characters can also be summed.
So this is exactly 65.
So there's going to be
66, and here we have
65 plus little a minus big A,
which will be, I don't really know.
But it will be exactly the gap
between the capital letters
and and the smaller letters, so
we're going to get small a, right?
Yeah.
So this is going to print a
character which is exactly this one.
Good?
Any questions?
>> Here we have a bunch of different
types for numerical variables.
We already talk about int.
Float is just a way to-- this is really
funny, because when I first learned
to program back in the day with
Python, the first program I ever
tried to write, I saw that there was a
type called in and a type called float.
And the float was for all real numbers.
So then I asked why should
I ever use an int then?
Because if I can use all
real numbers with a float,
I would just stop using ints, right?
Because real numbers are
much like more generic.
>> It turns out that this is
not the case in computers
because they're essentially
different things.
So integers and floats, the
operations that you do to them
are essentially different because
of the way that they are stored, OK?
We're going to talk a little
bit more about that in a second.
>> So double is just a bigger float.
Usually in most systems, a float
is four bytes, just like an int.
And a double is eight bytes.
A long long is actually just a symbol
that you append to a type like int.
You say long long int like this.
Long long int x to make it longer.
So in most systems, that will give
eight bytes instead of the usual four.
And you can actually drop the
in, so it can just say long long,
and that works too, OK?
You can also do other things like
unsigned int, or again just unsigned
would also work.
And that would make x be a variable
like everything is positive,
so you can't really have negative
numbers in the way that we saw up here.
So following wonderful
floating point and precision.
That's one of the reasons why you
want to use ints instead of floats,
because ints are 100% precise, right?
It's exactly that number.
For floating points, if you
say answer equals 1 over 10--
I happen to have this exact
program here, float.c.
That prints to 20 decimal places.
1 divided by 10, and that
usually is 0.1, right?
But here if we make
float and then we run it,
we see that it's not exactly 0.1.
It's 0.149 something.
>> And why is that?
Because you can't really represent every
single possible real number in memory
because there are
uncountably many of them.
So we're technically only able to
represent a finite amount of them
with a finite amount of data.
But it's really interesting.
Now this begs the
question of how you would
go about representing
this with bits, right?
So how are floats stored?
With integers it was easy.
But with floats you want
to maximize the range,
and you want to be able to represent
huge numbers and very tiny numbers like
0.000001 at the same time.
So again, same game.
Does anyone have any idea how we could
go about representing float in memory?
Just throw anything.
Yes, please.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] as
if it was two ints and one
being the [INAUDIBLE] and one being
everything after the decimal point.
GABRIEL: OK, cool.
So two different integers.
You can have 12.45, so that's 12 and 45.
Nice.
What ere you going to say?
The same thing?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] notation
where you separate the base.
>> GABRIEL: Scientific notation,
yeah that's usually what happens.
So this is what is called the mantissa.
That's what is actually the
number, and then the exponent
is just where the comma is, right?
So this is going to be something
of the form 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 times 10
to the minus 4.
I just realized that-- yeah, exactly.
And then this 10 to the minus 4 is
going to define where the comma is, OK?
In Brazil we use comma.
Here you guys use a dot.
So a dot.
>> And this is cool, because then you can
focus lots of your bits on this guy
here, on the mantissa, and then that's
going to be your actual precision.
And you can do this either in decimal
or in the binary based system.
There are different
ways to implement this.
Questions?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: How many places
after the decimal [INAUDIBLE]?
>> GABRIEL: That's a complicated question,
because it's never really 100% precise,
because as you see here, for
some numbers it is 100% precise.
I believe if we put 0.5 here,
it's going to be 100% precise.
It's going to be 0.500000.
So in that case, it's perfect.
But in other cases,
it's much less perfect.
In my experience, like up to four,
five decimal places is pretty precise.
If you use a double, it's going to
be way more precise than that, OK?
>> ROB BOWDEN: So just to throw
some more context at floats,
I never remember 100% how the
spec of floats actually works,
but I do you always remember
that floats start getting messy.
So the idea is that when you get really,
really big numbers or really, really
small numbers, we start
getting worse and worse
at differentiating
between two close floats.
>> So how I like to think about is
with floating point imprecision,
there are two floats that
if I try to specify them
in C, despite the fact that
they're different numbers,
they're going to be
interpreted as the same number,
because we can't store them differently.
We need to use the same bits.
And so when we get to
really, really large numbers,
talking like 10 to the 300 or
something, it's at that point
that 10 to the 300 or
5 times 10 to the 300
can't be differentiated
from 7 times 10 to the 300.
So that's a pretty big difference
between the two numbers.
>> But then when you get down
to the normal range things,
you tend to be pretty
good at differentiating.
And then when you get down really small,
you're also getting pretty bad again.
So like a whole bunch of
0.0000, it gets pretty bad.
GABRIEL: Yeah, so a quick note.
Never do this.
Never try to compare
floats using equals equals,
because even if they're almost the
same, almost the same is not the same.
So what you usually do is you subtract
them, take the absolute value of that,
and see if that's smaller than
0.0001 or something like that, OK?
And cool.
I know a lot of people have
some background in Java,
especially the ones who did
AP computer science, right?
And Java is a language
that mostly based on C,
it has a couple very big differences.
But for loops, and ifs, and stuff like
that, they're all the same syntax.
I have a few programs here to show this.
>> So for example, a simple hello world.
This is hello world in C, which you
guys are definitely familiar with,
and this and this one is in Java.
So in Java we have this
public class, hello world,
and public static void
main, and string args.
The string args are going
to appear in C very shortly.
But let's not go there yet.
Right now we have void here, which means
that main is not take any arguments.
And then we have
system.out.println, the and that's
kind of the equivalent for printf.
Here we don't really need the backslash
n because print ln does that for you.
It appends the backslash
n at the end of the line.
>> But if you go into
something like a for, you
can see that they're
pretty much the same thing.
So initialization, and the
condition, and the update
is-- I missed a space here-- they're
pretty much the same thing, except Java
has as a few more high level stuff.
Here we can do plus I and
Java will automatically
make this i here, which is
an integer, into a string,
and then append the
two strings together.
Here in C we need to do the &%d.
The line here, the for
looks exactly the same.
>> And if we look at if, the ifs
also look exactly the same, right?
So the real big differences are
in those things that you see here.
Public static, void, and
then public class if.
So Java has what is
called a virtual machine.
And it is very heavily based on what
is called object oriented programming,
which is a very, very common
paradigm for programming nowadays.
And this class thing is what you see,
something from object orientation,
is you create a class and then you
can derive objects from that class.
We're not going to talk too
much about that in CS50,
but that's definitely
something really cool,
especially if you want to go into
more sophisticated web development
at the end of the course,
like submit your final project
and some nice frameworks and stuff.
>> So basically the idea is that you
don't want to re-implement something,
so you create something that's
very generic, like the shape,
and then you create
different shapes from it,
and then from each of
these shapes, you create
some more specific shapes in three
dimensions or something like that.
And they have this hierarchy they
inherit from the other ones, so
all functions and all variables that
the big shape here has, all of these
are going to have, and all of these are
going to have, and so on and so forth.
So that's the basic idea.
>> C doesn't have that, but C++
does have that kind of feature.
And Java is heavily influenced
by object orientation,
so that's why you see
class here all the time.
And the other thing is
this Java virtual machine.
So this, I think, is a very smart idea .
So what the folks who
invented java did is
they didn't want to
compile their code twice
if they had to run it in a Windows,
or a Mac, or Linux, so what they do
is they literally run
something like the appliance,
but you don't really see it happening.
So they run a virtual machine
inside of your computer, which
is basically like a
mini operating system.
And that operating
system's purpose in life
is just to run what is called byte code.
>> So instead of in C, the way we would
compile this is make if, and then run
./if.
I forgot the backslash in.
In Java, you would do first
Java C to compile it, if.c.
It's not C. It's dot java.
And then you have to run not ./.
You get this new file
if.class, but you can't really
run if.class now just
like we did before.
This is not an executable.
You have to run.
You have to feed it into
a program called Java,
and that program is the virtual machine,
and then you do if.class, or if.
Yes.
And then it works.
OK so this is kind of the
virtual machine happening.
C does not have that, so if I were to
put this program in a Windows machine,
it would not work in C. In Java it does.
Questions?
Cool.
That's if for super section for today.