>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: All right,
everyone, welcome back to section.
Hopefully you all had a great
Halloween weekend, or Halloweekend,
as I like to say, all
rested and recovered.
And thankfully it's not snowing anymore.
It's actually sunny outside.
I was real happy about that.
Not ready to drag out my winter boots.
Hopefully, pset6 went pretty well.
>> If you are tired of C, I'm happy
to say you're done with C for now.
We have fully transitioned
into web programming,
so you'll be working in HTML, PHP,
maybe a little bit of JavaScript.
I don't know what next week's
pset is, so I can't guarantee
what your next pset will
be, but this week's pset
is CS50 Finance, which is basically
implementing the sort of web page
that allows you to buy and sell
stock, and keep track of them.
And it's pretty cool, because all
of it is dynamically generated.
You can have different users who
each have their own information,
and you're going to be
implementing all of that.
It takes a while.
I definitely think this is easier
than C psets, but it takes longer.
You're learning a new language,
PHP, which is very similar to C,
but of course is going to require
you to look up syntax and understand
how to convert between the languages.
>> But I don't think there's anything
super conceptually hard about this pset.
It's just learning the
new language and getting
through all these little pieces.
If you guys have read through
the spec, it's pretty long.
I think this one is like 21
pages, if I remember correctly.
It's a long spec.
So if you haven't read it-- 22.
32.
>> Wow.
So I was off by 50% there.
So, 32 pages.
So it's long.
There are lots of pieces, but none
of the pieces should be that bad.
It's just a lot.
So definitely get started early
if possible, as per usual,
but I think it should feel a little
nicer than especially the psets like
recover and resize that are just
very hard to wrap your head around.
>> So with that, we're going to dive in.
I don't have your agenda
slide today, but we're
going to be talking about PHP.
I'll be giving you kind of a
crash course on some things
that you might want to know about PHP.
Different syntax things,
things to look out for.
We're going to be talking
a little bit about SQL.
Just very simple things
there, and then also MVC
is Model View Controller, which
is how your pset is set up,
so understanding how that
works will be super useful.
All right.
So PHP.
You guys should have done
something very, very simple
with PHP, which is
this bottom thing here,
where you submitted some form on the
top here that had some name that you
input, and it would say like hello, Ben,
or hello, Allison, and it would pop up.
So this is actually what it
should've looked like from your pset,
in case you guys wanted to know
or didn't quite figure it out.
>> But we have these question marks
here that indicate that this is PHP.
They wrap it, and then
htmlspecialcharge, remember, is just,
make sure that you're safe
from any crazy injection attack
or if someone tries to put
crazy malicious characters
into your name field, it doesn't
like up your server or whatnot.
>> And then if we notice, this HTML
form had a method of $_GET, which,
if we remember our superglobals
from PHP, $_GET, $_POST,
we'll be going into
those in a little bit.
But we know that we have some name
here that corresponds to the name
that we submitted.
So this is just kind of like the
very simple PHP HTML collaboration
that you guys had from pset six.
>> But that doesn't really
answer what is PHP.
Obviously it's a language,
but we haven't really
talked about it in this section,
so there's a little bit more
about what PHP actually is.
So PHP is just PHP
hypertext preprocessor.
>> It's actually considered
a programming language
because it has logic, whereas if
we remember talking about HTML,
we called that a markup language versus
a programming language because HTML
is strictly modifying how
things look on the page.
It's just modifying
whether something's bold,
or whether it's a form,
element, or something like that.
It doesn't have any logic.
It doesn't have loops or conditions.
You can't error check things.
You would either display things
in a certain way or ask for things
from the user.
That's it.
>> So with PHP, it actually does allow us
to do all of these more logical things,
like validate the input or
manipulate it in some way.
We can combine it with HTML, as we just
saw in your last pset and right now,
and it allows us to create
these dynamic web pages.
So if you guys ever-- I don't know if
you were like me, but in middle school
they had us take this IT class where
we created just HTML web pages,
and they were static and click around
to other things, but they never changed.
>> With dynamic ones, what we can
do is, like with CS50 Finance,
you're going to have different users.
Depending on those users'
preferences, and what they're buying
or what they're selling
for their stocks,
you're going to display
different things.
So if there's some
identifying characteristic
for your user using this
web page, we can dynamically
decide what to display for them.
It's not the same thing for every single
person, which if we just had HTML,
the page would be the same for
every single person who visited.
PHP allows us to personalize pages.
>> And then we can either put them in
the same file, which, as in the case
before here, we saw that
we have HTML all here
and then we have this little bit of PHP.
We can do like that,
or with CS50 Finance,
if you guys have looked at the
files-- and we should have time
to step through a couple of them
together at the end of the section-- we
can see how you can
actually keep them separate,
which is actually a better thing to do.
>> So.
Crash course.
All the quick simple things
you might need to know for PHP.
Declaring variables.
That blue's a little annoying,
but hopefully you guys can see it.
If not, I'll write it
on the chalk board.
The declaring variables.
One thing to know is that, unlike C,
PHP is loosely or dynamically typed,
which means that you don't need to
tell a variable what type it is.
You can just simply say some variable
is equal to whatever you want it to,
and it will decide the type of
that variable at run time for you.
>> As you'll see, this can create
some very interesting things.
But for most purposes, you
don't need to specify the type.
You can, and you can type
cast things like you normally
wouldn't see if you want to
force it to be a certain type,
but you don't have to.
It's not going to yell at you
if you just declare a variable
and don't specify a type for it.
>> So in case you can't read
this-- I know it's not the best.
I thought it would show up better-- the
way you initialize any variable is just
with a dollar sign, what
you want it to be called,
and then what you're assigning it.
So in this case, this is some $var = 3.
So if we ever use $var
somewhere, it will just
be the same as putting 3 there.
OK?
>> So, any variable, just
dollar sign, whatever
you want to call your variable,
and whatever you want it to equal.
Little cooler.
Less to write for initializing
a variable, right?
Does that make sense to everyone?
Just quick syntax difference
between C and PHP.
>> Arrays are much cooler in PHP.
We can give them keys.
So the way to think about
it is that, if we ever
wanted to access an
element within an array,
we needed to know the
index of it, right?
So we know that with C, we
could access the first element
by doing array bracket zero, or if we
want the first element, array bracket
one.
And if we wanted something
in there, we might just
have to iterate through, unless
we actually knew the index.
>> One thing that is really
cool with PHP arrays
is that they're what
we call associative.
So we can associate
some key to some value,
and we're actually going
to-- I will show you
how we can use this in a second.
But basically, if you ever want
to initialize an array like that,
you have some $array.
>> So in the same way, it's just
some variable that we're creating.
This could be called
whatever you wanted.
This could be $example.
Just another variable.
What makes it an array is the
bracket syntax that we have here.
Just like normal C. And we
have some key to some value.
So key1 goes to value1,
key2 two goes to value2.
These pairs are separated with a
comma, just like normal arrays.
>> However.
Big one.
Keys are optional.
You don't have to use them.
And if you don't, then it's just normal.
Question?
Or, oh.
>> AUDIENCE: Well, about the right.
Where's the memory coming from?
Can it also be the same like
[INAUDIBLE] and from the stack?
Is that also using PHP?
Like when we're linking them?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
With PHP, We don't tend
to worry about where our
memory's coming from.
We don't spend a lot of
time talking about that,
so it's not really anything
you need to worry about.
So keys are optional.
In the same way, if you don't
want to make this associated,
you just want a normal array where
array zero is the first element
and array one is the second
element, you can do it exactly
as you would in C. You have some
variable that's going to be your array,
and it equals these brackets here.
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: Does it have the
same point to notation.
Like, I can do like a array++,
and that points to the second one.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: You can do--
Well, you can have some iterator, i,
that you can do i++ and do a
array of i in the same way.
But that's it.
So, like in this case,
array of 1 would equal 20.
Same sort of indexing notation.
This is basically just an implicit thing
here, where it says zero, zero to 10,
to 1 to 20, 2 to 30.
It's just implicit keys for it.
What changes with PHP is
that you now have the power
to reassign those keys to
do whatever you'd like.
>> So one thing is here.
So I have just some examples
here that I wrote up for you guys
because I feel like examples always
help more than just the abstract.
So, in this case here, we
have some associative array
that is my first name,
my last name, and I
am echoing, which is just
for all purposes here
going to print out to the output here.
>> And it says, OK.
Print out the value that
corresponds to array at key Allison.
And I can also send you guys
all this code after class.
So, when we run this, what do
you think is going to happen?
What's going to print out?
AUDIENCE: Your last name.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: My last name.
It does.
Right here.
Print out.
So if we were to change this and we
were to add someone else to our list--
So let's say we have Emma here,
and we associate your last name--
Let's see if I spell this right.
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: Good job.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Lovely.
So now if we have this here and
we wanted to find your last name,
you have it there.
So you can just think of it
as replacing this key here.
You're just replacing the index.
So it allows you to just search
through an array much easier.
You don't need to know the index.
As long as this key that you're looking
for exists somewhere in the array,
PHP will find it and it will return
the value associated with it.
So it gives you a lot more
power with your arrays.
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: If you have two keys the
same, will it give you an error?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It
should give you an error, yeah.
Does that make a little
more sense for you guys?
And in the same way, we have an array
here that doesn't have any keys.
Also this is a syntax
that you might want
to be aware of, because you'll
have to use this in your pset.
>> Whenever you're doing an
echo, you have these quotes,
and whenever you're referring
to part of an array,
you have to have these
curly braces around them.
It's kind of annoying, but
you just have to do it.
So just something to keep in mind.
If you're running into errors of,
I know that this exists in my array
but it's throwing errors at me,
try putting braces around it
and it should work.
>> So in this case here, this is a
normal C array that we're used to.
Has three, five, and six, and we just
want to print out the first element,
so this should print out three.
And I did run all these, so
hopefully nothing changed.
We see at the bottom here,
it just prints out three.
Cool.
That make sense for everyone?
Associative arrays.
Much cooler than normal arrays.
>> This is why-- Did David show you
the PHP implementation of pset6
during lecture at all?
OK.
So, I'll show you.
I don't know it off the t--
>> AUDIENCE: He did last week.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Was it last week?
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah.
So speller can be done in like six lines
with PHP, and part of the power of that
is this associative array where
you can just load each word in,
and you have it equal to true or false.
And so you can say, oh.
Return dictionary at some word, and
if it's there, it will return true.
Otherwise, it won't find
it and it'll return false.
So kind of a cool little thing.
>> All right.
So those are associative arrays.
They're pretty cool.
I really like them.
And obviously this-- Ah.
OK.
Now it's working.
Maybe.
OK.
Another thing.
So, with equality, just a
cool thing to keep in mind.
With PHP, because it
is dynamically typed,
the type can change depending on when
you run it, how you're running it.
I actually have some cool
examples that I'll show you guys.
>> But == just checks for
equality after type juggling.
So if you have something that's
like the character 1 and number 1,
PHP would tell you that
those are equal because it
can juggle the types of the
two of them until it's equal,
which maybe for your case is fine.
>> If you need to see if they are the
same kind of value and the same type,
you want this ===.
And I don't think you have any
case where you need to use that
in your pset, but for a lot of
you who will go on to do web pages
for your final projects and things, it's
a good thing to know that == and ===
are different, and it's a good
distinction to understand.
>> OK.
So.
Foreach loops.
They are a way to
iterate through an array.
So, just like arrays became
so much cooler in PHP,
your way to iterate
through an array, I think,
also becomes much cooler
and much more powerful.
So instead of having to create
some for i equals 0 and whatever,
and then update that
i as you go through,
we have this awesome foreach loop.
>> So here's the standard general
structure of these two.
So you either have foreach some array
as the value you want to iterate as.
So this is the name of the array
variable that you want to reference,
and this is what you want
to call it within the loop.
OK?
So this corresponds to
each element of the array,
and you use this value within this loop.
>> I have an example.
I know examples are so much better.
And so this is if there are
no keys, so this is like
if we just have one where the keys
are the normal indices for your array.
Or this is also in the case if
you have no use for the keys.
If you don't care about
the keys and you just
want to iterate through with the values
for each of those in whatever order,
that's fine.
>> You can use the structure.
Otherwise, if there are keys, our
$value just changes to $key value.
So it just changes to a key value pair.
And then we can refer to $key
and $value within our loop.
OK?
So.
Example.
Make it nicer.
OK.
>> So we have this one
here, which we have some
are-- You can also
create an array like this
by having some variable equal
to array with parentheses,
or you can just do bracket.
You should do the bracket, but
this is another way to do it.
So here we have some array of three
elements of one, two, and three,
and we have our foreach.
>> Notice this one corresponds to the
array that we're iterating over,
and this is what we're calling
each thing in our array.
And all this is doing is it's
going to print out each value.
So if we run it, we notice that we
have value one, value two, value three.
>> And in the same way that typically
arrays need to be of one type,
arrays don't have to all
be the same type here.
So now we have some int.
We have two strings.
So your arrays can
get much more powerful
and maybe a little
bit messier, depending
on the way you want to look at it.
So we can change this
to whatever we want.
We use value.
That's just the standard thing we use.
But, just important to know that we can
call this like counter if we wanted.
And as long as they match up,
obviously everyone's happy.
If you ever want to run a PHP
run something like this command
line you know this
here, you just do PHP,
and then whatever file you want to run.
>> So if you want to mess around
with PHP, and more the logic
and you don't really need to
see like in a web browser,
you can just run it in
the command line like that
and echo will print
out whatever you like.
OK.
The other way that we have is like this.
So this is a case where maybe you want
to use both the key and the value,
I know these are like
super contrived examples
but I hope they make
it a little clearer.
So here we have some array
again, but this time,
instead of just having
you know there's no key.
We have keys for each of these.
So a is gonna be one, b will correspond
to two, and c will correspond to three.
And in this case, if
we write it this way,
we have access to both key
and value for each of these.
>> So when we run this,
we get each of those.
So it prints out our keys
and corresponding values.
Another cool thing is that, and I know
said like this one didn't have keys,
but it always implicitly has a
key because if you don't delegate
a key, of course, your
keys are just your indexes
or indices so we could
always also do this one.
Like this.
I will print out.
So in this case, if you notice,
we have our implicit keys
of zero, one, and two here.
>> And the same way with this one,
you can always just say r as value,
and you just have access to the value.
You don't care about your
keys, even if your has keys,
if you don't care about
them, you don't necessarily
need to put them in your foreach loop.
Does that makes sense for everyone?
>> AUDIENCE: Can you just
call the keys, too?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah you
could totally do that, too.
Actually, wait.
Hold on.
would it-- No.
If you want the key, then
you need to do key to value.
AUDIENCE: Add value.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah.
And you just never use value is all.
>> AUDIENCE: OK.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: If you
just put one thing in there,
it's going to assume that you're
talking about the value, not the key.
Great question.
All right.
Cool.
Actually, hold on.
Let me see what I have.
So before we get into post and get, I
just want to show you guys a little bit
about how it's dynamically
typed, which is kind of cool.
I have all these.
I have like four examples up here,
and I will send you all this code
after class.
>> So here we have some variable a.
That's just 1 plus 1, right?
And we're going to print out what that's
equal to, and then we have some type.
And anyone have any guesses
about what type it's going to be?
>> AUDIENCE: An int.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah, it's an int.
So it just adds them together.
It's an int.
All good.
So this next one, we have
what look like strings.
When we run this, it thinks, oh.
You're actually trying
to just add things.
You just got confused.
So I'm just going to fix it for you.
You meant int.
I know you meant int.
>> So this is one of the ways you can
see, PHP has a mind of its own.
Even though we explicitly said,
look, these ones are strings.
I mean the string one.
But it says, oh, but
you're trying to add them,
so you must mean it's an integer.
Just trust me on this.
So it says it's an integer,
and it adds them like normal.
So kind of cool if you're going
to get lazy with your things,
or you want to add something.
>> A great thing is that, if
you think back to pset2,
something that was user
inputted, right, that we think
is a char or a string at first.
Now we don't have to explicitly
say, oh, make this an int.
PHP would just be like, oh yeah.
I know you meant an int.
Silly you.
You didn't mean a string.
>> So in that case, now
that we have this, what
do you guys think it's going to do here?
We have a string and an int now.
>> AUDIENCE: It's still an int.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It's still an int.
And the reason is-- I would put
more examples, but this one's fun.
The reason it's doing it is because
it's like you're trying to add things.
So if you're trying to add
things, I'm going to assume,
reasonably, you have something
reasonable that you could add.
I'm just going to make it an int, and
we're just going to add it, like usual.
And then the same way, I
think you guys get the idea.
We also have this one here, which is
just chars, and it does the same thing.
It's like, you silly user.
you know you want an int.
>> AUDIENCE: If we put a letter, will
it do the [INAUDIBLE] value or not?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Oh,
that's a good question.
Let's see.
Nope, still is an int.
So it's a little crazy.
This is just kind of to show you PHP
can sometimes behave in irrational-- Not
totally irrational, but it might behave
in ways that you don't really expect.
So, when in doubt, check
the types of things.
This function gettype
can be super useful.
>> Typically, if you're doing anything with
plusses or any mathematical operators,
it's going to assume anything
reasonable is just an int.
So, you have char 1, or a
string 1, or the actual int 1,
it's going to assume that.
If you want to typecast
anything, you totally can.
You could do something like
double here, I believe.
And in that case, it's going to say, oh.
I'll make this a double because
you explicitly said it's a double.
You can always explicitly
make PHP do something, but.
>> AUDIENCE: Wait, why is A plus 1 there?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Oh.
There.
It was just an echo.
That was my fault.
So, you can explicitly tell it to
make something of a certain type,
but most of the time, it's going to
dynamically decide that at runtime.
So it's going to keep going through
and it's going to be like, OK.
What makes the most
sense for this to be?
Should it actually be a string?
Should it be an int?
Should it be a float?
Should it be a double?
And it will decide that for you.
>> You can force it to do
what you want, but--
>> AUDIENCE: Does that make it slower?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Well,
I mean, C is very efficient.
I think it's definitely slower because
it has to the process as it's going.
C, I'm almost sure is faster.
But obviously there's a
lot of cool things in here
that we don't have to worry about.
So, if we're searching
through an array, we
don't have to actually create
some search through the array.
We can just ask for the key
and PHP will take care of it.
>> Cool.
Awesome.
Looks like the end of my examples.
You guys are never going
to forget that now.
You're going to be like, oh, PHP is just
like that mom who's like no, no, no.
I know what you mean.
I know what you want.
OK.
So this is, hopefully, useful for your
pset, at least in the very beginning,
because you are all about dealing
with forms and things from the user.
>> So there are two ways that we
pass around info with PHP and HTML
when we're passing
between those two things.
So we have $_GET, which is passed
through the URL, and we have $_POST,
which is passed in the message
body, and so we consider it hidden.
But one thing to understand is that
neither of these are considered secure.
>> If you have someone who is
intercepting the messages going
back and forth between you and the
server, they can still get this data.
They just have to look a little harder.
It's not really that-- it's
just hidden from the URL.
It's still in the message body,
though, so if they have access to that,
it's really just like--
>> It's like the difference
between something
being written on the outside of
an envelope and something being
written on a piece of paper inside.
It's not that hard to open the envelope
and get the piece of paper inside.
Granted, it'd be much easier
just read the outside.
But that's how you can
kind of think of these.
Neither of these are
really considered secure.
OK?
>> Granted, doesn't really
matter for your pset
because you're not dealing
with trade secrets,
but it's typically one
thing that we really
like to emphasize because people
think, oh, well, it's hidden.
It must be super secure.
No.
It's not secure.
It's just slightly
less insecure, I guess.
Or unsecure.
>> So we actually have an example.
As you know, I love
teach more with examples.
I feel like this helps better.
So, we have some simple form here
which actually, if you guys are ever
confused about PHP,
this is really small,
but php.net is actually
really good documentation.
I really like it.
I was using it to prepare for this
section, so I can vet it for you.
>> This is an example from them
on how $_POST and $_GET work.
The only difference
between the two of these,
besides where the information is
displayed, whether it's in the URL
or in the body, is also
what the method is.
So in your form for HTML-- This
is a very simple HTML form.
Can anyone tell me what it does?
AUDIENCE: Ask for your name and age.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Exactly.
So we have some form actions.
That lets us know it's some act form.
And what's going to happen
is, when we hit Submit,
it's going to call action.php,
which is what this is,
and it's going to call it
with a method of $_POST.
So in this case, your
information is hidden.
and it's just your name, some
input type called name, some age,
input type="text" that we also call age.
And then if we hit Submit,
Submit will call action.php.
>> So when we actually hit Submit, we
know that it has posted, per se,
and we'll actually see this in your
problem set that hopefully we'll
get to walk through a little bit.
And all it's doing here is POST
is some superglobal variable
that we talked about during lecture.
And how you can think about $_POST is
that it's just an associative array.
OK?
So this is some key, this
is some key, and whatever
the user input becomes a
value for each of those.
OK?
>> So if we were to write what this array
actually looked like right after we
submitted the form, we would
have, this is our $_POST,
and some array where we have some name.
Let's just say we'll do my name,
and then we have some age, 21.
Woo.
So this is all $_POST is. $_POST
is just an associative array, OK?
>> It just says, OK.
What are the things we've
asked for from the user?
What are the variables
that we're passing around
that we've asked for in this form?
And then what are the
values associated with that?
So in this case, if I submitted it
with a name of Ally and an age of 21,
this is what $_POST looks like.
OK?
And this is what this
PHP file has access to.
All right?
>> So in this case, this is just like
getting any other thing from our array.
Instead of an index in our
array, we have some key.
So this is going to give
me the value at key name.
So this is going to be Ally, and
this right here is going to give me
the value at $_POST where the
key is age, which will be 21.
You're going to be
doing this quite a bit.
Yeah, from which part?
>> AUDIENCE: When you were
pointing at the bottom part.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: This bottom part?
OK.
So, you understand this is our HTML
form, and we have some method $_POST,
which matters.
This could also be $_GET,
but for this purpose,
we're just going to say it's $_POST.
When we submit this form, this is
part of a PHP file that's called.
So this PHP file is now going to execute
given the information from our HTML
form.
>> So what it's doing is, when we
hit Submit on our HTML form,
it's passing you this superglobal,
which is just an associative array.
It's this.
It's just like passing that to the file.
And what it says is, OK, here's $_POST.
It's your associative array.
Do with it what you want.
And we're saying, OK.
Give me the value at name,
and give me the value at age.
>> So these are just keys,
and this is our array.
Does that makes sense?
>> AUDIENCE: Mhmm.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Awesome.
AUDIENCE: If you have to resubmit the
form does it just write over the data?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah.
Mhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: Why do you have
to specify that it's an int?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: In this case, the
user is just forcing it to be an int.
>> AUDIENCE: OK.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: I don't know
if you would actually need that,
but for their purposes, they decided
that they wanted it to be an int.
They're just typecasting it.
Maybe they're using it as
something else later on.
This is just one snippet.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: What if they typed
12, T-W-E-L-V-E, for age?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: If they
tried to type that as an int?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: I
forget what that does.
I think it might try to convert
the first character to an int,
or take the value and convert
it, but I forget exactly what it.
Be a fun thing to write
a program and try.
Do a couple lines.
OK, so this is one of the main
things that you're going to be doing.
I'm going to hopefully walk
through a couple of the files
from the pset with you guys.
It looks like we're going to
have time, so we can do that.
>> But you're going to be
doing a lot of things
like this, where you're passing
things from an HTML form
into this PHP form that will then
execute some set of instructions
on the data that was provided.
That's literally the gist of your pset.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: The type="submit", that
makes a button on the HTML form.
Is there way to call
that button something?
So would you be like name="submit"?
Or is that button just going to be
empty right now, because you only
gave it a type, not a name.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: I think it's
just going to be empty right now.
We can definitely look in the
pset, because we will definitely
be looking at the
register kind of thing.
But yeah, you can definitely specify
the text that you want on your button.
OK, so SQL.
>> When you're buying and selling stocks,
you need to keep track of those.
So the way we're going to do that is
with SQL, which is just a database.
Think of it as a table where
you're keeping all this information
about your different users.
And you guys are actually
going to create one of these.
It's pretty cool.
>> And there are just four main things
that you need to know for this pset,
and they are update, so you
basically update the data.
That assumes that it's already there.
If it's not there, it's going
to hit you with an error,
so maybe you want to check.
And you will update on-- I
should actually- I have time,
I'll write a couple of these.
I will actually give you guys a
couple of sample, full SQL commands,
because these are just the main
ones, but you can join them together.
So I'll do that and I'll send
that out to you with these notes.
>> So if you want to update something,
need to tell it what you're updating
and where you're updating it.
So a typical SQL command would be update
ID where something equals something.
Or like update address
where ID equals 3,
and this would update the address field
of your user who has an ID of three.
OK?
>> So if you go to SQL and W3Schools,
they have awesome examples.
In fact, I might pull
some up in a little bit.
And then insert into, you're just
inserting certain values there.
So if you're trying to create some new
entry, so you're creating a new user,
you could do insert into
whatever your database is called,
and you would have all these values.
>> Then you have select,
select values to view.
So if you're trying to check to
see if a user exists or you're
trying to grab specific
information about a user
you're going to be using select.
And then delete, I think,
is pretty simple there.
You're just deleting
something from the table.
And in fact, let me actually pull
up some examples for you guys.
Oh look, it's my 61 page.
>> So if we go to W3Schools,
hopefully it's up again.
Yes, Love it.
We go to SQL.
So, this is something here.
So, this is a very simple SELECT.
Man, I love this function.
So, you can have SELECT
some field FROM customers.
In this case, customers refers to the
online database that you're using,
so whatever your table is called, and
star just means select everything.
Give me every one.
>> So, I just want to give you guys a
couple of examples of where this is.
So we have SELECT, UPDATE.
So here is kind of the general syntax.
So UPDATE, whatever your
table name is, and then SET
is where you're actually going
to be what data you're changing.
So this could be-- Let
me make an example here.
So this is going to be--
>> OK.
So I created a little database for us.
We're going to have some ID,
some year, and some named.
So ID one going to be year '15,
and we're just going to make it me.
Who wants to be the second
person in our table?
Anyone.
I'm just going to choose Emma
because your name's quick.
Emma, what year are you?
>> AUDIENCE: What year?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: '16.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: '16.
You're just going to be
my guinea pig for today.
OK, so we have these two people.
Actually, let me do this.
Let's say I heard her wrong, and I
actually said she's a year younger.
She's '17.
What we want to do here, if we
wanted to update Emma's year
to be correct using that, what we'd
do is we'd say UPDATE data over here.
>> And this can all be on one line, but
since I'm compressed for space here,
I'm going to write here.
And we want to set.
So this is the table we're updating.
SET is going to be what column or
what data are we actually changing.
What we're changing is year, so
we're going to say SET year = 16,
and then WHERE tells us which user or
what row are we actually updating this.
>> So where?
We have two options here.
What are the two?
These are unique, right?
So our names are unique
and our ID is unique,
so what are the two options
for where we could do this?
I'll give you one.
We could do WHERE ID =
2, or we could do what
if we're going off this paradigm here.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Exactly.
So we could also do name = Emma.
And either of these would work.
And we ran this, it'd be like, OK.
We'll change it.
You're actually 16, so
now you're right again.
OK, so this would be
super useful in your pset
where maybe someone decided
to buy 100 shares of Apple,
and then they were like, just kidding.
I only want 90 shares.
And so they sell 10 of them, so you
need to update the amount of stocks
that they have.
So, updating stocks, updating table.
>> OK.
So that's one example there.
That's the update syntax.
DELETE.
Oh.
Insert into is our other one.
So, this one here is very similar.
We could just say, in this
case let's add someone.
We can add Ben this time.
We do INSERT INTO, and we
want the name of our table.
In this case it's data.
>> And then we just want, you're going to
say VALUES, and what you're going to do
is, you actually need to make sure
that you have something for each row
that you want.
You just put them in order.
So in this case, we would say 3.
You're 18, right Ben?
>> AUDIENCE: 19.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: 19?
AUDIENCE: 19.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Your year's '19?
You graduate in '18, right?
AUDIENCE: Oh.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Graduation year.
AUDIENCE: OK.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
I was like, are you
already planning to
take a year off here?
So, '18, we have Ben.
So in this case, it would go through,
it would create a new entry here.
Cool.
Not too bad, right?
A lot of this is going to
be syntax for you guys.
Concepts should come,
hopefully, relatively easily.
The syntax is the only thing
that can be a little tricky.
>> And then our last one is
DELETE, and as you notice,
I highly recommend this website.
It's great.
There's a ton of stuff.
So, in the same way that we had
some UPDATE, DELETE is very similar.
Instead we have Delete from Data.
So in this case, our last
one I'll write down here.
Let's say we wanted to delete me.
I cannot write today.
DELETE from whatever
table we're in, data.
And there are actually three ways
we could choose to delete me.
>> Can you guys tell me what the three
ways are, how you could delete me?
ID equals 1, where ID equals 1.
We could do where year equals
15, or where name equals Allison.
of course, there are only
three different ways,
because these are all unique.
Typically in your table,
and especially in your pset,
you're going to set one of
these columns to be unique.
>> It's probably going to be some unique ID
number, because if you have-- actually,
it might actually let you have two.
I can't remember if it'll let
you have two of the same thing.
>> AUDIENCE: Then it would
change their behavior.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It would.
It'll cause behavior that is unexpected,
that you can't really predict.
So you will definitely have one column
in your database that will be unique,
and it's typically you can set
it so that it's like a unique ID,
and it will just update every
time you insert into the table.
Any time you create a new
row, it will automatically
increment and give it some unique ID.
So hint for your pset.
OK.
So that is SQL.
>> So now we're going to talk about
the very last thing, which ties in
actually pretty well with your
pset, if it would go forward.
So MVC, model view controller.
This is really just a way
to keep things organized.
In the same way with C we ask you guys
to create functions and separate things
out, this is just a way to separate out
code when you're doing web development.
>> So it makes things much
more elegant and simplified,
and this is actually the way
that your pset is actually
set up, so whether you like it
or not, you're going to learn it,
even if you don't think
you're learning it.
And one thing is, it also allows you to
do much more like a user collaboration.
>> So when I took CS50, I did a
website for my final project,
and I was like, I'll
handle the database stuff.
I'll do back end stuff, and my
roommate who I was taking with it
was very artsy.
She does stage design, and she
wanted to make it all pretty.
So I'm like, OK.
You can take care of
all the front end stuff.
>> And the thing is, as
we'll see very soon,
that model view controller lets you
completely separate that code so
that I could work on
implementing our pages,
and manipulating information
in our databases,
and she could just make things
pretty, and we were both really happy,
because we got to do what
we both wanted and we
didn't have to deal with the other one.
>> So we hung out together.
We like to hang out.
I just didn't want to deal with
all the CSS and HTML stuff.
I was like, you make it pretty.
I'll deal with the database.
So we have this really
cool, great little table.
I love tables.
And basically, the model you can
think about is just your database.
>> I was the model person for my project.
It's all about the storage of
information and organizing that data.
So it's what we like to call back end.
So you guys will be dealing with
the SQL database and the data files.
That's your model.
>> Your view, as you might
think, kind of makes sense,
is what your user actually sees.
It's the user interface.
It's that front facing component.
So that's what my roommate
got to work on all the time.
She was super happy.
So that's all of the HTML,
and there's very little PHP.
>> If you're just talking about
what's being displayed to the user,
we're talking about hypertext.
We're talking about how it looks.
We're not talking about logic,
or conditions, or whatnot.
All of that gets handled
by the controller, OK?
So that handles the user requests
and gets the information.
>> So one thing you should know about
your pset is that, in your views,
anything that is actually
displaying information
should never be making
calls to your model.
All of that is handled
in your controller.
Your controller is the one
mediating between these two.
It will ask the model
for certain information.
It can iterate over that
information, figure out
what you actually need from
it, what to do with it,
and then it will pass on
just the information you
need to the view for you to print it
out or display it to the user, OK?
>> Because we see the view as
whatever is facing the user,
so it will be much easier
for them to figure out,
oh, if you're making
some call to your model
and you're asking for all users
who start with the letter A,
and you're doing that in your view,
anyone who can see your web page
could potentially access that.
>> You don't necessarily want that.
You don't want people to see
more into the database than what
they should be seeing.
Just their specific preferences.
So the controller handles all of that.
So all of your .php files that we'll see
you can consider your controller files.
And that's where you're
really going to be
asking for things from your database,
and iterating or manipulating
it as necessary before
passing it on to be viewed.
>> It's a really cool pset, in my opinion.
I think it's a little more
like instant gratification,
because you implement a
lot of little tiny things,
and each thing should work on its own.
Not like, do everything
and then see if it works.
Like with software
where you're like, I'm
really hoping this is
right, because if it's not,
there are a lot of
places it could be wrong.
>> All right.
Just making sure that I said
everything I needed to say about MVC.
Yeah.
Cool.
>> So in CS50 Finance, we have
our model, as I just said here.
It's going to be MySQL and phpMyAdmin.
I can definitely pull those up so
you guys get a chance to look at it.
Like I said before, it your SQL
database acts as your model,
and you can send what we call queries,
which are just these sorts of things.
These are called a query.
This is a query, where you're just
asking your database for something,
or you're changing your
database in some way.
That's all it is.
And you do that with the
functions we've given you here.
>> You can also manipulate
them by hand via phpMyAdmin,
which we can definitely take a look at.
I'll create a sample
database with you guys.
OK.
So, controller.
So in this case, if you
notice, this is all PHP.
Notice that's kind of your
main thing of your controller
is that it should be mostly PHP.
If you have HTML in your controller,
not really sure what's going on there.
The same way as I said, if you
manage to [INAUDIBLE] with HTML,
I'm real interested.
>> So what we have here
is you have some query.
Query is a function that
we built for you guys.
It's like a wrapper to make queries
to your database a little easier.
If you didn't have that, the syntax for
actually talking to your SQL database
would be different, so we
just supply it for you guys.
We like to make life easy.
>> So in this case, can you guys
tell me what this line is doing?
SELECT * from some table.
AUDIENCE: Select
everything from this table.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Exactly.
So it's saying, give me
everything from this table.
And it's storing it in
some variable result.
And this says, if result is not equal
to false, then we do each of this.
So if there's nothing here, if your
table's empty or it just doesn't exist,
it's going to return false.
So in this case, we're just making
sure that something was actually
returned to us.
>> And then here, we have
our great foreach loop
that we're iterating over our
result, and we're calling it row,
and we say render this template
where your data is this result.
OK?
So it's just processing
the row of the result.
Otherwise, it yells.
So, this is an example
of the controller.
As you see, this is the
only place-- Yeah, sorry?
>> AUDIENCE: Why is there
an ampersand before row?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
An ampersand before row.
We are just iterating.
That's also an address of--
>> AUDIENCE: So it's like C referencing.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It's
making sure that you're actually
modifying the original and not a copy.
It's in the same way with C where
we're passing by reference here, just
to make sure.
>> AUDIENCE: Is it not ==
instead of not = in PHP?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It's not the ==.
>> AUDIENCE: Because equals in C is just--
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It's just not =.
Yeah, no.
It's not ==.
Because == in PHP checks for
equality with toggling, granted,
but extra quality.
So, it's not == in PHP.
It's one of the little
syntax differences.
Yeah.
So we're just iterating
through each row,
and render, if you guys
read through your spec,
is just some other function that is
actually going to process all the HTML
and display it in your
web browser for you.
>> OK.
So, we like to think of your controllers
as what handles the business logic.
As you see here, this is where we're
taking our data from the table,
we are processing it in some way,
and then we're passing it off.
When we do render some template,
some template is our view,
and we're passing it only
the data that it should get.
Not all the data.
Just the data that we want it to get.
OK?
Basically the data after processing.
>> So this is the view, this is
the sum template that we have,
and all this is doing is, you can
have a little PHP in your view.
It's not like a no PHP in view.
You should just have
very minimal PHP in view,
and you should never be
querying in your view.
You should never be talking
to your database in your view.
That's the big difference.
>> So what's going on here is, we have
PHP that's iterating through the row.
So in this case, since we were
iterating through each row
and rendering something, this was
probably like a two dimensional array
where we have some row that
is, in itself, an array,
because we're iterating
through it again.
And we're just printing out
the row name, then end it.
>> You shouldn't need this in the foreach.
I've never seen that before actually.
I just do foreach.
OK, so that's the view.
Let's see if we can walk through
a little bit of your pset.
We have 15 minutes, so I'm sure you
guys would like that more than just
ending early.
Let me see if I can bring this up.
>> So I don't know how many of you guys
have downloaded it and whatnot yet,
but we have username here,
and we have some password.
And unfortunately, right
now the database is empty,
so we actually need
to create a database.
Well, that's weird.
Did not expect that.
Technical errors.
Technical difficulties.
We have some pset7.
Cool.
>> So, one thing you can do is, with
a query-- I'll create a table.
So this is going to be users-- what
you can do here is, if we have some--
Really now?
OK.
Obviously I'm not doing so hot.
Oh.
I know why.
Because I never created
my actual tables.
So when you first start with
a database, you obviously
have to decide what are the
things I need to have in here?
>> So if we just go off
our data table here,
we had some ID, which
can just stay an int.
And if we look over here, there's
a cool thing that-- So index.
If you do primary, it will make it the
thing that your table is organized by,
and it will also make it unique.
So in this case, we'll make it primary,
and I'm going to make this name,
then we'll just make it a varchar
of like 26 letters, because why not?
>> And then you can go to Save, and then
if you see, we have some users here.
So if we wanted to do an
insert, we could do it
this way, or if you wanted practice
with your queries-- Oh boy.
I have not used this in forever.
I take this back.
>> You can edit this on your own either
just by manually inserting information
with something like, you
can change any of these
if you wanted to make-- If you want to
suddenly get rid of name, you can drop,
you can do all those things.
If you need to ever
manually change your table,
I suggest doing it in
phpMyAdmin versus trying
to figure out the SQL
queries in general.
When you first start your pset,
you're going to have to work in here,
so get used to that.
And then when you actually want
to insert things into your table--
I really wonder where that is,
because there's-- Here it is.
That's what I wanted.
So if you go to SQL, you could
actually see, as we see here,
we have SQL queries.
>> So if we wanted to select something
or if we wanted to insert something,
we can do insert into the users, right?
I think you need the backslash.
One thing to know is, if
you're ever using this,
you have to use these back
apostrophes, which are typically,
if you're on a Mac, right above tab.
So a good thing to know.
>> You could insert into users,
and we have our values, right?
So we have values, and our values
in this case would just be,
we only have an ID so we
could do one if we wanted.
That's weird.
OK.
So that's just like a brief
little thing with SQL,
but it might be more useful to actually
look at some of the files in here.
>> So go to Downloads.
Oh, not Downloads.
So, just a quick walkthrough of
what's in each of these folders.
It includes, we just have things
that configure your browser,
we have these constants,
and we have these functions.
If you're interested in any of them,
I recommend looking at functions.
One of them that is super useful,
actually is this one here, dump.
>> So if you use this,
it will actually just
print out whatever variable
that you like it to.
So if you are having trouble figuring
out what this array looks like,
or what this data actually,
how it's formatted,
this is a great thing to use.
Especially when you have a
user with multiple stock,
this is going to be
something great to use.
Because it might be formatted--
>> I know at least for me when I did
this pset, it was formatted in a way
that I didn't quite expect.
So I was trying to iterate over
it and trying to manipulate it,
but I didn't really
understand what I was doing.
So if you just dump it, it will
print it out to the browser,
and you can see exactly
how it's formatted.
It'll typically print it out as an
array with its keys and its values.
So it can help there.
It can also help to make
sure that you're actually
grabbing the data that
you thought you were.
So if you were like, my table definitely
says there's a user with this ID,
but when you go to dump the
variable, it's not there,
you obviously know that's
where an error's going to be.
This is one of the best tools
for debugging, in my opinion.
And then there's a
couple other things here,
but for the most part, that's the
one I want to draw your attention to,
because it is very helpful.
>> Public, what we have here is,
this is all of our CSS stuff.
So CSS, fonts, our images, whatnot.
This is all stuff that
you don't have to modify.
Can you guys think about if this
has things like CSS in the fonts,
would this be a model, or
a view, or a controller?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It'd
be more of a view, right?
This is handling all
things, how things look.
So if we open this here, we see
that all that's happening here
is we're rendering something.
OK?
So this would very much
qualify as a view for this.
So this is just taking some,
it's calling some portfolio.php
that we have, and it's passing
in title and portfolio.
And it's just rendering that.
Actually, I take that back.
This is a controller, because
render, remember, renders the view.
So portfolio.php in this
case would be your view.
Sorry, guys.
Portfolio.php is going to be
your view, and this would just
be your controller for that.
And if we take a look at this
last one here, templates,
templates are all of your views here.
So if we look, obviously
we see a lot of HTML here.
>> So this one is just showing you what
the login page should look like.
You notice we have some
form groups, have submit.
Here's how you decide what
is displayed on there.
You have some button type="submit",
and then you have what you want it
to display in button.
So that's how you would make it
show up as whatever you'd like.
>> And we see here we have some
username, some password,
and when we actually hit Submit,
it's going to be some post,
and it's going to post to what?
What's the controller for this view?
When we hit Submit,
what's going to be called?
Do we know?
It's right here, so login.php.
Something you guys are
going to implement.
>> So you can always tell
what's going to be
called after you hit Submit
by this first line here.
What the form action is.
When this form is submitted,
what action do we take?
We call login.php, and we
call it with this method
of post, which has the
hidden information.
OK?
So this is your view, and then obviously
if we went to login.php-- Do we have it
yet?
Yeah.
>> So as we see here, this
has a lot more logic.
It's all our PHP here.
We're trying to see if it was $_GET,
if it was $_POST, validating things,
querying, all this stuff.
So those are just the three
different things here.
you don't have to change things.
You'll be creating things
in template, possibly,
but as far as HTML or the
styling of any of this goes,
you can leave it as plain or
as intricate as you'd like.
>> Some people get really into it and
make some pretty awesome websites.
You don't have to do that.
If you have time, it's
a really cool thing.
You can mess around with CSS and HTML
and get a much better feel for it,
but don't feel pressured to.
There's plenty for you to do on the
back end with implementing log in,
and register, and all of these things.
>> So hopefully that helps a little bit.
do you guys have any questions
about anything we've gone over,
any other resources?
I will definitely send all of
my example PHP code to you guys,
and then feel free to take
pictures or whatnot of this.
Also it's online.
You can always just watch again.
So if that's it, everyone good?
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: I just want
to confirm, when we're
doing select in SQL, the
star means everything, right?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yes.
AUDIENCE: And then if
you don't have the star,
if you want it to take from a specific
row, then you just put the name of--
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
The name of the row
and what you want you want the value of.
>> AUDIENCE: And then the date.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Whatever
you're looking for, yeah.
In the same way, if you do DELETE * from
some table, it'll delete everything.
So, * is just a wild
card for everything.
>> AUDIENCE: OK.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Cool.
Awesome.
Well, have a great Monday, guys.
I'll see you next week.
Good luck on your pset.