ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
All right everyone.
Welcome back to section.
It is our penultimate section.
It's so sad.
I don't know what I'm going to do
without seeing you guys every Monday.
I guess we should just--
maybe we could just
meet here and have dinner or something.
I don't know.
I'll bring food instead.
We'll just talk.
But yes, next week will
be our last section.
>> On that note, you have a quiz next week.
I know I forgot to do my, like,
two week advance notice last week,
but hopefully you guys
knew this was coming.
Hopefully this is one of the last
midterms for you guys for the semester.
But it's going to cover all the
material that we've gone over.
So it's not like you can just forget
about four loops or variables.
Because we learned
those in the beginning,
those are obviously
fair game for your quiz.
>> It's going to be the same format, same
length, so you already are used to it.
There's going to be
coding by hand problems,
maybe some true false,
maybe some short answer.
So you should be
familiar with the format,
especially if you take
the practice tests.
But as I say here, it's
cumulative, but we're definitely
going to be focusing on
things from week six onward.
So, we're probably not going
to ask you about how many bytes
are in each type or
those sorts of things,
but we're probably going to be
interested in things like linked lists,
or different data structures,
or different algorithms
that we've talked about.
So make sure you're really
up on those, and if you
need any resources,
here's lots of resources.
I just gave you kind
of a quick list there.
>> Next week will be quiz
review during this time.
So if you have any questions
or specific topics,
specific things on the quiz that
you'd like to go over, please
send them to me ahead of time so I can
kind of prepare some material for that.
And in addition to this
section review, we'll
also be holding the course-wide
review like we did last time.
And it's going to be
done by the same people.
I don't know if that
makes it better or worse,
but it's going to be me,
Hannah, Davan, and Gabe again.
So if you want to come see
us all banter with each other
and walk you through quiz
review, you should definitely
come to that next Monday also.
So you'll just have a Monday jam
packed of quiz review, which is good
because then you have Tuesday
to process through everything.
>> But definitely do check
out these resources.
Study.csv.net is by far, I
think, one of the most useful,
mostly because it has
a lot of sample code,
it has all the Power Points
with all the notes on it,
which are really what I draw most
of my section materials from.
If there's anything in previous
sections that I may have sent out
that you may not have
gotten, just let me know.
Like last week's sample code,
if anyone didn't get that,
just email me or come talk to me,
and I'll make sure that you get that.
>> So with that, today we are going
to be talking about JavaScript.
So here we Tommy, who I was
just talking to you last night.
I love Tommy.
JavaScript is his favorite
language, as he says here.
They'll try and tell you that it's
not the best, and they will be wrong.
So Tommy is a JavaScript master.
I'm not quite at his
level, but I was like,
"Tommy, how do I teach
these kids JavaScript?"
So I got some tips, so
hopefully they work out.
>> So a couple things to know is that
JavaScript is a client-side scripting
language, so whereas PHP is something
that we considered more server-side,
it was upload to the server,
compiled and executed there.
This one is executed
on your own machine.
OK?
So you load some JavaScript page,
and it executes on your machine.
Syntax is very similar to C and PHP.
We're going to go through
some examples of JavaScript,
and you're going to see that the
way we talk about variables, loops,
and conditions are all very similar.
OK?
The fact that they are so similar is
probably going to trip some of you
up, in some cases, just because
you'll incorporate a little bit of C
where there shouldn't be.
Maybe you try and type something
when it shouldn't be typed.
>> And on that, one thing to
know is that JavaScript
is a dynamically typed
language, like PHP.
So if you guys remember
from section last week,
when we were kind of doing
our PHP crash course,
we saw how a string one could be
turned into an int one, and so forth.
The type of your variables
are determined at run time,
so they may change over
the course of the program,
and in the same way that we never
really declare types for PHP variables,
we're going to be doing the same
thing here, where we're not really
controlling the types of our variables,
so to speak, like we do in C.
>> And then one thing
that is pretty cool is
that you can error
check via the console,
with this great function
console.log, which
allows you to print out different
variables or objects that we'll
talk about.
Just like last week when I was
like, "use this function," with dump
from your pset this is a function
you want to use, console.log.
I was so surprised how many
students at office hours
did not know about the dump function.
And I was like, "guys, this will
make your life so much easier."
>> All right, so that was kind of
just a brief thing, as always,
we have examples.
I know you guys love those.
So here's an example of a very
simple JavaScript file here.
So it's just going to create
this pop-up that says,
"hello world," when you
enter the page, but let's
try and walk through this a little bit.
So obviously this is just
like your normal index.html.
So, just our normal template here,
and we have HTML, we have our head,
and just like with CSS, how we
included some outside file, right?
We have some script type
text that is JavaScript.
And the source is hello.js,
which is down here.
This is the entire file of hello.js.
And then we have some
title and some body HTML
that we don't really care about.
>> What happens is, when we load this page,
it automatically executes this script.
OK?
So JavaScript will
execute automatically.
So what it's going to do, it's going
to immediately go and execute this.
And it's going to say, "alert.
Hello world."
Which alert is the function that
actually generates this box.
OK?
So it's kind of all encompass.
There's nothing extra we had
to do besides just alert,
and then whatever we wanted
within our Alert box.
OK?
So that's just a super simple
example of what JavaScript can do.
>> One of the really cool
things, as we'll see,
is that JavaScript allows you
to manipulate your web pages,
without having to
reload them every time.
So if you want-- for example, if
you are hovering over something,
if you guys ever have
seen like Menu bars,
or when you hover over some
topic, a Drop-down menu appears,
that's because of JavaScript.
OK?
So you're not reloading the entire
page to get this menu to show up,
you're just looking for some specific
action that the user has taken,
which are called events that we'll get
into, and once you see that, you say,
"OK, edit something on this
page and make it look different,
but only edit these specific things.
Don't reload the whole thing."
So it actually is much nicer, and
you don't have to reload your pages,
and it's really cool.
>> So variable declarations,
so you can kind of see,
I put on top here, loosely typed.
So this is very much like PHP.
We don't need to tell
JavaScript what type we're
expecting each of these variables to be.
They can be whatever types we want.
So you notice in this case, we declare
them very simply, just with "var"
and then whatever we want
our variable name to be.
One thing to note is that when you
put var in front of a variable name,
it locally scopes it.
OK?
It's totally reasonable for you
to completely just erase the var
and just have s equals CS50, and
that would just be a global variable.
OK?
So you can initialize it both ways,
just depends on how you want it.
So if you're initializing
it within a function,
and you want that variable to
stay scoped within that function,
you're going to want to do
something like var name a variable,
versus if you want it
globally scoped, you
can just do the name of
the variable and then
whatever you'd like it set equal to.
OK?
>> This is kind of cool thing down here,
because if we notice our variable
b starts out as true.
And what this does-- can
anyone tell me what this does?
So we have some alert.
What would type of b
be in the beginning?
AUDIENCE: Boolean.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Boolean.
Right.
And then we reassign b
to this string, right?
So then here, what type of b be?
It'd be a string, right?
So what's important to
notice is that in c, we
could almost never do
something like that.
We'd have to have a variable,
cast it as something else,
maybe do some function with a two
i, go from a charge to an integer.
But if we notice here, b
very easily changes type.
>> AUDIENCE: Wait, so you can just
be like, "make b an integer?"
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah.
You can just reassign b to an integer.
>> AUDIENCE: Really?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah.
And then it would be an int.
So your variables can change over
the course of the program too.
They are not strictly typed.
It is very loosely typed.
OK?
Basically your variables can do whatever
they want, as we kind of saw with PHP.
They can do some crazy things, so
it's important to be pretty careful.
Name your variables well.
If you don't, all of a sudden
you're going to be like,
"wait, I thought this was a
string, and now it's an int,
and I'm not really sure
what's going on here."
So this is just a simple example of
showing how a variable can easily
change its type over
the course of a program.
>> OK.
So this should look
super, super familiar.
So these are our loops in JavaScript.
They are exactly the same, except for
instead of four int i equals zero,
we could just say var i equals zero.
And then we could have our same sort
of condition, same sort of update,
i plus plus works just fine.
So fours are the same,
whiles are the same,
and do whiles are exactly the same.
Same sort of general format.
We notice, four, parentheses,
brackets, it's all the same.
Also there will be semicolons
when we get to example code.
You'll see it's pretty
much the same as c.
>> For function declarations,
again, very similar.
We have some function that just
says that it's a function, and then
the name of our
function, and the inputs.
And again if we notice, we
have no types here whatsoever.
Right?
We have nothing saying that these
need to be ints or doubles, or floats.
They could be whatever they want.
What is important is noticing that
we need to write function beforehand
to let JavaScript know that
this is actually a function.
>> So this is just some simple sum
function that returns x or y,
and then what's also cool
is that you can actually
assign a function to a variable.
So in this case, sum is now the
function that actually does sum.
So if you notice here, we have
function, name of function, inputs.
Right?
Here we just have function and inputs.
So this is called an anonymous function.
And this is something that should be new
to most of you guys, if not all of you.
So basically what that
means is that we don't
need to name of our
function in this case.
We can just say, "OK, I'm going to
have this function that executes, here
are its inputs, and here's
what it's going to do."
And especially when you're assigning
a function to some variable
that you're going to manipulate,
you don't necessarily
need to name it because
you're going to be referring
to it by this variable
name, not by whatever
the function was actually called.
OK?
>> So if we see here, we
have some variable sum now
that is equal to the
sum of three and five.
And we would get this.
And this would just have some alert,
three plus five equals the number.
This plus will just concatenate
whatever our answer was onto the string.
Also cool, plus can concatenate strings.
>> For JavaScript, as with PHP,
HTML, and CSS as we said,
a lot of it we're kind of taking
the training wheels off here
and you guys have a lot of the know
how to really understand these things.
They're slightly different,
but they're not so foreign
and that you can't Google things or
look them up online with w3 schools.
And we're really expecting you
guys to, kind of, experiment
and learn on your own.
So, I know this might seem a little
less thorough than some of the c things
we do, but that's actually for a reason.
But hopefully it's not too
different, and it's not overwhelming.
>> So arrays in JavaScript,
again very, very similar.
Right?
We have some variable array
that's equal to empty brackets,
and that's just an empty array.
This is often called
literal array notation.
That's just one thing we call it.
If we see array two here, we have some
literal array that has three elements,
right?
And then we have some
var third element that's
some variable that's just
going to hold this string, JS.
>> The elements, good to notice,
are separated by commas,
just like we would expect.
And you can also access these, as we did
in C, with this index notation, right?
So different from PHP
now, we're going back
to just kind of referring
to things by index.
Just like C, it's also zero index.
I feel like it would be really cruel
if they suddenly made JavaScript one
index, and you had to completely
rethink how you think about arrays.
>> One cool thing is that instead
of having to do-- if you ever
wanted the length of an array,
maybe you iterate through it
until you find some end, or
you would just know what it is.
Because JavaScript is very loose in more
ways than just type, as we see here,
we can just make this array
bigger because we decide to.
If we notice array three
has three things to start,
but then all of a sudden,
we're like, "oh, just kidding.
We're actually going
to make it 101 things."
So if you ever want to know the
actual length of your array,
you do it like this.
And we're going to see a lot
of this notation in examples,
but with JavaScript
it's typically whatever
object that you're talking about
dot whatever kind of function
you want applied to it.
OK?
>> So in this case, our
object is array two,
and we say we want the
length of array two.
So this just calls like length on that.
And that will return your length.
Also something to note is
that if we notice our arrays,
unlike C, they don't have
to be all of the same type.
This is much more like PHP.
JavaScript is basically just like
this interesting meld of C and PHP.
So we'll get into that.
For now, let's just assume
that your arrays are basically
like C arrays, in that
they are zero indexed.
OK, so that is everything.
You can also just extend an
array to whatever index you want.
Whereas this would probably seg
fault on you or give you some error,
JavaScript is like, "nah, it's fine.
I got this.
We'll just go straight
where you want to."
>> OK, so objects are very important.
You guys will be using a lot of these
in your P set, if I remember correctly.
So the thing that these are
similar to in C are structs.
So you can think about-- when
we go to an example right
after this I think it'll
make a lot more sense--
but we basically use objects to
organize of course related information.
When we talked about
structs in C, we often
talk about a student who had some name,
ID, house, you know, concentration.
And that's kind of the same thing
that we use objects for here.
It's just to organize
similar information.
>> You can also think of these as more
similar to associative arrays in PHP.
So this would be kind of the thing
where we have some key with some value,
very similar to PHP.
So you can initialize some
empty object, as we see up here,
just with curly braces.
So arrays are square brackets.
Empty objects are curly braces.
Good distinction to have.
And these are just two different
ways to set properties.
So this is kind of
much more of a way that
is similar to PHP, with our
associative arrays, with our key,
and our value, whereas
this one is-- you'll
see this a lot more in JavaScript.
This tends to be the convention.
And in the same way that we did
array two dot length, this is saying,
"OK, give me this
attribute of this object."
Right?
So the same way it was like, "give me
the attribute length of array two,"
this is saying, "give me some
property of our empty object."
Or in this case, we are
assigning it to some value here.
But you could also access it that way.
>> And then here this is just
showing two different alerts.
So this would show the alerts
would be the exact same,
it's just two different ways of
accessing the element that we want.
Does that make sense to everyone?
I feel like this one
probably makes more sense,
just because we're coming off of PHP.
But as we do more examples, this
is literally exactly the same.
A lot of it is just change in syntax.
>> OK, so examples.
I love examples.
So here is some CS50
variable that is an object,
and we store all this
information about it.
So we have course, instructor,
tfs, psets, and taped.
So we notice these are almost
all of different types.
Right?
So objects can store
attributes of different types.
We can think of this-- it's very
similar to our associative array in PHP.
So key, value, key, value,
key, value, so on and so forth.
What's also interesting in the same way
that we can have arrays within arrays,
we can also have objects within
objects, or arrays within objects.
You're never really limited to
just a single one of things.
We can get very Inceptionesque, just
keep going down the rabbit hole there.
>> So if we notice, we
have some course that
is a string, instructor that's a string,
and array, an int, and a Boolean.
So all of these different things.
>> All right, so, we have another one.
So in this case, we have
an array of objects.
So just like an object
can have an array in it.
We can also have an array of objects.
This might be useful to
think about similar to kind
of how we had a hash
table, we had an array
of all these different
types of structs that
were pointers to different
nodes and whatnot.
But in this case, we
have an array of objects.
So this is like an array
of associative arrays.
So we have some first element would
be the object with the name James
and house Winthrop.
>> You guys might remember
something very similar to this
with your last pset, where if you
pulled something from your database,
the first sort of
thing in your array was
all of the information about
the first user that met it,
and then you had to index into that
to get their stock or their cache
or whatnot.
So this is very much the same
thing, just a little change
in syntax, little bit change in
the words we use to describe them.
>> So if we wanted, can anyone tell
me what this alert would do here?
Or what this bit of
code would do for us?
AUDIENCE: It'll give you all the names.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Right, so it
would just alert with all the names
because it would go through
cottage i, so it'd start at zero.
So it'd say, OK we're looking
at this first object, which
is the first slot in our array.
And it says, "give me the
attribute, the name of that object."
So we go here, we'd
scan, we'd find name,
and we'd print out
James, Molly, and Carl.
Any questions so far?
JavaScript unfortunately
you're going to be
doing a lot of looking up on your
own, figuring out the syntax,
grappling with it.
But of course I'm always here,
office hours are always here.
I might be on Tuesdays this week.
So if you're there, you can
come visit me this week.
It'd be great.
>> OK, so DOM is Document-Object Model.
So this is just a way
that we like to think
about how our HTML and everything
within it is organized.
This is very much something that
will probably come up on your quiz.
I know my year, it was like here's
HTML file, fill in the DOM for it.
And you just fill in little things.
These should be easy points hopefully.
Hopefully you'll see--
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So
you see this tree here?
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
So they will ask use
to fill in what goes under the body.
Maybe under the body, we have some
divs or we have some paragraphs,
and we'll ask you to fill in
a tree very much like this.
So we'll be walking through it.
So the Document-Object
Model is just a way
to structure and think
about our HTML graphically.
And also when we get
into more JavaScript,
it's going to be the
way that we actually
manipulate different
elements on the page.
We need a way to access each
of the things in our HTML,
and so this gives us a very
concrete standardized way
across various web pages to do that.
>> So if we just walk through
this here, of course
our document is like our entire file.
That obviously makes sense
that it's the highest thing,
and then we have our actual HTML,
which corresponds to this tag here.
Also if you in indent your tags
properly, then creating this DOM tree
becomes super simple.
So we have some head here.
We have some body that
we see stem off of HTML,
which is why we have head and body.
Within head, we have some
title tag, an end title tag,
so we know that comes after head.
And within our title tag,
we have hello, world.
OK?
So that's this whole left hand branch.
And then for the right hand branch
here, we see that we have HTML,
OK we've done this head part,
we're looking just at body,
so we have some body area.
And within that, the only
thing we have is hello, world.
OK?
If we had things like
some bracket p and then
hello, world, and then another
bracket p of goodbye, world,
we would have two bubbles
coming off of here.
Because they're both under body, but
they're separate paragraphs this case.
There is definitely practice
on that in previous quizzes,
as well as plenty online on it.
OK so, this just lets
us see everything nicely
and manipulate things
very systematically.
OK?
We know exactly how to
traverse through this tree,
so we know what we want to access.
>> OK so this is why we want
to have this sort of model,
so that we can use things like this,
and we understand what they mean,
and they're standardized
across all things that we do.
So document dot title is just
the title of our-- all of these
are pretty self explanatory,
I like to think.
So the first three
examples are just saying,
"OK, just give me the
title of this web page."
So it will give you what
corresponds to the title.
>> Document dot body is going to give you
whatever is within those body tags.
So you can manipulate that.
And document dot body dot
enter HTML is a very cool one,
and maybe is not like super
intuitive, but the inner HTML
corresponds to this right here.
So if you ever want to
manipulate the text on a page,
typically you're going to be doing
something with body dot inner HTML.
OK?
So inner HTML tends to refer to
what is actually between these tags.
OK?
And then useful functions.
So if you wanted to get
any of these, any element,
we have some Id, class
name, or tag name.
This is very similar to
things we did with CSS, right?
Where we have some selectors that
correspond to either a tag, a class
that we give them, or an Id.
This is very much the same way.
If you have something that
has some class of dog,
and you say get elements by tag name,
and you put dog in there-- or sorry,
class name.
You can put dot in there.
It's going to return all of those
elements to you that have that class.
So you can manipulate just those.
In the same way, maybe you just
want to manipulate some header, so
some h1 header, like we did.
You could do get elements by tag
name, because h1 is a tag name.
And in the same way, if you want to get
some unique thing, you can do get tag.
Get element by Id.
And they are actually lots of these.
These are only like three of very many.
So if you go online, as
I'm going to encourage
you to do, and do some
research on your own,
I definitely recommend
looking into all of those.
They could be super
useful, especially when
you want to just kind of manipulate
very specific things without having
to go through and try
to parse out everything.
>> OK, so the last thing
is JavaScript events.
So when I was talking earlier
about going onto a website,
and when you hover over something,
or your mouse hovers over something,
something else happens.
This is what we'd like to
think about as an event.
So what we have that might
be useful here is onclick.
So mine was on hover, which, I'm
pretty sure, is just on hover.
Also a ton of these
that you can look for.
There's a whole list online
of the different things
that you can listen for.
>> But JavaScript events are
basically just responding to things
that your user is doing.
Right?
So your user does
something, that's an event,
and JavaScript will respond
however you'd like it to.
It will respond accordingly.
So in this case, we have
some window dot onload.
So what this says is, "wait
until the window's loaded."
OK?
So when everything's loaded, onload,
then you can execute this function.
So when everything's
loaded, you're going
to have some search button
that gets an element by Id,
and it prints whatever that
element is as the Search button.
And then we have this variable,
we say, "OK, onclick."
So when we hear a click
on the Search button,
execute this function, which is an
alert, you clicked the Search button.
>> So what happens is-- this is a nice
little graphic representation here.
So our document loads,
that's our onload,
we find our Search
button, which is this.
We're looking for our Search button.
And then when the Search button is
clicked, it corresponds to right here.
Onclick.
Then we finally alert our user,
which is this last line here.
OK?
So each of those four steps just
corresponds to the four boxes
down there on the bottom.
Does that make sense to everyone?
>> And then one thing that I'm just going
to mention very, very briefly, that I
encourage you guys to
go look more into is
jQuery, which is just a library
that is built on top of JavaScript.
It is super useful, as
with most libraries.
There are lots of functions.
So if there's ever something that
you want to do in JavaScript,
your first instinct
shouldn't be to think
of, "what function should
I code?" it should be,
"let me see someone's
already done this for me."
Because nine times out of ten,
someone will have done it already,
and they probably have done it better.
People spend a lot of time doing these,
and JavaScript is very widely used,
so people are constantly
trying to make it better.
And jQuery has a lot of functions
that will probably be useful to you
in your final project if you're
doing anything with web design.
As I like to say, "work
smarter, not harder."
If you guys do that, it'll be great.
When we're at the hackathon I don't
want you to be all stressed out.
I want you to be like, "I got
this. jQuery's got my back.
I don't need to write these functions."
>> So just two things to
remember, I'm going
to let you guys look more
into jQuery on your own.
All I'm going to say is it
does some pretty awesome things
and can make your life
a whole lot easier.
But what you want to
have is whatever file
that you're going to be using it in,
you're going to want these two lines.
You're going to want the
script of js jQuery dot js.
And actually your source
is going to be some URL.
If you Google jQuery, Google
actually hosts all the files for you.
So you definitely want to
input that URL instead.
I just put this here
for simplicity's sake.
All this means is where to
find your jQuery library.
It's massive, so you don't want
to host it on your own computer
if you can avoid it, which is why we
tend to just put in Google's URL that
hosts all of these files for you.
OK?
You Google it, I promise
it will be there.
>> And then whatever
JavaScript file that you're
using, so this is just some external
JavaScript file that you're using.
In the same way that we link to our CSS
files, this is the same sort of thing.
This just links to the file
where your JavaScript is.
And I have some examples
with simple JavaScript.
So we'll be going through it.
And then in your index JavaScript,
which is your JavaScript file here,
this is kind of the wrapper
that you have for jQuery.
You're almost 99.9
percent of the time going
to have this in your index.js file.
Because what this says is,
"don't execute anything
until your document is actually
ready," which is exactly what you want.
Because if your document's not ready,
and jQuery starts doing things,
it's just a mess.
So you always want to have this wrapper.
And then for things that go in there, I
shall leave to your guys' own perusing.
>> OK, so are there any questions right
now about JavaScript in general?
Or the DOM model?
If not, we have some cool
examples that we can go through,
that you guys can help me code.
But I'm also going to be
super nice, and if you
don't want to say anything
for these, that's fine.
I can also just give you examples.
But anything on the
PowerPoint before we move on?
Cool.
>> I feel like you guys need to energy.
So I think we're going to start
with my party example first.
We have three examples,
you have your choice.
So we have clock, where we're going
to implement an actual clock that's
going to update as time goes by.
We have this great Twitter function.
This-- you know what, hold on.
We're going to make this go away.
Bam.
OK.
>> We have this great Twitter function
here, that-- I know, right?
It's going to be great.
Are you guys excited?
That is going to count the number
of characters that you have left,
so if I type right now,
obviously it still says 140,
but we know that's not the case.
And then with our last one
here, click here to party.
What's going to happen is when
we click, the background's
going to change colors.
So you guys have your options of
which one you want to do first.
I promise I'll take it very easy on you.
I feel like everyone's kind
of just very low key today.
So I'll walk you through how
we will implement all of these.
If you want to chime
in, that's great, but I
feel like everyone's a little tired.
So I'll just walk you
through these examples.
Do we have something that
we'd like to do first?
Anyone?
No preference?
OK.
You know what?
We're on party.
I feel like you guys need a little--
so, we'll do the party one first.
OK.
>> So what we have here-- that's
not supposed to be there.
Now it's good.
OK.
So what we have here is
just a simple HTML page
that you guys should all be super
familiar with from your last two psets.
we have our doc type here.
Can everyone see?
OK.
Cool.
We have our HTML obviously.
We have some header that is
linked to a style sheet that
just made my font nice and big and bold.
So don't worry about that.
>> We have some body with
an Id background, OK?
Because we're going to be
changing the background.
So when we're changing the
background of our body,
we remember from two weeks ago
when we are dealing with web pages.
So good to have that.
And we have some Id equals party.
This h ref pound just means that
it's going to go to the same page.
And click here to party,
which is why when we click it,
it should change colors, thankfully.
>> And then we have some script here that
is just linked to this party dot js
file, that is empty because
we haven't done anything yet.
And it's so sad.
But very soon, it will change
colors, and it will be awesome.
>> So I'm just going to walk you guys
through how we might approach this.
So the first thing that
we might want to do,
if we are changing the background of
the body, the first thing we might want
to do is actually grab
what the body is, right?
So we want to have sum, our
background, and if you notice,
I just automatically just start typing.
There's nothing special that we
need to do for our JavaScript files.
I can start declaring variables,
and declaring random functions.
And it's much more free form.
It's like with C, we gave you all
these hard rules, and you grew up,
so we're like, "go forth.
Be free.
Do what you want."
And that's what JavaScript is.
So we have some background here.
With our DOM model, we know we
can do document dot get element,
and if we notice here,
our body has an Id.
Right?
So we can do get document by
Id, and here's a simple one.
What's our Id that we want here?
AUDIENCE: Background.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Background.
Perfect.
And semicolon at the end.
That has not gone away yet.
You still need your semicolons.
OK.
So that's our first one.
And when we click something, we
want something to happen, right?
So we might want some variable
that's waiting for a click.
What we're going to do is we're going to
make our link more similar to a button.
So we're going to have some button that
equals document dot get element by Id.
And if I'm talking about the
click link or click here to party
link, what might my Id be here?
Party.
Correct.
OK not too bad so far.
Everyone get what we're doing?
>> OK, so now we have our
button, and we want
things to change when we click on it.
So if we remember from our PowerPoint,
very simple thing we can do
is just button dot onclick, right?
And that's going to equal some function.
This is an anonymous function.
And this just as-- actually I'm
going to make this a little bigger.
>> So what I just did
here is I'm saying, OK,
when we click our button, which is
this link that we just referred to,
we are going to execute
this anonymous function.
We don't need any inputs.
We don't care what the user says.
When they click on it, we're
going to do whatever we want,
which is change the background color.
OK?
So that's why we don't have any inputs,
we just have this anonymous function.
And now we're actually going
to write this function.
>> So there's a bunch of ways you
could generate a random color.
The way that I did it was to
generate three random numbers
and convert them to an RGB triple.
So this just shows you some cool
things that if you're like, "oh,
I need to generate a random
number." if you Googled it,
this is what you would find.
>> So we have three different
things, var, not red again, green.
Right?
So those are the three
things that make up a color.
Blue, red, and green.
Cool.
And what we can do is that we know
that it needs to be between 255,
and if you looked up some
random number generator,
you could get something like math
dot random, which if you look this up
returns to some number
between zero and one.
OK?
And what numbers do our
RGB triples go between?
Zero and what?
What can they go up to?
255.
So if math dot random
goes between zero and one,
how might we want to convert this?
AUDIENCE: Time?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah, exactly.
So time is 255.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
It's like [INAUDIBLE].
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Math dot random.
AUDIENCE: Cool.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yes.
JavaScript just takes care of you.
OK.
So we can do that for all of these.
Right?
Math dot random times 255.
Copy that.
Cool.
So the thing is, this may
not return an integer.
Right?
Maybe we get some number
between zero and one,
and it causes it to be slightly
off, and our RGBs can't be floats.
They need to be ints.
So if you tried this, it'd probably
have some erratic behavior.
It would be a little funky.
So what we do is we want to make
sure that these are rounded,
and you could round either way.
I rounded with floor.
So I always made sure
that it rounded down.
But going off of how simple it
was to just get a random number,
how do you think we
might floor this number?
It's very similar.
Any idea?
So if random was just math dot
random, so do you think we'd do floor?
Math dot floor.
And you can also do math dot ceiling.
Round is kind of ambiguous
because you don't
know whether to round up or round down.
So typically we always do math
dot floor, math dot ceiling.
But honestly--
>> AUDIENCE: Does floor round down?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Floor rounds down.
And that's just a choice on my part.
>> So now we have our three numbers
that have been randomly generated,
and what we're going to do now is we're
just going to change the background.
OK?
So we already have our
background kind of stored
in this element called background.
So what you'll notice is, if
you played around with this,
we want to change the style.
And this is kind of something that
you would Google and figure out,
like how to change the color.
>> But the way you access this color is
background dot style dot background.
So this is saying given
this object, background,
which refers to that
element Id up there,
we're going to look at the
style within the style,
we're going to look at the background.
OK?
And if you go and look this up,
it might make a little more sense,
but this is basically just saying,
"give me this very specific attribute
of what I have defined earlier."
So what we're changing it to is
some RGB, because it makes sense.
We're using RGB triples, right?
And we have-- I want to make sure I
get the right number of quotes in here.
So what we do is we have
RGB, and we're going
to-- this is like
concatenation, which is red.
And then we want some comma.
And then we want plus green,
then some comma, and some blue.
>> So these pluses just
mean like concatenation.
So this is just creating this
string that's going within RGB.
OK?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] plus then
the green a plus then the red.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah,
because I messed that up.
That one's fine.
Oh, hold on.
No.
Because I need to make sure
that I got all these right.
So I will explain in uno momento.
Green, blue, perfect.
Now I'm done.
I believe.
>> OK.
So what this is, is that background
is going to be set to some string.
Right?
Which is what we have here.
It's going to be some RGB 255 comma
255 comma zero, or whatever number you
have there.
So we're doing here,
we have some string.
And what we want to do, is we're
kind of dynamically creating
that when we actually run this program.
So this is some string.
Plus concatenates it with
the value that red has,
which concatenates it with a
comma, which concatenates it
with what green is, and
so on, and so forth.
OK?
Until the very end, which is the
closing parentheses of this RGB here.
OK?
>> So what this is going to
generate is some command really
that is RGB of three numbers
that background is now set to.
OK?
So let's see if this works.
I hope it does, because if it
doesn't, I'm going to be real sad.
Oh no.
OK, hold on.
Definitely background
dot style dot background.
I'm definitely missing
something just small.
Don't you guys hate that?
When it's just a small little error?
Almighty background.
RGB.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: No.
I tried this before class.
I have everything I did before
class in case I was like,
"wait, what did I do wrong?"
Because I was like, "I will probably
mess this up at some point."
Plus green.
Everything looks like it's
concatenated correctly.
OK.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Oh, there you go.
That's what I needed.
Look at that.
Tiffany to rescue.
Perfect.
OK.
Now let's see if it works.
Oh my God.
OK.
Hold on.
>> AUDIENCE: Space after the second plus.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Which one?
Oh wait, hold on.
Space wear?
>> AUDIENCE: Second plus in
the green concatenation.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Oh.
AUDIENCE: There's no space
after the plus, yeah.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: You
don't need that, but--
AUDIENCE: Oh, you don't?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It looks pretty.
AUDIENCE: OK.
OK.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ AU:
Let's see if this works.
OK.
I'm obviously failing at
this demo, which reminds me
of a lecture the other week,
but I know this will work.
I know this will work.
So close.
Unless I accidentally deleted
my script on this one.
No, it is party dot js.
OK hold on.
I'm going to copy this, and I'm also
just going to delete everything,
because I had this working earlier.
>> I promise it works.
If not, I will show you what Tommy's is.
And there.
>> AUDIENCE: You're referencing party
dot CSS, and it's a party dot js.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Ah, well
right here is party dot js.
OK, what did I do different?
OK, we'll see if this works now.
Bam.
So, I don't know what I did differently,
but this is what should happen.
Kinda cool.
I clicked on this, like, forever.
But we can try and see what I did
differently that this one had.
I don't know about you guys, but this
looks basically what I just wrote.
There was probably a missing
semicolon somewhere is my thing.
Actually after, I think I was missing
a semicolon right here actually.
But I couldn't see it because
it was off the screen.
>> But if we notice, this is pretty
much exactly what I just wrote.
I think probably the hardest part about
this is just kind of this thing right
here, understanding
what it's doing there.
These sorts of things you learn
really just by Googling and honestly
just trying.
If you think there's some
attribute, there probably is.
So try it.
See what happens.
As I said, there's a lot of
experimentation with JavaScript,
and PHP, and all that
stuff, and CSS especially.
That's the only true
way to understand it.
>> OK, so after that fiasco with party
dot js, we have two other options.
We have clock or Twitter.
They're both interesting.
Maybe not quite as fun as party,
which had a cool little strobing
thing at the end.
Do you guys have any preference?
AUDIENCE: Clock?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Clock?
OK.
Cool.
>> So again, we have our
empty JavaScript file.
And as we see here, we
have some very simple HTML.
We have our style sheet, that just
formats what it should look like.
We have our div with
an Id of clock, which
just says, "this should be a clock."
And we have our link
to our JavaScript file
that's actually going to
generate our clock for us.
Because the cool thing, is that you can
set JavaScript to automatically refresh
itself.
OK?
So instead of waiting for the
user to hit Refresh on a page
so that you can get
updated time, JavaScript
can update it however it likes.
>> So, as with our last one, we wanted
to access our background, right?
So what do you think might be the
first thing we want to do here?
If we're kind of going off
this sort of paradigm here?
We probably want to
access our clock, right?
So, we have some var
clock, which equals--
what do we think it's going to be?
Document dot get element by-- I also
love Sublime-- Id and our Id is clock.
Semicolon.
Got to make sure to get
those semicolons this time,
because I feel like that
was the problem last time.
OK so, as I was just saying with trying
to have JavaScript refresh itself,
there's this great function, I
know it came in handy last year,
I'm not sure it comes in handy for this
pset, but it's called set interval.
And this is actually really
cool if you guys do anything
with time or getting
updated information.
On a website for a final
project, this is probably
a function you want to
get super familiar with.
So what set interval does is that
we're going to give it a function,
and how often it should
call this function.
OK?
>> So in this case, we're just going to
create some anonymous function again,
OK, that is going to get
our date, and our time,
and then update things and display it.
So we'll worry about that.
We'll be like generate clock here.
But what we need is how
often to refresh it.
So in this case, it's just milliseconds.
So we're just going to
do 100 milliseconds.
Of course, completely arbitrary.
If you wanted it to update
much more slowly, you could.
We can mess around
with the set interval,
how big our interval is after we get
a working clock, which hopefully I'll
get to.
So this is just saying, "OK, call
this function every 100 milliseconds."
OK?
That's all it does.
>> So what we want our function to
do is we want to have some date
and some time is what
we're going to have.
So We can start with our
date equals something,
and our time equals something
that we don't know yet.
Or actually, we just need date, because
date is going to include everything.
Again if you just Google anything about
what you want to do, if you write, "OK,
I want to get the time
via JavaScript," it
will give you this great
function called get date.
Literally, most things
that you want to do,
JavaScript is going to have
it done for you already.
So it's literally like new
get date, which is creating--
or new date, rather--
which is generating
some object that represents a date.
>> And what we're going to do here is
this is-- I'm going to write this,
and then explain what it does.
So I'll make sure I get this right.
>> OK, so what this function
does, is we're just
creating the HTML that's actually
going to go within our div Id of clock.
So what this is going to be doing
is just generating some string, OK?
That is then going to be
transplanted into our HTML.
Basically what it's going to do is
whatever we-- what I will show you
is that whatever we say HTML is,
we're going to replace this text here
with whatever HTML is.
So this is going to allow
us to change our clock dot
HTML from being just the text of this
should be a clock, to actually showing
the numbers and things that we care
about, and actually be o'clock.
>> So what we're going to do is we're
going to start generating this HTML.
So in the same way that we used
to do plus equals for integers,
you can now do that for strings,
except it's going to concatenate them.
Right?
As we saw with party dot js, this just
concatenates all these things together.
So you can concatenate different bits of
HTML from variables, or bits of strings
that you write out
yourself, and this just
really allows you to dynamically
generate HTML, which is pretty cool.
So if you have something
very user specific,
this can allow you to do that.
>> So we have HTML, to I'm going to
try and make sure I get this right.
So we're going to do some h1 header.
So what's important to realize here
is that this is actually just HTML.
Right?
We are writing actual
HTML code in here, it's
not just a string in the normal
way that we would think about it.
So we have some HTML.
This is considered a string here though.
And we do date dot-- we
want to get our hours.
Again, if you were to look
up anything about date,
it would tell you these are all
the attributes that date has.
And here's what you can use on it.
So it probably has things like
get hours, and get minutes,
and get seconds, and get milliseconds,
and who knows what else they have.
But if you look into the
documentation, it will all be there.
>> So we have get hours,
and then we would want
to concatenate that with-- I'm
going to move this over here.
So if we're generating right now, we're
actually generating the time, right?
We have hours, and then what's
between hours and minutes?
You have a semicolon, right?
So we want to do some semicolon here.
And then we want to get our
minutes, so in the same way
that we have date dot get hours,
how might we get our minutes?
It's literally date dot get
minutes, which I kind of like.
It's like, "oh, how
do I get my minutes?"
I just get my minutes.
>> OK.
And then we have another colon here.
And then if we want to get our
seconds, how might we get our second?
Date dot get seconds.
I think it's pretty cool.
And what's important to
realize, is that we also
need to close our HTML tag here, because
it should still be valid HTML, so h1.
Cool.
>> So after that, we can do clock
dot inner HTML is equal to HTML.
OK?
So remember how I said
inner HTML basically
takes whatever is between the
two tags that we talked about
and inserts or manipulates
whatever is in there?
So what this does, if
we go back to our clock,
is that clock refers to
everything within this div.
This is the inner HTML
of this Id clock div.
And so it's going to change it to
the HTML that we just generated,
which, which, hopefully,
hopefully, hopefully,
will show the time right now.
We'll see.
Of course.
So many technical issues.
Allison's just-- I'm
off my game today guys.
OK, that works.
clock dot inner HTML.
It was HTML Really?
Also this is what happens.
When you can't see something, you
just look at your source code.
OK.
Do you wanna know a cool work around
that we're going to do right here?
>> AUDIENCE: Can you do capital letters?
The capital letters?
Because you have get hours,
and then get minutes.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It
is get hours and get-- oh.
You are-- gold star.
It's all a test, guys.
I promise it was working before class.
>> OK, but something cool to know is
that you can also-- if sometimes
your external files are
getting a little crazy,
you can also just put them straight
in here, which tends to fix things.
Except this is like really ugly.
Of course format everything.
Make sure it's all pretty.
OK.
>> I wanted to do all the cool demos,
and they're just not working out.
OK.
Script var clock.
Anyways, what's important is
that this is the general way
that you would format JavaScript.
As you can see, it can be
very finicky sometimes,
even when it was literally
working two seconds ago.
Or not two second ago,
but very, very recently.
>> So to show you what it should look like,
and to show you that I'm not crazy,
and that everything is exactly the
same, this is what it should look like.
You're just going to do this top part
here, and if you view page source,
if you notice, he did some
crazier things, I simplified it.
Also, credit to Tommy
McWilliam, who actually
helped me create these examples,
which is why I know they work.
Because Tommy is a JavaScript master.
But if we notice, we have some set.
We have our clock function here.
This is all the JavaScript that
we just wrote, or some of it.
We just wrote this one right here.
And he has an extra
function that just pads it
by putting a zero before a
letter or before a number if it's
just one of them.
So if you notice, this is pretty
much exactly what we just wrote.
You have some variable clock that
has our element, get element by ID,
which is clock.
We have our set interval
function, that's
an anonymous function
that executes all of this.
We have some starting string of
HTML that we then dynamically
generate by having some
h1 header, concatenating
with get the hours, plus
our colon, plus getting
the minutes, plus another
colon, plus our seconds,
and finally the ending HTML for it.
And then we update our clock
dot inner HTML to HTML,
and we update every 100 milliseconds.
OK?
>> See I promise I'm not crazy.
I don't know.
I don't know why it doesn't like me.
I feel like looks the same,
but apparently it hates me.
>> So let's see if round three goes better.
We're about to see.
I'm not sure how this is going to go.
Is everyone at least getting the
cons, like just the general theme
of JavaScript, though?
I hope that's at least useful, more
than showing that it's a little finicky.
But your problem set will be very fun.
It's going to be great.
It won't be quite as tedious
as this, I don't think.
You'll actually get to
see really cool things.
>> So last but not least,
we'll try the Twitter one.
I'm really scared now, guys.
I don't know how this is going to go.
But just to give you a little
more taste, and this is actually
manipulating strings and
inputs, what we're going to do
is, if we notice here with HTML--
this one has a little bit more--
we have some text area, which
corresponds to this text area here.
OK?
And that has an Id of text.
We restyled it a little bit
with some width and height
that we've predetermined,
and we have h1,
which just is our header one that
represents our characters left.
We gave it some Id of
characters remaining,
and then we have some script
here, which I'm really
hoping third time's
the charm here, guys.
>> So what we want to do,
in the same general vein
that we've done with clock dot js
and party dot js as we've noticed,
is we've started by actually grabbing
the things that we care about, right?
So in this case, there are two
things that we care about, OK?
One thing that we're actually kind of
looking into and drawing data from,
and one thing that
we're actually changing.
So there's our HTML.
If this is our web page here, what's
the data that we're looking at?
It's going to be whatever
the text in our boxes, right?
So whatever I type in here.
That's what I want to know, or
that's what I want to look at.
And what's going to be
changing on our web page?
The characters remaining.
So in the same way, we want to
start by initializing variables
that actually hold onto those elements.
OK?
So if we have some var
that is our text area,
and we have some var that is remaining.
Right?
So these are going to
hold those two things.
So the same sort of thing,
document dot-- OK, I'm
going to make sure this is
going to work this time.
I am very adamant.
OK, so if we want our
text area, according
to our HTML, what's our identifier?
What's our Id?
It's just going to be text because
this creates our text area, OK,
and our Id is text, so that's
how we can grab what's in there.
OK, semicolon.
I'm going to be super
precise about this,
because I want this to work this time.
OK, do the same thing,
get element by Id.
I'm really wondering what has
caused the other two to mess up.
OK, then in this one,
what do we want to access?
What's our Id here?
We have another Id in
our HTML, what is it?
AUDIENCE: Characters remaining.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
Characters remaining.
>> OK.
Cool.
So I'm just going to
write this really fast.
I'm just going to write this in second.
So text area.
What's interesting is B function-- there
are lots of functions that not only
correspond to your
mouse, but your keyboard.
OK?
So you can say when any key is
pressed, you can do things like that.
So the one that we're using
is called on key up, which
says, "if you've pressed any key on
your keyboard, when the user has lifted
their finger off that button,
and the key has become unpressed,
then we're going to do something."
OK?
So this makes sense, right?
Because every character
we type, we're going
to have to lift our fingers off
of it, so when the key goes up,
we can know to decrement
our characters remaining.
>> So we have some on key
up, and in the same way,
we're going to say,
"OK, when we do that, we
are going to create some function that
is going to take e," in this case,
and what we want to do is
calculate the number remaining.
OK, so let's just start
by creating a variable.
So we have some variable r,
that's going to represent
how many characters we have left.
OK?
We know that we start with
140, and if we want to know,
let's say, the length of this
string that's been input,
do you guys have any idea
how we might do that?
Just based off of the obvious
things, like if we wanted hours,
we used get hours.
We know that our object is
text area, but could you guys
think of what might come after it?
Any ideas?
>> So this one's kind of less
intuitive, but it's value dot length.
So just give me some
value attribute that
is actually the length of this string.
So it's going to say, "OK, I'm looking
at this entire string within text area,
and I'm going to tell
you how long it is."
Because if we remember strings
are really just arrays,
so we can just take the length of them.
So we have that.
Cool.
>> Then what we want to do is we
never want to allow the user
to input more than
140 characters, right?
Because if we say like, "oh, you
only have this much remaining,"
and then let them do that
anyways, we've been lying.
And this is another
thing that JavaScript
can be really good
for, is user validation
and making sure that your
user fits within any rules
that you've provided to them.
So if you want to do things like making
sure someone input their email address,
or making sure that when they
enter two passwords, they matched.
JavaScript can do that.
You would do something like, "when
the form is submitted," or like,
"when Submit Form button is
clicked, check all these things."
And we can do that JavaScript.
So that's just what
we're going to do here.
>> So what might be a way to check if
they've gone over 140 characters?
What's going to happen to
our value of r if they try?
It's going to be negative, right?
Or it's going to be less
than or equal to zero.
So we can use an if that is
just like everything else.
OK?
And we have some text area dot
value, and what we're doing here
is we're just cutting-- what is it?
Sorry.
This one, we just want to return false.
I got confused.
All frazzled from things not working.
OK, we just want to
return false, and then we
want to display the
remaining characters, right?
So with the clock, we did
something with inner HTML, right?
Where we set it equal to some
variable, so what might we do here?
What are we changing the inner HTML of?
>> AUDIENCE: Remaining?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
We're changing remaining.
All right, and what do we
want to set it equal to?
It's going to be r, because that
should be our characters remaining.
OK?
So I'm really nervous to see if
this works now, but we'll see.
Leave this.
That's really fast.
[INAUDIBLE] OK.
Again, I'm just going to show you.
For whatever reason,
mine decides not to work,
but what I will show you is that this
is-- oh I was supposed to put that in.
OK, we notice the same sort of
thing here, getting the text area.
>> Also, if you guy notice, if there's
ever something you want to do,
and you don't know how to do
it, just click View Page Source,
and they're going to tell you.
Sometimes it'll be encrypted.
For your pset, we encrypt everything,
so it just looks like gibberish.
But if there's ever a really
cool website that you like,
if you just click View Page Source,
it's going to tell you how to do it.
So again, work smarter, not harder.
And as you see here, all of
these things are the same.
this one here just takes some substring
that, I forget exactly what this does.
But it obviously takes some substring
of the value from zero to ten,
and returns false what should stop
the user from inputting anymore,
and then obviously updates
the inner HTML there.
>> Cool.
So big take aways from today,
experiment, look at source code
because it's going to help you a lot,
and everyone, sometimes JavaScript
can be hard to work with and doesn't
always work the way you expect it to,
but just keep trying
because I promise it will.
I promise all of these examples
were working before class.
I don't understand what happened.
I literally have everything the same.
>> One more thing that I just want to
show you guys that can be super useful
is in-- what was working before?
We got party to work, didn't we?
I think so.
Yes.
We did.
Awesome.
OK, so one thing that
you guys should know
is the console log that I talked about.
So console dot log of hello.
So this is kind of the
JavaScript equivalent of printf.
So if you ever want to
inspect your variables
or see what's happening there, what
you can do is, if we inspect element,
is what you want to go
to, and you go to console,
you'll see that it printed hello.
>> So we could have it
print whatever we wanted.
If we wanted it to print background
dot style dot background,
we should be able to see the
RGB triple that comes up.
Or not.
I forget exactly how you
print a variable like that,
but you should be able to
print out things like that.
That will be very useful
for your pset when
you're trying to manipulate
coordinates or whatnot.
So they also change this piece in class.
This is different from last years, so
just be nice to your TFs, or the TFs
at office hours rather, because we're
kind of learning along with you guys.
But the console log was super, super
helpful for JavaScript last year.
So love it.
Learn how to use it.
It's easier to use than GDB, so that
should be at least a plus point.
But thank you guys are bearing with me.
I'm sorry that my
examples for some reason
just did not want to
cooperate with me, but I
hope that it helped kind of get you a
little more in the zone of JavaScript.
And send me all your questions for
next week so I can be super repaired,
and I'll bring candy and even extra
candy because this was ridiculous.
But you guys are great,
and have an awesome week.