>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Hey everyone.
Welcome to your first
official CS50 section.
As you can, see this is
section CS50-like, just
to pull up our agenda for today.
So, who am I, as I'm sure
you're all wondering.
I am your TF.
I'm not just a random student
who's impersonating your TF.
>> And I'm going to go through
kind of have sections will flow,
expectations we have,
resources, so on and so forth.
We're going to talk about arrays, ASCII
functions, command-line arguments,
and it's not on here, but
I will also be helping
you kind of think through
your next pset for this week.
Which I am sure you will all appreciate.
>> So, first question-- who am I,
besides your exuberant TF here.
I'm Alison Buchholtz-Au.
This is my second year TFing CS50.
I also TF CS51 in the Spring.
You might see again there
if you decide to take it.
I'm also a PAF, so any Freshmen--
and if you're not a freshman,
this is my third year
as an advising fellow.
I'm very well-versed in
advising you on life and courses
within CS and not within CS.
I am a Computer Science Concentrator.
I'm a senior in Adams House, best house.
And before I switched to
CS my Sophomore Spring,
I was actually a biomedical engineer.
I was going to go to Med school.
I was going to be a trauma surgeon.
And that has completely
changed since I took CS50.
I took the course my Sophomore Fall.
It was my first introduction to CS ever.
I was one of the 78% of you who
had zero experience coming in,
and it completely changed my life.
And now I'm working at
Microsoft, and your lovely TF.
And CS50 is probably one
of the best experiences
that I've had here at
Harvard-- both taking the class
and being able to help
teach students like you.
>> So I'm really excited
that you're all here.
In case you came in
late, there is candy,
which you should feel
free to come grab, or send
someone else to grab it for you.
it's OK.
I don't want to eat that.
My room has enough chocolate, so
y'all should try and finish that.
I know there are 100 pieces,
but like, 4 o'clock on a Monday,
I think everyone could use some sugar.
>> So all of you who are
officially in my section
should have gotten an email
from me with my phone number,
email address-- feel free to add me on
Gchat, feel free to add me on Facebook,
and also for the rest of you,
you can email me right here.
There are two H's.
Everyone always does
like two L's or two C's.
Two H's in the last name.
Otherwise it's going to bounce, and
I'm not going to get your email.
>> So feel free to email me,
to contact me at any time.
I may not get back to
you within 24 minutes,
but I promise to get back
to you within 24 hours.
If you call me half an hour before
your pset is due, you being like,
I have no idea what I'm doing Allison.
Help me.
I'm going to calm you down,
but at the end of the day,
if you're calling me half an hour before
your pset is due with nothing written,
I'm going to be like, well, maybe
it's time to use that late day.
So I will respond to all of your
requests in a very timely manner.
My phone is usually
attached to my hands.
I typically respond much
quicker than 24 hours,
but I can only guarantee
a 24 hour response.
>> All right.
So why are we here?
Also, if you have questions at
any time, please let me know.
I talk a lot.
I talk fast, but please
feel free to interrupt me.
It gives me breathing room as well.
So sections are a time
for us to really just dive
in, get some hands-on experience, to
go through topics that we mentioned
in class or in study materials that
we recommend to you guys online.
And we'll actually go through
some of those resources in a bit.
>> So some notes on section support.
CS50-- one of things that makes
it one of my favorite classes
is the feeling that you're never alone.
We have a staff of over 100
people who are here to help you.
We have office hours
Monday through Thursday.
So there are so many people who
love the class just as much as I do
and who are really here
because they want to be here.
Most of us are students, and this
is like a fifth class in addition
to the rest of our work.
>> And it's a lot of work, but
we do it because we love it,
and we really love to teach you
and help share our excitement
for this subject and this class.
So please take advantage.
Come talk to us.
I get lonely when my students
don't talk to me, so if you want,
come hang out with me.
It'll be great.
>> So section is obviously
one of your biggest things.
We'll go through things
that you learned in lecture,
do some short examples
when we have time,
and generally kind of
get an idea about things
you should be thinking
about for your problem set.
Shorts-- how many people actually
watched the video from your scratch
short?
Anyone recognize me?
So those are very great.
You should definitely watch those.
A lot of work has been put into them.
And they're just meant to be
bite-size pieces for you to just watch
for three or four minutes and get a
better understanding of a concept.
Walk throughs-- how
many people have watched
the walk-throughs for previous ones?
Zamyla is amazing, right?
Like, I wish I were Zamyla sometimes.
So definitely use your walk-throughs.
She will break it down into
small, bite-size pieces.
And when you have these huge
specifications from your problem sets,
it's going to be really important
to be able to just find somewhere
to start and work slowly through it.
>> All right, we also have Study50, which
is study50.harvard.edu, I believe.
You can just Google
study, and it'll come up.
This is one of the
best resources we have.
It is PowerPoints with notes
and practice problems for you
with solutions that you
can actually walk through.
So if you ever want more practice,
more than we do in sections or more
than your problem sets, this is
really a place I encourage you to go.
It was built last summer by
some of my really good friends.
And it's amazing.
In fact, a lot of the slides
that I'll be using for Section
will come from Study50.
>> So a lot of the TFs use it.
And finally, as I
mentioned, office hours.
If you're having trouble
with homework, you're
having trouble with a
concept, come to office hours.
Go early in the week if you can.
Get out to the quad,
because it is kind of far.
No one likes to walk out there.
But it is to your advantage,
because then you're
going to have all these TFs,
[INAUDIBLE] surround you.
And especially now,
just a tip, Thursdays
are very chill right now in
Mather because your psets
are due on Thursdays.
And knowing wants to
use your late days yet.
>> So if you're having
trouble with concepts,
there are lots of TFs who
are there to help you.
So come out to Mather on Thursday.
If you want to see me,
I'm going to be there.
I'm typically doing my own homework,
because no one wants my help.
So come see us.
>> Meet us halfway.
So how many people have attended
lecture or watched it online?
How many people went to
super section last week?
Cool.
That's actually a fair number.
How many of you have read your
spec for this week, for your pset?
Ooh, I'm proud of you guys!
More candy for y'all.
>> Good, so what we mean
"meet us halfway," is
that section is really only
going to be super useful to you
if you come in having read your
specification for your pset.
Because when I go through an overview
of things you should be looking out for,
it's not going to make
as much sense if you
don't know what your problem set
is going to be asking you to do.
>> If you don't come to section, obviously
I can't be that useful to you.
I'm not going to take it personally if
you don't come to my section right now,
but definitely you should.
If you can't, watch them online.
They're there for a reason.
Mine will be right there.
As you notice, we're being recorded,
so it'll be right there for you guys.
As well, going to
lectures-- that's obviously
where you're getting the
start of your material here.
So I will definitely try and
help you as much as I can,
but I can only meet you so far.
You have to kind of
meet us halfway there.
>> Grading-- so, all of you
who got an email from me,
you are my official section.
I will be grading your psets.
And I just want to say, one thing that
you should really pay attention to
are the comments.
The comments are often more useful
than the actual score we give you.
And the comments are actually
where I spend a lot of my time
when I'm grading.
So I would appreciate
it if you read them.
And they're actually how you're going
to learn more about design and style
and things that are a
little less cut and dry.
>> So really pay attention
to those comments.
If you have questions about them,
or questions about your score,
please come talk to me
either before section,
I'll probably be hanging out
in the lobby, or afterwards.
If you want to schedule
one-on-one meetings about how
you can help improve later
problem sets, just let me know.
>> And then just a couple
of tips for you guys.
So one of the biggest things
I always stress to my section
when you're learning how to code is
to write things out on paper first.
If you have a game plan for
where your code needs to go
and what it needs to
do and it's broken down
into little bits of pseudocode
code you've written out,
you're going to be less
likely to make syntax errors
or create an if loop that
doesn't have an else.
If you know where you're
going overall, you're
less likely to make these tiny
mistakes that will sometimes take you
hours to fix, because you're like,
where am I missing this bracket?
>> On that note, please use Style50.
Especially when you're
going to office hours,
if your code is all
switched over to one side,
it is course policy
that we can say, fix it
so that it looks like Style50 says
it should, and then we'll help you.
So it'll make your life easier.
It'll make our lives easier.
Everyone's happier.
Everyone gets better grades.
Isn't that what we all want?
>> So write things out on paper before
you ever touch your computer.
Talk things out at a high level, and
make sure you know where you're going.
And if you're unsure,
sit down with someone
and walk them through step by step
what your code is supposed to do.
And nine times out of 10, you'll be
like, oh, I forgot an if condition
or I forgot a semicolon here or
I'm updating this variable wrong.
So those are my tips for success.
>> So since about half of you look
like you attended super section,
I'm just going to very
briefly go through loops,
which weren't on our original agenda.
But they are really important.
And so I'm going to kind
of speed through those
before we get into our actual section.
Before I do that, are there
any questions-- logistically,
personally, is there
anything else you want
to know about me or about
section or class in general?
All good?
OK, cool.
Lovely.
>> So loops-- you guys should all
recognize these pieces from scratch.
So loops are basically just
a way for us to do something
some number of times, some repeated
action based on some conditional.
So we have three different types.
We have for loop, while, and do-while.
>> So for loops-- we just have a very
general layout here of a for loop.
And this is great for when you know how
many times something needs to execute.
When we talk about the
other loops, you'll
see why that's an important distinction.
But for loops are for something set.
You know you can either
calculate the number
or you know the number of times you
want this repeated at the beginning.
>> So if you see here, we
have just a general kind
of skeleton framework
for a for loop here.
So for-initialization, this is where
your variables are initialized.
With Mario, I'm sure you guys did
something like int i equals 0.
That's where that would happen in blue.
You have your condition, which
is what's checked every time.
If this condition is true, then
the rest of the code executes.
Then it'll run again-- and ask.
And then we have update, where
you're updating your variable.
So, again, with like Mario, I'm sure
you guys did something like i plus plus.
So every time the loop
ran, i got updated so
that when we were checking it against
some condition, it was changing.
>> Because if you just
have a static variable,
if it executes the first time, it's
just going to execute infinitely.
So you have to make sure you
update your variable properly.
And we also have just a
visual representation there.
Everyone good?
For loops.
Should have seen these in your pset.
Cool.
>> So here's just an easy example.
Print This is CS50!
10 times.
And so we have our initialization,
as we see there, with int i
equals 0, for i is less
than 10, and i plus plus.
And it'll print that 10 times.
>> So while loops-- while loops are
great when you don't necessarily
have to know how many times it's
going to update in the beginning.
You just have some
condition that's checked.
And this could be something like while--
let's take an example from your pset.
If Mario, you try to
input a negative number.
Right?
You were supposed to
re-prompt your user.
So you can say, well, if the user inputs
something less than zero, re-prompt
them.
And I'm sure that might have
been something that some of you
used in your code.
>> So it's a simple thing.
You have while, some
conditional that is checked
every time the code goes to execute.
If it evaluates to true, we run it.
Otherwise we don't.
And what's really
important-- something I
think that David talked about
in lecture-- are the braces.
Whatever's within the
braces is what's executed.
If you forget those
braces, it's only going
to be the line directly
after the while was executed.
>> So if you have three
things that are supposed
to happen when this
condition evaluates to true,
and you don't have those braces, only
the first thing is going to happen.
So be very cognizant of
where you put your braces.
If you stick with Style50,
this will definitely help you.
Cool.
>> So this is a countdown from 10 to zero.
And as you see here, we initialize
some counter outside of it.
One thing that's different is
we're not initializing our variable
within our while loop.
It's initialized outside of it.
We are simply just putting the
condition in for our while.
So in this case, it's while
count is greater than zero.
And we print out what our count is,
and then we decrement our variable.
And that's also another thing to notice.
Our update doesn't happen within
that first part of the while loop.
It will actually happen within
the braces, the body of your text.
>> So do-while loops-- do-while loops
are great for user validation.
So some of you might have
also used this in your pset.
You can say, do, like,
ask the user for input.
And then while, like, the
input is less than some number.
>> So for an explicit case with Mario, it
would be do printf, enter an integer,
and then some integer equals getint.
And then it'll actually
execute that code first.
You'll actually have
some sort of integer.
And then you could say, while
that integer is less than zero.
So what it's going to do is it's
going to execute at least once.
It's going to check the condition.
If the condition is
true, it'll run again.
>> So do-while loops are
great for user validation,
because you know the code
is going to execute at least
once, whereas with
while loops, you're not
guaranteed that it's
going to execute once.
It's going to check the condition
first and then decide to execute it,
while a do-while will
execute the code first
and then check to see whether
you need to repeat it.
Does that distinction
make sense to everyone?
OK.
Cool.
>> So in this case, this is kind
of what I was talking about,
this re-prompts until you
get a positive number.
So we know that printf
"enter a positive number"
and actually asking for that
input will happen at least once.
If the user is evil and keeps
entering a negative number, who
knows how many times it'll execute.
But this code is guaranteed
to execute at least once.
And that's why it's great
for validating input.
And you will use that quite a bit.
>> All right, any questions so far?
We're all good?
Am I talking too fast?
We're good?
OK.
Awesome
>> So we're going to go ahead
and talk about arrays.
Cool.
So arrays are basically
just data structures
that allow us to store
things of the same type.
So if you ever have an array, it's
either just going to have ints
or it's just going to have floats
or it's just going to have chars.
You're not going to have an int with
a char with a float with a double.
One thing.
Arrays are just one size,
or they're just one type.
>> So here we have an array of size
three with three integers in it.
They could floats, but we're
going to say they're ints.
So one thing to realize is that arrays
are a set size when you initialize
them, and they are not easily--
since you all are less comfortable,
you should just think of them as
not being able to extend in size.
However big you set out
your array in the beginning,
that's the size it's going
to stay, because arrays
are continuous blocks of memory.
And when you guys get
into a little bit more
of how memory's actually laid out on
disks and in the heap and the stack,
it'll make a little more sense.
>> But you could just think of like, it's
just a row of spaces on your disk.
And you can't guarantee that there's
going to be free space after it.
You could initialize an array
of three and then maybe you
initialize another array of five
later, and it's right after that.
So if you were to go past spot
three in that first array,
you would be writing
over something else.
So arrays are-- for you guys, just
think of them as a fixed size.
>> So creating an array-- you're going
to need to do this quite a bit.
So in the same way that we have a
general structure for our for loops,
we have a nice general
structure for our array.
Because they are of one type, all the
elements in an array are of one type,
you need to initialize
what that type is.
>> So, as you see here, we have a
nice little bracket data type.
So if we're creating an int
array, that will be int.
If we're creating a char
array, it'll be char.
If we're creating a string
array, it'll be string.
And then the name of your array,
whatever you'd like it to be.
So maybe it's test scores or maybe
it's students or maybe it's candy.
Whatever you decide to name your
array, that's what it'll be.
>> And then in brackets, you'll
have the size that you want.
So, are we storing 10 students or
are we storing 15 types of candy?
What not.
So in our example here,
we're creating an array
of size three, which you guys
see right here on the right.
And when we first initialize
it, everything is set to zero.
So it's just thought
of like a blank slate.
We have all these spaces, we have all
these boxes we could put our data into,
but they're just blank
for the time being.
>> So if we want to actually
assign them these values,
we do so as right under here shows.
So you have whatever the name of your
array is and then what index you want.
So the index just refers to,
like, what slot we're looking at.
And an important thing to notice
is that arrays are zero-indexed.
So if we want the first space in memory
of our array, it's going to be zero.
If we want the second, it'll be one.
If we want the third, it'll be two.
So on and so forth.
>> Which is also why, conventionally,
when we do for loops-- I'm sure
you guys were wondering, why
do we start at 0 versus 1?
And that's because when we transition
into using arrays, it maps correctly.
So if you want to
iterate into an array, it
makes a lot more sense to
do i equals 0, because we
know that will correspond
to the first spot in memory.
Everyone good with that?
Cool.
>> And then on the bottom here is just
another way to initialize an array.
You still have your
data type and the name,
but instead of actually
putting a size in there,
you can just do empty brackets.
And then with these curly
braces at the bottom,
you can just input the data that
you want separated by commas.
And that will automatically
say, OK, I see
that you have three
things in these braces.
So I know that I need to allocate three
blocks of memory and then store those.
>> So the first version you might use
if you're asking your user to input
values so that you can
iterate through the array
and ask-- get some int to input them.
If you know the values beforehand,
it makes a lot more sense
to use the second way.
But in most cases, you might not know
what those values are going to be.
Cool.
Any other questions?
Alright.
>> So accessing elements-- so one
of the great things about arrays
is that they are random
access, meaning that you
don't have to look through every block.
If you know that you
want what's in block two,
you can just say, give me block two.
And that's why these
indices are so important,
and that's how we actually access them.
So in this case, as we saw before when
we were assigning values, in the one
before, we had the name and the
index we wanted to access, right?
So in the same way, that's all we
do to actually pull that data out.
We have the name and we
have the index that we want.
>> So in this case, the for loop
down here at the bottom, anyone
know what it's doing,
what it would print out?
Mmhmm?
Exactly.
So yeah, it's just iterating through.
i is equal to zero-- we can walk
through the code just quickly.
i is equal to zero, i is less
than three at this point, right?
So that checks out.
And we say, OK, print f
whatever is in temperature i.
i is zero right here when we first
iterate, so we go to this first spot,
and we say, OK, 65 is the
number we want to print out.
So it'll print out 65
and then do a new line.
i will update, so it prints 87.
It updates again, and it'll print 30.
Everyone cool?
Awesome.
>> All right.
So here's kind of one
thing I was saying how
you can keep track of
someone's score and why
you would use the first
way of initializing it
instead of that second way.
And this just goes through.
And notice we have a class size of 30.
And we're initializing this
array of ints that is of size 30.
And then we are iterating
through and we're
asking the user to input
scores for each of these
and then assigning it to
a specific place in memory
somewhere in that array.
Cool?
Does that make sense to everyone?
Mmhmm?
>> So hashtag define class size
30 is a preprocessor directive,
which just means it gets-- it has
to do like the compiling process.
You can think of it
as a global variable.
The way we do it is
typically-- it allows your code
to be more easily changed.
So let's say that our class size
suddenly goes from 30 to 15,
if I hadn't defined it this way, I would
have to go through my entire program
and change every instance of 30 to 15.
But with this, I get to change one
spot, and everything else changes.
>> If you ever want to do
a hash define in a case
where you're keeping track of some
set number of scores for a class
or you're using a number
that will be used, like,
throughout a very long program, it's
better to define that at the beginning
so that if ever it changes, you get
to change one spot instead of 100.
Yes?
>> STUDENT: Between doing that and just
declaring [INAUDIBLE] over at the top.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So it
has to do with efficient--
it's kind of outside the scope of
what we can cover in this section.
It has to do more with efficiency
and how things actually
work in the compiling process.
If you want to really know
about it, I'm happy to send you
an email with resources about it.
Hash define tends to be
preferred for things.
And as you code more, you
kind of learn the nuances
of when you should use a
global versus the hash define.
But for the time being,
you don't really have
to worry about it is
that the short answer.
Everyone good with that?
And also, if you want
to use a hash define,
it's really important to notice
that the name should be in all caps.
We're not just doing
CLASS SIZE to be dramatic.
It should actually be in all caps.
Cool.
Anything else there?
We're good?
Lovely.
Welcome.
>> OK, so I want you guys to take a look
at this and see if you can find the bug.
I'll give you a hint.
It's somewhere in that for-loop.
Mmhmm?
>> STUDENT: Should be less than equal to 2.
>> ALLISON: So it could be less than or
equal to 2, or it could be less than 3.
And what's the reasoning for that?
>> STUDENT: The [INAUDIBLE], 0, 1, 2.
>> ALLISON: Exactly.
So in an array of size n, we
only have indices of n minus 1.
Cool.
And then we can get really crazy
and get multi-dimensional arrays.
One of the problems when I took it in my
year required multi-dimensional arrays,
and I think one of them might require
it this year, so be comfortable.
Wrap your head around it now.
It will come back to haunt
you, but in a cool way.
So you can really just think
of multi-dimensional arrays
as arrays of arrays.
So you can kind of think of this top
row as the first chunk of memory.
And this one is the
second chunk of memory,
and the last row is the
third chunk of memory.
And within that, there's an array.
But of course, it's easier
to depict like this.
>> So you initialize it the same way.
This is a character
board of three by three.
So you have three rows
and three columns.
We're representing it this way.
And you would access it the
same way, column by row.
And so 1,1 as we see here.
We assign a zero, zero up there.
2,0 and 0,2.
So you would just access them-- if
anyone's ever done linear algebra,
the same way you access an element in
a matrice, it's the same idea here.
So you can relate it back to math.
You don't have to worry too
much about this right now.
It's good to have exposure,
to know that you can do it.
You can create some
crazy number-- you can
create crazy arrays is
all I'm going to say.
[INAUDIBLE]
It gets a little crazy,
but it's really cool.
Awesome.
>> And then, so we have an example here.
It calculates a string length.
So how many people knew that
the strings that you're using
are just arrays of characters?
OK, yeah.
So you guys may think that you haven't
used arrays before, but any time
you use getstring in the
CSView library, you're
actually just asking for
an array of characters.
And we're taking care of all
that in the back-end for you.
But you have been using
arrays since you started.
You just didn't know it yet.
>> And whenever you have a character array
or an array that's storing a string,
the last thing is always what's
called a null terminator, which
is this right here.
And that is at the end of
every word that you're storing.
So if we want to figure out the
length of a string, we can say,
well, you know, the
contents of that block
is not equal to our null terminator.
That means that there is some
character there that we actually
care about that's part of the word.
You increase your length.
And then when we actually get to
the end of the word, it'll terminate
and it'll return our length for us.
Mmhmm?
>> STUDENT: Does the space
count as the null terminator?
ALLISON: So a space is
not a null terminator.
So if you have multiple-- a space
is actually a specific ASCII value.
STUDENT: What's the
exclamation equal again?
ALLISON: So, this is what you refer to.
If you ever hear me in office hours,
I always call it, like, bang equals.
So bang is not.
So this is not equals.
So if you're trying to
see if something's false,
you know always do, bang whatever
the variable is, and if it's false,
it evaluates to true and you
can do cool stuff with that.
More on that later.
Cool.
Everything good there?
Awesome.
>> So now it's your guys' time to
work, since I've been talking.
So I want you to just create an array
with the integers one, two, and three,
and then have them printed out.
You don't have to do, like,
main, blah, blah, blah, whatever.
I just want you to initialize
the array and then create
a for loop to print them out--
or a while loop, up to you.
>> I'll just give you a couple
minutes to work on that.
I'm going to rest my voice.
If you have any questions, I'm happy
to come around and talk to you guys.
Feel free to talk with each other.
Get more candy.
In fact, I'll just
walk around with candy.
How's that?
>> Do you want any?
Anyone else in this room want candy?
You can also take more than one, guys.
Take a handful if you want.
May as well.
Everyone else good?
OK.
>> Also, I'm going to create
an anonymous Google Form,
and you guys can just submit
feedback after every section
if there's something you want to
improve upon or something you want done.
If I'm a little too peppy
for you, I can tone it down.
I'll create that and send that
out to you all afterwards.
>> All right.
So let's start small.
How would we initialize our array?
What's the type of our array?
An int, right?
OK, so what do you want
to call your array?
Int array, cool.
All right, so we have int int array
equals, and what do we have after that?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] brackets.
ALLISON: Braces.
And then inside the braces?
One comma two comma three.
Cool.
So that's all right.
So now we have our for loop.
So in the first part of our
for loop, what do we have?
>> STUDENT: i equals 0?
>> ALLISON: So int i equals 0,
and then what is our condition?
What's i going to be less than?
Less than three, and
how we do we update i?
i plus plus, updating it by one.
And then we're going to have
some printf of the integer,
and what is that last
part that's actually
going to say what we should be printing?
It would be the name of the
array, which is int array, right?
And what's in the brackets of int array?
i.
[? So I ?] called my
example, but there you go.
Not that bad.
Everyone good?
Cool.
>> So we're done with the arrays.
Congrats.
You managed to iterate
through all the-- yes?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
>> ALLISON: Yes.
>> STUDENT: I have a question.
Are you supposed to indent the braces?
>> ALLISON: So the braces should line up
with the for loop, and then everything
inside the braces should be indented.
>> STUDENT: OK, should the
for loop be indented?
>> ALLISON: The for loop does not
need to be indented at this point.
If you were in main, if we
actually had a main function here,
it would be indented from main.
But in this case, it's fine.
Yes, question.
>> STUDENT: Do you need to have
the brackets after example?
>> ALLISON: Yes, if you're
initializing it that way.
So remember, this is the second
way of initializing an array where
we have the braces and then our actual
data separated by commas within.
>> STUDENT: I thought there were
brackets for that example.
>> ALLISON: No, they're braces.
They're braces.
If you're initializing it
that second way, it's braces.
If we were to say, int example-- if
we just wanted a blank array for ints,
it would be int example brackets three.
The brackets represent the size.
When you have braces,
it's the actual data
you're putting into it in this way.
We can scroll back really fast.
>> So in this one, this is just our
initial array, initialization.
And here, we are individually
assigning spots to them,
so this represents the index of our
array, which is why we have brackets.
But here, if you notice, we've
left our brackets without a size,
and we initialize it with the
actual data all-in-one with braces.
STUDENT: So why don't we have
brackets in this example?
ALLISON: So, in which part?
STUDENT: Wouldn't we
say, int example brackets
equals braces [INAUDIBLE]
brackets for example.
>> ALLISON: Oh, sorry.
You're right.
We do have brackets there.
Sorry guys, my bad.
Yes, you should have
brackets after example.
You're absolutely right.
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] not doing it.
>> ALLISON: No, you have to have
brackets, because otherwise it's
not going to declare an array.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
Sorry about that.
>> ALLISON: Sorry, you need
brackets after example.
Typo.
Good catch, gold star for you.
Also, if you are asking a question, if
you guys would just tell me your names,
I'd love that.
I'd love to be able to
know all your names.
I'm not going to cold
call you, I actually
do just want to know your names.
So please actually tell me your names.
>> LEAH: Leah.
>> ALLISON: Leah.
OK, so functions-- I know in brief
they talked about this during lecture.
So functions are kind of just
like these little bite-size things
where you pass in inputs, something
magical happens, and you get outputs.
Cool.
So you actually used a
lot of these already.
Get int, get string, print f.
These are all functions
where you just call them,
there's lots of magical things
going on in the background
that you don't necessarily see,
and you get out what you want.
Or at least you get
what you hope you want.
>> And basically the point of functions,
and one of the main themes of CS,
is to break your code
into manageable pieces.
When you start writing
these really long programs,
or in Scratch when you had
this grand idea for a game,
you need to be able to break it
down to, like, OK, how do I start?
What are the little pieces that I need?
Oh, I need to ask the
user for something.
Now I need to print something.
Oh, I need to calculate this value.
>> And learning how to break up your
code and the large problems you
have into these small pieces
and creating functions
is actually one of the
big cornerstones of CS.
So you can think of a function just as
like a black box, a magical black box,
that you put things into
and you get some output.
And the rest of the program
doesn't need to necessarily know
what's going on within that black box.
All it cares about is what
goes in and what comes out.
Cool.
>> So why functions?
Organization-- as I said, when you're
dealing with very large code bases,
how you organize your code will be
much easier if you use functions.
Because you'll be able
to be, like, OK, this
is what this function does and
here's what another one does.
And you can easily see
how they all fit together.
So breaking it up into all
these manageable subparts.
>> So simplification-- I'm sure you guys
all saw this, as I said, with Scratch.
You have this grand idea, and
you're like, how does all this work?
But if you approach it
piecemeal, you say, OK,
how do I make one sprite
float across the screen?
That's a little bit easier.
So good use of function makes
your code much easier to read.
It makes it easier to debug which as
you get into your later problem sets,
you're going to really
want to be able to do.
And they're also easier
to design and implement.
You can code up a small
function relatively quickly
and make sure it works versus trying
to create this whole long program
and then kind of go through and
see what's working and what's not.
>> And then reusability.
So functions only need
to be written once,
and then you can use them
as many times as possible.
So it's, like, eco-friendly in a sense.
If you had things like
print f, where you
had to write out the magic that goes
on behind print f every single time
you wanted to print something, you
would be pretty sick and tired of it
by the end.
>> One of the things that you'll
learn in later CS classes,
or one of the best
pieces of advice I get
is, if you are copying and pasting
code, it should probably be a function.
If you have the exact same
lines all throughout your code,
if you factored them out,
your code would probably
be, like, five times shorter
and be much more easy to read.
And instead of trying to troubleshoot
all these different places where things
might go wrong, you have one function
that you get to troubleshoot.
And I promise, a lot of this
might seem kind of abstract now,
but as you get into later
and later problem sets,
it'll make a lot more sense
and really be driven home.
Are there any questions
about functions so far?
Why we're using them?
I know we haven't gotten
into the nitty gritty yet.
So defining a function-- just like
arrays, we need some sort of-- this
is just the general output.
So this is a function that's
just going to cube some input.
And on the next page, actually, we have
all these awesome little things here.
So, can everyone read
that, out of curiosity?
I know the purple and black
might be a little hard.
>> But big things to know-- so the first
one right here is our return type.
So this is talking about the output
of this function when, in this case,
we put in some number, what we're
getting is that number cubed.
So it should be an int in this case.
Maybe it would be a double or
something else later, but in this case,
it's an int.
>> With c, you always need a return type.
It'll be an int.
It'll be a float.
It'll be a double.
But you have to specify what
this function is going to return.
Otherwise it will yell at
you, and it won't compile.
You'll be sad, and I'll be sad.
And it's just not good.
OK.
>> And then we have our function name.
And as you can see here, with c
there's this very consistent paradigm.
What's your type, what's the name,
and then some other thing at the end.
So we have our return type,
our function name, and then
we have our header with
our parameter list.
>> So the parameter list is, what is
this function going to take in?
A parameter list is simply a
synonym for, what are our inputs?
And in the same way that we
have to define our function
and give it a return
type, each of our inputs
needs to have a type associated with it.
So we know what our function
can actually work with.
>> So in this case, we have some int input.
So again, it'll be the type
and what you're calling it.
And then, as you see
here, we have our body.
So we have some int output, that
is just our input times itself
times itself, which just cubes it.
And then we return that output.
>> So as you see here, we have an
int times an int times an int,
so it returns an int, which
has been declared there.
So everything is cohesive.
Everything's happy.
Your function will run.
And this is just the general thing.
So always have return type,
name, and your parameter list.
Each thing in your
parameter list, or input,
needs to have a type associated with it.
And then you have your
body here with whatever
you want to do with your input.
>> And then obviously you
want to return something.
Sometimes functions will just return.
They don't actually return
something for you to use.
But you have to return in some way.
And when you're making
your own functions,
we can get into that a little deeper.
Personally, if you want, there are a lot
of different things you could do there.
Everyone good?
Anything on this list that you want me
to go over, that you didn't understand?
Everyone's good there?
Cool.
Awesome.
>> OK, so we're putting
all this together now.
So we have some int cube input, so
this is a complete program here.
Up until now, I've
kind of been giving you
guys snippets that might
be going within a program.
We've just been looking at functions.
But here's an entire program.
So how many of you remember the
word prototype from lecture?
Cool.
We've got one.
What's your name?
>> STEPH: Steph.
>> ALLISON: Steph?
OK, awesome.
So, do you remember what a prototype is?
>> STUDENT: You say [INAUDIBLE]
before you actually deal with it.
>> ALLISON: Do you remember why?
>> STUDENT: No.
>> ALLISON: OK.
Gold star.
So yes, a prototype we have
beforehand, because otherwise,
our compiler is going to yell at us.
It's going to say, OK,
what is this cube function?
Like, you literally have
told me nothing about this.
It's like when you
walk into a classroom,
and someone's like,
there's a quiz today.
And you're like, you
never told me about this.
I'm not happy with us.
The prototype is basically like
your syllabus saying, look.
Heads up.
There's going to be a quiz on this day.
Don't freak out when you get to it.
You're going to be fine.
>> So all the prototype does is tell
main, I'm going to use this function.
I promise I'm defining it later.
Don't freak out at me.
Just compile and do what I tell you to.
So we have the prototype there
just to make our compiler happy.
And it's basically a promise that
you have defined this function later
and that you aren't just calling
this random thing that it
doesn't know what you're
going to be doing.
>> So in this case, we have main here.
We initialize some integer x.
That's two.
We're going to print out what x is.
We're going to cube x.
As you see, we have our
function declaration
down here that we
talked about previously.
It'll cube x, and then, if we
remember, the cube function actually
returns an integer to
us, which is stored
in x again so that we can print
out eight, or cube x right now.
Does that make sense to everyone?
We're good?
All right.
Awesome.
>> All right.
How many of you guys
remember This so this
is basically just your
stack and your heap,
just a visualization of
how memory is stored here.
So we just want to make
sure that you understand
how these are represented in memory.
If you take classes like
CS61 and stuff later,
you get to learn this far more
in depth, and it's really cool.
I highly recommend it.
But for now, I'll give
you the broad overview
so you don't have to
know the nitty gritty.
>> So the top just a text segment which
contains the actual zeros and ones,
the binary for that.
And this is used for storing
global variables if you have any.
As you move down, we
have, as you see here,
initialized data, uninitialized
data, and then heap.
>> So we don't really talk
about the heap right now.
We'll get to it later.
For now, I'm just going to
wave my hands and be like,
you don't need to know about this now.
But we will talk a little
bit about the stack.
So the stack is where-- we have zoom in.
This is actually how the program
we just looked at occurs in memory.
>> So what happens is, every
time we call a function,
we get what's called a stack
frame, which is one of these.
So main's parameters.
So those are the things
that we pass into main.
So they're right here at the bottom,
because that's the first thing we call.
And then we get to main's
locals, and when we say that,
we mean the local variables
that are stored within main.
So locals here would be, like,
x is equal to two in this case.
Because that's localized to main.
Does everyone remember scope,
going over that in lecture?
OK.
So, just the variables that
are initialized within main.
So that's why we have main [? vocals. ?]
>> And then within main, we call cube.
Right?
So we get another frame
with cube's parameters.
So in this case, cube's
parameters are now
the x that we passed in,
the two that we passed in.
And then cube's locals, which is
where the actual cubing happens.
And then it returns.
>> So what happens is as cube actually does
what it's supposed to do, it returns.
When it returns, this frame leaves,
and its returned down to main.
And then within main, we
can actually print it.
So when you're returning something,
when your function returns,
it's like passing on those values to
the frame below it and then leaving.
And things have to execute in order.
>> And when you get to bigger programs,
we can make cooler and more complicated
diagrams.
But for now, this is
just a general overview
so you have kind of an
understanding of what
happens when you're calling a function
and how that actually looks in memory.
Cool?
Everyone good?
Awesome.
>> So this is one that is
just trying to swap things.
As we see here, we have
our function prototype
so that our compiler doesn't yell at us.
We have some main, and we
want to switch x and y.
They haven't done this demo
in lecture yet, have they?
They haven't?
OK.
So we're going to go
over this very briefly.
You'll get into this example more
in depth, I think, this week.
And then next week we can really
dive into why this doesn't work.
>> So we have this void
function here-- swap.
So void just means that
nothing is returned.
And we have swap int a and int b.
And we have some temporary
variable that's a.
a gets assigned to b, and then
b gets assigned to the temp
so that a and b's
values are now switched.
>> But, plot twist, this doesn't work.
And part of it actually has
to do with the fact that a
and b here, the ones that get passed in
here, are actually copies of x and y.
So when the function actually returns,
it switches the copies but not
the actual x and y's.
So one way to think about it is
that-- pretend these are swap.
OK?
So in main, we have x and y initialized.
But when we actually go up
to these frames with swap,
we're passing the values over
to it, and they're initialized.
>> And they only ever live right here.
So a and b live here.
And they get swapped.
But when we return, we don't
do anything with a and b. a
and b leave with our function.
And so x and y stay the same.
You'll get more into how to fix that and
how we actually deal with that later.
>> But it's just one thing
to kind of keep in mind.
Use it for the future.
Don't worry if that didn't make
all the sense in the world.
They are copies is the biggest thing.
If you're going to take anything
away from that, you passed in copies.
So the originals stay the same.
Everyone good?
Cool.
>> So command-line arguments.
I'm sure in the beginning you guys all
had those great, like, int main voids.
And you're like, OK cool.
I don't really care.
This is just what I have to write.
But in your new programs,
especially in this pset,
and why is there chalk on the ground?
>> With your next pset, you're
going to be seeing this.
Int main, int arg c,
string arc v, brackets.
So, from what we just
learned today, what
do we think that second parameter
or that second element is here?
It's an array.
What type of array?
String array, yes.
Cool.
So that's how you're going
to be declaring these now.
>> Does anyone remember
what these stand for?
No?
Hmm?
>> STUDENT: arg c.
>> ALLISON: So arg c keeps a counter.
It's an int.
It's a number, right?
So what do you think that number is of?
Yeah.
So arg c is the number of strings
that make up the command line.
So if we were to do-- actually,
there are examples after this,
so I won't get ahead of myself.
It's a number of strings that
just make up your command line.
>> So when you do, like, dot slash Mario,
that's one string that makes it up.
In this piece, you'll actually be
feeding things into the command line,
as I'm sure you guys who
have read the spec saw.
So in those cases, maybe you'll
have two or three arguments.
It's going to be a useful thing to use.
>> And then arg v, as we said,
is just a string array.
So that actually stores what
you input into the command line.
So we have these.
You have some dot slash
copy infile outfile.
So, if arg c is the number of strings
that we're passing into the command
line, what is our arg c in this case?
Three.
Exactly.
>> So what's arg v of zero?
So what's the first thing we've stored?
Dot slash copy, exactly.
And then the second would be infile.
The third would be outfile.
So what about arg v three?
It would be null, because that's
the end of our array, right?
Cool.
>> And then what about the sixth one?
It's kind of a trick question.
Ish.
Do we know what it is?
It's undefined.
We have no idea what that could be.
It's whatever is right
after the array in memory,
and we have no clue what that is.
And it's dangerous to touch those
things, because for all you know,
it's some part of memory that you
shouldn't be accessing or null.
And it can do crazy things.
It's called over-indexing
your bound to your array.
Don't go outside the bounds of your
array, or bad things can happen.
You come back and, like, the laws
of physics have been destroyed
or something.
Cool.
Does that make sense to everyone?
Not too bad.
>> So now, everyone's
favorite part, pset review.
Yay!
OK.
So for those of you who
haven't read the pset spec,
you are doing some really
cool stuff with cryptography.
You're going to create a Ceasar
Cipher and a Vigenere Cipher.
You should definitely read the
spec to see how those work.
And if you're having any trouble about
what it should actually be doing,
please come talk to me,
email me or text me.
I'm around.
>> So there are three main
things here that we
want to talk about-- just kind
of an extension of lecture.
Things that you might not know
about, helpful hints and tools.
So we're going to do a
quick review of ASCII,
because that's going to be super
important for Vigenere's Cipher.
We're going to conversion of
command line inputs, which
will be very helpful for Caesar Cipher.
And then modulo.
Cool.
>> So, ASCII maps characters to numbers.
This is a great chart.
You should have this
bookmarked somewhere.
You will want it for
your first mid-term.
I'm pretty sure everyone has this
chart on their mid-term sheet.
So learn it.
Love it.
Keep it handy.
It'll be useful.
>> And all it is is an encoding
that maps alphabetic, numeric,
and other characters to
numbers for our computer.
Because of course, in the
end, everything we store
is going to get converted
down to zeroes and ones,
so we need some way to represent the
text and characters that we're all
used to seeing as some sort of number.
>> So as we see here, we have
uppercase A, which is right there.
It's 65.
And lowercase A is 97.
So you can figure out--
as I said earlier,
if you had array of multiple
strings, what each of them
have a null terminator.
It would be a space.
Space has its own special--
I forget where it is here.
Ah.
32 is the space.
So everything maps to it.
>> So we have ASCII math.
Pro tip-- in Vigenere's,
you might be tempted
to convert your numbers to integers,
but it's actually better practice
to be able to use the
characters like this
when you're actually manipulating them.
So if you want to use numbers, you can.
But a better way, or a way that
we tend to like you guys to do it,
is this way where you're
actually subtracting characters.
>> So I want you guys to
kind of figure these out.
Why don't you try every other one?
So do the first one, the
third one, and the fifth one.
Because I want to make sure that we talk
about everything we need to talk about.
I'm just going to say, one of the
important things to-- oh wait,
you guys haven't seen this one.
OK so do the first three.
Let's do that.
Because we have to talk about modulo.
I know.
Math is hard.
You can use a calculator.
It's OK.
Or pull up an ASCII table, because
you're probably going to want that.
>> Cool.
So I will quickly walk
you guys through these.
So people have ASCII tables pulled up?
What is our numeric
number for lowercase A?
STUDENT: Seven.
>> ALLISON: So lowercase A is
97 and uppercase A is 65.
So 97 minus 65?
>> AUDIENCE: 32?
>> ALLISON: 62, yeah.
So in this case, what
would it print out?
That first one?
If we have percent d,
what would that indicate?
STUDENT: A number.
ALLISON: We're printing
out an actual number.
So we're actually going
to print out 32 here.
And if this were percent c,
32 would give us a space.
So understanding that
characters can be printed
both as numbers and as
the actual characters
is really important, and paying
attention to the actual types
that we're doing here.
Cool.
So for every other one of these,
what are we going to be printing?
>> STUDENT: A character.
>> ALLISON: A character.
Cool.
So if you guys want to know, you
can work these out on your own.
If you're having trouble, email me.
But the second one will
print out a lowercase b.
The third one will print out an
uppercase B. The fourth one will print
out an uppercase C, and the
last one will be a lowercase A.
And the last one-- we're actually going
to get into what that crazy percent
sign even means in a couple slides.
So try those on your own.
If you have trouble,
please come talk to me.
If you're typically in Adams D hall,
you'll probably find me around.
>> So, atoi.
How many of you have seen this
function or heard of it at all?
Anyone?
Cool.
So what it actually stands
for is ASCII to integer.
So what you can do is, with Caesar,
for those who read the spec,
you're going to do dot slash Caesar
after you write your program,
and then you're going to
input some number that you
want to encode your secret message with.
>> But, if we remember, all of our
inputs are stored as strings.
Right?
We have an arg v array
that is all type string.
So if you just try to
pull that one, it would
think that that one or whatever number
you used is actually a character.
So you're going to get
some crazy results.
So if you actually want to
turn this into an integer
that you can use to manipulate
your word or your message,
you'll want to use atoi.
atoi just converts
your string to an int.
>> So if we have a string of 12, if we call
atoi on 12, or whatever that input is,
it will actually return
to you the integer.
Not the character or the string 12.
Which, when you start
to add that to numbers,
will be very different,
because the string 12 is
some crazy number in
ASCII, but the integer 12
is actually 12, which is what you want.
So you want to make sure to use atoi.
>> You're going to want this
in Caesar, because you
need the int supplied by the
user in the command line.
But when they put it in the command
line, it's stored as a string
to begin with.
Does that make sense?
You don't necessarily
need this for Vigenere.
With Vigenere, as I said
before, you should try and use
ASCII math that looks more like
this, where you're actually
using the chars that we're given to you.
Cool.
Everyone good there?
Awesome.
>> So modulo.
So what if you're given
this huge number for Caesar?
You have this idea that
if you're at Z and you're
given a number two,
that means you need--
Z becomes the second
letter after itself, right?
So you need to somehow wrap around,
and modulo is the way to do that.
So all it does is it
gives you the remainder
of the division of the
first number by the second.
And we have some examples to
make that a little more concrete.
But basically, you use modulo when you
want to make something wrap around.
>> So if you only want the
numbers one through eight,
you can use modulo on any other
number, and it will always
return a number from zero to eight.
So some examples-- if
we have 55 modulo 10,
it just gives you the remainder of
55 divided by 10, which would be 5.
And then three modulo five,
anyone guess what that would be?
Three.
>> So if you have a smaller number before
the modulo, it can't go in evenly.
It's zero.
So it just returns the number itself.
So eight modulo eight would be?
>> STUDENT: Zero.
>> ALLISON: Zero.
Because it goes in evenly.
16 modulo 15?
>> AUDIENCE: One.
>> ALLISON: Cool.
And then this last one is just to
show you-- you might be wondering, OK,
what's the order of operations here?
Do we divide first?
Do we modulo first?
So modulo holds the same precedence
as division or multiplication,
and its left associative.
So it's in the same way.
You would always do parentheses,
then multiplication, division,
and modulo in order from left to right.
So standard rules.
Just put it in the same category
as division and multiplication.
>> So in this case, we would
have 1 plus 2 gives us 3.
We multiply that by 2, so we get 6.
We modulo that by 2, which gives us?
>> STUDENT: 0.
>> ALLISON: 0.
And then we add 2, so we
get 2 in this last case.
So modulo-- you're definitely going to
be thinking about ways to incorporate
that when you're wrapping
around the alphabet.
If you're at Z and you need to move
forward three spaces to get to C,
there's that whole concept
of wrapping around.
So I will leave it to
you guys to figure out
how exactly you're going to be using it.
But definitely a useful tool
for your pset this week.
I really like this.
This is one of my favorite psets.
Then after you do it,
if you have friends,
you can, like, send each other secret
messages and make sure it works.
Because it'll decrypt it or whatever.
Lots of fun.
>> And that is the end of section.
I finished early.
I still have 15 minutes with
you guys, so if there's anything
that you would like to go over
further, I'd be happy to do that.
Any other questions on
your pset for those of you
who have started or read the spec.
Anything that we've talked
about in the last hour
and 15 minutes that you'd like me
to kind of rehash, I'd be happy to.
Or we can call it quits, and you can
all leave and take more candy with you
as you go.
But if there are any lingering
questions, please let me know.
You can also come up and
talk to me afterwards.
I promise I don't bite.
Anything else?
Everyone's good?
Everyone's feeling like
they can handle this pset?
You're going to be fine guys.
Office hours are there for a reason.
Cool.
Alright.
>> Well, in that case, thank
you all so much for coming.
I hope to see you next week.
There will be more candy.
There might be other cool things.
And I look forward to getting
to know all of you this year.