THOMAS LIVELY: All right.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Thomas Lively.
This seminar is going to be
writing 2D games in C using SDL.
So I know you're all
asking, yeah, I really
want to play games and make games,
but what is this SDL business?
So SDL is a C library.
It stands for the Simple
DirectMedia Layer.
And it's a cross platform,
game development library.
It works on Windows, Mac,
Linux, even iOS and Android.
It handles things like
access to the audio systems
for the computer, the keyboard, and
mouse, joysticks, if they're attached.
On mobile, it can even do the
touch input and all of that.
And of course, it handles graphics,
drawing things to the screen.
>> So it's very widely used, even though
you may not have heard of it before.
It's built into, for example,
Valve's source engine,
which powers games such as
Portal and Team Fortress 2.
It's also in a very large number
of indie games that come out,
so I'm excited to see what you
all will be making with it.
>> The seminar goals are to get you
set out to be developing with SDL.
We're going to learn how
to create a game window.
We're going to create sprites,
which are the images in your game
that can move around.
We're going to learn how
to and animate the sprites,
so move them around, make
them change over time.
And we're going to learn how
to capture keyboard and mouse
input from the computer.
What we won't be talking
about today is 3D graphics,
because that's a very complicated
subject that we don't have time for.
We won't learn how to
play audio on our games.
And we won't be building
for anything but Linux.
>> Now the caveats there are that,
hopefully, by the end the seminar,
you'll be comfortable with
the SDL documentation,
so you'll be able to go figure out
how to play audio for yourself.
Also building for Mac or PC should work
exactly the same as building for Linux,
but the setup's going to
be a little different.
So you should be able to figure
out how to do these things
by the end of today's seminar.
>> So for the set up, we're going
to use a virtual machine.
We would use the CS50 IDE, because
we're just going to be writing in C.
But since the IDE isn't a browser, we
can't create new windows or display
graphics in it.
So we need a virtual machine.
So you can follow the instructions
here at manual.CS50.net/appliance/15
to install the official CS50 appliance,
which is merely a Linux virtual
machine.
>> And then once you have
that all set up-- it
might take a little while, because
a very large download-- you're going
to run in the VM sudo apt-get update.
And that's really going
to update all the software
packages on your virtual machine.
>> After that, you're going to run
sudo apt-get install, libsdl2-2.0-0,
libsdl2-dbg, libsdl2-dev, and
additionally libsdl2-image-2.0-0,
libsdl2-image-dbg,
and libsdl2-image-dev.
So what does that do?
That merely installs the debug
information, documentation, headers,
and binaries for two libraries.
Regular old, SDL 2.0,
and another library
called SDL Image, which
we're going to be using
to load image files into our game.
>> So once you have that also
that, just when it asks,
you just type yes, hit Enter
to install those packages,
and then you should be good to go.
So to get the distribution code, you
can-- oh dear, this is not updated.
Unless you have a GitHub account--
if you have a GitHub account,
you can do this Git
clone command to the repo
and that will download the Git
repo with all the code in it,
so that you'll have the code.
>> If you don't have a GitHub
account, what you should do is type
wgithttps://github.com/tlively/sdl
seminar-- and here it's different--
/archive/master.zip.
So again, that's the exact same
URL, except it's going to be
tlively/SDL_seminar/master.zip and
you're using wgit to download that.
And then you can merely
unzip that archive
and then you'll have
all the source code.
So sorry about that.
And then the code will also be hosted at
the CS50 seminar's web page in a couple
days.
>> All right.
So how do we get started
writing our own game?
Well, the first thing
we're going to want to do
is look at the SDL documentation.
So here's the VM.
And here's the web page.
I've navigated to live libsdl.org.
What I'm going to do here is go over
to the sidebar, under documentation,
and click on the wiki.
This will bring me to the wiki that
has most of the documentation for SDL.
Over on the sidebar here, we're
going to click API by category,
because is going to give
us a nice categorical view
of the entire API for SDL.
>> So for example, we have
the basic initialization
and shut down, all the sort of
administrative stuff for using SDL,
and then we have the section for
displaying things to the screen.
That's video.
Input events, that's getting
input from the keyboard,
getting input from the mouse, and
the joystick, if you have it even.
There's force feedback for things
like game controllers, which
we're not going to talk about.
And here's audio.
And then there's a bunch of other
stuff that SDL can do for you.
>> But today we're going to focus
on the initialization here,
displaying images in the video
section, and handling input events.
So these are the main
sections of documentation
that you should be worrying about.
Just for fun, if we go over
here and click on API by name,
we can see a list of every
single thing in the SDL library.
So all these functions, enumerations,
structures, a crazy amount of stuff,
alphabetical order.
And clearly, until
you know you're doing,
this isn't going to be too helpful,
which is why we do API by category.
>> So let's get started.
Hopefully you've already
downloaded the distribution code.
And so what you can do is, right
here in the CS50 appliance,
simply open a terminal.
Here we go.
So I've already downloaded the
distribution code using the .zip
method.
And I've unzipped it.
So here it is in the SDL seminar master.
So I'm going to go into that directory.
And what we see here is
that we have seven C files.
And this is going to the code
we're going to be looking at today.
We have a makefile.
And we have a resources directory,
which simply has an image
that you'll be seeing soon enough.
>> So let's open up these files
using the G-Edit editor.
So I want to open all the files that
begin with hello and end with .c.
Here we go.
So that's a tiny window, so we're
going to try to make that bigger.
No, it went away.
>> All right.
So here's the very first
file we're going to look at.
It's called hello1_sdl.c.
And all this does is initialize the SDL
library so that we can start using it.
How would you know to come
up with this code yourself?
Well, if we look over
at the documentation
and we go into the initialization
and shut down section,
it's going to tell us all
about how to initialize SDL.
So definitely read this some other time.
It's going to tell you all
about what's going on here.
But the main crux of the matter is that
we need to call this function SDL In It
and pass it what kinds of things
we want the library to initialize.
So in our case, we're just going
to initialize the video for now,
so that we can start displaying images.
>> Over here, you can see if
we click on a SDL In It, we
can get even more information,
including the return value.
So we see here that it
returnes zero on success.
So in our code, we're going to
see if it doesn't return zero,
and if it doesn't return
zero, so it wasn't successful,
then we're going to simply print
an error using this other function,
SDL get error, which returns a string
describing the error that occurred.
We're going to print that
error and then we're just
going to exit the program
with an error code.
>> Then another thing that we need
to do is, before program exits,
if we successfully initialized SDL,
we just need to call it SDL quit.
And that's going to handle cleaning up
all of SDL's internal resources for us.
So the documentation there-- again,
here we are in the initialization
and shut down section
of the documentation.
You can just click on the
function here, SDL quit,
and you can read all about that as well.
And a lot of these function
documentation pages
have example code, so this
is very good resource.
Definitely spend some time
reading parts of this wiki
if you're going to do
this for a project.
>> All right.
So that's our entire program.
What we can do now is-- I'm
going to open the makefile here,
so I'm going to take a
look at how that works.
And it's a very simple makefile,
similar to what you've seen before.
One of the main differences
is that, here, this
is going to insert the result of running
this command, which you've already
installed if you've installed SDL.
And this is a command
that's going to generate
some extra flags for the compiler.
>> In addition to that, we're giving it
all the usual commands, as well as
these two commands.
So the -lsdl2-image handles
linking in the SDL image library.
And the -lm actually handles linking
in the standard C math library.
So we aren't going to need
those for all of our C files,
but we just put them in so that we can
use the same makefile for everything
without modifications.
>> Over here in sources,
this is where you'd
put the files that you were going
to compile for your project.
But since every one of my C
files here has a main function,
it's going to get confused
if we put them all in.
So I'm going to just say,
for now, hello1_sdl.c,
which is the one we just looked at.
So if I go back over
here, I can do make.
And what it did is it just
compiled that first file.
And then we can type ./game, because
it's the executable it produced.
And all it did was print
initialization successful.
So we did something right.
But that was kind of boring,
because we didn't see a window,
nothing was moving around.
>> So great, we got SDL initialized.
Now, let's move on to something
a little more interesting.
So here we have hello2_window.c, and
this is going to be a slightly more
complex C program that
initializes SDL just like before,
except now we're also going
to initialize SDL timer.
And this is going to let us
access the internal timer
and use functions relating to time.
>> And then let's look down here.
What we do is we have this pointer
to an SDL window struct, which
is going to be created by this call
to the function, SDL create window.
Now, this takes a lot of arguments,
so let's go look at the documentation.
So again, I'm going to
API by category, I'm
going down to video here, and the first
section, displaying window management.
So this section has
a ton of stuff in it,
but if you look through
these functions, you'll
see that probably the one we
want is called SDL create window,
which happens to be right at the top.
>> And so this is the
documentation for this function.
The window's going to have a title,
an x and y position on the screen,
it's going to have a width, a height,
and then it's going to take some flags.
Now, we don't actually care about
any of these flags right now,
but if you wanted to do something
like make a full screen window,
you could take a look at that.
For now, we're just going
to use these special values,
SDL window plus centered
for x and y in order
to just create the window
in the center of our screen.
>> So that's what that's doing.
And if window happens to be
null, meaning there is an error,
then again we're just going to
print the error using SDL get error.
And then because we initialized
SDL, we now need to close it.
So we call SDL quit before
returning one for main.
>> So we have this window open hopefully.
And what we're going
to do is we're going
to call SDL for 5,000 milliseconds,
which is the same as five seconds.
And when we're done with that,
it's going to destroy the window,
clean up the SDL library,
and exit the program.
So let's go ahead and give that a shot.
>> So now instead of changing
the makefile every time,
I can simply do make, and
then on the command line,
say sources equals and then
the file we're compiling.
So it's hello2_window.c.
Fantastic.
No erros.
Now, if we run our executable,
we see this window.
Now there are a few
problems with the window.
We can move it around, but it has
this background junk inside of it.
So we haven't drawn
anything, and so it's
just full of garbage, which
is pretty much what we expect.
>> Furthermore, we can't close the window.
I'm pressing this X in the
corner and nothing's happening.
So we'll see how to fix
that in a little bit.
So let's fix the part where the
window is full of garbage first.
So if we go over to hello3_image.c, what
we can see is that we've added a few
more things here.
We've added this new header
file to get the timer functions.
I guess we did that in the last
one, too, and I didn't mention it.
But now because we're
working with images,
we need to include the SDL
image header file as well.
So it's the same thing as
before, initializing SDL here,
same deal with creating windows.
We've seen that before now.
>> Now we need to create something called
a renderer, which sort of goes along
with the window.
But it's a sort of
abstract object that's
in charge of doing all these
drawing operations to the window.
And it actually corresponds
to a program loaded
into the graphics hardware in your
computer or your phone or whatever.
So the flags we want to pass it--
and you can look at the documentation
to get more detail here-- are going
to be SDL render accelerated, which
means it's going to be
using the graphics hardware
and not just emulated in software.
>> And we're going to use
SDL RENDERER PRESENTVSYNC.
VSYNC is a thing that simply makes
your graphics look better and prevents
this thing called screen
terror, where half
of one frame and half of the next
frame get drawn at the same time
and it looks awful.
But again, you can go read
about that on your own.
>> So we have some flags here.
And so we're just going to call
this function SDL create renderer.
We're going to give it the window
to associate with that renderer.
Negative one means we don't care what
graphics driver we're going to use.
So that should pretty much
always be negative one,
unless you know about graphics drivers.
And then we're just going
to pass it our flags.
So if that returns null, then we're
going to print the error as usual,
but then we're also going
to destroy the window
to clean up those resources before
calling SDL quit and returning.
>> Now, the interesting part here
is where we load our image
using this function IMG_load.
This is the only function we're going
to use from the SDL image library.
It's the only one we need.
It's a function that takes the string
that is the path of any image resource.
And it can be a .png, a GIF,
bitmap, any of these things.
And that's why this function is so nice.
It can handle pretty much any format.
Loads it into memory and stores it
as a thing called an SDL surface.
>> Now an SDL surface is merely a struct
that represents image data in memory.
So you can read more about
that in the documentation two.
And if this errors, then we're
going to do the whole thing where
we print the error, close our
resources, and then quit the program.
Now the interesting thing is, before
we can draw this image to the window,
we need to actually make it a texture.
Now a texture corresponds
to image data loaded
into the graphic's hardware's memory.
>> So a surface is in main
memory, regular memory
that we've been using all semester,
and a texture is in this separate VRAM
memory that the graphics card controls.
So we call this function
SDL_CreateTextureFromSurface.
We give it our renderer and our surface.
And then we're actually
done with the surface,
so we're just going to free it.
We don't need it anymore.
And then so if this call
errored and returned null,
then we're going to do the whole
error reporting thing again.
>> All right.
Here, we get into some
actual rendering functions.
So calling SDL_RenderClear
and passing it
the renderer associated with our window
simply makes the window go black.
So it removes that junk that we saw in
our window before and makes it black.
And then we're going
to call SDL_RenderCopy,
give it our renderer, our texture.
And we'll talk about what
these fields are in a bit.
But that's going to
take the texture data
and copy it onto our
window to draw the image.
So after we've done this copy
the data onto our window,
we have to do this extra function
called SDL_RenderPresent.
>> And this is interesting
because this gets
into a topic called double buffering.
So double buffering is a technique that
makes your graphics look a lot better.
Again, it prevents that screen tearing
I was talking about earlier, where
you have two buffers.
There's a back buffer in
memory and a front buffer.
The front buffer is literally
what's on your screen at the moment.
So we do all these draw variations,
like SDL render copy or SDL_RenderClear
to the back buffer.
So they modify things
in the back buffer.
Here we might be drawing this
green square to the back buffer.
>> So then when we're done doing
our render operations, which
might take a really long
time, what we're going to do
is switch the buffers.
So it literally just takes the
front buffer and the back buffer
and switches them, so
that, instantaneously,
in one operation, instead of
maybe hundreds or thousands,
all of our newly rendered
objects are on the screen.
And this prevents things
like the screen refreshing
when we've only drawn half
of our objects for the frame.
So that's why we need to call
SDL_RenderPresent, as well
as SDL_RenderCopy.
>> Again, we're just going
to wait for five seconds.
Then we're going to
clean up our resources.
We have quite a few more this time.
And then we're just going
to exit the program.
So let's do that.
I'm going to type make, and then sources
equals hello-- this is now 3image.c.
All right, that compiled no errors.
And you can see here I've now
drawn out my image, Hello, CS50!
to our window, which
disappears after five seconds.
>> Now, this still has problems, right?
This is not a good application,
because when I try to close the window,
nothing happens.
That x is still not responsive.
So let's take a look at the
next file, hello4animation.
So this is the file
that's going to introduce
moving and movement to our image.
So we're going to do the
same thing as before,
initiate SDL, create the
window, create the renderer,
load the image into
memory, create the texture.
We've seen all of that before.
Now, this is new.
We're going to have a structure called
an SDL rect, which is just a rectangle.
If we go over here, we can
do a search for SDL rect,
and you can see it's a
very simple structure.
It has an x, a y for
the position, and it
has a width and a height for
the size of the rectangle.
>> So what we're going to do is we're
going to define this SDL rect dest,
for destination.
And this is the place
on the screen where
we're going to be drawing
our image, right So
if we're going to be
moving the image around,
then the destination where
we're going to draw the image
need to be moving around.
So we're going to call this
function SDL_QueryTexture.
And notice I'm passing the address
of dest.w, which is the width,
and dest.h, which is the height.
And so SDL_QueryTexture is going
to store in those fields the width
and the height of our texture.
>> And then what I'm going
to do is I'm going
to set dest.x to be window
width minus dest.w, which is
the width of the sprite, divided by 2.
And this is going to set it up so
that the image is perfectly centered
in our window, all right?
So now I have a y position.
And this is going to
be a variable that's
changing, because we're going to be
moving the image in the y direction.
And now we have something
called an animation loop.
>> So how does the animation work?
Well, human eye can detect 12 distinct
images in every second, all right?
So if you flash 12 image cards at me
in a second, I saw each of those images
as its own distinct individual image.
Now, if you flash more
images at me in a second,
then my eye would start
to blur them together
and I would perceive it as motion,
instead of one distinct image.
So, for example, movies and television,
they flash images at you 24 times
a second.
So that's 24 frames per second.
Computer screens, on the other hand,
often are at 60 frames per second.
That's their refresh speed.
That's how often they refresh
the picture on the screen.
So our target is going to be 60
frames per second for our games.
>> So let's see that in the code.
So for each frame, we're first
going to clear the window.
This is the general pattern.
You always clear the
window each frame, and then
do all of your drawing
operations, and then at the end,
do RenderPresent to show
everything in the frame.
And then you're going to
have a wait at the end
to wait until the next
frame should begin.
>> So if I was doing a lot of
complex computation here
that took more than 16 milliseconds,
it would be impossible for me
to get that frame rate of 60 that
I wanted, because each frame is
taking too long to compute.
Furthermore, we're really doing
sort of a negligible amount of work
here, because there's only
one thing we're drawing.
So I just wait 1/60 of a
second, which is the length
of a frame in between frames.
So I'm sort of pretending doing
all my work takes zero time.
But in a real game,
you'd have to subtract
the amount of time it took to do
all this work from your rest time.
>> So anyway, what am I
actually doing in this loop?
I clear the window.
I set the dest.y, which is an int to
my actual y position cast into an int.
Now, I want float resolution
for my y position in my game,
but then to actually
draw it onto the screen,
it needs ints, because it's in units of
pixels, so that's what the cast is for.
I'm going to draw the image.
So this is the source rectangle.
And this is the destination rectangle.
So I passed null for
the source rectangle
to say I want to draw my entire texture.
But if you had a lot of
textures in your game
and they're all in one big texture map
that was loaded into SDL as just one
texture, you could
use a source rectangle
to pick one of the smaller textures,
one of the smaller sprites,
out of that big texture map.
>> So again, I'm passing my render, my
texture, and now the destination.
This is going to be where in the
window it's going to be drawn.
And then, because I'm animating
something, I need movement,
I'm going to be updating the
sprite position on each frame.
So I have this constant called scroll
speed in units of pixels per second.
Now, each time we do a movement,
the frame is only 1/60 of a second.
So I'm going to divide that by 60.
And then, let's see, I'm
subtracting that from y position.
Why am I subtracting?
We'll get to that in a second.
So then I clean up my resources
and the program's over.
>> So let's make that.
So let's go into make SRCS=hello4
animation.c, all right?
Game.
There you go.
So I have it scrolling up the
window, which is pretty neat.
But hold on, I was subtracting
from the y position every time.
What's going on there?
Well, it turns out that in SDL, and
in fact, in most computer graphics,
the origin for the coordinate system
is the top left of the window.
>> So the positive x direction goes
across your window to the right.
And the positive y direction
actually goes down.
So again, the origin's in
the top left of your window,
positive y direction is down,
and positive x is to the right.
So when I subtract from
the y position, that's
going to make it go on the negative
y direction, which is up the window.
So that's what's going on there.
Cool.
>> Let's look at the next file.
Here is the part of the
show where we finally
get that X in the corner of the window
that's supposed to close the window
to work.
So what's going on?
We initialize SDL, create the window,
create the renderer, load the image,
create the texture
like we've seen before.
We have the same destination rectangle
as before, same call to query texture.
But this time, we're then
going to divide the width
and the height of our destination by 4.
This only has the effect of
scaling our image down when
we display it in the window by four.
So that's pretty neat.
We can just scale just like that.
We're going to start the sprite
in the center of the screen.
And now we have x and y velocity and
they're both going to start at zero.
>> This is the wrong file.
I'm sorry.
So that's all true.
That's all still in this file.
We have the divide by 4 and everything.
So here we have our x and y position
for the center of the window.
And we give it an initial velocity
of this constant speed, which
I believe is 300 pixels per second.
Now, we have this int could just as well
be a boolean called close requested.
And instead of doing an
infinite loop on a timer here,
we're going to be animating as
long as close is not requested.
>> So how do we process events?
Well, SDL queues up events in a
literal queue behind the scenes.
And then each frame,
we can dequeue events
from that queue using
this call SDL_PullEvent.
And again, definitely go read
about this in the documentation.
There's a lot more detail and a lot
more functions you can use with this.
We pass it the address
of this thing, SDL_Event
that we have here on the stack.
>> Now, what is an SDL_event?
Because SDL, if we look in
the documentation-- let's
see, API by category, input
events, event handling,
we can look at the number
of different events here
and we can see there's
a whole ton of them.
So what is this SDL_Event thing?
SDL_Event is a union.
Wow, what's a union?
You've probably never
heard of that before.
And that's OK.
>> A union is kind of like
a struct, except a struct
has a space for all of
its fields and memory,
whereas a union only has
enough space to fit the largest
one of its fields, which means it
can only store one of its fields
at a time, which kind of
makes sense for events, right?
We can have a keyboard
event or a window event,
but a single event cannot be both a
keyboard event and a window event,
so it'd be silly to have space for
both of those inside our event union.
So if you wanted to
create your own union,
it looks exactly the same
as creating a struct,
except that we use the union keyword
instead of the struct keyword.
And remember, for all of the
things inside your union,
the actual variable that is the union
can only have one of those values
at a time.
>> So how can we tell what kind of event
we just popped off of this queue?
Well, we can test for event.type.
And if that is equal
to SDL_Quit, we know
it's the event that
was generated when we
hit that X in the corner of the window.
And we can set close requested equals 1.
The rest is just some animation
that you've seen before.
So let's go ahead and make
this and see how well it works.
So I'm going to type make and
then SRCS=hello5_events.c.
There we go.
Games.
>> Now, we can see it was
indeed scaled down by four.
And now it's bouncing around.
I have some collision detection
going on with the sides of the window
that we can take a look at.
And what happens when I go to close it?
It closes.
Fantastic.
We received that event.
And we handled it.
>> So let's look back at the code.
So how did I get it
bouncing around like that?
Remember I set both x and
y initially to the speeds.
And speed is a positive
constant, so that's
going to get it starting out
going down and to the right.
>> Now, each frame, in addition to handling
any events that may have occurred,
I'm going to detect whether my sprite
is trying to go out of the window.
So we can do that by just checking
x_pos with 0, y_pos 0, and then
also x_pos and y_pos with
window width and window height.
Notice I've subtracted
the width of the sprite.
And this is because if I didn't
subtract the width of the sprite,
it would only check that
the origin of the sprite
did not go outside the window.
But we want the entire
width of the sprite
to always be inside the window and
the entire height of the sprite
to always be inside the window.
So that's what the subtraction is for.
A lot of geometry here can
be helpful to draw it out
on paper with the coordinate
system to see what is going on.
>> So if I do collide, I just
simply reset the position
so that it is not going
out of the screen.
And I'm going to, if it bounces
on one of the sidewalls,
I'm going to negate the
x velocity so that it
starts bouncing in the other direction.
And similarly, if it hits
the top or the bottom,
I'm going to set the y velocity
equal to the negative y velocity,
so that it will bounce back.
So that's just how we got that here.
>> And the updating positions
just like we've seen before,
divide by 60, because we're
only handling 1/60 of a second.
And then rendering,
exactly the same as before.
And so that's everything
that was going on this file.
So that's how we do events.
The main thing to take away here
is this SDL_PullEvent function.
And you should definitely read the
documentation more about SDL_Event
the union, because this data type is
very, very important, because we use it
for all sorts of events.
>> For example, we use it for keyboard
events, which is what this file is for.
So what do we have?
We have the same thing as before,
initialize SDL, create a window,
create a renderer, load the image
into memory, create the texture.
Again, we're going to
have this dest rectangle,
we're going to scale the image
by four, make it a bit smaller.
Now, we are going to start the
sprite in center of the screen.
But this time, we're going to set the
initial x and y velocities to zero,
because the keyboard is
going to control those.
And furthermore, we're going to
keep track of these variables
up, down, left, and right.
And that's going to keep
track of whether we've
pressed the keyboard buttons that
correspond to up, down, left,
and right.
>> Now, this is kind of fancy
because we can use W, A, S,
D here, or the actual arrow keys.
We'll see that in just a second.
So we're going to process
the event just like before.
We pull the event.
But now we're going to
switch on the event type.
If it's SDL_Quit, we're
going to set close
requested to one, just like before.
That handles the x in
the corner of the window,
so that our window actually closes.
>> Otherwise, if we get an SDL key down
event, which means we pressed a key,
then what we're going to do is we're
going to switch on this thing here,
which means-- so event.key
means treat our event union,
go and get the key
event structure in it.
So it turns out that this
union is a key event structure.
And then go to the key
event's structure its field
called keysym and then scancode.
And again, definitely read
the documentation about this.
Keyword inputs quite interesting.
You can get scan codes or key codes.
And it's a little subtle, but
the documentation is quite good.
>> So if we see the scan code for
our key press being W or up,
we're going to set up equal to 1.
And then we break out of that switch.
If it's A or left, we set left to 1, et
cetera, et cetera, for down and right.
Now, out in this outer switch,
if we see a key up event,
that means we've released a key
and we're no longer pressing it.
So I'm going to say up equals 0,
left equals 0, down equals 0, right
equals 0, et cetera.
>> And notice we have in each of these
two cases put right next to each other
with no separate code
for the first case, which
means that whether it's
an S or a down right here,
it's going to execute this code.
So that's pretty handy.
It prevents us having to do more
conditions and ifs and things
like that.
>> So we're going to
determine the velocity.
We set the velocity to 0.
Then if up is pressed
and not down, then we
set the y velocity to negative speed.
Remember negative, because the
negative y direction is up.
And the positive y direction is down.
If down is pressed
and not up, then we're
going to set it to positive speed,
which means going down the screen.
Same thing with left and right.
>> And then we're going to update
the positions just like before.
We're going to do collision
detection with bounds,
but we're not going to reset the
velocity, because the velocity is just
controlled by the keyboard.
But we are going to reset the
positions to keep it in the window.
And we're going to set the
positions in the struct
and then do all the
rendering stuff from before.
So let's see what it does.
So make SRCS-- let's see,
this is hello6_keyboard.c.
>> Oh, no.
So we got some warnings here.
And that's simply saying we didn't
check for every single possible kind
of event.
That's OK, because
there's 236 of them or so.
So I'm going to ignore those warnings.
It's still compiled fine.
So I'm going to play the game.
It's not moving.
But now, when I mash on my keyboard,
I can do some WASD movement here,
I use my arrow keys as well.
And notice, even though I'm
pressing right right now,
it's not going out of the window,
because I reset it on every frame.
So that's pretty neat.
You can imagine moving around Mario with
some arrow keys or something like that.
And yes, the X does work.
>> So final file we're going
to look at, hellow7_mouse.
This is about getting mouse input.
So in this one, we
import the math header,
because we're going to have
a little bit of math here.
Same old, same old stuff, destination,
same old, seen that before.
Well, this is interesting.
So we're back to only checking
for the SDL quit event.
Why is that?
So you can get mouse input from events.
Like when the mouse moved,
you get an event for that.
When a mouse button is pressed,
you can get an event for that.
>> But there's another, slightly simpler
perhaps, API for getting mouse input.
And that's simply SDL get mouse state.
So I have an int for x and
y for the cursor position.
I pass it to SDL_GetMouseState,
which sets these.
And this is position in the
coordinate system of the window.
So if the mass is in the top left
of the window, that would 0, 0.
>> Now, what I'm going to do is I'm going
to do a little bit of vector math.
I bet you thought you wouldn't
see that in CS50, but here it is.
I'm going to do some vector
math to get the vector
from the image to the cursor.
And so why do I have
this subtraction here?
Well, if I just used dest.-- so
I need to translate the mouse x
and y by half the width and
the height of the image,
because I want the center of the
image to be going towards the mouse,
not the origin of the image.
>> So that's just to make sure I'm talking
about the center of the image here.
Then we get delta x and y, which
is the difference from the target
to the actual position of the image.
And then we can get the
distance here, which
is going to be Pythagorean
theorem, square root of x
times x plus y times y.
>> Now to prevent jitter, and I can show
you what this does if I don't do this,
if distance between the cursor and
the image center is less than five,
I'm just not going to move the image.
Otherwise, we set the velocity.
And we set it so that the
velocity will always be constant.
And the net result of all
this math is that the image
is going to move towards the cursor.
>> Now, it turns out that
SDL_GetMouseState,
in addition to setting the
x and y arguments here,
it also returns an int that corresponds
to the state of the mouse buttons.
So we can't read that
directly, but we can
use these macros, a single
bitwise operator, not that scary,
just a bitwise and.
So we say buttons, which is the result
of our SDL_GetMouseState, if that
and bitwise and, this macro
here, SDL_BUTTON_LEFT.
>> So this is going to simply resolve
to the bitmap that corresponds
to left mouse button being pressed.
And so if the bitwise
and occurs and it's
not zero, which means
left button was pressed,
then we're actually going to negate
both the x and the y velocities,
which will just make the image runaway.
Update positions.
Collisions detections, seen it
all before, rendering, all right.
Let's make it.
So you got make SRCS=hello7_mouse.c.
Great.
No errors.
And game.
>> So here I have my mouse.
And the image is indeed
chasing my mouse.
Now, in a game you make, maybe
this is like an enemy chasing
your little character or whatever.
But here we have the
image chasing the mouse.
And when I click, the mouse
starts chasing the image
and the image is
running away from mouse.
So that's pretty cool.
And notice again, there's
still collision detection here.
>> So that is the final little
demo I have set up here.
And let's take a look at one more thing.
So back here, I mentioned this jitter.
All right.
So if distance is less than five pixels,
I was setting x and y velocity to zero.
What happens if we get rid of that?
So I'm going to just do this.
Please excuse this horrendous style,
but we commented out the correct code.
So I'm going to save that and do the
same command from before to make it.
>> All right.
And now what happens?
Good.
We're still following the
mouse just like before,
but when we get to the mouse,
we've got this gross jitter.
What's going on there?
Well, in our vector
math, remember we were
taking the distance between the
cursor and the center of the image?
Well, as that approaches
0, we start getting
like this sort of crazy behavior
where the image is sort of
like oscillating around the cursor.
And that's creating this jitter.
And that's really ugly.
And you probably don't
want your games doing that,
unless it's some sort of special effect.
>> So that's why we have
just this arbitrary
cut off of five pixels, where we say
if it's within five pixels, we're good.
We don't need to move the image anymore.
So that's what's going on there.
>> So that's pretty much it.
You now know how to create
a window, load an image,
draw an image to the window, get
keyboard input, get mouse input,
there's a bunch of other
input that you wouldn't
know how to get if you just spend a
few minutes looking at documentation.
So you actually have quite a
few tools at your disposal now
to write a full-fledged game.
>> Now, every game needs some audio,
but the audio documentation
is also pretty good.
And I'm willing to bet that if
you understand all of the things
we talked about today with
the images, and surfaces,
the windows, and everything, then
figuring out the audio API is not
going to be that bad.
So I look forward to seeing
what you create with SDL.