CONNOR HARRIS: Still I
think some exciting video
produced by a professional consultancy
that uses R a lot in its work.
>> NARRATOR: What's behind the statistics,
the analytics, and the visualizations
that today's brightest data scientists
and business leaders rely on
to make powerful decisions?
You may not always see it.
But it's there.
It's called R, open source R-- the
statistical programming language
that data experts the world
over use for everything
from mapping broad social
and marketing trends online
to developing the financial and climate
models that help drive our economies
and communities.
>> But what exactly is R
and where did R start?
Well originally, R started
here with two professors
who wanted a better statistical
platform for their students.
So they created one modeled
after the statistical language S.
They, along with many others,
kept working on and using R,
creating tools for R and finding
new applications for R every day.
>> Thanks to this is
worldwide community effort,
R kept growing with thousands
of user-created libraries built
to enhance R functionality and
crowd-sourced quality validation
and support from the most recognized
industry leaders in every field that
uses R. Which is great, because
R is the best at what it does.
Budding experts quickly and
easily interpret, interact with,
and visualize data showing their rapidly
growing community of R users worldwide
and see how open source
R continues to shape
the future of statistical
analysis and data science.
>> CONNOR HARRIS: OK, great.
So my own presentation
will be a bit more sober.
It will not involve that much
exciting background music.
But as you saw in the video, R is sort
of a general purpose program language.
But it was created mostly
for statistical work.
>> So it's designed for statistics,
for data analysis, for data mining.
And so you can see this in a lot of
the design choices that the makers of R
made.
It's designed for largely,
people who are not
experts in programming, who
are just picking up programming
on the side so they can do their work
in social science or in statistics
or whatever.
>> It has a lot of very
important differences from C.
But the syntax and the paradigms
that it uses are broadly the same.
And you should feel pretty
much at home right off the bat.
It's an imperative language.
>> Don't worry too much about that
if you don't know the term.
But there's a distinction
between imperative, declarative,
and functional.
Imperative just means you make
statements that are basically commands.
And then the interpreter or the
computer follows them one by one.
It's weakly typed, there are
no type declarations in R.
>> And then the lines
between different types
are a bit more loose than
they are in C, for example.
And as I said there are
very extensive facilities
for graphing, for statistical
analysis, for data mining.
These are both built into the
language and, as the video said,
thousands of third party libraries that
you can download and use free of charge
with very loose license conditions.
>> So in general, I'd recommend
that you look at these two books
if you're going to work on R. One
of them is the official R beginner's
guide.
It's maintained by the
core developers of R.
You can download it again, free of
charge and legally at that link there.
All these slides are going to go
up on the internet, on CS50 website
after this is done.
So no need to copy
things down frantically.
>> The other one is a
textbook by Cosma Shalizi,
who is a statistics professor at
Carnegie Mellon, called Advanced Data
Analysis from an
Elementary Point of View.
This is not principally an R book.
It's a statistics book and
it's a data analysis book.
But it's very accessible to people who
have a modicum of statistics knowledge.
>> I have never taken a formal course.
I just know bits and pieces
from various allied subjects
that I've taken courses in.
And I was able to understand
it perfectly well.
>> All the figures are given
in R. They are made in R
and they also have code listings
below each figure that tell you
how you make each figure with R code.
And that's very useful if
you're trying to emulate
some figure you see in a book.
>> And again free download
stat.cmu.edu/cshalizi/ Sorry,
that should be slash tilde cshalizi.
I'll make sure to correct that
when the official slides go up.
/ADAfaEPoV which is just the
acronym of the book title.
>> So general caveats-- R
has a lot of capabilities.
I'm only going to be able to cover
the surface of a lot of things.
Also the first portion of the seminar
is going to be something of a data dump.
I'm quite sorry about that.
Basically, I'm going to
introduce you to a lot of things
right off the bat, going
as quickly as possible.
And then we get to
the fun part, which is
the demo where I can show you everything
that we've talked about on the screen.
And you can play around on your own.
So there's going to be a lot of
technical stuff thrown up on here.
Don't worry about copying all that down.
Because A, you can get all the
stuff on the CS50 website later.
And B, it's not really that important
to memorize this from the slides.
It's more important that you get
some intuitive facility with it
and that comes from just playing around.
>> So why use R?
Basically, if you have a project that
involves mining large data sets, data
visualization, you
should use R. If you're
doing complicated statistical analyses,
that would be difficult to in Excel,
for example, it would
also be good-- also
if you're doing statistical
analysis that's automated.
Let's say you're maintaining a website.
And you want to read the server log
every day and compile some list,
like the top countries that
your users are coming from,
some summary statistics on how long
they spend on your website or whatever.
And you want to run this every day.
>> Now if you're doing this in Excel,
you'd have to go to your server log,
import that into an
Excel data spreadsheet,
run all the analysis manually.
With R, you can just write one script.
Schedule it to run every day
from your operating system.
And then every night at 2:00 AM,
or whenever you schedule it to run,
it will look through your
internet traffic for that day.
And then by the next day, you'll
have this shiny, new report
or whatever with all of the
information you asked for.
>> So basically R is for Cisco
programming versus Cisco analysis.
Preliminary is done.
Let's get into the real things.
So there are three real
types in the language.
There's numeric type.
There's sort of a difference between
integers and floating points,
but not really.
There's a character
type, which is strings.
And there's a logical
type, which is Booleans.
>> And you can convert between types
using these functions as numeric,
as character, as logical.
If you call, for example,
as numeric on a string,
it will try to read that string
as a number, the same way
that a2i and scanf do, and C. If
you call as numeric on true or false
it will convert to 1 or 0.
If you call as character
on anything it'll
convert that into a
string representation.
>> And then there are vectors and matrices.
So vectors are basically
1 dimensional arrays.
They are what we call arrays in
C. Matrices, 2 dimensional arrays.
And then higher
dimensional arrays you can
have 3, 4, 5 dimensions or whatever
of numeric values, of strings,
of logical values.
>> You also have lists which are
a kind of associative array.
I'll get into that a bit.
So one important thing
that trips people up in R
is that there are no
real, pure atomic types.
There's no actual distinction between
a number, like a numeric value,
and a list of numeric values.
Numeric values are actually the
same as the vectors of length 1.
And this has a number of
important implications.
One, it means that you can do
things very easily that involve
like adding a number to a vector.
R will basically figure
out what you mean by that.
And I'll get to that in a second.
It also means that there's no way
for the type checker-- to the extent
that something like that
exists in R-- to tell
when you've passed in the single value
when it expects an array or vice versa.
And that can cause some odd
troubles that I ran into when
I was using R during my summer job.
And there are no mixed-type arrays.
So you can't have an array were the
first elements is, I don't know,
the string "John" and the
second element is number 42.
If you try to do that, then you'll get
everything just converted to a string.
So we have string John, string 42.
>> So unusual syntactic features-- most
of R syntax is very similar to C.
There are a few important differences.
Typing is very weak.
So there are no variable declarations.
Assignment uses the strange
error operator less than hyphen.
Comments are with the hash mark.
I guess now days we call it hashtag
though that's not really accurate-- not
the double slash.
>> Modular residues are with %% signs.
Integer division is with %/% which is
very hard to read when it's projected
up on the screen.
You can get ranges of
integers with the colon.
So 2,5 will give you a vector
of all the numbers 2 through 5.
>> Arrays are one-indexed,
which screws a lot of people
up if they're from more
typical programming languages,
like C, where most
things are zero-indexed.
Again, this is where R's heritage
as a language for like not
professional programmers comes in.
If you're a sociologist or
an economist or something
and you're trying to use
R basically as an adjunct
to your more important
professional work,
you're going to find
one-indexing a bit more natural.
Because you start counting
at 1 in everyday life, not 0.
>> For-loops, this is similar to
the foreach construct in PHP,
which you'll get to
learn in-- pretty soon.
Which is for value in vector and
then you can do things with value.
AUDIENCE: That's come up in lecture.
CONNOR HARRIS: Oh, that's
come up lecture, excellent.
AUDIENCE: The assignment, is it
supposed to point from right to left?
CONNOR HARRIS: From right to left, yes.
You can think of it as the value on
the right shoved into the variable
on the left.
AUDIENCE: OK.
>> CONNOR HARRIS: And finally
function syntax is a bit strange.
You have the function name foo, assigned
to this keyword function, followed
by all the arguments and then the
body of the function after that.
Again these things may
seem a bit strange.
They'll become second nature after
you work with the language for a bit.
So vectors, the way
you construct a vector
is you type C, which is a keyword, then
all the numbers you want or strings
or whatever.
Arguments also be vectors.
But the resulting array gets flattened.
So you can't have arrays where
some elements are single numbers
and some elements are arrays themselves.
>> So if you try to construct an
array were the first element is 4
and the second element
is the array 3,5 you'll
just get a three elements array, 4,3,5.
They can't be of mixed type.
If you try to read or write
outside of the bounds of a vector
you'll get this value called NA a
which stands for a missing value.
And this is intended for
like statisticians who
are working with incomplete data sets.
>> If you apply a function that's supposed
to take just one number to an array
then what you'll get is, the
function will map over the array.
So if your function let's say takes
a number and returns it square.
You apply that to the array 2,3,5
What you'll get is the array 4,9,25.
>> And that's very useful
because it means you
don't have to write for loops for
doing very simple things like applying
a function to all members of a data set.
Which if you're working with large
data sets, you have to do a lot.
Binary functions are
applied entry by entry.
I'll get into that.
You can access them with arrays
or vectors with square brackets.
So vector name square brackets 1
will give you the first element.
Vector name square brackets 2
will give you the second element.
>> You can pass on a vector
of indices and you'll
get back out basically a sub factor.
So you can do vector name brackets C,2,4
and you'll get out a vector containing
the second and fourth
elements of the array.
And if you want just a
quick summary statistic
of a vector like interquartile
range, median, maximum, whatever,
you can just type summary
vector name and get that out.
That's not really useful in
programming but if you're playing
around the data sets, it's handy.
>> Matrices-- basically
higher dimensional arrays.
They have this special notation syntax.
Matrix with an array that gets
filled in-- sorry, matrix with data,
number of rows, number of columns.
When you have some data, it fills in
the array basically going top to bottom
first.
Then left to right.
So, like that.
And R has built in
matrix multiplications ,
spectral decomposition,
diagonalization, a lot of things.
If you want higher dimensional
arrays, so 3, 4, 5 ,
or whatever dimensions you can do that.
The syntax is array dim equals c,
then the list of the dimensions.
So if you want a 4 dimensional array
with dimensions 4, 7, 8, 9, the array,
dim equals c(4,7,8,9).
>> You access single values with brackets
first entry comma second entry.
You can get entire slices
of rows or columns.
With this incomplete syntax it's
just row number comma or comma column
number.
So lists are a kind of associated array.
They have their own syntax here.
Again don't frantically
copy all this down.
This is just so that people
going through the slides later
have this all in a nice reference.
And this will become very natural once
I actually walk through the demos.
So lists a basically associated arrays.
You can access values with
list name, dollar sign, key.
So if your list is named foo,
then you can access it like that.
You can get an entire key-value pair
by passing in the square bracket index.
If you read from a non-existent
key, you'll get null.
It won't error.
Thing is, R will do as
much with null as it can.
And this can mean that if you're
not expecting to get null out
of some list read, you'll get some
unpredictable errors further down
the line.
>> This happened to me my
summer job when I was using R
where I changed how a certain
list was defined in one spot
but didn't change later on the
code that read values from it.
And so what happened was I was
reading null values out of this list,
passing them into functions,
and being very confused
when I got all sorts of
random infinities cropping up
in this function.
Because if you apply certain maximum
or minimum functions to null,
you'll get infinite values out.
>> Data frames, they're a subclass of list.
Every value is a vector
of the same length.
And they're used for presenting,
basically, data tables.
There's this initialization syntax.
This will all, again, be much
clearer when you get to the demo.
And the nice thing about
data frames is that you
can give names to all the columns
and names to all the rows.
And so that makes accessing
them a bit friendlier.
Also this is how most functions that
read in data from Excel spreadsheets
or from text files, for example,
will read in their data.
They'll put it into
some sort of data frame.
So functions-- the functions
syntax is a bit weird.
Again it's the name of the function,
assign, this keyword function and then
the list of arguments.
So there are some nice things
about how functions work here.
For one, you can actually assign
default values to certain arguments.
So you can say R1
equals-- you can say foo
is a function where R1 equals something
by default if the user specifies
no arguments.
Otherwise, it's whatever he put in.
And this is very handy
because a lot of our functions
have often dozens or
hundreds of arguments.
For example the ones for plotting
graphs or plotting scatter plots
have arguments that control
everything from the title and the axis
labels to the color of regression lines.
And so if you don't want
to make people specify
every single one of these
hundreds of arguments
controlling every single aspect of
a plot or a regression or whatever,
it's nice to have these default values.
>> And then you can actually
write as you saw back here.
Or find a better example.
When you call functions you can actually
call them using the argument names.
So here's an example of
the matrix constructor.
It takes three arguments.
Usually you have data,
which is a vector.
You have N row, which
is the number of rows.
You have N cols-- number of columns.
The thing is if you type
N row equals whatever
and N col equals whatever when
you're calling this function,
you can actually reverse them.
So you can put N col first and N row
second and it will make no difference.
So that's a nice little feature.
>> Did import and export.
This can be done, basically.
There are also facilities to write out
arbitrary R objects to a binary file
and then read them back in later.
Which is handy if you're doing
a big interactive session R
and you need to save
things very quickly.
By default R has a working directory
that files get written out into
and read back in from.
You can see that with
getwg, change it with setdw.
Nothing especially interesting here
>> So now the actual statistics
stuff-- multilinear regression.
So the usual syntax
is a bit complicated.
The model is a big object basically.
It gets assigned to lm,
which is a function call.
The first element, the y
tilde x1 plus whatever.
My syntax here is a bit confusing.
I'm quite sorry, this
is the standard way
that computer science books do this.
But it is a bit weird.
>> So basically, it's lm
parentheses, first item
is variable-- sorry, dependent
variable tilde x1 plus x2 plus
however many independent
variables you have.
And then these can either be
vectors, all the same length.
Or they can be column
headers in a data frame
that you just specify in the
second argument data frame.
>> You can also specify
a more complex formula
so you don't have to linearly
regress a one dependent variable,
or one vector on a pre-existing vector.
You can do, for example, a
vector component y squared plus 1
and regress that against the
log of some other vector.
You can print summaries of the
model with this command called
summary-- just summary parens model.
Again something else I should clarify.
Something else that will get corrected
when the slides go up on the internet.
If you just want to calculate
a simple correlation
you can use correlation vector
1 vector 2 function core.
Method is by default
Pearson correlations.
Those are the standard ones you can do.
There also Spearman and
Kendell correlations
which are some variety of
rank order correlation.
Well they don't calculate product
moments between the vectors themselves,
but of the vector's rank orders.
I'll explain that later.
>> AUDIENCE: Quick question
>> CONNER HARRIS: Sure.
>> AUDIENCE: So when you're calculating
for the simple correlations do
you assume that there's a statistical
significance to the correlation?
CONNER HARRIS: You don't have to.
An lm is basically just a machine.
It will take in two things
and it will spit out
coefficients for the best fit line.
It also reports standard
errors on those coefficients.
And it will tell you, like is the
intercept statistically significant
or difference from 0.
Is the slope of the best
fit line statistically
different from zero, et cetera.
So it assumes nothing, I think
is best answer to your question.
OK.
>> Plotting-- so the main reason you should
use R, like multilinear regression.
Basically every language
has some facility for that.
And honestly R's syntax for
regression is a bit arcane.
But plotting is where it really shines.
>> The workhorse function is plot
and it takes two vectors, x and y.
And then the ellipses stands for a very
large number of optional arguments that
control everything from titles to colors
of various lines or various points,
to the type of plot.
You can have scatter
plots or line plots.
>> [INAUDIBLE] 2 vectors
of the same length.
You can precede this with attach
data frame in your script.
And this will let you just use column
headers instead of separate vectors.
You can add best fit lines and local
regression curves to your graph.
>> These commands listed
here, ab line and lines,
by default these get
written into pop up windows
because it assumes that
you're using R interactively.
If you're not you can
write two files that
are in really any format you'd like.
Sorry, I have a typo I just realized.
If you want to open
another graphical device
you can use this function called PNG or
JPEG or a lot of other image formats.
And you can write graphs to
whatever file name you specify.
To cancel that you have to use--
I didn't write this in the slide--
but there's a function called dev
dot off that takes no arguments.
>> Then there are facilities
for 3D plotting
and for contour plotting
if you want to make
graphs of two independent variables.
I won't get into these right now.
>> There are also some
facilities for animation
those are usually
maintained by third parties.
I have done animations with R graphs,
but I haven't used these third party
libraries.
So I can't really attest
to how good they are.
What I recommend if you want
to make animations using R
is you can write out all of
the frames for the animations
and then you can use a
third party program--
typical ones are called FFmpeg
or ImageMagick-- to stitch
all of your frames into one animation.
>> So time for demo.
So if you're using any Unix like system
which is Linux BSD but who uses BSD.
OS X open a terminal window and
type R at the command prompt.
If you have R studio or
the like, that also works.
For Windows users you should be
able to find R in your Start menu.
It should be called something
like R x64 3 point whatever.
Open that up there.
>> So now let me just
open a terminal window.
All right, search.
AUDIENCE: Command-Space
CONNER HARRIS: Command-Space, thank you.
I do not ordinarily use Macs.
Terminal, show new window.
New window is settings
basic, R. So you should get
a welcome message, something like this.
>> So I'm using R interactively.
You can also write R scripts of course.
Basically scripts run
the exact same way as
if you were sitting at the computer
typing in every line one at a time.
So let's start by making a vector.
A arrow C 1, 2.
1, 2, 4.
OK, sure.
I can make the font size bigger.
>> AUDIENCE: Command-Plus
>> CONNER HARRIS: Command-Plus.
Command-Plus.
All right, how's that?
Good?
OK.
So let's start by
declaring a vector list.
Do a, arrow, C 1,2,4.
We can see a.
Don't worry about the bracket there.
The brackets are so if you print out
very long arrays, we can where you are.
One example would be if I
just want range 2 to 200.
If I printed a very
long array, the brackets
are just so I can keep
track of which index
we're on if I'm looking
through this visually.
So anyhow, we have a.
>> So I said before that arrays interact
very nicely with, for example,
unary operations like this.
So what you think I'll
get if I type a plus 1?
Yep.
Right, now I'll make
this different array.
Let's say b c 20,40, 80.
So what do you think
this command will do?
Add the elements.
And so basically that's what it does.
So this is pretty convenient.
So I how about I do this. c
is, let's say, 6 times 1 to 10.
So what do I want to see
contained, do you think?
So all multiples of six.
Now, what do you think
will happen if I do this?
I'll make this a bit clearer, c, c.
So what happens, do you
think, if I do this?
a plus c.
[INAUDIBLE]
>> AUDIENCE: Either an error or it
just adds the first three elements.
>> CONNER HARRIS: Not quite.
This is what we got.
What happens is a shorter
array, a, got cycled.
So we got 124, 124, 124.
Yeah.
And basically, you can view
this behavior before, a plus 1,
as a subclass of this behavior, where
the shortest array is just the number
1, which is a one element array.
I just be saying vector all
the time instead of array,
because that's what the r
documentation usually does.
It's an ingrained c habit.
>> OK, and so now we have this array.
So we have this array, c.
We can get summary
statistics on c, summary c.
And that's nice.
So now let's do some matrix things.
Let's say m is a matrix.
Let's make it a three by three one.
So nrows equals 3, and ncols equals 3.
And for data let's do-- so what
do you think this is going to do?
>> Right, it's the next one.
It's nrow and ncolumn.
So what I've done is I've
declared a three by three matrix
and I've passed in a nine-element array.
So the logarithm of all the
elements one through nine.
And all those values fill
up the array-- sorry?
AUDIENCE: Those are base 10 logs?
CONNER HARRIS: No, log is
natural logarithms, so base e.
Yeah, if you wanted base
10 log, I think you'd have
to log whatever, divided by log 10.
And so the data of the [INAUDIBLE] just
fills up the array, so top to bottom,
then left to right.
And if you wanted to do some other
array, let's say n is matrix.
Let's do, I don't know, 2 to 13.
Or I'll do something more interesting.
I'll do 2 to 4.
nrow equals, let's say, 3.
ncol equals 4.
n.
So we've got this.
>> And now if we want to multiply these,
we would do n percent times percent,
because that's n.
And we have matrix products.
By they way, did you see how
when I declared n, the 2 to 4
vector got cycled until
it filled up all of n?
If you wanted to take
eigenvalue decomposition,
this is something we can do very easily.
We can do eigen n.
And so this is our first
encounter with a list.
>> So eigen n is a list with two keys.
Values, which is this array here.
And vectors, which is this array here.
So if you wanted to extract,
say, this third column
from the eigenvectors matrix, because
the eigenvectors are column vectors.
So we can do vec eigen n dollar sign
vectors, comma 3, of [INAUDIBLE].
Vec.
Is that, as you might expect.
>> Then say n times percent times vec.
So the result here certainly looks like
if we took the third eigenvalue here,
which corresponds with
the third eigenvector.
It just multiplied everything in
this eigenvector, component-wise,
by the eigenvalue.
And that's what we would expect,
because that's what eigenvalues are.
Has anyone here not
taken linear algebra?
A couple people, OK.
Just turn your brains off for a bit.
And indeed if we take eigen n
dollar sign values 3 times vec,
well get the same thing.
It's formatted differently as a row
vector instead of a column vector,
but big deal.
And so those are basically the nice
things that we can do with matrices,
demonstrated lists.
I should demonstrate the nice
things about functions as well.
>> So let's say-- [INAUDIBLE]
function, let's call
it func against function n n squared--
actually, that's not really the best.
a, b, a squared plus b.
So one thing about
functions, again, is they
don't need explicit return statements.
So you can just-- the
last statement evaluated
will be the statement returned,
or the value returned.
So in this case, we're only evaluating
one statement, a squared plus b.
That will be the default return value.
It never hurts to put in
return values explicitly,
especially if you're dealing with a
function of very complicated logic
flow.
But you don't need them.
So now we can do func 5, 1, and
this is basically what you'd expect.
Something else we can do,
we can actually do func b
equals 1, a equals 5.
So if we specify which number here,
which argument goes to which argument
in the function, we can flip around
these values wherever we want.
>> AUDIENCE: Is there a reason
to write it out with the b
equals as opposed to just using
the numbers and the comma?
CONNER HARRIS: Yeah, usually
do this if you have functions
with a lot of arguments.
That might often be like
flags that you'd only
want to use in rare occasions.
And this way you can only-- you
can refer to the specific arguments
that you want to use
non-default values for,
and you don't have to write out a
bunch of flags equals false after them.
Or I can write this again with
a default value like b equals 2.
And then I could do f func,
I'll do 4, 1 this time.
And 17, which is 4 squared
plus 1, as you might expect.
>> But I could also just
call this with func 4,
and I'll get 18, because
I don't specify b.
So b gets the default value of 2.
>> OK, so now if you're
following along with the demo,
type this line at your command
prompt and see what comes up.
Actually, don't do that.
Type this.
You should get something like this.
So mtcars is a built in data
set for this demonstration
purposes that comes with-- that comes
in by default with your r distribution.
This is a compilation of statistics from
a 1974 issue of Motor Trend's magazine
on a number of different car models.
>> So there's miles per gallon, cylinders--
I forget what disp is-- horsepower.
Probably.
If you just Google MT cars,
then one of the first results
will be from the
official r documentation
and it will explain
all these data fields.
So weight is-- wt is
weight of the car in tons.
Q sec is the quarter mile time.
So now we can do some fun things
about MT cars is a data field.
>> So we can do things
like row names, mt cars.
And this is a list of all the rows in
the data set which are names of cars.
We can do colnames, mt cars this.
If you do mt cars,
sub-numerical index, like 2.
we get the second column out of
this, which would be cylinders.
>> AUDIENCE: What did you do?
>> CONNER HARRIS: I typed
mt cars, brackets e,
which gave me the second
column out of mt cars.
Or if we want a row, I can type
mtcars comma 2, for example.
Other round 2 comma, like that.
And that goes in your row.
This here just gives you a
column, but column as a vector.
I just realized now I
forgot to demonstrate
some cool things about vectors
that you can do with indices.
So let me do that right now.
So let's do c gets-- putting
this on pause-- 2 times 1 to 10.
So c is just going to be
the vector 2 through 20.
I can take elements like this, c2.
I can pass in a vector
like this, c-- let me
use different name than c, like vec c.
Basically, I'm doing
this so you don't get
confused between c as a
vector construction function,
and then c as a variable name.
Vec brackets c 4, 5, 7.
This'll get me out the fourth, fifth,
and seven elements of the array.
I can do vec, put in a negative
index, like negative 4.
That will get me out this with
the fourth element removed.
Then if I wanted to do slices,
I can do vec 2 through 6.
2 colon 6 is just another
vector, which is 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
Spits out that.
>> So anyhow, back to mt cars.
So let's do some regressions.
Let's say model gets-- let's
linearly regress-- I don't know.
First let's do attach mtcars, of course.
So [INAUDIBLE] model lm, let's regress
miles per gallon on tilde weight.
And then data frame is mtcars.
So summary model.
>> OK, so this looks a bit complicated.
But basically, seeing as if we
try to express miles per gallon
as a linear function of weight,
then we got this line here,
which intercepts at 37.28.
37.28 would be the theoretical miles
per gallon of a car that weighs zero.
And then for every additional ton,
you knock about five miles per gallon
off of that.
Both of these coefficients you
can see, standard errors there.
And they are very
statistically significant.
>> So we can be very certain to
1 e 10 to the negative 10.
So 1 times something to the negative
10, that if you make a heavier car,
it will have worse miles per gallon.
Or we can test some other model.
Like instead of
regressing this on weight,
let's regress it on log of weight,
because maybe the effective weight
on mileage is somehow not linear.
>> This gave us an r squared of 0.7528.
So let's try this.
This time let's do a
different variable, too.
Model2.
So summary, model2.
All right, so again, we
got our best fit line here.
And this time-- this is saying,
basically that every time you
increase the weight of
a car by a factor of e
you lose this many miles per gallon.
>> And so this time our residual standard
error it-- that doesn't matter, really.
The residual standard error is
basically just the standard error
that you have left after you
take away the trend line.
And our r squared here is 0.81,
which is a bit better than what
we had before, 0.52.
>> And so now let's add a
term to this regression.
So let's regress miles per gallon
both on the log of the weights
and, let's do, q miles,
quarter mile time.
OK, it must have the-- all right, qsec.
Qsec.
Actually-- sorry, what?
Let me call this something
else besides model2.
Let me call this model3.
And so now we can do summary model3.
And so again, this is basically
what you might expect.
You have positive intercept.
The effective increasing
weight is negative.
And the effective
increasing quarter mile time
is positive, but though
less so than weight.
Now intuitively, you can make sense of
this by saying think about sports cars.
There's a very fast acceleration,
a very short quarter mile times.
They're also going to use more gas,
whereas more sensible cars are going
to have slower acceleration,
higher quarter mile times,
and use less gas,, so
higher miles per gallon.
Great.
And so now it's time to
plot something like this.
So let's do-- so bare
bones we can do plots--
because I've attached this data frame
before-- we can just do plots, wt mpg.
Make this a bit bigger.
There, we basically have a
scatter plot, but the points
are kind of hard to see on this.
>> I don't remember offhand what the
syntax is for changing the plot.
So I guess this will be
a good time to bring up,
there's a very nice builtin help
feature, help quotes function name.
We'll bring up basically
anything you'd like.
I think I'll actually do this
type equals p for points plots.
Did that change anything?
And no, not really.
All right.
>> For some reason, when I did this
on my own computer a while ago,
all the scatter points
were much clearer.
Anyhow, are the scatter kind of visible?
There's one there.
A few there, a few there.
You can sort of see them, right?
So if we want to add a best fit line
to this plot here, which is a bit bare
bones-- let me make it a bit nicer.
Main equals versus weight.
Miles per gallon.
Again, you can see how useful
optional arguments are here with also
not having to put things in a
certain order with keyboard arguments
when you have plots, because
these take a lot of arguments.
>> Xlab equals weight, weight, tons.
All right.
OK, yeah, this device
is being a bit annoying.
But you can see sort of up there,
there's a graph title on the side.
Over here there's-- on the bottom
here there are axis labels.
I don't remember offhand
what the commands ars--
what the functions are to increase
the size of those labels and titles,
but they're there.
>> And so if we want to
add the best fit line,
we could do something like-- I
have the syntax written up here.
So remember we just add model
was mpg, weight, mtcars.
And so if I wanted to add a best fit
line, I could do a, b line model.
And boom, we have a best fit line.
It's kind of hard to see again.
I'm quite sorry about the
technological difficulties.
But it runs basically
top left to bottom right.
>> And if the scale were
bigger, you could see
that the intercept is what you can
find from the summary statistics
if you type summary model.
OK, so I hope everyone gets
something of a sense of what
R is, what it's good for.
You could make far nicer plots than
this on your own time, if you like.
>> So the foreign function interface.
This is something that is not typically
covered in introductory lectures
or introductory anything for r.
It's not likely you're going to need it.
However, I found it useful in
my own projects in the past.
And there's no good
tutorial for it online.
So I'm just going to
rush you all through this
and then you're free to leave.
And so the foreign
function interface is what
you can use to call out to see
functions with an R. Internally,
R is built on C. R's arithmetic is just
C's 64-bit floating point arithmetic,
which is type double [INAUDIBLE].
And you might want to do
this for a bunch of reasons.
For one, R is interpreted, it's
not compiled down to machine code.
So you can rewrite your
inner loops in C and then get
the advantage of using R. Like
it's a bit more convenient than C.
It has better graphing
facilities and whatnot.
And while still being able to get
top speed out of the inner loops,
which is where you really need it.
>> Reusing existing C libraries,
that's also important.
If you have some C library for like,
I don't know, Fourier transforms,
or some very Archean
statistics procedure used
in high energy astrophysics
or something, I don't know.
High energy astrophysics
isn't even a think, I think.
But you can do that instead of having
to write a native R port of them.
And on the-- and again, like if you
look in most of R's default libraries,
on the internals, the internals are
going to use the foreign function
interface very extensively.
They'll have things like Fourier
transforms or computing correlation
coefficients written in C, and they'll
just have R wrappers around them.
The interface is a
bit difficult. I think
its difficulty is exaggerated in a
lot of the instructions you'll find.
But nevertheless, it is a bit confusing.
And I haven't been able to
find a good tutorial for it,
so this is it right now.
Again, this whole segment
is more for later reference.
Don't worry about copying
everything down right now.
So the following instructions
are for Unix-like systems,
Linux, BSD, OS X. I don't know
how this works on Windows,
but please just don't do your
final project on Windows.
You really don't want to.
Unix is much better set
up for casual programming.
So, basically foreign
function interface.
If you want to write a C
function for use with R,
it has to take all the
arguments as pointers.
>> So for single values, this
means it's pointed to the value.
For arrays, this is a pointer
to the first element, which
is what array names actually mean.
Again, this is something you should have
pretty totally down after p set five.
Array names are just pointers
to the first element,
The floating-point type is double.
And your function has to return void.
The only way that it can
actually tell R what happened
is by modifying the memory that R gave
to it through the foreign function
interface.
>> So I've written this
example here, this is
a function that computes use
dot product of two vectors.
It takes two arguments, vec1, vec2,
which are the vectors themselves,
and then n, which is a
length, because again,
R has built in [INAUDIBLE] to find out
the length of vectors, but C doesn't.
In C, vectors is an arbitrary
delimited chunk of memory.
So the way you can
calculate dot products
is just set this out parameter
to zero and then iterate through
from 1 to star n, because
n's a pointer to the length,
just add something to
this out parameter.
And it can be good practice
if you're going to do
this to write two separate C functions.
One of them has-- One of them just
takes the arguments and the types
that they would ordinarily be in C.
>> So It takes a array
arguments as pointers.
But single-value arguments like n,
it just takes as values by copy,
without pointers.
And then it doesn't
[INAUDIBLE] out pointer.
And then you can have
a different, basically,
wrapper function that basically
handles the requirements
of the foreign function
interface for you.
>> The way you call this in R is, once
you have your function written in C,
you type R cmd shlib, R
command shared library,
foo dot c, or whatever
your file name is,
and the OS shell not in the R terminal.
And this will create a
library called foo dot so.
And then you can load it in
our script or interactively
with command dyn dot load.
Then there is a function
in R called dot c.
>> This takes arguments that are
first the name of the function in C
that you want to call.
And then all the parameters
to that function,
they have to be in the proper order.
You have to use these type
coercion functions as integer, as
double, as character, and as logical.
And then when it returns the
list, which again is just
an associated array of the
parameter names and the values
after the function has run.
>> So in this case, because dot prod has
arguments vec1, vec2, and int n, n out.
To dot c we have dot prod,
the name of the function
we're calling, vec1, vec2, type coerce.
The length of either vector,
I just chose vec1 arbitrarily.
It would be more robust to say s
integer min length of vec1, length vec2.
Then just as double zero,
because we don't really
care what goes into the
out parameter because we're
setting it to zero anyway.
>> And then results are going to be a
big associated array of basically
vec1 is whatever, vec2 is whatever.
But we're interested in
out, so we can get that out.
This is again, a very toy example
of a foreign function interface.
But if you have to compute dot
products of massive vectors in loops,
or if you have to do
something else in a loop,
and you don't want to rely on R,
which does have a bit of overhead
built into it, this can be useful.
>> Again, this is not usually
an introductory topic to R.
It's not very well documented.
I'm just including it because
I found it useful in the past.
So, bad practices.
I mentioned that there's a
for loop in the function.
Generally you shouldn't, in
the language, not use it.
Based on how R implements iteration
internally, it can be slow.
They just also look ugly.
>> R handles vectors very nicely, so
oftentimes you don't need to use it.
Then you can usually
replace a vector often
with these functions called high
order functions, Map, Reduce,
Find, or Filter.
I'll just give some
examples of what these do.
Map is a higher order function because
it takes a function as an argument.
So you can give it a function,
you can give it an array,
and it will apply the function
to every element of the array
and return the new array.
Reduce, basically you give
it an array, you give it
a function that takes two arguments.
It will apply the function first, the
first argument with some starter value.
Then to that result in the second.
Then to that result in the third,
then to that result in the fourth.
And then return when it gets to the end.
So for example, if you want to
compute the sum of all the elements
in an array, than you might call reduce
with [INAUDIBLE] reduce an addition
function, like func
a, b, return a plus b.
And then start a value of 0.
>> And all these, you can find them
described in the R documentation,
in any textbook on
functional programming.
There's also this class of
functions called apply functions,
which I don't-- they're
a bit hard to explain,
but if you look in [INAUDIBLE]
booked that I cited at the beginning,
he explains them pretty well in
his appendix on R programming.
More about practices,
appending to vectors.
Yeah?
I think I should correct that.
In that first line, vec arrow,
that arrow should not be there.
You can assign to a vector,
again, by take its length plus 1
and assigning some value to that.
That will extend the vector, or you
can do vec equals c, vec newvalue.
Again, if you use C with
one argument as a vector,
the resulting hierarchy gets flattened.
So you'll just get a vector
that's extended by 1.
Never do this.
>> The reason why you
shouldn't do this is this.
When you allocate a vector, it
gives it a certain chunk of memory.
If you increase that vector size,
it has to reallocate the vector
somewhere else.
And so reallocation is quite expensive.
I won't go into the details of how
memory allocators are implemented
on the operating system level,
but it takes a lot of time
to find a new chunk of memory.
And also, if you're
re-allocating lots and lots
of progressively larger
chunks, you end up
with something called
memory fragmentation,
where the available memory is
divided into lots of little blocks
in the memory allocators point of view.
And it gets harder and harder
to find memory for other things.
So instead, if you need to do this, if
you need to grow a vector from one end
to the next, instead of appending to it
constantly, you should pre-allocate it.
Vec arrow, vector length
equals 1,000, or whatever.
>> And then you can just assign
to the vector's values one
a time after you've allocated it once.
I ran into this, again, my summer job
when I was writing NRA differential
equation solver.
Not symbolic numerical.
The idea is that once you have
one value for your solution,
you use that to compute the next one.
So my natural naive
inclination was to say OK,
so I'll start with a vector
that's a substantial value.
Compute from that the next value
that goes onto my solution vector,
and append that.
>> Create something else, append that.
It went very, very slowly.
And once I realized this
and I changed my system
from appending to this vector
like 10,000 to 100,000 times,
to just pre-allocating a vector
and just running with that.
I got more than 1,000 fold speed up.
So this is a very common
trap for R programming.
If you need to build up a vector
piece by piece, pre-allocate it.
>> Another common trip up-- this is my last
slide, don't worry-- is error handling.
R, to be frank, doesn't
really do this very well.
There are a lot of
problems that can crop up.
For example, if you get an array
or a vector out of a function
that you were expecting a single
value to come from, or vice versa,
and you pass that into a function that
you wrote expecting a single value,
that can be a problem.
>> Certain functions
return null as do, say,
reading from a
nonexistent key in a list.
But null isn't like C
where if you try to read
from an old pointer, [INAUDIBLE]
to null pointer, it just seg faults
and if you're in your debugger it
tells you exactly where you are.
Instead, null will do-- functions
will do unpredictable things
if they're handed null.
Like if you're handed max null,
it'll give you negative infinity.
And so, yeah.
And so this happened
to me once when I had
changed a bunch of fields
in my list structure
once without changing them elsewhere
when I was reading from them.
And then I got all sorts of random
infinity results cropping up
and I no idea where they came from.
And unfortunately, there's
no real R strict mode
where you can say if something
looks like it might be an error,
just stop there so I can be
disciplined and fix that.
However, there is something
called stop if not.
This is equivalent to C's assert,
if you've talked about that.
I don't think C assert
is a lecture topic,
but your section leader
might have gone over it.
And stop if not basically takes any
predicate, so any statement that
can be true or false.
And if it's false, it stops its program.
It tells you exactly what line you
were on and what condition failed.
>> And this very useful, for example,
sanity checking, function inputs.
So if you have a function
and you expect, say,
if you should give me a date, I want
the dates be just a vector of length 1
and somewhere between 1 and 31.
And if not, I know
something's gone wrong.
And I choose to stop there before this
has random knock on effects with code
that it's harder to trace through.
So that's one possible
use for stop if not.
>> Anyhow, OK.
So that's the end.
Thank you so much for coming.
I am a rank amateur at this.
So sorry if you're bored or
confused or what have you.
I'm happy to take questions by email
at connorharris@college.harvard.edu.
This goes also for everyone
watching this live or later on.
Also, though I'm not
a TF, I am also very
willing to serve as an unofficial
advisor for anyone who's
using R in a final project.
>> If you'd like to that,
then just talk to your TF
and then write me an email so
I know what you're working on
and so I can set up meeting
times with you if you want.
So again, thank you very much.
I hope you enjoyed it.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> CONNER HARRIS: Of course.
>> AUDIENCE: What kind of a project
would a CS student use R for?
CONNER HARRIS: So if you're not do
something that's purely in data mining,
for example, and there
are lots of things
you could do with that with data
mining and machine learning.
You might want to use R for
a component of something.
I brought up, originally, the example
of if you're writing a website
and you want to run automated
statistical analysis of your server
logs at a certain time every day,
that might be something that's
very easy to do in just a brief
R script that you can schedule
to run every night, for example.
>> And I'm sure, if
there's any reason you'd
want statistics or graphing capabilities
and have this run automatically instead
of having to interact
with things in Excel,
for example, that's something
you might want to use R for.
So any more questions before I leave?
No?
All right, well, again, thank
you very much for coming.