>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> NEEL MEHTA: Here it goes.
>> Well, everyone, welcome to web
apps of the future with React.
This is CS50.
My name is Neel.
I'm a TA for CS50 and a sophomore
at Harvard College and a very, very
passionate web developer.
So I'm very exciting to
be talking to you today,
whether you're here or at home
watching, about React, which is, again
as I said, the future of web apps.
>> So React is a web framework.
And as I've been telling
to some people here,
a framework is just a
set of tools you can use
to structure and build your web app.
And web apps are, again, websites
that are interactive like Facebook,
Twitter.com, Instagram.com, whatever.
>> So Facebook is a web framework
that was developed by Facebook
a couple years back-- React is.
It's since been used in
Facebook on their mobile apps
and the web app, Instagram.
Khan Academy is another
prominent early adopter of React.
>> It's really been getting
extremely popular.
If you ever use things like Angular or
Backbone, this is of the same family,
but it has since far
outstrip their popularity.
It's the hot new thing.
It's really, really huge.
>> And so React is good not just as a
web framework for building interfaces.
It's good for building web interfaces.
There's also a thing
called React Native which
lets you build interfaces
for Android and iOS
and maybe other platforms in the future
using just the same JavaScript code.
You could use the exact same
JavaScript code to render websites,
to render Android apps and iOS apps.
>> It's a very, very exciting time.
It's a really, really cool opportunity.
It's really a universal web
interface development tool,
so it's a very, very
important thing to know.
And, as I was telling people
before, this, I think,
is going to change how we
build web apps forever.
So it's maybe a bit hyperbole, but I
think it's a pretty good thing to know.
>> OK, so what is React?
React is a framework you can
use for building interfaces.
An interface is, again,
a web page, right?
So here's Instagram.com, uses React.
>> React is built on the
idea of components.
A component is a HTML
element on steroids,
so an HTML element is like a button.
It's a paragraph.
It's a header, right?
And Instagram will use these, but it
will also use components of React.
>> React components are
souped-up HTML elements
that have their own behavior
contained within them.
So, as an example, we could have
a time element, a time component,
which will contain like
the time stamp, you know,
a profile component which
will contain the profile image
and the name of the person.
It can have a like counter, which
can count like the number of likes,
and if you click on it, it'll
increase the number of likes.
A component is just a
bunch of HTML code that
has some functionality
wrapped inside of it.
So it's like a HTML element
on steroids, as I said before.
You can take these components,
and you can put them together
to make new components, in
this case, a post component,
which contains all this stuff.
It would contain Time, Profile,
LikeCounter, maybe the comment
and maybe the image itself.
And so web apps are just built by taking
components and putting them together.
An Instagram feed is nothing more than
a bunch of posts one after another,
each post contains like the Time,
Profile, LikeCounter, and so on.
It's kind of like building a house.
You don't build the
house from the top down.
You take components-- you
take like the bathroom.
You take the bedroom-- you stick them
together, and you have a new component.
You have a new part of the house.
>> So React is all built around
this idea of components that
are interactive, that are declarative.
Like you just say what a
profile is, and it renders it.
They are composable.
You can take a time and a profile, put
them together, make something better.
And they're reusable, so if you
have the source code for a post,
you could embed that anywhere.
>> You can embed an Instagram
thing on your own website.
You can embed in Facebook, for example,
as long as it uses React as well.
So components are really, really, really
powerful building blocks of the web
that can be used anywhere and put
together to make new building blocks.
That's the very, very
high level overview.
So, again, if you have
any questions at any point
about the philosophy of reactor, the
coding, to stop me, and let me know.
>> OK, so react is cool because it
has a different way of looking
at how you build web apps.
You've probably heard of MVC, a
model you control in CS50 or whatever
other probing classes you use.
And most frameworks are
built around the idea of MVC.
React is not.
React is built around the idea
of unidirectional data flow
as seen by this chart or graphic here.
>> Basically, you have a data source.
And the data source will decide
how to lay out certain components.
And the components will
then, when they change,
they will tell the
data source to change.
>> To use the Instagram
example, you might have
a list of post objects like
in a database or something.
That the data.
And then our post components
will take that data,
and use that data to render
a thing on the screen.
That's what the arrow
from data to component is,
and then that same data is used
to render a bunch of components.
>> In Facebook Messenger, for
example, which is React,
you might have a list of
messages as your data source.
And that would render not
only the list of messages
but also the list of friends you have.
You have the unread count.
Maybe also render the Facebook thing
that's at the bottom of Facebook.com.
The same data is a
single source of truth
and that causes a lot of
components to be rendered.
And whenever one of those
components is changed,
it goes back and
changes the data source.
>> You send a message, right?
That changes the data source.
You read your messages,
so you set unread to 0.
That changes the data source.
And notice that all of these of one
arrow going back to the same data
source, so you know,
given a certain data set,
you know exactly what the
page is going to look like.
It's deterministic.
You know, given certain data, what
the page is going to look like.
You can predict how it's going to
behave and how things are going
to work when they're put together.
>> And if I had a million components
here, it would behave the same, right?
You wouldn't have any
weird interconnections.
One data rendered a million components.
A million components could
go back and edit the data.
And so this is very nice.
We're building composable,
easily scalable web apps.
>> You have one data source,
the source of truth.
That tells your components
how to lay out the page,
and the components will
handle interaction.
And if they want to change
things, just go back
and tell the data source to change.
Make sense?
So React is all about understanding
how to build a component
and how to make your component
interact with the outside world.
>> Making the component interact
with the outside world
uses another technology
called Flux, which
is a framework that is
added on top of React.
We're not going to talk about that.
We're going to talk more about, given
data, how can you render a component?
>> And so React is really cool because you
can use it with any back end you want.
If you have like a Python back end,
if your Python can spit out some data,
React can render it.
If you are no JS outputs
of data, React renders it.
Ruby rails up with
data, React renders it.
>> So React is basically a web
view-- a front end with components
for any data source whatsoever.
And so going from data source to
react components is pretty easy.
Going the other way is a little harder.
That uses Flux as I mentioned before.
We won't get into that.
We'll focus more on the
data-to-component side.
This way you can make
cool, fun web apps.
It won't affect the outside world
for now, but that's another story.
>> OK, so if you were here
for my last seminar
you'll know that all of the code for
today's talk is going to be at this URL
here, sorry, this URL here.
And basically we're going to go
through four steps, maybe five,
probably not five.
We'll move through four steps
of building a sample React app.
And so all the source code
for every step of the way
is going to be right here, so if
you're following along at home,
feel free to peruse this code.
If you're following along here,
we'll be showing it on the screen,
so don't worry about it.
But if you're at home, feel
free to visit this website.
And, Yeah, you should be able to get
all the code you'd ever need here.
So it's a good cheat sheet as well
for your future adventures with React.
Cool, so if everyone who's here,
and even if you're at home,
pull up this website, is.gd/cs50react,
no capital, no underscore, no nothing.
>> You'll see a page that looks
a little bit like this.
This is a thing called CodePen.
CodePen is a collaborative
coding environment
with which I can write code here, and
it'll be automatically sent to you.
And to this way, I can write code.
I can run code here.
>> For example-- and if it reloads-- see,
I'm running JavaScript code on the page
right here, and it'll
automatically render a web page
with this JavaScript code.
And so this is a way
for us to try out code
really quick without having to use
our ID or use our local machine
or whatever.
It's a very quick way for you to mockup
and test out different kinds of code.
>> So I'm going to be taking
example code, putting it here.
We're going to be working through it.
And if you're at home, you
can pull this up as well.
And I've already installed
React here, so you can just
write your own code here, and
try it as your own playground.
>> Yeah, if everyone to
open up this link here.
Please give me a thumbs
up once you have it open.
Cool, cool cool.
There's nothing here for now, but
we will change that very soon.
>> OK, so React is a JavaScript
library, and as such,
requires knowledge of JavaScript,
which is the web programming language.
And it's being used for other things
now too but primarily the web develop
language, so if you are unfamiliar with
that, read a site called JSforCats.com.
It's wonderful.
You can learn JavaScript
in half an hour.
It's incredible.
>> So give it a read.
We also is a lot of HTML here because
we're designing web pages of course.
So if you're unfamiliar with
HTML, check out HTMLdog.com.
I think learning React is a
million times easier if you already
know the building blocks.
If you have the components, it's
easy to make a bigger component.
That's React language for you.
>> So go ahead and give
these things a read.
Pause this video.
Give it a read if you are
at home if you are not
familiar with HTML or JavaScript
OK, so what we're going to
do is we're going to make
a very basic flashcard app using React.
We're going to have a flashcard.
You can flip the card back and forth.
And we'll also have a list of
all the cards that we have,
and if we're feeling
ambitious, we might be
able to switch between
cars by clicking on them.
>> But this is, of your bare
bones, a very simple React app.
And so this is actually
not trivial to implement,
but we're going to show that, if you do
this, it's very, very easy to extend it
if other people help you with it.
So we're going to go through four steps
starting from scratch to build this.
>> OK, so the four steps, we'll
start off with the first step.
The first step is going to be
building your first component.
As I said before, a component in React
is just an HTML element on steroids.
It specifies the HTML
and some behavior, and it
will specify how people
can interact with it how
it would have internal state.
Like a button will know like how many
times it's been clicked for example,
and it will know how to lay itself out.
>> So let's go ahead and build our
first component using JavaScript.
So if the syntax looks weird,
that's because it kind of is.
So, again, we're going
to make a variable called
app using the keyword let,
which makes a variable,
let App equal React.createClass.
>> React is a library and has
the create class function.
And this function is
a bit of code that you
can use to create a new
type of React component.
And so React.createClass
makes a component,
and this component will
be able to do stuff.
The main thing it can do is render
something, render as a function.
>> Again, if this index is not obvious to
you, I recommend you go on JS for cats
and check it out.
Is that zoomed in well enough?
Cool.
>> So every component needs
to have a render function.
The render function says,
what do I print on the screen?
But the component is
useless if it doesn't
know what to print on the screen, so
you need to have a render function.
>> So in the render thing, you
just need to return some HTML.
And what's cool is that
there's a thing called
JSX, which is a extension of
JavaScript that is used by react.
It let's you write HTML inside
of your JavaScript, which
sounds kind of weird when
you first think about it,
but it makes a lot of sense afterward.
So we can do this.
If you're familiar with HTML, I know
we have a div with a general purpose
container for stuff.
We can return a div, and inside
this div, we can put stuff.
>> So let's say we want to render just
a straight-up flashcard for now.
The flashcard, I would say,
will have a question and answer.
So inside this div, let's
print out a paragraph
that says question-- What is the
ultimate answer to life, the universe?
And then the answer is
going to be, of course, 42.
>> That didn't come up well at all.
Yeah, so basically you can really
write HTML inside your JavaScript.
And this is going to be
printed out into the screen.
So let's try it out.
>> So we have our component.
We need to tell React to put
the component on the screen
so React.render, so notice that we
treat app like any other element.
We write it as it was an HTML element.
Like instead of saying like img
for image or p for paragraph,
you write App, so App is
treated like an HTML element.
As I said before, it's
an element on steroids.
>> So you render App, and you
give it a place to put it.
And this is how you can
tell it where to put it.
I have created a simple div on the
page called with an ID of page,
and that's where the
element's going to go.
>> And we're not going to run with HTML.
Basically this is going to get
put inside of this page element
that we have on the screen.
So it runs this code, and it draws this
thing on the screen, so here we are.
We have made our first React component.
>> So just as a recap, we gently made
a new type of component, right?
That's what the React.createClass.
And in that component, we
told it what it should do.
Whenever this component is to
be printed onto the screen,
it will print out the div with
the two paragraphs inside of it.
>> And what we did, we made a new app
using the angle bracket app notation.
We told it to put it
inside the page element.
And so what I did, it created
a new app from that template.
And then I told it to render it.
So it said, OK, app,
what should I print out?
App says, go print out a div
with two paragraphs inside of it.
And voila, there's our div with
two paragraphs inside of it.
Make sense so far?
>> So, again, the whole challenge of React
is just knowing how to make components.
How to make the
components work together.
Now that we've made our first
component, let's go back
and make components customizable.
So you know how in HTML you
can give your buttons classes?
You can give your anchors the href.
You can give your inputs a type, right?
You can give more custom
properties to all of your elements
to make it more interesting.
And we actually can do
the exact same thing.
>> So let's say we want our
app to go render any card.
Right now we just
rendered a hardcoded card.
We know there's only one
card it can do, so we're
going to try and change this now so
that we can just give it some card.
It'll print out the card.
>> You ought to try and make your
components a very general purpose.
So this way I could email
this my friend and be like,
whatever flashcard you have,
just feed it into here,
and it'll do it by itself.
You can put other
things in your own app.
>> But first, let's break this
up into two components,
but we want to separate the card
printing part from the actual app part.
So what we can do is we
can change this from App
to CardView, just a
new name for the app,
and we can make a new
component called App,
not to be confused with the old App.
We've got the createClass,
and like in HTML,
you can nest React components
inside of each other.
>> So in this render function,
function return CardView,
and this is the exact same thing.
See why it's the same thing?
Instead of rendering just the app that
has the div and pairing inside of it,
the app renders the CardView, and the
CardView renders the div and paragraph.
So this is our first example of
nesting elements inside of each other.
Does that make sense?
So, again, we have a CardView element.
We have app elements
that it's bigger than.
>> OK, so we want our CardView-- if you
give a good CardView a certain card,
it'll print out for you, right?
So first, we need to make a card,
so let's make a card object.
So let my card equal--
if you're all familiar,
this is just the notation-making
object in JavaScript.
It's kind of like a struct
in C, so we made a card,
and so now we can pass this card as
a property or as an attribute in HTML
terminology to our app.
So we can do this, App
card equals myCard.
>> You know how in input, you do
input type equals text or button
class equals btn for bootstrap,?
Same idea, App card equals--
you've got to put braces here--
App card equals myCard, so this
says we have this card object.
I'm going to pass it as a
property to the app component.
And this app component will
be able to access it and do
interesting stuff with it.
>> So our app is going to be
given a card, so for now,
let's have the app just give
the card to the CardView
itself because like the app is not
going to know what to do with it,
so we'll just give it to the CardView.
So we'll pass it the
same way, card equals,
and so each component can access the
things that has been given to it.
They can access the properties
that have been given to it
using this syntax, this.props.card.
>> So what happens here is
you have the myCard object.
You pass it into the app
using App card equals myCard.
That card object is given to your app.
The app can access it
as this.props.card.
It's kind of like an image
knows what it's source is.
>> This app knows what it's card
is, and it can do stuff with it.
It can do computations.
It can make decisions based off of it.
>> For now, I was going to pass
this.props.card onto the CardView.
Make sense so far?
It'll make more sense now.
>> OK, so now we're at CardView.
Our CardView, given the card, should
print out its question and answer.
Right now we just printed out some
hardcoded questions and answers.
We need to figure out-- we need
to ask the card that they gave us
what is the question and answer, and
then print this out into the screen.
>> So we can do this here.
In render begin-- first do equals.
So what we're doing here is we know that
the cards are given us to a property,
right?
It's given to us as an input.
Like it's almost like
arguments to a function.
The card is an argument
almost to this CardView.
>> We'll extract that, and put
it into the variable question.
Make sure the answer went
to the variable answer.
Prompts that card to answer.
And now that we have these,
instead of printing out that text,
we're going to print out
whatever they gave us.
>> So this stuff-- so we're going
to put out Question Answer.
Let's see if this works.
Cool, so let's step through it
one more time just to be sure.
>> So my card is card object, and we
are giving that card to the app.
And the app is going to take the
card and give it to the CardView.
And this CardView says, if you
give me any flashcard object,
I'll print out its question
and its answer, right?
>> So what I could do is I can
send this code, the first
like 10 lines of my code, to my friend.
He could embed it in
his own application.
And as long as he did the same thing,
like CardView card equals this,
as long as he created the CardView
and gave it the right information,
he could render his own card.
And so this way, it's a really
cool way for you to build
components that use each other, right?
This card, I could publish
this CardView on the internet,
and people would be able to use it.
So basically, it's like one of the
standard functions in the C library.
>> It is a function where
someone has written it.
You give a certain input.
It'll produce a certain output.
You don't care how it works internally.
As long as you give it the right
input, it'll make the right output.
>> And a component can be
thought of the same way.
This CardView is like
a library function.
If you give it some card
as a property, it'll
print out the contents of that card.
Like if I change my card to
instead be like what is 5 plus 37,
it will update accordingly.
So just by changing the input,
it gets a certain output.
So you can think of components almost
as functions in this way, which
you can put together.
You get input, like this CardView
as the input, you get output.
In this case, output is the HTML.
Make sense so far?
Cool, so again, properties are
how you can pass information
into and out of components.
>> OK, so let's make this
thing interactive.
Right now it's kind of boring.
What is [INAUDIBLE]?
You can print some out,
but that's all it can do.
>> So let's go back to the
old question just for now.
OK, so right now these components
are boring because all they do,
they get input.
They make output, right?
That's kind of boring.
We want to have our
components to be able to have
some kind of internal state,
like remember something.
>> For a flashcard, for
example, what kind of state
might you want to
remember for a flashcard?
What temporary status
might you want to remember
for a flashcard in a flashcard app?
AUDIENCE: Whether it's been flipped?
NEEL MEHTA: Yeah, right.
So you might want to keep
track of are you face up or are
you face down on the card.
On Facebook, for example, you would
want to remember where in the news feed
are you or like who's profile
are you doing right now.
>> On Messenger, like what text you
type in the input box, right?
If you refresh the page, it goes away.
But you don't really care.
It's just temporary.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
NEEL MEHTA: Like a flash
card, like you can be seeing
the question side or the answer side?
>> AUDIENCE: OK.
>> NEEL MEHTA: Like a
two-sided flashcard, right?
Yeah, so you want to
have this idea of now
I have properties, which is like inputs,
but state, which is temporary, uh,
where you are on the page, right?
Again, I said in Facebook
Messenger, I have like which person
you're viewing Facebook
or who's profile, right?
>> This is only temporary.
It's important to show the user
what's going on, but refresh the page.
It doesn't really matter.
So it's temporary state,
so we all it state.
>> So, again, there's state and props.
Props is input given
from your data source.
State is just like defaults.
It's just like stuff that
makes the thing interactive.
>> So in our CardView-- let's have
our CardView-- so it was nice.
What we're going to do here, we're going
to touch CardView and only CardView.
And so my friend who got this, they
wouldn't notice any difference.
They wouldn't have to change
any of their own code,
but they'd see their
CardView got souped up.
That's a nice part about components.
>> OK, so in our CardView, let's try and
keep track of whether we're phase up
or face down.
In React we do this by first
specifying the initial state.
Where does the card begin?
>> So be a function called getInitialState
function, and we return an object.
This object contains some state, and
a state is just a key-value pair.
Like in instruct, you have a key and a
value, you have like name is a string.
>> In this case, let's say front is true.
This says that we have a state.
One component of the state
is an attribute called front.
[INAUDIBLE], so by default,
we're in the front of the card,
and we can change this
as we flip the card.
Make sense?
>> OK, so in render, right now, we're
showing the question and the answer.
Now what we should do
is show the question
if we're on the front of the card so
the answer is for the back of the card.
That's why you all make
the card interactive.
So let's try and to this here.
Well, first just make a variable.
We can ask now this.state.front.
We access state the same we
access props, so this.state.front.
>> If we're front, then text
is this.props.card.question.
If we're on the front of the
card, we're going to try and grab
the question from the card.
Otherwise, if we're on the back
of the card, what do we do?
>> AUDIENCE: The answer?
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yep, so text
equals this.props.card.answer.
But if you notice, we're using
the state to make a decision
because now the component
will look different
based off how these interact with it.
So instead of printing out this,
we'll just print out the text.
Cool, so now, as you see,
we see only the question.
And if I change the state here manually
to front is false we get 42 back.
>> So, again, this component
has its own state.
Like a button knows whether
it's been pressed or not,
this thing knows what is on
the front or on the back.
By default, it's on the front.
And then if it's on the front,
we'll print out the question.
If it's on the back, we'll
print out the answer.
So, again, the information
given is the same.
It just looks different
based on how you program it.
So, for example, Facebook Messenger,
even if you get the same data source,
it might look different
because the state is different.
You're looking at a
different person's message.
>> OK, so this is all well and
good, but now what's actually
make us able to change, whether
our card is front or back.
We can do this by adding a flip
button, a button to the card that
will flip the card if it's [INAUDIBLE].
So let's add a button here, this
button, and this button will say flip.
>> And so right now, it
doesn't do anything.
It just looks nice.
What we can do is we can add a click
handler, onClick equals this.flip,
and we'll define flip later.
But basically, onClick
is a function that
gets called when the user clicks it.
>> So the button will know
when it's been clicked.
Went it's been clicked,
it will flip the card.
It's kind of like your
pizza delivery guy.
You're like, all right, whenever someone
calls me, I'll deliver pizza, right?
>> You register this listener.
You listen for an event.
You get called, and when the
event happens, you do something.
You get pizza.
In this case, when you're
clicked, you flip the card.
>> And so we need to define a
function that will flip the card,
so we'll write that right
here, flip function.
And so what do you think flip will do?
Again this gets called when
we click the flip button.
What should the function flip do?
>> AUDIENCE: Change this.state.front
from true to false, false to true.
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yep, so take whatever
this.front is-- the front state is.
Take the front state, if
it's true, make it false.
If it's false, make it true, right?
So let's try that.
>> You can't change state
just by doing this.state.
You can't do this.
You can't do that.
You have to use a function
called this.setState.
>> So you can say this.setState front
colon this where, again, the exclamation
point means the opposite.
I guess if this. state.front
is true, it'll turn false.
So we'll set the state
from true to false.
If it's false, we'll
set it false to true.
>> Just notice that we set and get slightly
differently, and so let's try this.
Bada bing, look at this.
The flip button will now
switch the front to back state.
>> And so here's where you see a
little bit of the magic of React.
Like we never told it it to re-render.
We never told it redraw anything.
If you're doing this
without React, you'd
have to-- like when the
flip button is clicked,
you'd have to tell it to
manually re-render, right?
>> React is really cool in that if you
give it a certain state and properties,
it will always render
the exact same thing.
And so when we ever we change
the state and the properties,
react just re-renders the whole thing.
It knows that there's a
one-to-one correspondence
between state and parameter and HTML.
So whenever either of those
changes by through a set state,
it will change how the
pay is re-rendered.
And so basically React is like
waiting for you to change.
>> Whenever it changes something,
it'll re-render the entire page.
And if it sounds inefficient,
it's because it would be,
but react uses a thing
called a Shadow DOM.
Instead of drawing the page directly, it
keeps the virtual HTML tree in memory.
>> You know, HTML is like a tree,
like a hierarchical data structure.
It keeps a fake tree in memory,
and whenever you update the page,
it'll draw another fake
tree, and it'll calculate
what change it needs to make the
page to make the two trees equal.
So basically, it virtually
re-renders a lot.
And then it only like changes the
page in little tweaks as needed,
so it's very, very, very efficient.
>> So basically React will
whenever you change something,
it'll re-render the page virtually.
It'll figure out what do I need to
change to make the real page reflect
the virtual page, and it'll do that.
That's the virtual DOM.
It's one of the biggest
features of React.
>> Does that make sense?
Any questions?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: How does
compare still to the MVC
that we talked about
before like resources.
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yeah, the question
is how does it compare to MVC?
You asked about resources.
Well, let's talk about how it functions.
>> In MVC, you'd update the model.
In this case we'd have a card model.
The view would have the
flip button, and the control
would have the flip function.
So the view would tell the
controller to flip flip.
Flip would tell the
model to change, right?
>> And so when you do an MVC, you
listen for the model to change,
and you re-render the view accordingly.
Or you just have to like
have the controller.
Wait for the model to change, and then
pick and choose a part of like a thing
to change.
Here we have one thing,
but in a big app,
you have to like remember what
the change in every single place,
so it's a little annoying.
And so React is nice
because it has a Shadow Dom.
It can afford to just
rewrite the entire thing.
You don't have to selectively
like guess what to update.
>> On Facebook if you like
get a new message, in MVC,
you'd have to remember,
OK, change the things
at the top of the
page, the message icon.
Also pop a new window at the bottom.
Also make a new thing in that window.
Also play a sound.
>> That's a lot of stuff
going out at the same time.
And so if you don't
have a Shadow Dom, you'd
have to do that manually because
you can't get rid of the whole page.
You can't afford to, so you have
to change each thing manually,
which is really annoying in MVC.
>> So in order to be
thrifty, they selectively
update the page, which is
efficient, but also annoying.
In React, because of the Shadow
Dom, you get both things for free.
It's efficient because
of the Shadow Dom.
The bottleneck is updating the page.
It's not doing the tree manipulation.
You get the efficiency.
You also get the ease of use because
if you just rewrite the entire page,
but you just know, all right, the things
are going to be on the page somewhere.
It might be in a different place, but
it's going to be on the page, right?
So you just re-rendered
the entire thing virtually,
and you might make a couple
changes to the page itself.
>> So, again, in MVC you
would have to choose
between ease of use and efficiency,
and React, you get both.
So it's better.
Make sense?
Solid.
>> OK, so let's see let's talk
a little bit about step 4,
how we can embed components.
So we have this right now.
We have our cool little button.
We can flip it back and
forth, and that's all it does.
Let's say we want to
have another component.
Let's say our flashcard app should
contain a list of all the cards
that you have, so that means we
should have another component.
Well, maybe call it a list view.
Let's make a list view that
coexists with the CardView,
and this list view and CardView
will like work together.
And you can combine them
to make our app for you.
>> So first, let's make a
couple more cards right.
Let's say, what cards?
And just so I don't have to
bore you with typing it in,
I'm just going to copy it from here.
And so I'm going to not
give it just one card.
I'm going to give it an array of cards.
So first the apps
going to break for now.
All right, so we're going to make
this able to handle multiple cards.
So first, we're going to give it, not
just one card but an array of cards,
like a list of cards.
And in this case, we have three of them.
>> All right, so so app is
going to get a list cards,
and it's going to decide which
one to show to the CardView.
The CardView can only
render one card, but the app
gets a list of all the cards, right?
>> So when you figure out one
card to give to CardView,
how would you guess you might be able
to make a decision about which card
to show?
To give you a hint, it's temporarily
You'll be viewing a certain card.
If you refresh the page, you'll
just go back to the first card.
That's OK because it's temporary.
What technique might we use?
>> AUDIENCE: You could make a variable
so just like you had front.
Is this true, you could
have current card equals 1?
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yeah, so we
want to have state, right?
You would use state in the
component to figure out
which card do we want to get.
Like we have a list of
all the cards, we'll
use state to figure out
one of the first card,
second card, third card, and so on.
>> So an app so an app will get a
have the getInitialState function,
getInitialState function return.
And we'll just say activeIndex 0.
So now our app has it's own state.
>> And so now on render, to figure out
a card, let's just go to the array
and grab the thing at that index.
Select card equal this.props.cards
this.state.activeIndex.
So as you see here, the props and
the state actually work together.
So now that we have our activeCard,
we'll call it activeCard,
and let's see if this works.
[INAUDIBLE]
>> Oh, that was a text error.
Ah.
>> Cool, yep, so now we were back
to where we were before, right?
Same old program except
now we can support
a list of cards, not just one card.
And now, again, if we change the
activeIndex, we can go from 0 to 1,
and now that second card,
and then we went to 0.
So here's a new
souped-up version of our.
>> OK, so now let's have a list view that
shows all the cards in your program,
so we'll make a new
component called listView.
Let listView equals react.createClass.
So we want to render an unordered
list with a list item for every card.
And so we have a bunch of cards.
We want one list item
for every card, right?
We could do a for loop or
something to make a new list item.
But the way you do it in
React, use a thing called map.
Map is a tool or a function you use
that for every item, runs some function,
takes return value, and
gives you that back.
>> So as an example, we have the array
1, 2, 3.map function-- and this
is shorthand for a
function-- x arrow x times x.
This says, for every number
in 1, 2, 3 , take it.
Square it, and give it back.
So what do you think 1,
2, 3.map x goes to x times
x gives you back given
that this function is
run on every element of that array.
>> AUDIENCE: 1, 4 9?
>> NEEL MEHTA: Yep, 1, 4, 9
because you do 1 times 1.
That gives you one.
That's the first element.
>> 2 times 2 is 4.
That's a second element.
3 times 3 is 9.
That's a third element.
Make sense?
So map has a technique you
use in functional programmers,
the new style of
programming to do something
to every element in your list.
And so this sounds familiar.
We have a list of cards.
We want to get a list item for every
one, so we'll just use map here.
We'll say, let list equals
this.props,cards,map.
>> And so given a card, we're
going to generate a list item
with that card's contents side of it.
Let's just say we want to give out
the cards question so card.question.
So this list contains an
array of LI's or List Items
where there's one list
item for every card,
and that contains the cards question.
Make sense?
>> Cool, so now let's
actually print that out.
So we will return a ul.
Inside that unordered list,
we'll just stick the entire list
that they gave us.
Cool.
>> All right, so now this
list view works just find.
Any questions about the list view?
You have a bunch of cards.
You make a list item for every card.
And you put them inside an unordered
list, and you give it back.
So now let's act so we embed
this inside of our app,
so we can do this, list view.
What argument do we pass to list view?
What properties do we give it?
Remember, if you give
it a bunch of cards,
it'll make the list
view for those cards.
So what would we pass
here as the argument?
AUDIENCE: A list of cards?
NEEL MEHTA: Yeah, so cards
equals this.props.cards, right?
And so the only problem
is that you can only
turned one top level element in render,
so you've got to wrap it in a div.
It's weird.
So let's see if that.
Does that work?
>> Yep, there you go.
So now we have a list
of cards at the bottom,
and then we have our
CardView itself on top,
and that will flip between
the two sides of the card.
Now does that make sense how I did that?
Yeah, so again, we have two components.
The first component prints
out every card in the list.
That's the list view.
And the second component
prints out just that card.
If you give it a certain card, it'll
print out information about that card
and let you flip back and forth.
>> So if we want, we can try and talk
about adding some new features to this.
Otherwise we can talk a bit more
about of the velocity of reactor,
or we can answer
questions you might have
because these are all of the core parts
of react that I want to talk about.
We can go ahead.
We can answer questions.
Whatever you want.
>> AUDIENCE: Can you use
JSX in normal JavaScript?
Or is that something that
came with the [INAUDIBLE]?
>> NEEL MEHTA: The question is can
you use JSX with normal JavaScript?
The answer is yes.
JSX is just a way of it takes your
JavaScript that has HTML inside of it,
and it compiles into JavaScript that
does not have HTML inside of it.
So notice that-- so notice here.
This looks like you have like div
and you have stuff inside of it.
>> That compiles to JavaScript that
like generates the same thing.
I guess what I'm saying is that
JSX is just a syntactic, like it's
a preprocessor for JavaScript much
like PHP is a preprocessor for HTML.
JSC is a preprocessor
for JavaScript that lets
you put HTML inside of your JavaScript.
And so if you have the right transformer
which is a thing called [INAUDIBLE],
which will transform.
The right preprocessor,
it'll let you do that.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
NEEL MEHTA: Usually you don't need
to put HTML inside of JavaScript
unless your doing React.
But you can do it anyway.
Yep?
>> AUDIENCE: I think you
had described React
as a functional programing language.
We've been learning C in CS50.
Is C also a functional language?
NEEL MEHTA: So the question
is about functional
versus another thing called
imperative or procedural programming.
There's two kinds of programs popular.
One's called procedural, which
is all about like doing commands,
and one is functional, which is all
about having functions and having
input and output of those.
React is a functional paradigm.
C is a very procedural paradigm.
>> And as an example, C for example,
you don't do this declarative way
of making the program, right?
You have to say, print this.
Change this data structure.
Print this.
It's all about commands.
>> In React, there's not
that many commands.
It's all about having
components you put together.
They're like functions.
You have like a function
called CardView,
which is a function
that has input, output,
and so React is all
about this philosophy
us of having-- you have data.
You pass it through this
algorithm, and it'll
output HTML that you
just printed the page,
and so you have to
build it piece by piece.
>> So to draw a metaphor to what
I said before, you know how
on Facebook if you get a message,
and you choose what parts to update,
that's procedural.
It's imperative, right?
OK, I got a message.
Let's change account there.
>> Let's pop a window here.
Let's draw this here.
That's a procedural approach.
>> That's what things like Angular,
Boost, Backbone, other frameworks use.
React is functional.
It's a very different way
of thinking about things.
It takes this idea of let's have
functions or algorithms that will you
give it data.
It'll spit out what it
should be, and the computer
will take care of weighing out.
You don't handle it yourself.
Does that make a little bit of sense?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: In a functional language,
everything happens at once?
>> NEEL MEHTA: No, things happen in order.
Like here there's still
order, but it doesn't
happen in order of like
commend, command, command.
It happens in order of
function gives you output.
Put that into another function.
Put that into another
function, another function.
>> If you do CS51, you'll
learn functional programs
a little out of the scope of this.
But basically, what makes
React cool is not only
the one-way data flow
and the virtual Dom,
but also this idea of
functional programming.
And functional programming is very easy
to compose and make cool stuff out of,
and it's very easy to think
about and reason about.
So it's another good draw of React.
Any more questions?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Um, why would you
use let as opposed to var?
>> NEEL MEHTA: So the question is
why do you use let instead of var?
This is a thing called
ES6 or ECMAScript 6.
It's the new version of JavaScript.
There's a bunch of technical reasons,
but let is a better version of var.
>> It's how you declare variables.
You can use let.
You can use var.
Let has a bunch of technical
reasons-- you can look them
up later-- for why it's better.
Basically, ES6 has some nice
new syntax, some new features
on top of the old JavaScript.
>> So we have like five minutes.
I just wanted to talk about
one more thing real fast.
If you had any questions,
let's talk about it after this.
But just so this gets
caught on camera, I just
want to talk a bit about how you
actually use React in your apps.
>> If you go here,
Facebook.GitHub.IO/react,
this is the home page for React, and
it'll show you how you actually use
React in your pages.
Basically, it's a little
complicated trying to install React.
It's not as easy as you just drag
and drop a JavaScript in there.
>> You have to have your transformer
set up, which will, as it did before,
turn your JSX into
the normal JavaScript.
You have to thing that'll
compile you ES6 to normal.
JavaScript there's a lot of moving
parts you have to do, so there's a thing
called Yeoman, Yeoman.io.
And this is a command line tool that'll
help you scaffold out your React
projects easily.
>> So you can read about this
later, but there are some tools
that Yeoman offers.
They'll let you create a React
app with everything built in.
Like it'll have built
in, components built in.
It'll have your transformer built in.
They have a lot of cool
stuff built in automatically
using these things called generators.
>> So read about this if you like.
Just go on Yeoman, Y-E-O-M-A-N, and
you can find generators like these.
And with generators like
these, you just like one
is a couple command line commands.
It'll scaffold out an
entire React app for you.
It'll get all the manual piping,
and grunt work done for you,
and this is why you just focus
on just writing in React.
>> So basically building a
React app is nontrivial.
It's wired all together, but there
are tools that'll do it for you.
So if you want to make a React
app, try doing it that way.
If you just want to experiment,
you can try using this CodePen
because this CodePen has
all the react wiring.
I've done all the work for you already.
>> So if you want to make like a
production to release React app,
try one of these generators.
If you just want to play
around, it's often worth just
like try playing around on CodePen here.
Sound good?
Cool.
>> So that's all I have.
Again, all the code and examples are
going to be on this website here.
So, again, we didn't talk
about much syntax of React,
but to find all those
little syntactical details,
it's all going to be available
on this website here.
>> So I'd recommend like
take the first step.
Put it into your CodePen.
Try working on making
it to the second step.
There's a fourth step, and just
see where you get from that.
>> Any more questions, check
out that page or email me.
That's my email.
But I'd love to help you with any
questions you might have about React.
So, yep, that's all I have.
Thank you all very much for
watching or for attending.
And I'll take any questions
you might have after this now.
So thank you all for watching.