>> SPEAKER 1: All right, so what
is it you concretely need to do?
Well, turns out there's
just four functions
that you need to implement
whose functionality is
integral to the proper
operation of the web server,
but all of whose
behavior is very narrowly
defined, so that they only
do pretty much one thing.
First thing you're going
to need to do is implement,
per the specification,
the LOOKUP function.
This is a fairly simple function in
the end, that takes as an argument
whatever the path to the file
that the user wants to request,
and you need to respond with the
so-called MIME type, or Content-type,
of that file.
For instance, if it's
a file like, hello dot
HTML you're going to respond with a MIME
type of quote unquote text slash HTML.
>> Or if it's an image, you might want
to respond with image dot slash
JIFF or image slash JPEG.
See the specification for the various
file formats you need to detect.
But it really boils down to taking a
look at the path, that you are past,
and looking at its file
extension, the last few characters
after the trailing period or dot.
So we'll leave it to you with some
of the hints in the specification
to figure out exactly how to find
that dot and the file extension
so that you can do the
mapping from one to the other.
>> Next up is the parse function.
So this one's a little
more involved, in that
you need to take in that
argument [INAUDIBLE],
it's iterated over it, character
for character, or string by string,
in order to make sure
that it meets exactly
the formal definition of that first
request line, as per the specification.
And you need to load into absolute
path that substring, that represents
something like, slash hello dot HTML.
Meanwhile, optionally, after that
path might be a question mark
and then a query string
like, q equals cats,
or q equals cats ampersand, and
then another key value pair.
So you're going to need to
step over those characters,
as well, up until the
first space, in order
to create a string that stores
inside of it the query string itself.
Next, you're going to
implement the load function.
So it turns out, if you look through
the source code, as the spec directs,
the load function is used in two places.
It's either used to load the
output from the PHP Interpreter.
And we wrote all of
the PHP handling code,
but it does need to
use a function called
load, that essentially reads all of the
bytes of output from PHP's Interpreter
into a big array.
>> That same function load
is also used to load
into memory all of the bytes from a file
like, a JIFF, or a JPEG, or dot HTML
file, that the user has requested.
So you will need to use some tricks and
tools from problem set 4 in file IO,
but you should find that relatively
familiar and in a nice way, hopefully,
of tying together the newer web
stuff with the older file IO stuff.
>> Finally, in the indexes
function, all you need to do
is to decide whether or not there
exists some file effectively
called index dot HTML, or index dot PHP,
inside of the directory, whose path you
are past.
The upside of this means that if
the user does request a directory,
we're not just going to show him or
her the contents of that directory,
we'll literally show them index dot
HTML, or index dot PHP, by default.
But it's going to be left to you to
figure out, using some of the hints
in the source code, that
we've already given you,
how you can actually check
whether a certain file exists
in the current directory, so that
you can return the correct response.
>> So in the end there's
relatively few bytes
that you need to take out of the
problem set to implement the server's
incomplete functionality.
But definitely make sure you wrap
your mind around as much of the code
as you can, taking
comfort in that you don't
need to understand all of the
lowest level networking code, all
of the lowest level file IO code.
Really, what we're doing
with this problem set
is synthesizing the past several problem
sets, introducing a bit of WebLogic,
and networking concepts,
so that ultimately you
build something that's really quite
interesting, really quite powerful,
but still using the
same building blocks,
that we've been using for some time.