>> DAVID MALAN: Now let's take a
look at the actual distribution
code in the file called server.c.
Now keep in mind that this
file's pretty large this week.
It's over 1,000 lines of code but
most of those lines we have written.
And what we've left is
a few blanks that you'll
need to fill in to add some of the most
compelling features of the web server
to actually get it started.
Indeed, if you run the distribution
code after compiling it
you'll find that the web server
doesn't do all that much.
Instead the user gets a 501,
not implemented, error message.
But that should make sense because
we've indeed not implemented
all of its functionality.
So let's take a look at server.c.
And you'll want to go over
this in a little more detail,
a little more slowly, at your own pace.
But for now let me try to guide
you through it to give you
a sense of what's useful to
know, what's less useful to know,
so that you can guide
your own exploration.
So at the top of server.c, of course,
we have a whole bunch of defines.
As well as a whole bunch of includes.
Worth noting is that we have
a few global constants here,
which we use in our code to make
sure that certain arrays are
of sufficient length.
Based on how long the HTTP requests we
expect to be receiving, potentially,
from web clients, or browsers.
>> Meanwhile, let's scroll on down
here, to one type definition.
Notice that just like in P set 4,
whereby we played with file I/O,
similarly here, we're
playing with a lot of bytes.
And so we've typedeffed
char to be a byte.
In other words, the data type, capital
B-y-t-e, doesn't exist by default in C.
So we've created it as a synonym for
char so that we have some 8-bit value
with which to work.
Now there's a whole bunch of
prototypes here, a few of which
are for functions you'll write, but
most of them we've written ourselves.
Let's scroll down now to finally,
just a few global variables.
One is this char star, AKA root.
Indeed, you'll notice we're not
using the CS50 library anymore.
So we're instead just using char star.
And root is going to be a
pointer to the string that
represents the root of the server.
So, for instance, when I
ran the command earlier
and specified the root of "public," that
directory inside of the distribution
code.
Root, here, would be a pointer
to exactly that string, "public."
Or really the full path /home/ubuntu/
so forth to that public directory.
>> Meanwhile, in line 67 here, we have
what are called file descriptors.
These are similar in spirit
to file star pointers.
But it turns out there's
another set of functions
you can use with reading files or
reading from network connections.
Like a web server web
browser connection that
actually just uses integers instead
of pointers, like we saw on P set 4.
But it's the same idea.
And I've made these global to keep
track of a client file descriptor.
Like a pointer to my web client.
And a server file descriptor.
Sort of a pointer to the web server,
but they're not actually pointers,
they're just numbers.
>> Finally, we have this global
variable here called signaled.
Which is my way, true
or false, of keeping
track of whether the user has
signaled that he or she wants
to stop the web server.
And indeed there's a function
that listens for Control C.
So that if you, the user, want to
kill the server by hitting Control C,
that boolean variable you'll
see in the code is set to true.
And then within a loop we keep
checking the value of that variable.
And if it's true, we just
quit the program altogether.
>> Let's now take a look at main.
You don't need to understand
everything in main,
but let's give you a sense
of the overall workflow.
And then take a closer look
yourself at some of the comments.
In the first place,
part way through main,
we parse the command line arguments.
It turns out that main is
going to expect either dash
h for help, which just tells you how
to run the program very succinctly.
Or dash p, which lets
you specify a port.
But again, using the
port 80 80, by default,
is what you should use CS 50 IDE.
>> Next, we just do some error checking.
Making sure that the
port value is indeed
as we expect, within a particular range.
And then some of the magic starts.
We call this function
start, which we wrote.
We pass into with the port, as
well as any optional arguments
in order to start the server.
Specifically, that port number.
>> All right, next, this is fairly cryptic
code that you won't see too often,
but it's a fancy way of telling
the program to listen for a signal.
A signal being something like a
special key stroke, like Control C.
So this code here is how we register
what's called an event listener.
Whereby, anytime the user hits
Control C that code tells the computer
to run a function called handler.
Which is written lower down, implemented
lower down in this file, server.c,
that stops the program altogether.
But no need to worry about
the inner details there.
>> Let's now focus on the inner loop.
Indeed, what the web server is doing
is deliberately looping infinitely.
Because after all that's pretty much
what you want a web server to do.
Until you explicitly
stop it, you just want
to be sitting there
effectively in a loop,
waiting for someone on the
internet to connect to it.
So that the web server can
then respond to some request.
>> Now notice at the top
of the program I free
some variables, because later on you'll
see we're using malloc in some places.
So I just want to make
sure all of my variables
are initialized to some known values.
Down here I check whether the
program has been signaled.
In other words, if the user hit Control
C, let's just quit out of this loop
by calling stop.
>> And then now this code gets
a little more interesting.
But notice that you don't have
to write anything in main.
Rather, inside of main
we do the following.
If the user has connected--
this is a function we wrote,
that returns true or false.
And every time it's called
it just says, yes, a client,
a browser has connected to the server.
Or, no, it has not.
And in this way can we just
loop infinitely waiting for true
to be returned by that function.
>> Meanwhile, this next function,
request, we also wrote for you.
This takes whatever is inside of that
virtual envelope, the so-called HTTP
request, and actually
parses it so to speak.
Looking at it top to bottom,
left to right, and loads
all of those initial lines.
Like the get line and
anything else below it,
into a variable that
we've called message.
For an HTTP message.
And we've also loaded
its length into length.
Now this is a bit different.
So let's take a quick look at this.
Even though you don't
have to implement request,
it's helpful, perhaps, to
understand how it works.
This function request apparently
is taking in two arguments, message
and length.
But notice that I'm passing in an
ampersand to both message and length.
But if we scroll up, what
are message and length?
>> Well notice that message and
length are declared inside
of main to be a char star.
And a size t.
Which is really just
an int, respectively.
So what's curious here, though,
is that if message is a char star
but I'm passing in ampersand of
message, that's kind of like tech
getting the address of a pointer.
A double pointer, if you will.
>> And in fact, if I scroll on down.
Way down into this file, where
request is actually implemented,
I'm going to see the following
signature, or prototype,
for this function.
Which you've probably not seen before.
The request function returns a bool.
That's probably familiar.
But notice its first argument.
It's called message, but I
could've called it anything here.
But it's char star star.
>> And this is kind of a neat thing.
Because I want this function
request to allocate memory
for however big the HTTP request
is in that virtual envelope
that it receives from the browser, I
want to be able to return a string.
But I also want to be
able to return a length.
So as you'll see in the
specification, C, of course,
cannot return multiple values.
And in fact I'm only
returning a bool here.
But just like we saw in
lecture a while back you
can return two values if you
pass in two values by reference.
Or by pointer.
So that you can actually go to
those addresses, put values there,
and effectively via this
back channel, so to speak,
can a function return
multiple values to the caller.
>> In this case, request
can return three values.
Its actual return type, a bool.
The message, a char star star.
And length, a size t.
Which is just an int.
Because this function request
can go to the address length
and put a value there.
And it can go to the address of
message and put a value there.
And that now should make sense.
>> Because even though message is
a char star star, as soon as
you go there with star message,
as we've seen before in code,
what are you going to find?
You're going to find waiting for
you there, a chunk of memory that
should be a char star.
Or the address of a string.
And it's OK if you don't quite wrap
your mind around that too quickly.
But consider that all we're doing
is taking the address of a pointer
so that we can go there and
actually put a pointer there.
But not to worry if that
doesn't quite sink in just now.
Know for now that the
request function effectively
provides you with those three values.
>> So let's now go back to main.
What's going on next, in
main, is the following.
Once I have gotten inside of message
and length, the two values I care about.
Then we go ahead and write
some code for you that
allows you to read just the first line.
The so-called request
line from the request.
Specifically, something like
get/HTTP 1.1, and nothing more.
So there's a whole bunch of
other HTTP headers, recall,
that a browser sends from
a client to a server.
We're just ignoring all those so that
all you see on the terminal window,
recall, is just something
like, get/hello.HTML HTP/1.1.
>> So notice though, that these
tricks we're doing here
are going to be useful, perhaps,
in your own parse function which
you will implement.
Notice how that I'm just
declaring a variable.
Happens to be const, which means,
I promise not to change this.
Called haystack.
Then I cleverly named
my next variable needle,
so that I can proverbially look
for a needle in a haystack,
using a super handy
function called str str.
S-T-R S-T-R, which per its man
page, or per reference.CS50.NET,
allows you to search for
one string in another.
And this is my way of
searching for the end of a line
so that I can actually read
just one line into memory.
>> Meanwhile, notice on
line 176 here, I actually
allocate enough memory for that line.
And then using str and copy, and
using just a ray bracket notation,
do I store in that array?
Exactly that first line.
In fact, let me just jump over quickly
to the specification for problem set
six.
Do read through this in detail.
But what you will find is
this particular line here.
Whereby based on the specification
the formal definition
HTTP we specify what the very first
line should be from any browser
to a server inside of that
so-called virtual envelope.
>> Specifically, the browser should
mention a method, like a get,
or post, or the like.
Then literally a space,
represented here with just sp
so that it's explicit that
we really want a space here.
Then request target which will
be something like /hello.HTML.
Followed by another space.
Followed by a version.
Which would be something like HTTP/1.1.
Followed by C-R-L-F. Which is an
acronym you're going to see a lot
in the specification.
And this is just a fancy way of
saying backslash r, backslash n.
In other words, carriage
return, new line.
Or line feed.
Carriage return, line feed.
That's what C-R-L-F means.
>> Now, meanwhile, if we
go back to our code,
let's see what remains for you to do.
Inside of main, finally, there's
a call to a parse function.
The purpose of parse is to take that
very first line, whose definition we
just saw on the specification, and
extract the so-called absolute path
and query.
Now take a look at the spec
for what we mean by that.
>> But in the long story short,
this thing here, request target,
is a string that can be
broken up into two parts.
Or an absolute path like /hello.HTML.
Followed by an optional question mark.
And then something like q
equals cats, or q equals dogs,
or any number of key value
pairs that we saw in lecture
being part of the parameterization
of an HTTP request.
>> So what you're going to need
to do is implement parse.
And figure out how to iterate over
line, which is just the first argument
that we're passing in.
Character for character for character.
Only going up to the end of that string.
Looking for that absolute path
and looking for that query.
And what's nice about the fact that
we've given you in the documentation
this grammatical definition
of that first line,
here you're going to have to figure
out, well, what is the method.
Is valid or not?
And we tell you in the spec
when it is or isn't valid.
Get, for instance, will be valid.
Space will be easy to check for.
Just using week two style or problem
set two style string checking.
Or character checking.
>> Request target is the thing
you're going to want to parse.
So take a look at the spec
for what's expected there.
And then lastly, HTTP
version, you just want
to make sure it's among the
supported versions like HTTP 1.1.
So essentially a parse function's
going to be an opportunity
to just read this thing character
for character for character,
or string by string, making sure
that it matches this specification.
All right, back to main.
Let's see what remains.
So suppose you've now
implemented your parse function.
We've parsed out from it the
so-called absolute path and the query,
what does main now have to do with this?
Well, one, you'll see
in the code that we URL
decoded in case the browser has
encoded certain special characters
and special way, we go
ahead and convert those back
to the appropriate Ascii characters.
>> Then we go ahead and figure out if
the user has requested /hello.HTML,
what file do they really mean?
In other words, we need to
take the root of the server,
that path to the public directory, and
concatenate it with something like,
hello.HTML.
So that we have one bigger
string that leads us exactly
to the actual hello.HTML file on
CS50 IDEs hard drive, or disk.
>> Next, we check that the
path actually exists.
Otherwise we throw a
404 error for the user.
And, in fact, throughout
our code you'll see
a lot of uses of this error
function which we ourselves wrote,
and the specification walks you through.
This is just a way of returning
something other than 200 to the user.
>> Now down here, I go ahead and
figure out is what the user
has requested a file, or a directory.
Because if it's a directory, I
want to do a couple of things.
One, if the user visits a
URL that is for a directory,
but does not end in a slash,
for conventional reasons,
I want to make sure that we change
the URL to actually end in a slash.
And so you'll see in the source
code that we've given you,
we force the user to redirect to not
[? fu ?] but [? fu/, ?] if they've done
that.
And see the specification accordingly.
>> Meanwhile, we check one other thing.
If the user has visited a
directory and that directory
contains a file called index.html
or index.PHP, by human convention
we don't want to show them the
contents of that directory.
We want to show them the contents
of that default file, index.HTML,
or index.php.
And so the code I've
highlighted here calls
a function called indexes
that simply checks,
does there exist a file in here
called index.html, or index.php.
>> Otherwise, if none of
those conditions apply
we simply call function
list, which we wrote,
which literally lists the
contents of a directory.
All right, and what if the request
that the user's browser has made
is not for a directory, but for a file?
Well, first we call a lookup function.
Which is going to tell the
server, is this a JPEG, is this
an HTML file, is this a
GIF, or some other format.
If so, it's then going to
check, well, is it a PHP file.
If so, we want to call a function
called interpret, that we wrote,
that interprets that PHP file
and spits out the results.
Or, more compellingly,
if it's anything else,
let's go ahead and
just transfer the file.
Like the GIF or the JPEG
from the server to the user,
as though they requested an HTML page,
image, or any number of other things.
>> Finally, if nothing else seems to
work, we're just going to say 501.
Which is that 501, not implemented
message, meaning the server
is not yet complete.