>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
ROBERT KRABEK: Hello, guys.
My name is Robert Krabek, and
I will be teaching you guys
how to scrape the web with
Nokogiri, which is a Ruby library,
and Kimono, which is a Chrome extension.
>> So first there's a
couple things that you
can do if maybe you've been
doing all the psets so far
and your workspace is
getting a little full.
We can actually just go and
create a new workspace for you
to just do a brand new project in.
So if you do want to continue
working in the CS50 template ID
that you currently have,
feel free, and you can just
install Nokogiri with CFLAGS
equals-- gem install nokogiri.
But otherwise I'll show you
how to set a new one up.
And then this is essentially
dropping more training wheels.
And you're coding as if you were
just coding in Sublime or something.
So if we shift it over.
>> So say this is your current CS 50 ID.
You can just go to Cloud9 here.
You can go to your dashboard.
It should bring up Workspaces tab.
And then you can just click
here, Create a New Workspace.
Name your new workspace,
maybe test, or scraping.
And then click this custom tab here,
instead of the CS50 templates tab.
And then you can just go
and create a new workspace.
>> I've already created a workspace here.
So we'll be working with this.
And if you created a new
workspace so with the Custom tab,
you can just type gem install
nokogiri, which is not going here.
OK, it's a little frozen.
But you can type gem install nokogiri.
And that should be all that
there is to the installation.
>> As I said before, if you're still
working in your CS50 template ID,
you just need to type CFLAGS
equals gem install nokogiri.
And I've already installed
it here so I won't do that.
But for those following
along, feel free to do so.
>> So once you've got your Nokogiri
workspace or library installed,
I'm going to give you a little bit
of a crash course in Ruby syntax
because Nokogiri is a Ruby library.
So you'll need to know some basic
Ruby syntax for working with Nokogiri.
So some basic differences
from what you're used to
perhaps if you've been working
so far in just C and PHP,
you declare variables with no type.
You don't use semicolons,
which is kind of a relief.
There's no parentheses now around
for or while loops, for example.
You just have a block of code, and
then you put end at the end of that.
There's no plus plus
or minus minus, so just
know that for when
you're doing for loops,
just plus equals and minus equals.
And instead of hash include,
you'll use require and then
whatever library trying
to load into your program.
>> Ruby isn't a compiled language.
So that's another relief.
It's more similar to PHP where
it's an interpreted language.
You can run any Ruby script that
you write with Ruby followed
by the name of your script or program.
To signify that it's a Ruby program,
you just end it with .rb instead of .c.
And there are variable
sized arrays in Ruby,
which is super convenient when you're
scraping and perhaps want to append
data that you've scraped into an array.
You don't have to malloc a new array and
copy the old array into the new array.
You can just append with
the two arrow signs.
And there are no chars, there
just single letter strings.
So that should be a little easier.
>> So we'll just give you some
examples of some basic Ruby syntax.
So here you can see that instead of
the slash slash, to comment in Ruby,
you just use the pound sign.
And variable declaration, you
just type the variable equals
whatever you want the variable to be.
They can be strings.
You can have array, which
you populate with values.
puts and prints are similar.
For our purposes, the
only difference is really
that puts, which stands for
puts, just puts a new line
character at whatever you're printing.
>> So if we give a small
demonstration here,
we can run this with--
open a new terminal.
You can see all of these
files that are in my terminal.
And if I just run
Ruby, ruby intro.rb, it
puts out five Hello
Mather, Quincy, Carrier.
Adams.
So that's all there is
to declaring arrays.
AUDIENCE: Robert, can you make
your font a little bigger?
ROBERT KRABEK: Yes.
And I can zoom in because you can't
zoom in to terminal fonts apparently.
>> So that's how you print
variables to your terminal.
You can also use
variables inside a string.
So recently in PHP,
you might have learned
that there is string interpolation.
So if you take a look here, if I
declare three variables, name, library,
and language, and I puts, I
write a string, hello my name is.
And then instead of the PHP
version of string interpolation
which looks a little more like this,
you have a pound sign, and then
a curly brace, and then
the name of the variable.
And that's how you'd print, say,
whatever the variable name is.
>> And then you can also
concatenate strings.
Ruby makes it super
easy with the plus sign.
You just have one string
on the left plus a variable
or another string plus a string.
So if I print this out, it should
just say Hello, my name is Robert.
I will be teaching you nokogiri in Ruby.
>> And let's just confirm that that
is indeed the case-- ruby intro.
Hello, my name is Robert.
I will be teaching you nokogiri in Ruby.
>> Moving on, if else statements,
it's a little different
from what you might be used to
if you've been working in C.
You don't need the parentheses.
You don't need the curly braces.
And instead of else if,
it's a concatenated elsif.
So in here, if I've declared x up
here, as we can see, x is still 5.
So if x is less than 3, it'll put small.
If it's less than 7, medium, else large.
So 5 is a medium number.
And I end this block of code with end.
>> Here is my for loop.
And this syntax is also
slightly different.
The 0 to five just essentially
is declaring an arrays of 0 to 5.
So there's five slots in the array.
And then for each slot in that
array, I will be incrementing i.
So this should print 0 to 5, or 0 to 4.
And this should print medium.
>> And I'll just blaze through.
You guys will have access
to this code later on.
So you guys can run this yourselves.
>> So this is your basic while loop.
This will just be printing j,
incrementing by 1 until we hit 5.
>> Super quick Ruby crash course
on how to write a function.
Instead of, say, int factorial
number, we just have def.
And essentially you're
defining a function here.
This is going to be the
name of the function,
and this is any variables that you
want to pass into the function.
You can have if statements within.
You can return.
In this case, we're
defining a recursively
implemented factorial function.
So we just call functions
in Ruby like this.
>> So if I've defined this, I
can call factorial, pass in 3,
and then 3 will be the number variable
that I can use within the function.
And this to_s is just turning the
return value of factorial into a string.
Otherwise this will throw
an error saying oh, I
can't print a string--
because as you remember,
puts is put string-- because this
factorial has returned a number.
So we can convert that
to a string like such.
And conversely, you can also convert
a string to an integer with to_i.
>> So making everything super simple,
if I just comment this out, save
and run the factorial function.
We should be able to see
that factorial of 3 is 6.
And that is indeed true.
>> So that's your crash course in Ruby.
And now that you know Ruby, we can go on
to the basic Nokogiri scraping set up.
Essentially all you have to do is,
in Ruby, require the libraries.
And for our purposes we'll be using the
library OpenURI as well as Nokogiri.
And then what you do-- and it'll
give you the syntax for this--
is you open the URL much as you would in
a cURL request, which stands for C URL.
>> So you take the URL of
the website in question.
You store it in a variable.
And then you can search through that
variable for unique HTML tags using
the .css command.
And then you can output the
content to wherever you want.
You can start in a database.
You can output in a file, or
even just print it to the screen.
>> So we'll show you a basic scraper.
So up here you can see we have
requiring nokogiri, require open-uri.
Your basic set up, let's
call it document or doc,
equals Nokogiri::HTML open, which is the
command provided to us by the OpenURI
library.
And we'll be searching, for those of
you who might be living in the quad,
for bikes that are in Boston listed
on the Boston Craigslist bike section
site.
>> So if you are unfamiliar
with cURL, I'll just
show you real quick what cURL will do.
If I wanted to get all of the URL from
the Craigslist site, if I type curl,
it just dumps all of the URL
from the Craigslist bicycle site
onto my terminal.
That's not particularly
useful because I don't
want to manually go through and
find the thing I'm looking for.
But just so you can
see that I'm actually
using the right code, if you look
at the URL for Craigslist in bikes--
for some reason it's not found.
If you look at this page
and you look at the URL,
this should be identical to the
cURL request that I just send.
And indeed, that's what's being
stored in the doc variable.
>> So when you go back to our code, we
can then operate on this doc variable
by using .css.
So say I wanted to get all of
the tags that are span.txt,
and all the a tags within that tag.
And why might we want to
do this, I hear you cry?
>> If we Inspect Element, it gives you a
breakdown of how the URL is structured.
If I scroll down through
here, you can see
what each of these different
elements represents.
So maybe I want to access
this particular element.
So I'm using Chrome developer
tools to Inspect Element.
I can see down here that this
is an a tag within a span
tag with a class of txt.
>> So this gets to our
first operation which
is doc.css span, which is the tag that
I'm looking for within all this URL.
And then .txt operates much like CSS
does when you're just writing CSS
in your HTML files by
specifying a class.
So this particular operator will
specify a span tag with class of txt.
And then if I leave a space,
this will then go within that tag
and then find an a tag within that.
>> So if I just put this to
the terminal, I should
be able to see essentially everything
that is within this span of class txt.
So we'll give that a go.
ruby craigslist-scraper.
And indeed that gives us all of these
tags of the various listings that
are on the Craigslist page.
>> So if we go back, we can turn this
into something a little more useful.
Maybe we want just the links.
Because within this tag, I'll also
have the hyperlink of the path
that this page goes to.
So if you look at this code here,
what I'll do is instead of .css,
I can go at_css.
And this will just get the first
element of all of those things.
So if I were to do that up in the
code I just previously demonstrated,
instead of returning all
of this, it would just
return the first one of those.
So that's how the at_css operator works.
>> So we want to store the
path all of the first a tag.
And because a will give us a--
so we're still going to use .css.
But because this is going to give
us back an entire array of tags,
we are going to access
the first element.
So this is another way that you can
access any particular element if you
have an array of elements
that is returned,
because you can treat anything that
.css returns as an array, essentially.
And then we're going to access the
hypertext reference attribute of this.
>> So if you take a look, if
you looked really close here,
if you just essentially
look at the URL bar,
this is the path that
you're going to be scraping.
So if we just run this again,
and make sure we've saved it.
You can check at home.
This actually matches up with this link.
>> So why might we want to use this?
If you want to scrape
the page and it has
a page of links like
Craigslist does, you
might want to go then
into each of those links
and then scrape the
content of that, which
is exactly what we're going to do.
>> So once you have path as a
variable, I no longer really
care about printing it out.
I just need to store it as a variable.
And then I can access another
page the same way I access
doc in the first place.
Except with the URL, we're going
to use string interpolation
like I was describing in
Ruby earlier on to append
the path to the end of the root.
>> So what this is going to do is
this is going to put on the path
that I scraped previously
and then turn that
into a new item, whatever you want to
call it-- first_listing, for example.
But I'm going to leave
it on item for now,
because that is what I'm using here.
>> So say I wanted to get the description
of the first posting in Craigslist.
So I would go down here.
I would click on Inspect Element
again, because this is the description.
I'd go down here and see
if I can find how I might
be able to search for this unique tag.
And in this case, it has
an ID, which leads us
to our next way of searching for
tags, which is with a hashtag.
>> So for classes, you can
use the dot operator.
So .txt is specifying a class of txt,
whereas the hash specifies an ID.
So in this case, the tag is
section, and the ID is postingbody.
>> So this goes and finds
the first-- because we're
using at_css-- this goes and
finds the first element that
comes up with the tag of section
and the ID of postingbody.
And then you can access the text element
of that item returned with .text.
And then we can store
that in the description.
>> So now that we have a
variable description,
we might be able to do, say,
file I/O. So file I/O in Ruby
is very similar to file I/O
in C where we open a file.
We might write to it.
And then we'll close that file.
>> So here, we're just naming the
file, some arbitrary variable.
We could also have just put this here.
We have a variable that we're storing
the open file as with File.open.
And we're writing to this file,
so we open it with the w operator.
And then we put string into the
file with the .puts operator.
And then we put the variable that we
want to write to the file within that.
And then we just close the file.
>> So if we go ahead and run this,
this should produce a document
with description.txt which will
have this description within it.
So if I run it-- no.
It's produced a text file with,
hopefully, the same thing.
So there might have been a new posting
that's come up while I've been talking.
And indeed it looks like there has been.
So if we go to this classic bike,
1962 to 1966, that seems to match.
And there you go.
>> So that's the most basic
functionality of scraping.
We could have instead of
just writing to this file,
we can add things to an array.
So if I declare three arrays,
title, price, and description.
And we're operating on the doc item now.
We can go through and
find all of the span.txt.
And remember, this returns an array
of all the items that it finds.
And then in Ruby, you can just use
.each to iterate through every item
of the array.
And then for each item,
I'm just going to call it
a link, because that's
essentially what it is.
>> So if I put each link.css dot a.hdrlnk,
this is actually going to the link
and finding within that link another
HTML element and corresponding class.
So if we remember what
this was, the span.txt,
you can see- let me just go back
real quick-- within span.txt
we have a lot of other classes.
So inside span.txt, we're looking
for an a tag with a class hdrlnk.
So let me just find that
for you guys real quick.
>> So you can see here, this is an a tag
that's within the span of class txt
that has the class hdrlnk.
And that's indeed what
we're trying to get.
>> So we're now trying to store all
of those links inside the title.
And then we're going to print
out each of those links.
No, sorry.
We're going to print out
the price of each of those.
So let's run this really
quick and see what it does.
>> So this just basically went
through each of the links
in turn, accessed the tag in question,
and then pulled out the price.
And it did that because after
you have everything in the title,
we've just stored the title there.
We've just stored the link
within the array title.
And in this for loop operation,
where instead of going to a.hdrlnk,
we're looking for a span.price.
So if I can just really quickly find
the price, if you inspect the element,
you'll see that it is a span
with the class of price.
And that's essentially how
we're getting the price there.
>> So that's the really
basic case of scraping.
That's how you get all
the elements on a page
that, say, you already know the URL of.
>> So if we want to get a
little more in depth,
we can scrape pages within pages.
And for this example, I'll
be outputting to a CSV file.
So I'm requiring csv up here
because Ruby doesn't, inside itself,
have the functionality
to just output CSV files.
So that's super simple.
Let me just go to the next.
We covered file I/O. So this
is similar to how it is in C.
And before we move on to Kimono,
I'll just show you really quick how
to scrape sites within sights.
>> So we already learned how
to declare arrays in Ruby.
So I'm just declaring a
bunch of arbitrary arrays
that I will be storing data within.
doc is operating the same way
as it did in the previous file.
We're going in, finding
each of the span.txt's.
We already know that.
That is the container within which each
link has all of the data that we want.
>> So here what we're doing is for each
link of span class txt, we're going in
and we're finding the a tag,
finding the first element of that.
Remember, .css returns an array,
so you can't just access it as is.
We're going to find the first element.
Even if it's an array of one
item, you have to use this syntax,
and then pull out the href attribute.
>> So we did this earlier.
So this should look familiar.
And so now we have an array
called paths of all of our links
that we're going to want to use.
So if we have this array of all
of the paths that we want to use,
we can then create an item for each
of those pages when we open that page.
So as we also saw on
the syntax before, where
doing string interpolation with the path
here, so the syntax is just for path.
And I could name this
variable any arbitrary name.
>> This is the important one.
This is the array that you'll
be accessing each element.
But when you say for path in paths,
this means for each element in paths,
call it path, and use that.
This is essentially like when you
do a for loop and you use int i.
So you can treat the path as the
variable that's incrementing.
>> And then for each of those,
go into each of those links.
Because we're storing it in item page,
so we're creating a new page every time
we access it.
And then within that new page, find
span.postingtitletext, span.price,
and then section#postingbody.
We already covered section#postingbody
when we looked at the description.
>> So we can go see in the Craigslist post,
if you're just looking at the title,
you can see it up here,
span postingtitletext.
And that's why it's there.
And then for the price, you can
access it with span class of price.
>> So we also perhaps might
want to store the URL.
So we'll just run this
again, store it in an array,
because if you're looking
on Craigslist, you're
probably going to want a way to, if
you see something that interests you,
go back to that site.
So you just want to store
the URL for references sake.
>> This is just essentially
another syntax for the for loop.
I could just do paths.each instead
of for path in paths with index.
And this syntax is Ruby for--
path is what we did up here,
declaring a variable for each item.
And index behaves like
the i in C for loops.
So you can keep track
of what the index is.
>> So here is just a
little convenient thing
for when you're running the scraper.
If you're scraping hundreds of pages,
to make sure that it's not hanging,
it will just output,
I'm accessing this page,
and making sure that
it's still continuing.
But for our purposes, because
there's a hundred items,
I'm going to access just three of them
so that we don't run out of time here.
>> But before we get to that, I'm just
going to show you really quick,
I will be outputting the title,
price, description, and URL
of each of the links that I've scraped.
And then this is just the
syntax for the CSV library.
You open a CSV.
This is what I'm going to call it.
Open it with write do.
And then CSV will be the file that
you're inputting everything into.
This is just a sanity check for
me to know that it's running.
And this is my sanity check
to know that it's completed.
So I'm putting title into a row in
the CSV, price, url, description,
all into rows in the CSV.
>> So if we go and run
this now-- and I just
make sure that I've saved it-- instead
of just outputting it to the terminal,
we should have a CSV
file that's produced.
So here we can see the CSV
file that's been produced.
This is the output of the
scape that I just ran.
As you can see here,
accessing page 0, 1, 2, 3.
These are the titles,
prices, descriptions.
And if we look at this CSV
file that we've generated,
you can see its outputted here.
This isn't Excel, so it's not
formatted in rows and columns.
But you can imagine how
it might be formatted.
>> CSV stands for comma separated values.
So you can imagine this might be a row.
And each comma would
indicate a separate column.
Just a word of caution--
sometimes you're
scraping things with a lot of commas.
So if you're outputting
it to a CSV file,
it might not output the
way you might think.
>> So that's essentially all
there is to scraping basic HTML
pages with Nokogiri.
>> So the internet being
innovative as it has come up
with a more automated and GUI
version, albeit less robust
version of scraping various websites.
And for our purposes
I'll be demonstrating
a Chrome extension called Kimono.
And all you have to do is you navigate
to the page that you want to scrape.
You click on a field of interest.
You calibrate the fields,
because it will automatically
detect what it thinks
you want to be scraping,
and then you just create an API.
>> So if we were to demonstrate it on
Craigslist, it actually wouldn't work.
And this is what I was going back to
saying about it not being as robust.
It has trouble creating the API.
But as a demonstration
of what it would do,
if you install the Chrome extension,
all you do is you click on it.
It Kimonofies the page, and then you
click on the thing you want to script.
>> So if I were to click on
that, it would highlight
what it thinks I want to
be scraping off that page.
So maybe I call this listings.
This is how many items I have selected.
And I can just confirm or deny some
of the other suggested listings
to get it to add to
what will be scraped.
>> So now we can see there's
a hundred items selected.
If I want to have another field that I
also scrape which is related to this,
say I want to scrape the price
as well, then I can do the same.
>> So here's a demonstration of how it's
much less robust, because now it's
picking up the city instead
of just the price that I want.
And now it's picked up 200 things.
You can go back and delete.
You can try again.
But no guarantees.
This is how this works sometimes.
As you see here, now it says 96 up here.
It's picked up most of the links
that you want to scrape, but not
necessarily all of them.
>> Another useful tool of Kimono though
is you can go to Advanced Features
here, go to Advanced,
and it will show you
the breakdown of the unique
way to access the HTML
tags that you want to scrape.
So for listings, if you look at here,
if you access div p span span a,
you can actually just use
this in your Nokogiri code,
where before we had span.txt
to access each of the listings.
If I just want the text
within the listings,
I could input div space p
space span space span space a,
and it would achieve the same effect.
And for those of you who are interested
in using regular expressions,
it happens to also give you the regular
expression sort of string to input
to find the things
you're trying to find.
>> So there's another cool feature
of Kimono where you can paginate,
which is not only can I scrape
the results of this page,
I can click on this little
button here, Pagination,
specify the button that would
take me to the next page,
and then it will just know that
it can iterate to the next page,
and then scrape all of the-- as long
as it's the same format of course--
scape all of those links as well.
>> So because Kimono doesn't want to
work with Craigslist, what we've done
is I've Kimonofied the Harvard Crimson.
I've pulled out some of the sort of
top featured articles, confirm here.
Say all of these.
I've compiled this API
for you ahead of time.
But otherwise what you would do
is you would just click Done.
Enter in your API details.
Set it to either
automated or manual crawl.
So you could update your
data every 15 minutes,
weekly, daily, whatever you want.
Name your API.
Create the API.
For your benefit, I've created the
Crimson front page API already.
>> So you just create an
account on Kimono, and it
will store all your APIs for you.
So essentially that's all your
separate different scrapes.
>> So if we look here, this is the
opinions links that I've collected.
These are the featured
links that I've collected.
And these are the most read
links that I've collected
from this most recent API scape.
>> So if you can see here,
these would be the featured,
these would be the opinions,
which in this example,
I've combined them all
into one collection.
But if you just play around with it
a little bit, you can split it up
and divide it up however
you want to as long
as the formatting is slightly different.
>> Just to play around with this, the
crawl set up, one of the downsides
is you can only crawl up
to 25 pages at a time.
That's one of the limiting factors.
But here, if you set it
to manual crawl, this
is how you can tell it
to update your data.
And here you can see your crawl history
of everything that you've crawled.
And you guys can go back, sign up,
play around with all the different ways
that you can modify and use your data.
>> Kimono can be set up to
scrape links within links.
And you would do so by first
scraping a list of links,
and then using that API as a
jump off point for another API
that you create the script.
But that's more complicated than
what we're going to get into today.
>> So that's Kimono.
We'll talk about the pros and
cons of Nokogiri and Kimono.
>> Nokogiri, it's really fast.
It's easy to test.
You can just puts anything to
console, easy to configure.
You can decide exactly what
you want to scrape and store.
There are no page limits.
I actually used it to scrape like
1800 South African school websites
for emails for an internship that I did.
>> So that's possible, though best practice
would be to split up the script.
Because if it fails, then
you don't get anything.
But if you do a hundred,
maybe 200 pages at a time,
then you have some chance of at least
getting it piecemeal, especially
if you have bad internet.
>> Unfortunately it can only scrape HTML.
So if you have
dynamically loaded pages--
and I'll show you an example
like Kayak in a second--
Nokogiri unfortunately
cannot scrape that.
>> But Kimono is also easy to use.
As you saw, it's essentially
a point and click.
It can scrape JavaScript.
Unfortunately, there's a maximum
to how many pages you can scrape.
Sometimes it's a little
hard to configure.
It gets confused.
But it's definitely
something to consider
if you're not trying to have a
super robust maintainable scrape.
If you just want to get
everything off of a page quickly,
then Kimono is a really
good tool to use.
And as I mentioned before, there's
the advanced feature of Kimono
that shows you how to
access the unique HTML
element, which is super useful even
if you are working in Nokogiri.
>> So if we go to the Kayak site, for
example, you can see there is--
or maybe you can't see.
But if I show you the URL for Kayak,
this actually is just the source URL.
This is the URL prior to being
modified by whatever JavaScript scripts
that they have going on.
And it's going to look different
from inspecting the element.
>> So if you go through and you
match up the Inspect Element
code to the source code, it's
actually going to be different.
And this is essentially why Nokogiri
can't scrape dynamically loaded sites.
Because Nokogiri is
scraping the source URL,
whereas Kimono is actually
scraping what you're essentially
seeing in Select Element.
>> So if I go through and I
try and Kimonofy Kayak,
I can actually go through
and select the price.
It's a little harder,
and in this case, it's
actually seeing this price
as different from these.
So whereas you can configure-- or
if this weren't dynamically loaded,
you could configure Nokogiri
to get all of these.
>> Because the formatting is slightly
different for this listing
as it is compared to the rest
of them, and you can see here
it's actually gone and
selected all the flight prices.
Maybe I want to select
time of flight as well.
And I can go through and
sort of configure that.
I don't want that.
I just want the next flight's time.
And then after a couple of these
going through, it gets the picture.
So Kimono's pretty smart.
It's just not quite as robust.
>> There are some other
alternatives that you can use.
And I'll show you them here.
If you are more comfortable in
Python instead of Ruby maybe,
there is a library
called Beautiful Soup.
You can use that.
It's very similar to Nokogiri.
It has a few more features.
You can find an HTML tag and
then move up or move sideways.
>> There's PyQt.
This can actually scrape dynamic
sites, because it's sort of
is a WebKit that pretends to be
a browser without there actually
being a browser.
So it would wait for all the
JavaScript to load first, and then
go in and try and scrape the site.
>> If you want to stick with Ruby, you
can go one level up from Nokogiri.
You can use Capybara with
a Poltergeist wrapper.
And this can actually
essentially do the same thing
as PyQt, which is it is a WebKit.
It waits for the
JavaScript to load first.
If you fiddle around with it enough,
you can even get it to click on things.
>> So if there's a link that
isn't a classic href where
the path is easily accessible, and
it's some JavaScript thing that detects
a click, you can actually do that.
The more popular library
to simulate a user
is in JavaScript, which is PhantomJS.
This can obviously scrape dynamic
sites because this is essentially
pretending to be Chrome
without the user interface.
>> And then, of course the most
robust, but slowest option,
is a Selenium browser automation.
And unfortunately,
you're not going to be
able to do this within your CS50 IDE.
Because essentially what it
does is it boots up your Chrome,
Firefox, whatever browser
that you want to use,
and it tracks maybe your mouse
movement, whatever you type in,
and it just sort of
automates this process.
So it was developed as a sort of
website automation testing tool.
But a lot of people use
Selenium to scrape websites
that they otherwise have a
lot of difficulty scraping
with some of these other, faster tools.
>> So that's all I've got for web scraping.
Have fun.
>> AUDIENCE: Question.
>> ROBERT KRABEK: Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: Is there a mechanism to hash
the website so you could basically
go through it later on.
ROBERT KRABEK: Yeah.
So we put the, in our
example, for both of them,
we put the entire website into doc.
And so you could actually just take the
variable doc and write it to a file.
So if I wanted to, I could
write it out as an HTML file,
and then instead of using
OpenURI and a cURL request,
then I could just open up doc
HTML and then search for that.
>> AUDIENCE: But can you preserve
the sort of online experience
while you do offline.
For example. when you're
flying for several hours,
I want to basically archive
the whole website. [INAUDIBLE]
>> ROBERT KRABEK: Yeah, that's exactly--
so literally what this is doing
is it's taking everything
that would be at this URL.
So if we ran cURL, it's
taking all of this HTML,
and it's storing it
inside the variable doc.
So then you can do whatever
you want to do with doc.
You can output it to a file.
AUDIENCE: But it's not linked up.
It's not dynamic.
It's not recursive, right?
You see what I mean?
I'm trying to basically sort of a hash
the whole website on my hard drive
so that I could basically do it
for several hours without internet.
>> ROBERT KRABEK: Right.
So if I had-- so where's my file I/O?
So this is the file I/O. So say instead
of this, I call this craigslist.html.
I'd open that up.
I'd puts doc into it.
I close the file.
And then just because the CS50 IDE
is on the cloud, that's whatever.
I can go here.
I can download the file.
And then that would be on my hard drive.
So you can do it that way.
Or if you're at home, not using the
CS50 IDE, like Sublime or something,
this is even easier, because
this is all available locally,
not tied to the internet.
>> AUDIENCE: I see.
This is for one particular problem.
Can you do it recursively so that you
go several layers deep kind of thing?
>> ROBERT KRABEK: I can download folders
as well, if that's what you're asking.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
>> ROBERT KRABEK: Cool.