>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVIN: All right, guys.
So this is the review
for the first quiz.
Is everybody ready for
the quiz on Wednesday?
ALLISON: Woo!
STUDENT: Woo!
DAVIN: Yeah.
ALLISON: Yeah!
DAVIN: That guy's ready.
That guy, two hands, nice.
So quiz review today, it's going
to be about an hour and a half.
We're going to go over all the major
concepts you should know for the quiz.
We're going to go over some coding by
hand examples, which are on every quiz.
And if you have questions, feel free
to raise your hand and everything
like that.
Well, logistics about
the quiz are online.
So we're going to split people
up into different rooms.
It's based on their name.
So if you have any questions about where
to go or about what material is, like,
the official word on what's going
to be on the quiz, check online.
And that's all up to date.
So if there are no questions to
begin with, we're going to start.
And here's Allison.
>> [CLAPS]
>> ALLISON: OK, thanks, Rob.
Appreciate it.
Davin should have flipped to this.
This is the non-exhaustive list of
topics, as always, as Davin just said.
Consult the documentation
online about quiz zero.
But this is pretty much--
it's on the syllabus
is everything we've gone over thus far.
Everything here is fair game,
as well as anything else
that may have been mentioned in lecture.
>> My section, here, is
just a lot of review.
There are a couple exercises
that you guys might work on.
But for the most part, we really
want to get to Davin with those code
by hand exercises.
>> So I am going to fly through this.
If you have any questions, stop me.
Raise your hand.
I promise I'll probably see you.
If not, just wave it around.
I'm going to be talking fast.
I hope everyone's OK with that.
>> OK, special word, Davin obviously
forgot to flip through these slides.
[LAUGHS] You're in trouble, man.
So tips for quiz zero,
practice coding on paper.
You guys are going to get some
practice with that now with Davin,
so you won't be completely by yourself.
I think we're actually going
through these two functions.
So you'll be well prepared there.
>> Be familiar with your problem sets.
There have been questions
on previous quizzes
that will ask you, for example, to code
up something very similar to Mario.
So being very familiar with
your problem sets, as well
as the questions we ask you
in the beginning on the form
that you fill out, will
serve you very well.
>> Do a previous quiz under
the time constraints.
These quizzes are long.
The time goes really fast.
And often, you don't realize how
fast it goes until you actually
put yourself under those constraints.
So if you can just carve out, you know,
75 minutes, either tonight or tomorrow
to take one of these quizzes under
that, you will be in much better shape.
>> And also, creating your reference sheet.
Remember, you get one
page front and back
as reference for your quiz on Wednesday.
Creating that is a great way to study.
Anything that you're having trouble
with you want to include on there.
Anything that your TFs have been,
like, this is really important.
You should know this, are
maybe things you have on there
if you don't have them memorized.
Even if you do know them really
well, sometimes having it on there
is just kind of comfort for you,
which I know quizzes are stressful.
So any comfort you get can help.
All right, also, get sleep and
eat and like the normal things
that we tell you for quizzes.
>> So starting off easy,
data types and sizes.
As I said, this is just going
to be me throwing a lot of stuff
up here that you should know.
So we have our chars
that are one bytes, ints
that are four bytes, long
long, which are eight bytes.
Basically, it's just you
want to hold larger integers.
Floats, which are four,
doubles, which are eight.
Again, just gives you more
space for your floats.
And then type star, so any
pointer on a 32-bit machine,
which is all you guys need
to know, is four bytes.
>> So all things you should
know, maybe things
you want to have on
your reference sheet.
OK, binary conversion
to binary, conversion
to hexadecimal, back and forth,
all things you should know.
So from binary to decimal.
You guys want to take a quick minute
and try and figure out each of these
and then tell me what they are?
>> I also have candy in my bag, so anyone
who answers gets candy, by the way.
And I have lots of it.
Let me grab this.
I'm going to give this to Gabe.
So you can hand out candy to
whoever's nice and cooperative.
>> OK, I saw a hand there in the back.
>> STUDENT: Yeah, the first one is 42.
>> ALLISON: Yes, first one is 42, correct.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
[LAUGHTER]
ALLISON: Second one,
there back in yellow?
STUDENT: 110010.
ALLISON: Correct, and this
last one, down here on bottom?
Also, yeah, you know want?
Just toss out candy.
How about candy for everyone?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] when we're done.
>> ALLISON: Shh.
And then the last one.
Who wants to answer?
Right there.
>> STUDENT: 11100.
>> ALLISON: 11100, look at that.
Congratulations, great job, everyone.
OK, everyone kind of understand
the process for doing this?
You have, going from binary to decimal
the way I tend to do it, is writing out
the powers of 2.
So I say, OK, 0 times 2 to 0, so
that's 0, 1 times 2 to the first,
is 2 going onwards that way.
Does anyone want me to explicitly
go through an example of binary?
OK, cool.
>> Decimal to binary is very similar.
I tend to write out the powers of 2.
Start with the one that is the greatest,
but doesn't go past the decimal
that you're looking for.
And then kind of work your way
backwards adding up things as necessary.
>> And then with addition, it's
just like normal addition.
If you ever have the case where you're
adding two 1s, it obviously becomes 2.
2 in binary is now 1 0 so you need
to carry your 1 into the next column.
Cool.
>> Hexadecimal, this might be something
that is slightly less familiar.
So as Rob was just telling me
beforehand, his trick for this
is to just split it up
into four byte chunks, OK?
Bits, sorry.
See?
Thanks Rob.
This is why you're here. [NOISE]
OK, so we just break it up
into four bits chunks.
So with binaries to hexadecimal,
we look at the first 4,
which is if we have four 1s in a
row, what number does that symbolize?
>> STUDENT: F.
>> ALLISON: So in this case,
what is 11111111 or-- yes?
STUDENT: FF.
ALLISON: Perfect, FF.
So great, candy for you.
Now, for how hexadecimal to binary, we
just think about it kind of in reverse.
For each number or letter that
we have in our hexadecimal,
just convert it to its four bit
[LAUGHS] to its four bit conversion.
So 5, in this case, what is 5 if
we're representing it with four bits?
>> STUDENT: 010?
Mm-hm.
And then A, which is
actually 10, would be?
1010.
So we have that, here.
So converting between hexadecimal
and binary actually isn't that bad.
If you look at it in four bit
chunks, going to be golden.
Everyone-- yes?
>> ROB: This is silly,
but I always remember
A, since A's supposed to be 10.
And binary's just 10 10, so--
>> ALLISON: Ah, there we go.
>> ROB: Hey.
>> ALLISON: Hey, candy for Rob.
There is non-chocolate stuff in there.
So you can have some.
So ASCII math.
Behave.
So ASCII math, as you guys
probably well remember
p set 2 with Visioneer and
Caesar, you did a lot of this.
Remember, the characters are
fundamentally just numbers.
So we can do math with them,
just like we do math with ints.
>> So we have just a little
simple thing here.
We have some in A that's
initialized to 65.
And B equal to the ASCII value of A
plus 1, char C equal to D minus 1,
and char D equal to 68.
So then we are going to print
all of them, as we see here.
And can anyone tell me
what this will print out?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
ALLISON: Exactly, so
one thing to notice is
that we are printing out
characters each time, here.
We are designating even though A and B
are ints when we declared them above.
We are printing them as characters by
the percent C and our printf statement,
so they will all print as characters.
And of course, the ASCII value 65 will
print as A. The ASCII value of A plus 1
would be 66, which would
proud to B. So in fact, we
get A B C D. Everyone good there?
Any questions?
Awesome.
>> OK, scope.
So scope is obviously a very
important thing to understand, here.
A lot of you, if you
have compiling errors,
and it says you don't have
access to some variable,
it's probably because you
defined it within a loop
and then tried to access it
out of it, or visa versa.
>> So scope at its core,
it just determines where
we say a variable exists, where we
can change it, where we can access it.
It's just kind of saying these are
the only places where you have access
to this variable.
>> So the two scopes that we talk about
during class are global and local.
So global variables we talk about
when you are defining them above main.
It means that your entire
program has access to it,
and it exists for as long
as the program runs, OK?
Local means that it's
more confined to a region.
So whenever you have specific functions
like swap, we always talk about.
We always talk about swap with A and
B. A and B exist within that function.
They don't exist anywhere else.
>> As well, when you have if
statements or for loops.
Whenever we have, for example, in
a for loop we have int I equals 0.
We have some condition and we update it.
I only exists within the
braces of that for loop.
If you try to access it elsewhere,
your compiler would yell at you.
It'd be like, what are you trying to do?
This doesn't exist.
So that's the two
different types of scope.
Does that make sense to everyone?
>> So for example here, this
is just some simple program.
What do you guys think is
going to happen at each point
that we try to print?
So this one here,
what's going to happen?
STUDENT: It will print three.
ALLISON: Right.
It'll print three.
What about here?
STUDENT: It won't work.
ALLISON: It won't work.
You're out of scope, right?
Local variable doesn't exist
outside of these braces, all right?
And then what about here?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> ALLISON: What?
Rob, go.
>> ROB: I just said.
Global variables should be
global underscore variable.
>> ALLISON: Ah, yes, sorry.
Thanks, Rob.
Rob's like our resident compiler.
He'll just yell at us when we
need it. [LAUGHS] Yes, that
should be global underscore variable.
So assuming that that
was global underscore
variable, what's going to happen here?
STUDENT: That will work.
ALLISON: It'll work.
So it'll print, so just
a very simple example.
OK, prototypes.
So obviously, we really
emphasize for you guys
to make functions if it
make sense in your programs.
But of course, when you
make your own functions,
typically you'll define them after main.
And you'll try to call them in main.
And if you don't use a prototype,
your compiler will yell at you.
>> Prototype is basically
just telling your compiler
that I have this function below main.
I'm going to call it before I define it.
Just hold on.
I promise that it's defined, and you
will have everything that you need.
>> So the way we do it is just your return
type, your function name, your input
list.
It's basically the first line
of your function declaration.
It's really all it is.
But this is just a
general kind of format.
>> So in our example here,
which you guys should
have seen in section
at some point, we have
some int cube that
takes some int of input.
And we have our main
function, which calls cube.
And cube is defined after the fact.
>> So if we didn't have int cube input
at the top, when we called cube
within main, our compiler
would get mad at us.
It'd be like, what
are you talking about?
Cube does not exist.
I don't know what you're asking for.
And I'm just going stop.
>> But because we did our prototype
at the top, we've said,
you know, when you see
cube, don't worry about it.
I promise it's defined later.
And it'll let you do what you want.
So if you ever have a function
that is declared after you call it
for the first time, you need to
have it prototyped at the top.
>> Yes?
>> ROB: It's squared, not cubing.
>> ALLISON: Oh my God.
I didn't have-- Gabe, I thought
you were our proofreader.
OK guys, bear with me, here.
I hope everyone's getting the idea.
OK, so this should have
been squared, not cubed.
But the idea remains the same.
Any function that we're calling after
the fact should have a prototype.
Everyone good with that?
Any other typos?
OK.
Any typos here before we start, Rob?
[LAUGHS] OK, so structs.
Basically, structs allow you
to create your own data type.
So much like an int or a char or
a float, it's just another type.
I like to think of it as, like,
create your own data type.
So it allows you to do that.
And it holds different types of data.
>> So if you remember, in an array, we
can only hold things of similar type.
Structs allow us to hold multiple
things of different types.
So in this case here, we
have a struct called Student,
named here at the bottom.
And we have some int id
and some string name.
So this is just another data type.
We now have a data type called Student.
>> So because we can think of
it as just another data type,
we can declare variables
as we would any other.
So instead of just having, like, an
int student, we just have a student,
student 1.
Oh, look.
It's Rob.
So here we're declaring
a struct, or a variable
called student 1 of type student.
So it's going to have id
and name associated with it.
>> And the way we access these
elements within our struct
is with the dot operator, here.
So in this case, we
declared some student 1.
We assigned the ID to be 1.
And we assigned the name to be Rob.
OK, everyone good with that?
Use it just like-- yes?
>> STUDENT: Yeah, typedef-- when
do we need to use typedef?
>> ALLISON: So typedef just
says that-- Rob, you
can correct me on this if I'm wrong--
but typedef is just actually declaring
it as a type that you can use, right?
>> ROB: Yeah, it's basically,
so it's just creating
an alias, or a nickname for a type.
So you can type that [INAUDIBLE].
So [INAUDIBLE] exists,
and now we just have
[INAUDIBLE] means
exactly the same thing.
And so here, we're typed, I think,
some struct type 2 [INAUDIBLE].
So it's just a nickname
for a given type.
>> STUDENT: String [INAUDIBLE] library
was typed up like char star.
>> ALLISON: For our purposes here,
if you're declaring a struct,
just do typedef struct.
OK, so beforehand, this is
just a normal variable here.
We access it with a dot.
if we have a pointer to
a struct, we can actually
use an arrow, which is pretty cool.
>> So in this case, we have a pointer to
a student 1 that is of type student.
Remember, with your
pointer construction,
you want whatever type your pointer
is pointing to to be at the beginning.
So we have some student 1, here.
And since this student
1 is now a pointed,
we can actually go student 1 arrow name
instead of dot, because it's a pointer,
and assign Rob.
And now if we want to
change Rob to Davin,
this is just showing you
a different way to do it.
>> So instead of using the arrow, you
can also-- I will finish this and then
take that question-- you could
also do reference student 1.
That's saying like go to
whatever is at student 1, which
would be our student struct.
Access it with a dot and the element
that you want, and then reassign it.
There was a question.
STUDENT: Yes, so how come you have
to use [INAUDIBLE] when you're
doing student star without
[INAUDIBLE] student?
ALLISON: Because this
is creating a pointer.
ROB: We're going to talk about it.
ALLISON: We're going to talk
about that later in the review.
So just hold onto that thought.
If it still bothers you at the
end, come talk to one of us.
>> So these do exactly the same thing.
We're just showing you two
different ways to do it.
Student 1 is now a pointer, so
you can access the Name element
within the struct with an arrow.
Or you can dereference your pointer, and
then access it as you normally would.
Does that makes sense to every one?
If the whole pointer things are a little
confusing, Gabe will talk about that,
and then maybe this
will make more sense.
Yes?
>> STUDENT: Yes, so how is
this different from the?
ALLISON: The previous one?
So the student 1 in this
case is not a pointer.
It's just your actual struct.
>> STUDENT: OK.
>> ALLISON: Whereas this one
is a pointer to a struct.
>> STUDENT: OK, but does it kind of
end up working the same [INAUDIBLE].
>> ALLISON: It effectively works the same.
Your syntax is just different.
STUDENT: OK.
>> ALLISON: Yeah, they are
effectively the same.
It's just depending on context,
you may want one over the other.
Yes?
>> STUDENT: When you do
references to the 1--
ALLISON: Mm-hm?
STUDENT: Why do you
have the parentheses?
ALLISON: Because student
1 is the pointer.
So you need to make sure you're
just dereferencing the pointer.
>> STUDENT: OK.
>> ALLISON: So in this case here,
the parentheses around it
means you're dereferencing student 1.
So you're going to where student
1 points, which is your struct.
So now you can think
of it as that struct,
so we can use our normal dot operation.
Any other questions?
Cool, awesome.
>> So last thing, I think
is my last slide, woo!
OK, so floating point imprecision.
We talked briefly about
this during lecture.
Basically, we have
infinitely many real numbers.
And if any of you guys
love math, there's
all sorts of cool stuff with us.
>> But there are infinitely
many real numbers.
But they're only finite
many bits that we have.
So you're always going to
have imprecision, is all.
And that's that's just kind of
like something you should know.
That like we may ask you why does
floating point imprecision exist?
So just something you should know.
And with that, I'm turning
it over to Pointers.
>> BINKY: Hello, guys.
My name's Binky.
I'm going to talk about pointers.
Yeah, so pointers is actually
my favorite part in this course.
So just to make clear what Allison
was talking about here, so the reason
why-- the only difference here,
the big difference was the way
we declare things.
So student star means this
is a pointer to a student.
Whereas the slide before, student is an
actual struct, like an actual student,
containing any of those things.
>> And the reason why we
want to-- yes, Davin?
>> DAVIN: What does the arrow mean?
>> BINKY: The arrow means
exactly the same as this.
So you don't really need the arrow.
Like, if you're only program
in C, you can just use this.
Sorry, I don't what that is.
You can just use this syntax.
>> But some people, when
they were designing C,
they figured that people
used that syntax so much,
that they will like just come up
with a syntax structure for it.
And this took place in
the form of this arrow.
And it's really nice, because
it symbolizes something
like we're actually following
this arrow, this pointer,
toward some space in memory.
And when we get there, we want to
look to the name of that student,
if that makes sense.
OK?
>> So this is exactly the same.
This is exactly the same thing as this.
They get compiled exactly the same, OK?
And the reason here why we malloc
something, is because in this case,
our variable is actually
just a pointer variable.
So we only have some space in
memory that's holding a pointer.
We don't really have any space
that holds the actual struct.
>> So this has to be done in two steps.
We have to create the
memory to put the struct in.
And we have to create the
memory to put the pointer in.
So they're basically two
different variables, here.
One of them is of type student,
except it doesn't really have a name.
And the other one is
of type student star.
And then student 1 points
there, if that make sense.
OK?
>> So the reason why we use
pointers is because everything
in a computer, every variable
in a computer has two things.
It has its value.
And it has its address.
And a good way to
conceptualize this is there's
many problems when you
try to use functions.
And we're going to try to
look into one of those.
Namely, it's going to
think of memory as boxes.
>> You always thought of variables
when you say na equals 5.
You think of putting 5 into a box.
So what if you want to pass
that int into a function?
You just pass-- I don't
know-- x into a function.
But what happens is
normally as humans, you
would think something like I'm
passing the box to a person.
And it doesn't really
happen in computers.
What happens is you copy the value
of the box to the person's box.
>> So what I'm trying to say is that if
you have a function-- sorry-- here,
if we have a function like to five up
there, if you try to pass a variable,
it's just going to copy.
If a initialize nx equals 3, it's going
to copy this value up to the variable a
up there.
OK, and this is kind of the reason
why we want to use pointers.
Because instead of
giving just the value,
instead of just passing just
the value to a function,
we want to pass by reference.
What we call pass by reference is kind
of giving the box to the function,
so that the function can also
change the values within that box.
>> OK, so just some basic pointer
stuff is to create pointers,
you just declare it a type, and
you put a star right after it.
And the type is just
what you're pointing at.
So if it's an int star,
you're pointing at an int.
If it's a char star,
you're pointing at a chart.
And if it's a student star,
you're pointing at a student.
OK?
>> And they're all 4 bytes long.
Because this variable
it doesn't actually
need to hold a char,
an int, or a student.
It only needs to hold an address.
That's why they're all 4 bytes
long in a normal 32-bit machine.
OK?
So here, x is a variable that points
to an int. y points to a char. z points
to a float.
Any questions here?
Cool.
And there are two
different symbols they have
to keep in mind when
coming to the pointer.
So referencing and
dereferencing are the big ones.
So the ampersand of the
variable name gives you the?
STUDENT: Address.
BINKY: Address.
So if you declare int a
equals 5, then ampersand
of a is going to give you the address.
And you can actually try
to print that and see
what address in memory
your variable has.
And then dereferencing--
so that was referencing,
getting the address-- dereferencing
is the exact opposite.
OK, just like times is the
opposite of a division,
star is the opposite of ampersand.
So dereferencing means go there.
So if you give star-- I
don't know-- 50, that's
going to try to go to the address of
number 50 inside of your computer.
OK, and why do we see
that they are opposites?
Because what happens if you do
something like star ampersand a?
Well, ampersand a gives you the address
of a variable, the address of a.
But star means go there.
>> So what happens if you
go to the address of a?
You just get to a, right?
So going to the address of
a is the same thing as a.
That's why they're usually
referred to the same-- this
and this are referred to
as opposite operators.
OK?
So cool.
>> Under the hood, for example,
if we declare int x equals 5,
we have a variable.
And remember that I said every
variable-- and this is a good thing
to keep in mind-- it has two
different things associated with.
It has an addressed and a value.
OK?
>> So the value in this case is 5.
And the address is-- let's say, I'm
making something up-- it's 0x04.
And the only reason why we usually
represent addresses in hexadecimal
is one, because it's like good.
It goes well with binary.
It's easy to convert to and from binary.
And it doesn't get too big if
you have a very big number.
So we like to use hexadecimal
in printing addresses.
But I could represent
this as an integer.
It's fine.
>> And so it has an address
4 and a value of 5.
And then I said int star pointer.
So this is a different type, notice.
Int star pointer equals
the address of x.
So what is going to be the value of ptr?
It's going to be the
address of x, down here.
OK, so the value is going to
be the same as the address.
That's the assignment operate I'm doing.
And then ptr is going to have
its own address, which turns out,
in this case, the 8, OK?
>> And then I create a new integer copy.
And I say int copy equals go there.
So go to what ptr is pointing to.
Well, what this ptr have?
Ptr has 0x04.
What happens if I try to go there?
I will find the guy who has
address x and who has address 4.
And who has address four is x.
Does that make sense?
Yes?
>> STUDENT: In this case, is
the pointer in a stack?
>> BINKY: In this case,
it's-- good question.
I didn't really think about this
when making up these addresses.
But if this is, like, all
these are local variables,
then x is going to live in-- everything
is going to live in the stack.
So everything is going
to be pointing to stack.
You only get to the heap when
you start to use malloc, right?
>> So if you recall stack is every time
you call a function in your program,
like, main for example, or any
other function, like printf.
All of the local variables are
going to get put in a stack frame.
And they're going to get
like piled up in the stack.
That's what's called a stack.
And all those local variables
are going to be there.
And the heap-- and we're going
to talk more about this later--
the heap is where all of
dynamically allocated memory lives.
Cool?
>> We go to this slide.
Yes?
>> STUDENT: Why isn't int
copy returning 0x04?
>> BINKY: Why isn't int
>> STUDENT: Why isn't that [INAUDIBLE]?
>> BINKY: Because what is a value of ptr?
>> STUDENT: 0x04.
>> BINKY: 0x04.
What happens if you go to 0x04?
What do you get?
>> STUDENT: Oh, OK.
BINKY: You see?
STUDENT: Yes.
BINKY: So you get 5.
So copy is going to have
5, if that makes sense.
Yes?
>> STUDENT: Could we have gotten
5 in the value box [INAUDIBLE]
if we put int copy [INAUDIBLE].
>> BINKY: Int-- we would, yeah.
That would have done
pretty much the same thing.
But this way, we can pass
address to functions.
And that's the cool thing
we're going to do right now.
>> So this kind of exercise always comes up
on-- very usually comes up on quizzes.
So it's really good to try to
do that kind of thing yourself.
So try to keep track of what the address
is and want the values of the variables
are at each point.
So this is exactly
what we're going to do.
Here, we have steps, one,
two, three, four, five.
One, two, three, four, five.
And we're going to keep track
of the values of x and a.
>> So what this is doing, if this is a
buggy code, we're trying to do to five.
So we're trying to get in a
variable and change its value to 5.
And remember my analogy of having a
box and handing the box to someone?
So main has this box called x.
And it contains the value 3.
And I'm trying to hand
this box to to five.
>> And I want to five to change
the value of this box to 5.
And then I just print the value of x.
This is what my function--
this is what I'm trying to do.
I'm just trying to update
the value of x to 5.
Is it clear what the function does?
>> OK, so what are going to be the
values of x and a right here,
the first line, right before the first
line-- I would say-- of the program?
>> STUDENT: Probably garbage.
>> BINKY: Just garbage stuff.
So I just put N/A. So
we don't really know.
Like, a doesn't even exist yet,
because we haven't called to five.
Int a is not declared.
And x is going to exist
here, but we haven't really
assigned any value to it, so OK?
>> And then, what are going to be the
values of x and a in number two?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> BINKY: So x is going to be 3.
That's easy, because
we're assigning 3 to it.
And a still doesn't exist
because a just lives in to five.
So I'm going to have 3 and nothing.
or like garbage, whatever,
not really defined.
And now, this is the important line.
Here, we're going to
actually call to five.
And remember what I said.
We never pass in the box.
We just copy the value of
the box to another box.
That's all computers do, copy
things from one place to another.
>> So to five, what it actually does
is it copies the value of x to a.
So what is going to be here?
The values of x and a.
3 and 3, we'll just copy
it over from x to a.
Cool.
>> Now we're here.
And now we're going
to update a equals 5.
What's going to happen in line four?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> BINKY: a gets updated,
but x didn't get updated.
Because x still lives in main, it's a
completely different block of memory.
It's a different variable.
a is another variable.
They happen to have the
same value because I
copied over the value of x to a.
But now when I do a equals 5, it
doesn't really effect x in any way.
This is the trickier part.
Does it make sense to everybody?
Yes?
STUDENT: One more question, you have 3.
Why is a already-- oh, no, it's 3.
Sorry, never mind.
I read 5.
>> BINKY: Yeah, 3, 3.
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE], yeah.
BINKY: And then we assign 5 to
a, but doesn't really change x.
Good?
STUDENT: Yes.
BINKY: Yes?
Can you explain again how
a gets copied [INAUDIBLE]?
>> BINKY: OK, so when you call to five
of x, so this line of code here.
to five of x, what is x?
x is just 3 at this point, right?
So you could just think of putting
a 3 in here and forgetting about x.
Just put a 3 here.
Like, we're going to copy over the
value of x to the int a that's up there.
OK?
>> So the value of x is 3.
We're going to copy 3 over to a.
And all this other block of
memory, this other variable
called a will have 3, as well.
Does that make sense?
Yes?
>> STUDENT: If you give to five like
have it as integer x instead of a,
would that fix everything?
>> BINKY: If it's an integer-- no,
that would not fix everything.
So that's a very good question.
It doesn't really matter what
you call those variables.
Again, it will be an issue of scope,
because they're not the same x.
They're completely
different spaces in memory.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
BINKY: So it doesn't really
matter what you call them.
That doesn't fix things, OK?
More questions?
Yes?
>> STUDENT: How is it back to
number five [INAUDIBLE]?
BINKY: OK, we haven't done that yet.
Let's go to number five, then.
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]?
>> BINKY: What?
>> STUDENT: Do you have a return at all?
BINKY: We don't have
a return, not of main.
But main returns 0 automatically
if you don't return anything.
Yes?
>> STUDENT: Could you make main-- or
could you make to five return a?
>> BINKY: We could have
to five return a, yes.
But then we would have to assign x
equals the return value of to five,
which would be a slightly
different program.
It would work.
But what we want to do is what is
called change something in place.
So we want to actually
change that box and not worry
about having to return
values or anything.
OK?
>> This is just like the swap function
David showed in lecture, except I'm
only dealing with one variable.
And he used two, so int a and b and
then temporary variable and whatnot.
OK?
So what's the last line?
After to five returns, it's
simply the a is going to go away.
We won't have a anymore, and
only x will still live on.
>> And guess what? x
didn't change its value,
after all, because we're
only changing the value of a.
That's why x was 3 throughout.
OK?
Good.
So this program does not
achieve what we wanted.
Now let's fix it.
>> And the fix program is using pointers.
What we do is we have three
lines that are different.
The first ones is we're not passing x.
We're passing the address of x.
So instead copying over
the value of the box,
I'm still going to copy over something.
But I'm copying over
the address of the box.
>> So if I pass the address of the
box to to five, then to five
will be able to find that in
memory and change its value.
>> So and then up there, I have
that a is not an int anymore.
a is an int star.
It's a pointer to an integer.
And then, because I'm passing the
address here, and then what I do
is not a equals 5, because
a is holding an address.
So what I want to do is go there and
update the contents of this address
with 5.
>> OK, so let's go through
all of lines one by one.
So when I start here, I
still have N/A, N/A, N/A
for everything in the first
line, because I haven't really
declared stuff yet.
And then line two, I have x equals 3.
A int star a don't exist,
same thing as before.
>> Now it gets interesting.
So I'm going to pass.
And let's assume that the address
of x is 12 in hexadecimal.
Let's just assume this.
I made it up.
So what am I passing here is a to five.
I'm passing 12.
>> So what value does a have?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> BINKY: Sorry?
BINKY: Yeah, like, to let's
assume that we are here, now.
I'm asking.
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> BINKY: It has been initiated.
BINKY: Because we passed
something to the function.
Yes?
>> STUDENT: Address of x.
BINKY: It's going to
have the address of x.
And the address of x is 12, good.
So x is going to be 3, because
we haven't really changed x yet.
And then a is going to be 0x12, so
the address of x, because that's
what we passed to to five.
>> And then what happens
if we try to go there?
What are we going to find?
So if you try to print star a,
we're going to follow this address
and get the value inside.
And the value is just
the same value that x
has because that's the
address of x, which will be 3.
Are we good?
>> OK, and then now, we actually go there.
And we update whatever
is in this address 12.
We make it 5.
So now both x and star a are 5.
>> Why is that?
Because the address of x is 12.
And a has also 12 as its value.
So if we follow 12, we're
just going to find x.
So whatever we do with
star a is going to happen
to x, because a contains
the address of x.
OK?
>> And this is like the crux of the fix.
So now we're able,
from to five, actually
access memory that lived in main.
So this memory doesn't live in to
five, like before, this address 12.
And we were able to go there
and change its value to 5.
>> And then when we return,
we forget about a.
We forget about star a.
And x is still five.
So if you want to
implement a swap function,
you would just do the exact same thing,
except you need to int stars here,
and so on and so forth.
OK?
Are we good?
Cool.
>> So pointer arithmetic.
This is a slightly tricky topic.
So it turns out that
pointers are just integers.
You can think of them as integers.
Because in memory, you have like
memory address zero, one, two, three,
four, five.
So we can sum memory addresses.
>> And that's usually what you do when
you're in and array, for example.
An array is just like a contiguous
block of memory, of lots of chars,
for example, lots of ints.
So if you want to go to the
second int or to the third int,
you can just sum something to the first
address, and you're going to get there.
So this is really useful for that.
>> And the thing to keep
in mind, though, is
that it's not just like
normal arithmetic in the sense
that if you're dealing with, say,
an int star, and you add 1 to it,
then you're not going
to add 1 to the address,
you're going to add 4 to the address.
Because an int is 4 bytes.
>> So this is just like
walking on an array.
If we have an array of lots of ints and
then we try to go to the second one,
it's basically just summing the
address of the first one plus 1.
But that won't be-- just let's say
that the address of the first one is 4.
Here, in this case.
And if we sum, so this
is what's happening.
We have an int.
Int x equals 5.
X has a value 5.
And we initialize this pointer, int
y int star y equals the address of x.
>> Let's assume the address of x is 4.
What's going to happen
now if I sum add 1 to y?
It's going to actually
sum 4 instead of just 1.
So I add a 1, but it actually
added 4, because computer's smart.
So it's going to actually add by i times
the size of the type of the pointer.
OK?
>> So if it were a char, for example,
if this were a char star y,
and if we added 1 then this would
be 5, because char is 1 byte long.
Good?
>> And finally, we got to
pointers and arrays.
It turns out that every time
you're dealing with an array,
you're actually dealing with a pointer.
The very nice conceptual reason for
this is that arrays are very big.
So remember that I said that
every time you pass stuff around,
you copy everything.
So if you have an array
that's really, really big,
you don't really want to
copy everything every time
you pass it around to another
function, because that's just
massive amounts of work.
So what you do is just past
the address of the first byte.
And then the function will have access
to all the elements in that array.
So you passed the array by its address,
so the address of the first byte.
>> So if we declare int
array 3, here, we know
how to access the first element
using the bracket notation.
If you remember the bracket
notation, array bracket 0 equals 1.
Well, this would be exactly the
same as just go there and put 1.
OK, is exactly the same thing.
So the bracket notation in here
will be the same as this line.
>> And guess what the bracket notation
for array bracket 1 will be?
It will just be the same thing as this.
So add one to array.
Move one along in memory.
Go there, and put a 2.
OK?
And this line's the same thing.
We want to go to the third
box, so array plus 2.
Go there, and put a 3.
So in memory, what's
going to happen is we're
going to have 1, 2, and 3 as the
three elements of this array.
>> We could have done this using
our familiar bracket notation.
I just want you guys to know
that they are the same thing.
OK, questions about this?
Nice.
Now, I'm going to hand
it over to Hannah,
>> HANNAH: Yay, yee-haw.
>> BINKY: Talking about
memory and article stuff.
[APPLAUSE]
>> HANNAH: Hi, cool, so we're
going to talk a little bit more
about memory, which we just
addressed using pointers.
So there are two main parts of
memory that we're concerned with.
We have the stack, which grows
up in the bottom, and heap, which
goes down from the top.
And the stack is going to hold
all of our instance variables.
So each calls to a function gets
its own little frame on the stack.
So as Gabe mentioned earlier, if we
call the function again and again,
we're going to stack
things up on the stack.
>> And similarly, the heap,
which starts at the top
is going to hold all of the memory
that we dynamically allocate.
And so as we dynamically
allocate memory,
this will come down towards the bottom.
Couple things to be aware of when
we're using the stack and the heap,
with the stack, if we have too
many-- let's say-- recursive calls,
and we're calling a function again,
and again, and again, and again,
and it's stacking up,
stacking up, stacking up.
And it's going to crash into the heap.
We're going to run out of memory.
That's going to cause a
problem for the computer.
And that's called the stack overflow.
So that's definitely something you
should be aware of and try to avoid.
And the heap, have to remember
not to accidentally leak memory.
Any time you use malloc, don't
forget to free that memory.
Otherwise, it'll just
be on the heap wasted,
and the computer won't know that
it is free to use that memory.
So those are a couple things
to be very careful with when
you're dealing with
the stack and the heap.
Any questions with this?
Awesome.
>> OK, cool.
So this kind of has the same
idea as stack overflow, where
we're going beyond the
bounds of what memory
is we're supposed to be able to use.
So take, for example, a buffer, or you
could just think of it as an array.
And we said, OK, we're going to
create this nice little array.
It's going to be a string.
Or it's going to store characters.
And it's just going to say hello.
And it's indeterminate.
That's it.
>> But if I were someone evil and wanted to
do something bad with this array, what
I could do is try to write
past the end of the string.
And as you'll see, if
I write far enough,
I can actually affect
the return address.
And if I start to affect
the return address,
I affect how the program actually runs.
And instead of returning, you
know, a happy string like hello, I
could do something bad, like go to
somewhere else in your computer, still
memory, change it,
whatever I want to do.
So that's what this would look like
is if I just kind of filled it up
with random garbage value,
in this case, just a.
And then when I actually
got to the memory address,
I started filling it with something
that did what I wanted it to do.
Any questions with buffer overflow?
Awesome, flying right
through this stuff.
>> OK, so we talked a lot of
about pointer with Gabe.
How do we actually get a pointer?
How do we get an address in memory?
Well, we can use this nice
function call malloc, which
is going to get a
little piece of memory,
specifically in the
heap, as we discussed,
and it's going to give you back a
pointer to that address in memory.
And the argument that we
have to give to malloc
is how much space in memory we want.
>> So you can see the size in byte.
Let's say, for example, or
actually, in this example,
we allocate enough
space for 10 integers.
So probably what we're going to want
to put here is an array of 10 integers.
So we give it size of ints, which
we learned was how many bytes?
STUDENT: 4.
HANNAH: 4, beautiful, and we
want 10 of those in a row,
so that we have enough space to
store all 10 integers, in this case.
Something super important,
any time you call malloc,
you have to check for null.
If you don't check for null, well,
malloc if it runs out of space
and can no longer give you any
more memory, it will return null.
So if you don't check,
malloc may return null.
And then if we try to
dereference a null pointer,
we're going to get a segmentation fault,
which we will talk about right now.
Awesome.
>> OK, questions with malloc?
Yes?
>> STUDENT: Does checking null
[INAUDIBLE] don't do it on the quiz?
>> HANNAH: Sure, the question was
does it matter-- on the quiz,
will you get points off if
you don't check for null?
Yes, you will get points off
if you don't check for null.
Any time you call malloc , both on the
quiz and your psets and in real life,
you have to check for null.
Good question.
>> GABE: What if I don't free?
HANNAH: Gabe wants to know
what if we don't free.
Then we will have a
memory leak in our heap.
Any other questions?
Yes?
>> STUDENT: Can you-- go over
buffer overflow real quick again?
>> HANNAH: Sure.
The question was can we go over
buffer overflow really quick.
Let's go back to those slides.
So a buffer, you can just
think of it as an array, right?
You have some space in memory.
And when we first create our array,
we know arrays have fixed size,
or our buffer has a fixed size.
>> So let's say in this case, we have just
enough space to write the string hello.
If we go past that bound, if we go past
what our array we said it could hold,
we could actually start
writing into memory
that the computer doesn't
want us to write into.
And specifically, if we hit
something like the return
address of the function, which,
like any other piece of memory,
is just somewhere in your
computer, you can actually
change that and start to do evil things.
Answer your question?
Awesome, anything else?
Yes?
>> STUDENT: So stack [INAUDIBLE], you
said go from the bottom going up.
Within stack range, does
the memory go from, like,
top down pertaining to each break?
>> HANNAH: How do you--
defer to Rob on this one.
>> ROB: It will grow in the same
direction as the stack grows.
HANNAH: OK.
ROB: So I get confused.
This is going to be abstraction.
HANNAH: OK.
ROB: This is correct.
So if the stack is growing
up, then generally-- it
doesn't have to be like this.
but you can declare int x.
Then you declare int y.
Then int x will generally be
lower on the stack than int y.
But that's just a fact.
That's not like an important seed thing.
>> ROB: So the question again was just
what happens each frame builds up.
So each function gets a
little piece of the stack.
And as you go up, within that
little piece, within that frame,
we'll say that variables
within that frame also move up.
Question?
>> ROB: Just to be on mic.
HANNAH: Oh, yeah.
ROB: I'll speak into you.
HANNAH: Oh, yeah, OK.
ROB: The exception is
for arrays and structs,
where arrays, a lower
index in the array,
and in structs at higher
field in the structs
are guaranteed to be at lower addresses
than a later value in the array.
So those are guaranteed.
But any particular variables within,
like int x and int y within a function,
there's no necessary relationship
between their addresses.
HANNAH: Another question over here?
STUDENT: So in buffer
flow, only buffer overflow
only happened when you
have, like, assigned
an amount of an array
that then is greater?
Like, can you?
So if you're asking for
something from the user--
>> HANNAH: Mm-hm.
STUDENT: Can they forcibly
give you something back
that's larger than whatever
you've allocated for them?
HANNAH: Sure, so the
question was basically,
can the user give you
more than you ask for?
STUDENT: Yeah.
HANNAH: Well, you could prevent
the user from doing that.
You could specifically say don't
give me more than x number by bytes
I've only given you room for x number
of bytes, x number of characters.
So that's something you want to prevent.
Yes?
What is the difference between
stack overflow and buffer overflow?
>> HANNAH: OK, so the stack
overflow-- oh, what
is the difference between stack
overflow and buffer overflow?
So we want to think of stack overflow
happening when we're actually
stacking up these function calls.
Let's say you have a recursive function,
because we know that every time you
call a function, it's gets
its own frame on the stack.
>> So we stack up too high, and
then we start to overflow.
And we use too much memory, And
we don't have anywhere left.
We get that error.
>> Buffer overflow is within a program.
We want might not necessarily have
run out of memory in the same way
that we might if we're stacking
up so many function calls,
but we write past the memory
that we know we can use.
And that allows us to do evil things.
Yeah?
>> ROB: Yes, you might want
to just repeat this,
but you can also think
of a stack overflow
as like a specific type
of buffer overflow.
Or you just think of your
stack as a really big buffer.
Then when you overflow you stack,
it's kind of like a buffer overflow.
But a stack overflow is just a
specific term used when the stack
itself overflows.
>> HANNAH: Right, so to
repeat for the video,
it you can think of stack overflow as
a specific type of buffer overflow.
Cool?
Any more questions before we go on?
Awesome.
>> OK, cool, so let's talk about
some common error messages.
This is something that has
shown up on multiple quizzes,
so something that's worth
taking a second look at.
I'm sure you've encountered
at least some of these
as you're doing your problem sets.
So make sure you can talk
about them on the quiz.
>> So the first one is
a segmentation fault.
And that's any time we
try to access memory
that we're not allowed to access.
So you migh have seen this,
for example, in breakout.
If detect collision
return null, and then you
tried to do something
with that null value,
the computer would give
you a segmentation fault.
So one, an important thing to
do in order to try to avoid this
is to always check for null.
>> You might have also seen
implicit declaration of function.
So this is what happens
when Allison showed you
how we make a prototype, right?
So let's say we have some
function that we define.
Let's say cube.
And that goes at the bottom
of our function, under main.
>> If we forget to tell the computer about
cube, when main tries to call cube,
the computer will be, like, oh my gosh.
I have no idea what that means.
I don't know what to do, here.
So the prototype says don't worry.
I'm going to tell you.
>> It'll come.
Don't yell at me.
Don't give me an implicit
declaration of function.
So if you get this error, one
thing you're going to want to do
is make sure you have your prototype.
OK?
>> And last but not least,
undeclared identifier
is essentially when you try to use a
variable that you haven't declared.
So all of a sudden you start
saying like n plus plus.
And the computer says what's n?
You never told me n was a thing.
>> So one thing you have to make sure you
did is tell the computer what n is.
So for example, n might be an integer.
And then you will avoid this error.
Any questions on common errors?
Yes?
>> STUDENT: For the implicit
declaration of function,
could it also be that you omitted one
of the libraries you were supposed
to include, rather than the prototype?
>> HANNAH: Right, so the
question was, could you
also get this error if you
forgot to include a library.
>> STUDENT: Yes.
>> HANNAH: Absolutely,
because in the same way
that we want to put our prototypes
before the main function,
if we have a library, those are going
to essentially include the prototypes,
include the definitions
of the functions.
Great question.
>> STUDENT: For a segmentation
fault, would that also
happen if we, like, tried
to access a variable,
like, in a different [INAUDIBLE]
than it was declared in?
HANNAH: Sure, so would we
get a segmentation fault
if we tried to access a
variable out of scope?
Was that a question?
STUDENT: Yes.
HANNAH: Beautiful.
So probably, you're going to get an
undeclared identifier error instead.
So it's just going to say
I don't know what that is.
Cool, anything else?
Yeah, OK, beautiful.
>> All righty, so recursion.
So I mentioned a couple times
that we might get a stack overflow
because we're calling our
recursive function so many times.
We're getting all these stack
frames, blah, blah, blah.
What even is a recursive function?
Well, a recursive function is
any function that calls itself.
>> Some things to be aware of when you
are implementing recursive function,
don't forget to include a base case.
A base case is the
point at which we end.
So, for example, if we're coding,
, say, Fibonacci recursively,
we want to make sure that when we get
to the 0 or the first Fibonacci number,
those two numbers have these cases,
because those aren't dependent
on things that came before.
Those have their own values.
>> Some pros to recursion, which is a
question we've seen on past quizzes.
They can lead to more
concise, elegant code.
And a lot of functions, a
lot of different algorithms,
actually lend themselves to recursion.
Their definition might be
recursive in and of itself.
So Fibonacci is one.
Factorial is one.
Merge sort is one-- all
things that you can look at.
OK, any questions?
Yes?
>> STUDENT: Is a corner case
similar to a base case?
Or is that for some other
kind of [INAUDIBLE]?
>> HANNAH: Sure, so a
corner case is any-- so
is corner case the same as base case?
A corner case is anything that your
code might behave a little differently.
Base case is sort of related, in
that they're like particular cases
that you want to look at.
But the idea of a base case is that
you want your recursive function
to stop at some point.
It can't keep calling itself forever.
It needs to stop at some point.
>> ROB: Yes, frequently, your base cases
might be examples of corner bases.
>> HANNAH: Right, cool, anything?
>> STUDENT: Could you explain
bases a little bit more?
I don't quite understand
[INAUDIBLE] base cases.
>> HANNAH: Of base cases?
>> STUDENT: Base cases, yeah.
>> HANNAH: Oh yeah, sure.
Let's see.
Do we have chalk over here?
Yes, we do.
OK, so really quickly, I'll
try to write big enough
so you can see on the screen.
Let's talk about, really
quickly, Fibonacci.
So I'll give you the Fibonacci sequence.
You can look up the definition.
>> Essentially, each number in the sequence
is the sum of the two previous numbers.
OK, so the way that I
just described Fibonacci,
you could hear the recursion, right?
When I said each number is the
sum of the two previous numbers,
we could say OK.
Well, the nth Fibonacci
number-- so let's
say we have this function
called fib-- fib of n
is going to be equal to fib
of n minus 1 plus-- sorry,
we'll going on to the next line
over here-- fib of n minus 2.
>> OK, so this works great if you're
looking at, for example, the zero, one,
two, three, four,
fifth Fibonacci number,
where you can say that
5 is equal to 2 plus 3.
But what if you're at the beginning?
What if you're just hitting
these first two values?
>> To get this 1, you can't
say add the previous two,
because that zero and-- I don't know.
So at some point, we need to stop.
At some point, we need to say that these
two just have their own definitions.
The 0 Fibonacci number is 0.
And the first Fibonacci number is 1.
>> So the way I might code this, I
would say if n is less than two,
then just return n.
And that would be my base case.
That's how I know to stop
with a recursive function.
Is that clear?
Awesome.
Anything else on recursion?
Beautiful.
>> Let's quickly talk about
search and sort run times.
And then I will give Davin some
time to talk about coding examples.
So here are the main search and
sorts that you should know about.
Guarantee-- I can't guarantee,
because I haven't seen the quiz--
but this comes up quiz
after quiz after quit.
So definitely use this chart.
Like, take this chart.
Put it onto your cheat sheet.
You'll be a happy person.
>> This tells us the run times of each
of these sort and search algorithms.
So linear search, you can see run
time, and same with binary search.
Go over what these algorithms
do, the general idea.
Look at some pseudocode,
if not code itself.
>> You'll see that bubble sort has a upper
bound in the worst case of n squared.
So if our array was completely
backwards before we wanted to sort it,
we would say that that's
going to take n squared steps.
But in the best case, so the
lower bound for the best case
is going to be if it's
already perfectly sorted.
Then all we have to do is
check that it's sorted.
Is there a question over here?
>> STUDENT: When would
you want to use sort?
The sort.
I'm just curious.
>> HANNAH: When would you
want to use selection sort?
This one?
The one that's n squared in both cases?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> HANNAH: So it's very different.
If you have specific
requirements for your program,
like things like if we just said
implement a search-- sorry--
implement a sort, you'll
probably want to go
for one of the ones that
has a best case of n,
or a lower bound in the best case of n.
But there might be
certain things like, say,
swaps are really
expensive for some reason.
Then you would want to do
bubble sort, because you
have to do so many
swaps, things like that.
Any other-- yes?
>> STUDENT: Would it be [INAUDIBLE]
to say that [INAUDIBLE]?
HANNAH: That's one thing
that would tell you
if you're looking at the implementation.
The way I would actually
think about why it's n
squared is that we have to run
through our array of length n,
each time making at most, n swaps.
And we have to do this process n times.
>> So when you have to make at most, n
swaps and for n runs through the array,
there's going to be n squared.
But yes, this will be revealed
through this double for loop,
as the question asked-- or
nested for loop, I should say.
OK?
>> And then merge sort, which
is the fastest sort we now,
or that we've covered in CS50,
know that the main algorithm is
this idea of breaking into
sorted pieces and then
merging together these sorted bits.
And will get us log n log n.
Any questions on searches and
sorts before I pass it on?
Let's see.
>> Oh, linked lists.
Sorry, I have one more topic.
OK, awesome, linked lists.
Problem with the arrays,
they have a fixed size.
So if you don't know how big
your input is going to be,
you don't want to create an array.
Because if we create an
array that is too small,
we might run into buffer overflow.
>> So instead, we could do something
with linked lists, which
allows us to have a dynamically
sized data structure
that will allow us to store a
more flexible amount of data.
So within each node in our
linked list, we have two pieces.
We have the actual value that it stores.
So that's just the thing you would
see in the array, for example.
And then we also keep track of a
pointer to the next thing in memory.
>> Unlike arrays, which
we know are all going
to be-- array elements are all one
after another in memory-- linked
lists could be anywhere in memory.
They're arbitrary locations.
So if we were to
actually go find them, we
need to keep track of the
next thing in our list.
>> And then in order to know
where that list as a whole is,
all we have to keep track of is the
very first element in our linked list.
And that'll allow us to follow through.
>> So this is how you might define a mode.
This is a great opportunity
to take advantage of structs.
Because you have this idea, well,
for a given node, I have two pieces.
I have the actual value itself.
And then I have a pointer to the
next element in the linked list.
So you see, we have an integer n,
which is going to be the actual value,
and then a pointer to
a node, called next.
So that's going to be the next
element in our linked list.
STUDENT: Yes?
Do you have to specify that
the star is like a struct?
>> HANNAH: Yes, so since this
is almost like a kind of,
it seems like a recursive
definition in that we
need to know what a node is
inside to finding a node.
Since it doesn't actually
know what a node is completely
until we get to the end of this--
and after this we can just call it
a node-- inside of this definition,
we need to call it a struct node.
Great question.
Anything else?
Yes?
>> STUDENT: Why do we
have to say node twice?
Because when we were in [INAUDIBLE]
we just had to do it in semicolon,
but now we have to find that
struct node? [INAUDIBLE].
HANNAH: So I believe
in the last example,
we were just creating anytime you
wanted to use a student after that, you
had to use struct node--
I'm sorry-- struct student.
This allowed us to, after the fact, just
use node add a new type, essentially.
That make sense?
So we'd have to go back and
look at the code before.
But I would guess that
we didn't use typedef.
And we asked the question,
why do we need to use typedef?
Typedef allows us to avoid the
word struct in the beginning.
Yes?
STUDENT: What sort of
questions would come up
in terms in terms of
nodes and linked lists?
>> HANNAH: So one thing is we could say how
might you search through a linked list?
OK, because it's a
little more complicated
than if we're searching
through an array.
We can just look at element zero,
element one, element two, blah, blah,
blah.
If we want to search
through a linked list,
we'd actually have to follow
this little maze of pointers.
So let's actually go
through this really quickly.
What we could do in
order to-- let's say we
want to just iterate through
our entirely linked list.
We would start at the head.
And then in order to
move to the next element,
instead of just incrementing by one
like we might in going through an array,
we're actually going to
follow the next pointer,
so we can find where in
memory the next element is.
So I know it's not enough to
take all this in right now,
but you'll have these slides.
So you can go through
this a little more slowly.
But essentially, what we want
to do is follow these pointers
through the entirety of the linked list.
So this is a question
you might be asked.
>> Something to notice with
insertion, let's say
we wanted to put a new element
at the front of our linked list.
We have to be very careful
about the order in which we
reassigned the pointers.
Because let's say I just said OK.
Make head point to this new element.
Just make it point to 1 Then, we've
essentially lost the rest of our list,
because I don't remember where 2 lives.
>> So we have to do in a
very specific order.
First, we make the new
element point to the head.
And then we make the head
point to the new element.
So let's see what that looks like
with arrows-- just like that.
So you first have the new
element point to the old head.
And now, we have the head
point to the new first element.
Any questions with this?
>> OK here's some code again, something
to look at a little bit later.
And now I will turn it over to Davin
for GDB and a little bit of practice
coding on paper.
Beautiful.
>> ROB: And Rob.
>> HANNAH: Oh, Davin and Rob.
I'm sorry.
>> STUDENT: Woo!
>> ROB: Thanks.
>> DAVIN: Do you want to say
everything real quick?
ROB: Yeah, yeah.
DAVIN: Once I'm up.
OK, while Rob puts the
microphone on, so what's GDB?
Everyone should have seen GDB in
class and also at office hours.
And you should be using it.
So what is GDB?
Anybody?
>> STUDENT: It's a debugger.
>> DAVIN: It's a debugger.
And what does it allow you to do?
Like, why do we like GDB?
STUDENT: To slow down the program.
DAVIN: Right, so you can walk
through it like a human pace.
And so what are some
commands you can do?
Well, break is probably
your favorite command.
Because that lets you break the
program and actually walk through it
line by line.
>> Run allows you to run it.
Next, like stepping through.
What's the between next and step?
Wait, say that out loud.
It was correct.
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVIN: Yes, awesome.
So like, next and step, if you're--
let's say you have a function you
define.
Let's say some in your main function,
and you're just hitting next, next,
next .
You're actually going to
execute that function,
but you're going to jump over it.
If you hit step, or
s or whatever, you're
going to actually jump
into that function,
and then you can hit next
to see the different calls
inside that particular function.
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: Is there a way
to jump, like, back out?
DAVIN: Finish, yeah,
finish with jump you out.
So it's going to finish that
function, and then you're
going to be back in main, for example.
Print will print it out one time.
Something I always use is display.
Display will print it out
constantly throughout the entirety
of your program.
>> For example, if you're
in a for loop, and you
want to see how something's changing,
and you don't want to, like, constantly
be doing like print,
print, print, display
will display that variable
continuously, every time you hit Next.
And continue.
So GBD, that's GDB.
>> STUDENT: What's the one
where you [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVIN: What is it?
>> STUDENT: What's the--
the local variables.
ROB: There is something actually
like locals or something.
I can't--
>> DAVIN: It might be
something like that, yeah.
>> HANNAH: In the locals?
>> DAVIN: That's it.
That's the one.
ROB: Beautiful.
>> DAVIN: Yeah.
>> STUDENT: What does continue do?
>> DAVIN: It continues-- so it's just
going to continue your programs.
So if you break and hit
continue, it's going
to just run that program until
it hits that break again.
So for example, if you
broke in a function,
and you're going to do like for
loop or something like that,
and you hit continue, it's going to
continue and go back to that break.
Or there's no break, it's going to
continue and finish the program.
>> ROB: So just like run stops
at the very first breakpoint
you hit, if you then
hit continue, it'll keep
going until it's the next breakpoint.
And then continue will go
to the next breakpoint.
DAVIN: Any other questions on GDB?
So I think in the past,
we've asked you what
GDB is and give an
example of some things you
can do with GDB, so
real simple, but yeah.
There you go.
And nodes?
>> ROB: Yes, so which direction was it?
STUDENT: That was it.
DAVIN: Wait.
ROB: This guy?
DAVIN: That one.
ROB: This guy, oh, I didn't realize.
So we weren't clear
on what the-- I don't
know who it was-- but the question.
We don't know exactly what you
were asking about it, so just
to clarify something.
So first, like I said before,
typedef you're always using just
create a nickname for a type.
So right here, the nickname we're
creating is for this type struct node.
>> So first, ignoring this node in the
typedef, so this struct node curly
brace down to next curly
brace is the struct node type.
And we need to that node
up there, because we
need to reference node in here.
So with this sort of recursive struct,
you need to give this struct a name,
or else you couldn't
say struct node in here.
Whereas before with student
when we were typed, I think,
we didn't have to say
student up there, because we
didn't have to say struct
student inside the struct itself.
So it's the recursive that
forces us to say node there.
>> This node is just the name we're
giving node for the typedef.
So that node is not
the same as that node.
But this struct node is the
same as that struct node.
DAVIN: So whenever you call,
like, node in your main function,
you're not going to
have to say struct node.
You can just say node, because
node is a different-- is basically
you're saying, OK.
Instead of having to call
struct node in my code,
I just want to rename it
as node to make it easier.
>> ROB: If you always
use typedef, then this
is the only place you're going to have
to declare a variable with struct node
star, yeah.
>> DAVIN: OK, so the last part
is hard to teach because--
ROB: What?
>> DAVIN: Because it's coding on paper.
So every year we have
code on paper questions.
So I think last year, 12 out of
80 points were code on paper.
Year before that, 10 out of 80,
year before that, 20 out of 100,
so quite a few of these.
So you're going to have to be able
to code up these functions by hand.
>> So I figured we might go through a
couple of them and see how people do,
kind of walk through
them slowly with people.
So generally, strlen and
atoi have been very popular.
Last year, I think we had
GetPositiveInt and RandomInt.
But pow, so power, also
a positive one too.
Let's just go through maybe
one or two of these together.
What do people want to see?
>> STUDENT: Atoi.
STUDENT: Yeah.
DAVIN: Atoi?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVIN: OK, I'm going
to do it on the board.
Do you have a preference
if I do it here or there?
There, Gabe says there.
>> ROB: And this is general thoughts
on these coding questions.
Try to write something.
Don't leave it blank.
>> DAVIN: Yes.
ROB: If you can get the
return type correct,
or maybe we might give it to
you, but if you can, like,
write the general function signature,
If you can get the base cases correct,
or corner cases, or
remembering check for null,
as long as you have some
things, then maybe we
can give you a couple
points for the problem.
Don't just leave it blank.
>> DAVIN: Yes, and if you
are just completely
stumped at how to
actually turn into code.
If you write pseudocode,
that's pretty good too.
So it's like, it's a six point question,
and you write the correct pseudocode,
you'll get at least two points.
So don't just leave them blank.
Try to put something.
>> ROB: It needs to be the
correct pseudocode, though.
>> DAVIN: Yes.
ROB: So we are generally are less
lenient with bugs in pseudocode.
DAVIN: OK, so you guys
wanted to see atoi.
OK, so just really--
so what you want to do
is you're going to be
given some kind of number.
But this number is not
going to be an int, right?
What's it going to be?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVIN: It's going to be a string, right?
So if you were given
a string-- let's say--
>> ROB: Should I pull up an editor?
I can pull up--
>> DAVIN: Oh, you want to do it on--
>> ROB: Would you prefer the board?
>> DAVIN: What do you want to do?
I mean, do you want to do it by hand?
Or do you want to do it by computer?
>> ROB: Do it by hand.
>> DAVIN: [LAUGHS]
ROB: Do it by hand.
>> DAVIN: OK, so it's going to be atoi.
So what's it-- I mean, we'll
probably give this to you.
But what's it going to return?
>> STUDENT: Int.
>> DAVIN: It's going to return int, right?
So-- I don't want to do it there.
I'll do it here.
>> ROB: You can pull it down
and then push up on it.
>> DAVIN: yeah.
[LAUGHS] Game change.
OK, so it's going to be int atoi,
and what's it going to take?
A char star, so just a
string, star s, like that.
>> ROB: Nice star, nice.
DAVIN: This might not be there, OK.
ROB: Yeah.
DAVIN: OK, so the first
thing you want to do-- I
don't know if anybody looked
at the practice solutions--
but what you're going
to want to do is you're
going to want to have
a loop, because you're
going to want to actually
step through this string.
So helpful-- so let's say
we're going to a for loop,
and we're going to step through
every element of the string.
How long is that?
How many times are we going
to iterate in that for loop?
STUDENT: Sterln?
DAVIN: Sterln, yeah.
So let's say int length equals sterln s.
And just curious, why is it always kind
of better to do this outside of loops?
Like, why is it better to call
this function outside of a loop?
Just a quick sanity check?
Yeah?
STUDENT: So you don't
have to keep checking it.
You can just [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVIN: Exactly, so yeah,
exactly what she said.
So we don't have to keep checking it.
So for example, if I'm calling
this function inside a loop,
then I'm going to keep calling
this function multiple times.
And that's going to decrease
the efficiency of your program.
So it's always useful
to declare it outside.
>> ROB: That's said, on
any of these problems,
pretty much as long as you get a
working solution, you get full credit.
So don't worry if your design
is absolutely horrendous.
It might make us upset
reading your code.
But as long as it works,
you'll get the points.
>> DAVIN: Yes.
OK, so then I'm going to
declare some variable.
It's just going to call int sum.
And I'm going to set this
equal to zero, like that.
And that's just going
to be a placeholder.
So that's going to be
what I'm going to return.
So I'm going to eventually
return sum out of this program.
So I have these two variables.
I have length.
I have sum.
And now let's jump into our string.
>> So lets have our for loop.
So four int I equals 0 w , while
I is less than length I plus plus.
And now--
ROB: Nice.
DAVIN: OK, and now here
comes the meat of our code.
So you can actually do
this basically in one line.
So does anybody have an idea
of what we're going to do next?
OK, so that's OK.
So we're doing to say sum equals--
let me scoot this over-- sum
equals sum times 10 plus-- we're
going to take s I minus one
quote 0 one quote done, like that.
ROB: Very intuitive.
>> DAVIN: Crushed it.
OK, so someone-- I got it, I got it.
OK, so this is clearly going up.
What does this mean?
So does anybody know what this means?
Can everybody see this?
No, nobody can see this, OK.
I'm going to--
>> ROB: I'm going to write the
formula just right here.
DAVIN: OK, Rob's going to do it
on the computer, which is fun.
ROB: Oh my God.
Or I won't.
DAVIN: Stand by.
STUDENT: I have a question.
DAVIN: Yeah, sure.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVIN: OK, so it actually,
like, just in general,
if you were to put, like,
in this declaration int
I equals 0 comma length
equals sterln, that--
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVIN: That's fine, because that--
STUDENT: Why would you
even need to use length?
Why couldn't we just [INAUDIBLE] sterln
s, like the whole time [INAUDIBLE]?
>> DAVIN: You mean right here?
>> STUDENT: Yes.
DAVIN: Because every
time this for loop runs,
it's going to evaluate this condition.
STUDENT: Right.
DAVIN: And if you have
sterln there, then it's
going to have to actually call
that function every single time.
So instead of just
comparing it to an int,
you're going to be calling a
function and then comparing it
to the return value.
Yeah, so it's just, yeah.
>> Nice, OK, so now everybody can see it.
What does-- this is like, this is it.
This is the jam, right here.
What does that mean?
What am I doing?
Yeah, an idea?
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: Well, so when
you're entering an array,
you're going to be going
from left to right,
so you're going to be going in
decimal from down the [INAUDIBLE].
DAVIN: Exactly.
STUDENT: So each one
you have to multiply
what you saw as the value of the int by
the time you get to move that over one.
>> DAVIN: Perfect, perfect,
so for example, let's
say I gave you-- I'm
going to write over here.
No, I'm not.
I'm going to write over here.
Let's say I gave you 76, right?
Let's say I give you 76.
That's a string to begin with, OK?
>> So length is what?
2, right?
Sum is 0.
Then we jump in our for loop.
OK, the first iteration of
this, what's it going to be?
It's going to be sum is 0.
So sum times 10 0.
That's meaningless.
Then what does this do?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVIN: It's going to turn that
character into an integer, right?
It's kind of like with your
problem set-- this light--
it's kind of like with
problem set to Visioneer.
You're dealing with ASCII values.
So if I give you, like, a
seven, but it's a character,
and you want to know,
OK, what digit is that?
Yeah, you could, yeah.
So what digit is that?
You could subtract 0 from it, but you
have to subtract 0, the character.
>> And where some people
get tripped up, they're
like, OK, well, do I have to know
the ASCII values for this quiz?
No, you definitely don't
need to know the ASCII
values of, like, lowercase
a, uppercase A, zero.
>> ROB: There is no reason to ever
put this on the cheat sheet.
>> DAVIN: Definitely do not
waste your space with this.
You can literally-- just instead
of saying 48, like right up
there, that is equivalent to
saying one, one apostrophe,
like that, exactly the same.
>> ROB: You could almost think
of it as if-- God, I need my,
oops-- you could almost think of it
as if we have something like that hash
define 0 as 48.
That won't work.
But think of it as single quote 0
single quote, and for all characters.
Think of it as a constant that
represents that ASCII value.
>> DAVIN: Yes.
OK, so the first time through, so
with 76-- so the first time through,
this is just the character
7 minus the character 0,
and those are seven
integers-- well, those
are seven spaces away from each
other on the ASCII chart or whatever.
So that's going to return an int of 7.
So now, sum equals 7.
>> OK, well, let's jump
into this for loop again.
OK, now it's sum times 10.
So you're effectively
moving the 7 to the left.
Does that make sense?
You're effectively
moving it to the left.
>> And then you add-- this
is going to be 6 minus 0.
That's 6.
So it's going to be 70 plus 6.
76, that's your number.
So regardless of what number
I gave you, it's slowly just
going to shift the larger values
to the left, 1 factor of 10
each time in the for loop,
and then add on as necessary.
>> In the back?
STUDENT: We don't have to do
any checking in the program?
>> ROB: So as far as checking
goes for the program,
we would tell you pretty
much what you need to check.
If we don't tell you
anything, then generally
assume you have to check most things.
Like you might, just to be safe, you
should probably check hey, is s null?
Then I have no idea what to return.
But we would tell you
this sort of thing.
0, I don't know.
>> DAVIN: And why would you want
to recheck if s equals null?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVIN: Because of char star.
It's a pointer.
So a perfectly acceptable
declaration, I could say, OK,
s equals null, because it
could be a pointer to null.
So whenever you have pointers
in your path in like this,
you should probably check.
Because if you don't check that, and
then you then go into your for loop,
and you're doing-- scoot down.
Scoot down.
>> ROB: Sorry, that's it.
>> DAVIN: And so, like, if
it is null, and then you
do this, what error
are you going to get?
STUDENT: You're going get a set fault.
DAVIN: You're going to set
fault, right, because you're
trying to index into null.
So you're going to try to index
into memory that you don't own.
So this, if this is null, and
you do this, you'll cycle.
>> ROB: I also think on the exam in which
we asked this question, we tell you
that you can just assume
it's a positive number.
Because atoi is also expected
to handle negative numbers,
so you would have to special case.
Hey, is the first character
a dash, in which case, OK,
now it's a negative integer.
We'll tell you these sorts of things.
We'll tell you what you need to handle.
DAVIN: Yes.
So I'm sure some people might have--
if you started looking at old exams,
you've seen sterln.
That's a popular one.
And I think in sterln, you had to
do this check for null, the return
0 or something like that.
Like, you had to check for null.
And if you didn't, that
was point off on the quiz.
So anyway, does everybody
feel OK with atoi?
Does anybody want to
go over parts again?
ROB: Oh yeah, I think
we also tell you you
can assume that everything is-- that
they're actually entering a number,
that you don't have to worry about,
like, letters being in the string, so.
DAVIN: Yeah.
Yes?
STUDENT: Can you go
over one more time when
you use double quote and single quote?
>> DAVIN: Sure, so double quotes, very
simply, is double quotes are strings.
So if you double quote
anything, that's a string.
So, like, if I had this 0 over here,
and I did this, that's a string.
That's no longer a character.
So I can't find this value on my ASCII
chart, because it's a string, yeah.
>> OK, any other questions?
Yes?
>> STUDENT: So you've
already answered this,
but like, when we're actually
writing this on the quiz,
do you want us to write with
slashes zeroes [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVIN: No.
The question was should you
put a slash through the zeros
to indicate if they're zeros?
No, we'll figure it out.
Yeah, thanks, they're good.
OK, anything else?
Does anybody want to-- so I think
we've run a little bit over time.
Do you want to see another one, or?
STUDENT: RandomInt.
>> DAVIN: RandomInt, OK, exactly.
So let's do RandomInt.
I'll do it over here.
So RandomInt is actually much simpler.
I think atoi is probably the hardest one
that we've asked in the previous years.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVIN: What?
ROB: I'm seeing if it's kind
of viewable from over here.
DAVIN: Is it?
ROB: I don't think it's going-- I think
it's going to run off to the right.
DAVIN: OK, so I'll do this one.
And then you just put it on the screen.
>> ROB: All right.
>> DAVIN: You want to be my scribe?
>> ROB: Yeah.
>> DAVIN: Nice.
OK, can I erase this?
>> STUDENT: Yeah.
>> DAVIN: That's so hard.
(SINGING) You're doing
what you're doing.
And doing what you don't.
All right.
>> OK, if I remember correctly, on
the quiz the RandomInt was like,
OK, I'm going to give you two
numbers, like an a and a b.
And I want you to give me a
RandomInt between those numbers.
So RandomInt is going
to take two numbers--
so RandomInt-- and it's
going to return an int.
>> So what's the return value?
I just told you.
Int, right?
Like this, and then it's
going to take two ints.
So it's going to take int
a and int b, like that.
So what RandomInt is
going to do is it's going
to return some random value
in between these two values.
So it's going to be greater
than a, less than b.
So I think you can probably assume that
a is the smaller of the two values.
So if we're dealing with
randomness, what function
have we seen that
gives us random things?
STUDENT: Drand.
DAVIN: Drand, exactly.
So you're going to probably
want to use your drand.
So you can say int random, and we'll
just say it equals 0 right now.
And they're we're going to say,
OK, random equals drand 48.
And what does this return?
What does this function give you?
>> STUDENT: Between 0 and 1.
>> DAVIN: Yeah, between 0 and 1.
So it's going to be--
>> ROB: And this is-- I think
we would tell you this.
Like, you can use drand 48.
You can verify this on the past exam.
But we'd probably say you
can use drand 48, which
returns a float between 0 and 1.
>> DAVIN: Yes, yes, I'm
pretty sure on the exam
it says you probably
want to use drand, yeah.
So it's going to return
some value between 0 and 1.
And then what are you
going to want to do?
Well, you want to multiply by--
wait, I think it's like this, sorry.
I'll just do this.
I don't know.
>> So b minus a.
So why b minus a?
So let's say drand gives you back
an int-- OK, I'll just do the rest,
so plus a.
So what does-- y is b minus a.
So let's say that drand gives you back
the maximum value it could possibly
give you.
What's that going to be?
STUDENT: 1.
>> DAVIN: 1, right?
So if this is 1, and you're
multiplying it by b minus a,
well, that's just the
difference between minus A.
And if you then add that
back onto a, that is what?
It's basically b.
Does that make sense?
>> STUDENT: Yes.
>> DAVIN: So if this is the maximum
value it could possibly be,
it's going to be 1.
And then this is just the
difference between the two.
Add on a, so this is
going to return random.
And in the corner case that
drand gives you back 1,
random will just be effectively be b.
But that's the maximum it can be.
So if it's going to be less than
that, so let's say that its like 0.9,
so then 0.9 times b minus
a is going to be less
than the difference between b minus a.
>> And then if you add that
on to a, then that value is
going to be greater than a, because
you're adding something onto it,
but it's going to be less than b.
So you're going to get a random
number, because you're calling drand.
And that rand, that random number is
going to be somewhere in between a
and b.
Does that make sense?
>> ROB: Just to put it in
concrete numbers, so
let's say we want to pick a
random number between 7 and 10.
So b minus a is our range.
So there is a range of three
numbers we want to choose from.
And then multiplying
that between 0 and 1 1,
if that then gives us some--
let's say that gives us 1.5.
>> Then 1.5, we want to go from 7 to 10.
So 1.5 plus 7 brings us
back into our 7 to 10 range.
And then we're storing it inside of
an integer, so it truncated down to 8.
And then we just return that.
So b minus a is our range.
a shifts it up into the numbers
that we want within that range.
So between 7 and 10, and then we
can return what we end up with.
>> DAVIN: Yeah, nice.
>> ROB: Thank you.
>> DAVIN: Yeah, what's up?
>> STUDENT: Do we run it to any kind of
ASCII errors when we're-- if drand is
returning a float [INAUDIBLE].
>> ROB: So just like Rob said,
because random isn't an int,
so drand will be a float.
So and then it multiplies out.
And you might get some
kind of float numbers.
And then it's going to truncate.
>> STUDENT: OK.
DAVIN: Yeah.
ROB: And if the compiler were to warn
you about, like, loss of precision,
just thrown an int in
there, and then it's good.
DAVIN: Yes?
>> STUDENT: Would it have the
same probability of getting,
like, b or a [INAUDIBLE]?
>> ROB: So is-- I'm actually
wondering-- is RandomInt supposed
to be a number from a to less than b?
Like, if it's between 7 and
10, what are the possibilities?
7, 8, and 9, or 7, 8, 9, 10?
DAVIN: I forget.
On the problem set--
>> ROB: I think it's 7, 8, 9.
>> DAVIN: It specifically says one's
inclusive and one's exclusive.
>> ROB: Yeah.
>> DAVIN: But I don't-- I'm not--
>> ROB: So I think these is
not included, in which case,
there's an equal
probability of 7, 8, and 9.
There's no probability of 10.
DAVIN: Yes?
STUDENT: I have a question.
We want to define a function
returns not one value, but an array.
Then what would be the
syntax after return?
>> DAVIN: OK, so then you
would-- after return?
So let's say you had declared
an array somewhere up there.
Then you would just return
the name of the array.
>> STUDENT: OK, thank you.
Then just return with a--
DAVIN: Oh wait, so sorry.
The question was how
do you return an array.
>> ROB: Though it couldn't
be an array declared
on the stack or anything like that.
It would have to be something
malloced, because malloc
is how you get around
automatic memory allocation.
>> DAVIN: Yes.
ROB: How you get around local scope.
>> DAVIN: But you would
just return its name--
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] it's not one
value, for example, two numbers, so
[INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVIN: You can't return multiple number.
You can't, like, return--
>> STUDENT: I talked about returning
an array or something like that.
>> DAVIN: Yeah, so the question is
can I return multiple values.
You can't return multiple values.
You can't, like, return a then
return b or something like that.
Because after you return, you
return out of the function.
And then the function is done, and
like Rob said, is on the stack.
>> So all that memory just gets
returned to the computer.
Everything gets forgotten, basically.
So if you want to return multiple
values, you have to return an array,
And the way you do that is mallocing.
And then you would return x like that.
Basically, you just return the name.
And when you return
something like this, you're
not actually returning the value.
>> So let's say you stored
the values in an array.
You're not actually
returning those values.
Like, if I returned an int, I'm
really returning copies of the values.
But if i were to return
something like this,
I'm returning a reference
to those values.
So I'm returning, basically, a
memory address to the values.
Does that make sense?
STUDENT: Yes.
DAVIN: Nice.
Yes?
>> STUDENT: When you're
using drand over here,
do you have to put srand before that?
>> DAVIN: No, no, I don't think so.
>> ROB: Yeah, so do you have
to say anything about srand?
The default of you never saying srand
at all is to just do srand of null.
So drand on its own will work.
And it will automatically seed with
the current time, is what it uses.
DAVIN: Yes?
STUDENT: Do you [INAUDIBLE]
with the numbers?
DAVIN: Yes, you can.
STUDENT: So you could
say, like, 4 times 2.
The thing is, you cannot assume
then an int is four bytes.
The only--
>> DAVIN: I mean, for the quiz you can.
[LAUGHS]
>> ROB: Mm, no.
DAVIN: Yes, yes you can.
If they ask you how big an int is,
you can't be, like, four or eight.
ROB: Oh, so if the
question is specifically,
like, if it is a coding problem,
you should say size of int.
If it is a table, or
it says how many bytes,
you shouldn't fill in size of ints.
>> STUDENTS: [LAUGHS]
>> DAVIN: Right, so why is
size of int important here?
So like, if we're going to 32-bit
processor or something like that,
then it's going to be four bytes.
But on some of the newer
stuff, it could be what?
It could be eight, right?
So this-- if you just hard code four,
then on some machines, it will work.
Some machines, it won't work.
But if on the quiz we're
like how big is an int?
Put four.
ROB: Right.
DAVIN: Yeah?
STUDENT: So because we're declaring
[INAUDIBLE] inside a function,
should we put 3 inside that function?
Or can we use it outside?
DAVIN: You can use it
outside that function.
So he's asking for free.
>> STUDENT: Lose track
of where [INAUDIBLE].
>> ROB: Oh, the free does not happen--
that's part of the magic of malloc
is that you're not
restricted to local scope.
You have full control over
how long your variables live.
So we call malloc here, it might
be a completely separate function.
It might be 10 hours later
that we finally call free.
>> DAVIN: So for example, like, a couple
weeks from now when you finally
do your dictionary speller
psets, you're going
to have some function that
creates tons of nodes.
So you're mallocing tons
of nodes in this function.
And then later in a
separate function, you're
going to want to free all those nodes.
So you can literally just pass to
free a pointer, so a memory address
to what you malloced.
And that will be fine.
You don't have to free,
like, in the same function.
Yes?
>> STUDENT: So a malloc
variable [INAUDIBLE] outside?
Is that what you're saying?
DAVIN: Wait, say that?
Sorry.
>> STUDENT: If a malloc variable
can be free anywhere in the code,
then can they be accessed
anywhere in the code?
Can you keep them local?
>> DAVIN: Oh, she asked,
like, the variable, like--
>> ROB: So you still need to
have some sort of reference
to the malloc's block of memory.
So here, we're returning x.
STUDENT: Oh.
ROB: If we didn't return x
here, and this were just void,
then we would have no access to
the pointer that was malloced ,
and it's leaked memory.
>> STUDENT: OK.
>> DAVIN: So like, let's say you
have this, like, right here.
ROB: No.
DAVIN: In my main function, I can't
just call this x and be, like, OK,
in this function, I did this.
>> ROB: Right.
>> DAVIN: So I'm going to call x in,
like, main or something like that.
You can't do that.
You're going to return something.
But what are you going to return?
You're going to return a memory address.
And because you return a memory
address, that can be accessed elsewhere.
Any more questions?
Yes?
>> STUDENT: Is the function above
being check for [INAUDIBLE]?
>> DAVIN: Why do I not need to do that?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVIN: Because you're
not mallocing anything.
So it's not-- yeah, it's
not like a string s.
It's a pointer somewhere.
These are just values.
STUDENT: OK.
DAVIN: Yeah.
Anything else?
ROB: Yep?
STUDENT: But when you [INAUDIBLE]?
>> ROB: So in order to free the
memory, we would say here.
So x is our pointer to
the block of memory.
We free that pointer.
And we wouldn't necessarily do it here.
We can do it anywhere.
But you only call free on
something that malloc returns.
So malloc, here, returned
what is being stored in x.
So we can call free on x.
Any last questions?
>> DAVIN: Any last questions?
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: Sorry, can you re-explain
why you would free in there?
Why [INAUDIBLE]?
>> DAVIN: For here?
>> STUDENT: Yeah, like right after.
DAVIN: You probably
don't want a free here.
ROB: You probably wouldn't.
DAVIN: Yeah, that this would do nothing.
This would, like, create
memory, do stuff to it,
and then immediately
forget about it, yeah.
>> ROB: But we might do, like,
in here for some reason.
We might say int star
y equals return array.
Do some stuff with y,
maybe print the contents.
And then, finally, we're done.
We can free y.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVIN: Should I scroll down?
Thanks.
ROB: Nice.
>> DAVIN: OK, that's it.
ROB: All right, good.
Good luck.
>> DAVIN: If you have questions, email us.