>> [THEME MUSIC]
>> SPEAKER 1: Hi, everyone.
Welcome back to section.
Lovely day out-- which is why, I'm
sure, there are only four of you here
and not our usual pack.
I have been sick this weekend.
So I don't have Starburst for you guys.
And I may start coughing
terribly throughout this.
So just bear with me.
I'm going to really try
and get through this first,
though, before I have a coughing attack.
But just be easy on me a
little bit-- that's all I ask.
>> So our agenda for today-- just a
reminder-- your quiz is next week.
I told you this last week so it
wouldn't catch you off guard.
So I'm reminding you again.
Next week's your quiz.
To that end, next week's
section will be much more
of-- I'll try and work in some review.
So if you guys could
help me out by sending me
things that you're comfortable
with, that you're worried about,
topics that you'd like for
me to cover, that'd be great.
So I can try and work them
into our section next week
or send you extra material or prep
that you might not get elsewhere.
>> Yeah!
More people are coming!
I thought, did I do that badly last
week, that no one wants to come back?
I'm scared.
So the other three things
that we're going to go over
are redirection, file I/O, and
then pointers and dynamic memory.
I'm sure you're all super excited about
pointers-- everyone's favorite topic,
so simple to understand.
I'm sure you guys all got that, right?
>> So first things first, redirection--
this is basically just a way
to control how you input
things into your program,
how you output things from your program.
The main ways that you guys
have been interacting with it
is just through standard out
with your print screen here.
But there are ways to
pipe-- as we see here
is one of our words-- kind
of pipe that information
or that data into a file from a file.
It's just different ways of
getting things into your program
and out of your program, instead of
just printing them to this screen
or inputting things
from the command line.
>> So first one is little
greater than caret.
So output-- it just prints the output
to a file instead of your screen.
So if you had something that printed
"Hello, world!" to the screen,
if you put it instead
to output.text, that
creates this file called output.text.
And when you open it, it'll
say "Hello, world!" in there.
This can be super useful
if you have a ton of errors
actually, as we see in this one.
If you do two caret, it'll
print the error messages.
>> So if you're having a problem with
compiling, it has a lot of errors
and you're getting bogged down in trying
to scroll through in your command line
through all them, you can
just print them to a file,
open up that file so that you
can scroll through them easier.
I actually used that a
lot when I was debugging
my 181 psets for machine learning.
So it can be super useful later on.
It's also useful if you have a program
that maybe is generating a library
or generating some set
of strings, and you
need to be able to see that
it's generating them properly.
This is the way to do that.
>> So if you print them to a file, you
can more easily examine them, right?
Versus trying to scroll
through your command line.
And then one thing to note
is that with just the greater
than caret, if you are writing
to a file that already exists--
so like if we ran this the first
time, we put it to output.text,
and then we had a second program
that printed this as program two
and did a greater than to output.text,
it will overwrite that-- so
overwrite what was ever in
that file to begin with.
>> So if you want to append
to a file, as we see here,
you just do two greater than signs.
And it will append to it.
It won't overwrite it.
So if you need to run multiple
programs and kind of keep
track of what all of them are
returning to you in a file,
that's a way to do it.
If you don't care what's in your file
and it's allowed to be overwritten,
you can just use a single greater than.
Does that make sense to everyone?
>> AUDIENCE: Like dot slash hello greater
than output dot text, like twice,
it'll just only show on output
dot text a second time--
>> SPEAKER 1: Right.
So it would basically just completely
overwrite what was there to begin with.
If this file here, the
output.text already
exists, basically whatever you call
that again with a single greater
than you can just think of it
as like it replaced the file.
Like when you're saving a Word
document and you do save as,
and you keep the same name, and
it completely overwrites it--
this is the same sort of thing.
Anyone have any questions on
just outputting to a file?
Awesome.
>> So obviously, if you reverse the
arrow direction, it can do input.
So when you guys had
like Caesar or Visioneer
and you had to input something,
you had a command line argument
that actually input it.
This is another way to do that.
So instead of waiting
for a command prompt,
like when you asked for your
message in Caesar or Visioneer,
if you had a text file
that had your message,
you could just type it into that.
>> So if this were like dot slash Caesar
3 less than arrow input text, which
is your message, that
would run just fine.
When your Caesar program actually
asked for input from the user,
it would already have it because
you've typed in this file.
That's just another way.
Just a reverse of output--
just input for your data.
>> And then the last one is pipe.
So this one's pretty cool.
Because it allows you to
take the output of one
program and put it as
input to another program.
I don't know if any of you
played with the decipher
that CS50 might have
given you, but it would
allow you to take some sample
file, type it into your encryption,
and then from there type
that into your decryption
to make sure it turned out the same.
So it's kind of like three-way loop.
Go for it.
>> AUDIENCE: If a program
has multiple inputs,
is there a way to tell it which input
to use the text file or the output for?
>> SPEAKER 1: It has multiple inputs.
Whatever file your input-- when it's
asking for input that first time, it's
going to assume, I think, it's
going to pipe in the entire file.
So if you have multiple inputs, you're
going to be piping in multiple files.
So if you're asking for messages
three times in your code,
you're going to be putting
in three different files.
And it gets crazy.
And you shouldn't have to
worry about that right now.
But that's the idea.
>> So yeah, pipe is just output of one
program uses input into the other.
Everyone good there?
Cool.
OK.
You probably won't have
to do too much with it.
But you should understand
ways you can use this.
And there are some cases that
you might want to use it.
>> So file I/O-- I know what you're
saying-- we're used to reading from
and writing to our screen there,
which is standard in and standard out.
And that's what you guys have been
doing since the beginning of class here.
But you can also read and write files,
which is all file I/O-- so file input,
output is all it stands for.
So this basically means that
you can store your data now.
>> When you just print it to the
screen, it's basically gone, right?
As soon as you make "Hello
world" and run "Hello world"
it prints "Hello world" to the screen.
But you can't really do
anything with it from there.
If you store in a text
file, then suddenly
you have this data that you're allowed
to manipulate or put it into a file,
or put it into a program later.
One of the reasons
why we do this is just
as a way to store data for later use.
>> I have a couple of steps here
just walking through standard
I/O. In step one, you
need to create a reference
to the file with all
caps FILE star file.
So that creates a pointer to a file.
So then you want to open it.
And you say, literally,
just file equals fopen.
And this is going to return a
pointer to the file you just opened.
I saw a couple of you
guys at office hours.
>> But one of the things
is remember-- pointers
can be some address or null, right?
If we ever have a case where
something can return null,
what do we have to do
before we ever use it?
We need to check if
it's null or not, right?
Because some of you may have had
the issue where whatever object
was being returned in breakout was null.
You tried to perform
some function on it.
And your computer site faulted.
Right?
I bet a couple of you
may have had that issue.
>> So with fopen, fopen will either
return a pointer to the file,
or if something goes wrong,
it's going to return null.
So you always need to check
that it has not returned null
before you attempt to do anything else.
This is like a standard paradigm
that you're going to need here.
If there's ever a chance that
something could return null,
check to make sure it
doesn't before you proceed.
Otherwise, you're going
to get lovely site faults.
And no one likes to deal with those.
>> So as we see here, the first argument
is just the path to the file.
If that file doesn't exist,
it's going to create that file.
And it's just going to be blank.
And then the second argument
is the mode that you want.
Do we want to read from this file?
Do you want to write from it?
Do you want to append?
So actually what I just said--
if the file doesn't exist
and you're trying to read from
it, it's going to throw an error.
If the file name-- like if
file.text doesn't exist yet
and you want to write
to it, it will create
a blank file called file.text for you.
And if you want to append,
you should do the same thing.
Does that make sense?
If you're trying to read from
a file that doesn't exist yet,
it'll throw an error.
Otherwise, it will create the file
for you do what you want to it.
Cool.
Now we can read from the file.
And this is just kind of going
through the different functions
that we have for file I/O. This will
be necessary in this week's pset,
if I remember correctly.
Yes, it absolutely will be
necessary in this week's pset.
So fgetc returns the next character.
fgets just returns a line of text.
It will return anything up to
a new line, and it will break.
So fread reads a certain
number of bytes and places them
into an array, which
is something you might
want to do with re-size--
might be useful.
>> How many people have read
the pset spec, by the way?
OK.
[INAUDIBLE]
>> SPEAKER 1: OK.
All right.
Definitely read that-- it's a fun pset.
You get to recover a deleted memory
card-- really exciting when it works.
But definitely, start reading that.
Come talk to me if you
have questions about it.
>> OK, so as I was saying, fread
reads a certain number of bytes.
That's some arbitrary number
that you're going to set.
And then fseek just moves
to a certain position.
So maybe you don't care
about the next 10 bytes.
You just want to skip ahead.
You don't care about those.
You want to read starting at byte 11.
fseek allows you to do that.
So it allows you to be selective
about what you're reading.
Because fgetc, fgets, and fread read
from a certain place in the file.
>> A way to think about this is if this
is our file, when you first open it,
you have this position in file
that starts at the beginning.
Whenever you call
fgetc, fgetf, or fread,
it's going to start from
this position marker.
Let's say you just want to read
this chunk of memory over here.
You can't just call.
You have to seek over here
and then read from there
or read, gets, or getc,
depending on what you want.
So seek just allows you to
skip portions of memory.
And that's the only
way you can skip things
without reading them into your buffer.
Does that make sense to everyone?
>> Obviously, there's a
lot of parallel here--
our output, or input redirection,
you have read and write.
So fputc just writes a
character into the file.
fputs writes a line.
Fprintf prints a formatted output.
So if you have tabs,
or space, or whatnot.
And then fwrite writes some
array of bytes to a file.
So this is the same way
fwrite and fread are analogous
opposites-- fgets, fputs, and
then fputc and fgetc-- lots
of crazy, quick things.
>> Just kind of keep this handy--
you'll have different times
where maybe you just want
one character at a time.
Maybe you want a whole line.
With your dictionary pset--
which is in two psets,
I believe, we give you a whole
dictionary in a text format
which has every word
separated by a line.
So if you wanted to read
in one word at a time,
what might you use if you're reading
and they're all separated on new lines,
and you just want one word at a time?
>> AUDIENCE: Fgets
>> SPEAKER 1: Right.
Fgets-- because that returns
whatever is on one line.
And if every word is its
own line, we can use fgets.
Cool.
Does that make sense, everyone?
Cool?
Yeah, we're going to get to
the fun part with pointers
very soon, where you
get to do some math.
And it'll be great.
>> Last step-- close your file.
With so many things here,
one of our paradigms
is if it can return
null, check for null.
If you open something,
you'd better close it.
OK, so you're not done until you're
done unless you've closed it.
Kind of like it's not over
until the fat lady sings.
That's like closing your file.
As it says here, just
to reiterate, always
open your file before you're
reading or writing to it.
And always close it if you've opened it.
All right?
Cool.
>> So here's an example.
So tiny-- I don't know if you
guys can see that very well.
If only we could increase
the brightness somehow.
Let me actually do this if I can.
OK, you guys can't really
see that at all, can you?
OK, we're going to do this, then.
[INAUDIBLE]
>> I assume this is much better to see.
Can anyone see where my
mouse went is the question?
Ah, there it is-- what struggles!
>> OK.
Basically, you guys should have kind
of an idea of what this is doing.
It's not perfect.
But I'd rather explain it than spend
more time trying to format it properly.
Basically, as you see here,
we start with file open.
And we have some
database file that we are
opening that says it's our students.
And we're going to write to it.
So of course, return null.
So we have to check for null.
And then if it's not
null, we go through.
And as you see, we're
looping through here.
There are students.
Students is hash defined as three.
And what we're doing is we are
printing to the file, right?
So what are we printing out to our file?
>> AUDIENCE: The scores
that are in the array?
>> SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
The scores that are in
the array-- exactly.
So we are opening this
database file, which
I assume is some sort
of grades database.
And we're just printing out the
scores of each student to that file.
Cool?
Good.
Awesome.
OK.
Let's get back to--
>> AUDIENCE: I have a quick question.
Is the printf not in the for loop?
That's just in the if loop?
SPEAKER 1: No, it's in the for loop.
I cannot see my mouse very well up here.
So I'm struggling to
format that properly.
This bracket should be gone.
It should be down here.
This is what's in your for loop.
There.
Now it's pretty.
So that's how it should be-- except
for that last bracket that I dismissed.
OK.
Does that make sense to everyone?
We're going to move on
to the next thing then--
which, actually, you're going
to need to see the code.
So I'm just going to
copy that over right now.
OK.
So I'm going to show you guys this code.
And I want you to try and figure
out what it's supposed to do.
>> So given that-- take a minute or so.
Try and figure out what's going on here.
>> Any ideas?
>> We know that we have at least two
arguments in the command line, right?
I assume one of which is going to be
that [INAUDIBLE] of our program is
and then something else.
Because if [INAUDIBLE] is less
than two, we yell at them.
Right?
And from the usage, it looks like
it's going to be some sort of file.
We all agree to that?
So now, what's the loop doing?
What's it going through?
>> AUDIENCE: All the files.
SPEAKER 1: Exactly.
It's going through all the
files that we've input there.
So for each file, it's
opening up some string there.
It's opening up that file.
Right?
And it's reading from it.
Of course, checking if it's null.
And then it's printing.
If it's null, it's just telling us
that that's not a file that exists.
Because remember, with
read our file has to exist.
Right?
With write and append,
you can get away with it.
But with read, our file has to exist.
>> And then if it does exist,
what are we doing here?
Let's just start here.
What's this do-- this first character.
What does it do?
He gets one character, right?
So what is this doing?
It's getting the first character.
Anyone know EOF?
>> AUDIENCE: End of file?
>> SPEAKER 1: End of file-- exactly.
So it's going to go through
the entire file, right?
And then it's going to update by
getting every subsequent character.
Right?
And what's it doing?
AUDIENCE: Putting that in--
>> SPEAKER 1: Putchar prints
to your screensaver.
[INAUDIBLE] the character.
And then when it [INAUDIBLE]
this will close the file.
>> AUDIENCE: Do you not need an [? else? ?]
>> SPEAKER 1: Not necessarily.
I mean, it's kind of implied in this.
Because this returns, though, as long
as this doesn't catch this, you're fine.
I mean it's probably good
practice to do an else.
But an else is not always
necessary especially
if you have something
like a return, which
means that in this case if it catches
it, your program's going to end
and it'll never get to this.
It's more for the case where you're
not necessarily returning something.
Because if this wasn't
returning anything,
it would mean that if this were true,
the rest of this would still run.
And in that case, you
would want a false.
If it's returning, and
your program's ending,
an else isn't necessary all
the time, depending on context.
Jacob, did you have a question?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
So does fgetc get the next character?
How does the character increase?
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So fgetc gets the next character.
You can think of it like C++ in a sense.
>> AUDIENCE: So what was EOF?
>> SPEAKER 1: EOF is end of file.
It's just a marker that lets you know
that you're at the end of your file.
So this is going to print
to your standard out.
And then it's going to close
the file when it's done.
And then let's go to
the next file, right?
So overall, what does this program do?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
It just prints out everything there.
So if you guys have ever used CAT
and then the name of some file--
I don't know if any of you have
ever done that on your terminal.
But if you ever use the
command CAT-- C-A-T--
and then whatever file
you have there-- it
prints it out to your terminal, which
can be super handy for some things.
I use it a lot.
Does that make sense to everyone?
Cool?
>> OK so your task now-- either by
yourself or with the people around you--
is to just write a simple program
that will just write "Hello, world!"
out to a file.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> SPEAKER 1: I was like, did
I do that badly last week?
I didn't think it was that bad.
I'm glad you're all here.
It really makes me happy.
I'm a girl of simple pleasures.
I just like when my section attends.
So I'm just getting this started for
you guys so that we can code together.
I don't like putting anyone on
the spot unless you want to be.
>> AUDIENCE: For the quiz, do
we have to write a program?
>> SPEAKER 1: You may be asked to
write simple programs by hand.
Yup.
>> AUDIENCE: The quiz is next week, right?
>> SPEAKER 1: The quiz is next Wednesday.
That means there's a lovely [? CSE ?]
grading party afterwards, which
means you'll get your scores
back that night-- at what time?
Who knows?
But it will be that night.
>> All right.
How do we want to start this?
I'll give you a hint-- starts with this.
>> AUDIENCE: You have to open a file.
>> SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So what do you want to call this?
Do you just want to call it "file"?
Let's make it easy.
So fopen-- what's our
output test going to be?
Call it "Hello."
And what is our mode?
What are we doing to this file?
>> AUDIENCE: Read.
Writing.
SPEAKER 1: We're writing to it.
Lovely.
OK, so we have this file now.
What do we need to do?
AUDIENCE: Check if it's null.
SPEAKER 1: Check if it's null-- exactly.
That's what I like to hear.
That should be automatic, especially
pretty much from this point on.
If you start segfaulting, you probably
didn't check for null somewhere.
Nine times out of ten, that's
going to be your error.
So if you could just get in the
habit, always check if it's null,
your life's going to be
nice and easy-- or easier.
>> So check to see if it's null.
So if it's not null, which
is what the bang equals
means-- not null-- it's valid.
What do we want to do?
We just want to print
to that file, right?
So what are we going to use?
>> AUDIENCE: Fprintf
>> SPEAKER 1: Fprintf-- lovely.
And fprintf takes two arguments-- where
it's going and what we want printed.
So what's the first one?
Where is it going?
>> AUDIENCE: File.
>> SPEAKER 1: It's going to file.
And what do we want printed?
"Hello, world!"
All right.
We have one last thing--
another big paradigm here.
AUDIENCE: Close.
SPEAKER 1: Close.
There you go.
>> AUDIENCE: Is this happening
if the file is null?
SPEAKER 1: No, this is if it's not null.
AUDIENCE: Oh, if it's not-- OK.
For the fopen and then the
two arguments that go inside,
what does the first argument mean again?
>> SPEAKER 1: The argument is
just like the name of the file
that you want to go to.
So after this runs, you would
have some file called "hello"
that had "Hello, world" within it.
That's all.
Just the name.
>> AUDIENCE: And since it's writing, the
file doesn't have to already exist.
Is that what you said?
>> SPEAKER 1: Right.
Exactly.
If "Hello" as a file
doesn't exist yet, it's
going to create a file called
Hello" and write to it for you.
>> AUDIENCE: When you're telling
the program to wrote to the file,
why do you write "file" instead of
the name of the file and fprintf--
>> SPEAKER 1: Because in this case, we have
that large FILE-- all in caps-- star,
file.
So it's a pointer to the file
that you're talking about.
This is the way that
we just refer to it.
So in this case, you
can think of file-- aha,
we can use this-- file here
refers to the opening of "Hello"
and letting it write.
>> AUDIENCE: Could we put a "Hello"
instead [? of just ?] f file?
SPEAKER 1: No, because "Hello"
needs to be open and writeable.
File here is like a
designator that says OK, we
have this file-- hello--
that we're looking at.
It has been opened.
And we are going to write to it.
If you just use "Hello",
that is encapsulated in it.
So it's going to freak out.
I mean, you could have named it.
You could have done file,
star, "Hello", equals that.
But the whole point is that you
need a file star pointer in order
to be able to use these functions.
AUDIENCE: Could you do
file, star, file, "Hello"
or do you have to put
file star, file by it?
SPEAKER 1: You could
do file, star, "Hello."
You can change this to
whatever name you want.
It's completely arbitrary
what that name is.
You can name it anything.
Name it flying spaghetti, if you wanted.
>> AUDIENCE: What is the "w" in quotes for?
>> SPEAKER 1: The "w" is just the mode.
So we're writing to this file.
Everyone good?
Clear?
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: So when it writes this
file, where do we then find that file?
>> SPEAKER 1: It'll be in the same
directory that you're currently in.
If you're in pset three and
you run this, within your pset
three folder is going to be
this file called "Hello."
Cool?
Everyone good?
I feel like you're all
getting it, which is great.
OK.
So back to my slide show--
I love when things work.
OK, pointers-- Are you guys excited?
Pointers are great.
They take a little bit
to wrap your head around.
This is my second year
teaching pointers.
And I think I finally got it.
So if you struggle, it's OK.
As I said before, drawing pictures
helps a lot with things in CS,
as much as I think people tend
to think oh, we're at a computer.
We should just code.
No-- drawing pictures
will really help you.
And I really encourage you to
tap into your kindergartner side
and bring out crayons
or markers and draw.
Because it will help you.
And if you see me at office hours, I
will be carrying around stacks of paper
with pens drawing things out.
>> So especially with
pointers-- draw pictures.
And I'm sure we're actually going to
be drawing some pictures here too.
>> So you guys all got to see Binky,
this cool claymation thing.
And we think it's really funny when
he explodes into a bunch of pieces.
It's some comic relief for class.
C [INAUDIBLE] this great ability
to be able to control memory.
And it's one of the things that really
makes it such a powerful language.
But with great power comes
great responsibility.
And crazy things can happen
if you're not careful.
So when you're using
pointers, you want to make
sure you really understand
exactly what you're doing.
Hopefully the next little bit of
time will help you really understand
pointers, how to use them,
and how to manipulate them.
>> So memory-- I'm sure we've
seen this diagram before.
So this is just a simple diagram of
how things might be stored memory.
So you basically have these
huge arrays of one byte blocks
is what we have here-- slight
increments by one each time.
This is in hex [INAUDIBLE]
so eight-bit blocks.
And every block is associated
with some hexadecimal address.
So if you ever see the
0x, that's just notating
that it's a hexadecimal address.
You can assume this means
some address in memory.
We're talking about memory addresses
whenever you see hexadecimal.
>> We have ints are variables,
floats are variables that store.
So ints store ints.
Floats store floats.
So we also have pointers
that store memory addresses.
That's a sort of mapping.
Pointers are exclusively
for memory addresses.
So that's like your type there.
Your appliance is 32-bit, which means
that your memory address is four bytes.
So any pointer that you have
is also going to be four bytes.
Or else if it's four bytes,
memory is four bytes.
Pointers store memory.
Therefore, they're four bytes.
Cool-- just want to reinforce that.
>> You should get this comic now.
I don't know how many of you
are xkcd fans, but I love xkcd.
It's great.
>> All right.
So creating pointers-- as I said, it's
pretty much just like anything else.
You have a type.
You have a name.
Right?
That's what we have there.
[? Hex ?] star means it's a pointer,
and then whatever you want to call it.
So the type represents
what you can store.
All right?
In the same way that if we do ints,
we know we're storing an int there.
With a pointer, it
holds a memory address.
But what it means is that-- here's where
a drawing is going to come in handy.
So in this case, we have
some value-- let's say four.
Four is at address one.
OK?
>> This first one here means
that it's a pointer 2x.
Right?
It's some pointer x.
x may be something, whatever.
Whatever x is-- say x is four.
It's going to store the
memory address here.
So int, star, x-- this is
some other slot in memory--
who knows what this is.
But it's going to store an address here.
So this would be like--
in this case, Whatever,
is stored at 0x1-- whatever is stored
at the address that our pointer holds,
has to match up with
what we've designated.
So at 0x1, in this case, this is x.
This can only ever be a
int while we're using this.
>> Similarly, if we have
another 1y, whatever
address is stored with a y has
to be a char-- same thing with z.
In the same way, whenever you
try and do intx equals 0.4,
it's going to yell at you and be
like no, you said you wanted an int.
This is supposed to be an int.
Stop trying to make it a float.
>> So let things be what they want to be.
Let things be themselves.
So big thing is just
whatever type of pointer
it is, that's the only
thing you can store there.
OK?
With practice, as with
last week, everything
seems really kind of abstract.
We're going to do some practice.
It should make more sense.
>> So referencing and dereferencing-- it's
really important to get these straight.
I still have to refresh
every now and then.
And I'm like wait, which one do I want?
So the ampersand will actually give
you the reference or address of.
So it returns the address in
memory of which variable is stored.
So it's going to actually return to you
a hexadecimal, whereas dereferencing it
is actually going to give you
the data that is stored there.
OK?
So we're going to look at an example
really fast, or actually up next.
>> OK.
So we have to think really
carefully about this.
So here we have some integer x.
I'm going to try and draw this
out to the best of my abilities.
So we're going to have this slot x.
And it's storing five.
Its address is 0x4.
Cool?
All good.
>> So now we have this pointer.
It was over here.
And the ampersand gives us
the address of something.
So, in this case, it's the address of x.
What is the address of x?
04-- and this pointer is at 0x08.
Cool?
So you can think about this
pointer, 04, just points over here.
And they're called pointers
because as we get more into this,
you're going to see pointing to things.
And one block pointing to another
block will make a lot more sense.
So here are two.
And then we have some
copy, which is what-- 0x0c.
And it's going to
dereference our pointer.
>> So what it's saying is
OK, here's our pointer.
The value it stores is 0x04, And what
it's saying is go to this address
and tell me what's in it.
So that's effectively
what this arrow is doing.
You can think of this like your star.
So OK, when we do star, it means follow.
Go to this address.
And that's basically just following
this arrow to this memory chunk.
And give us what's in it, which is 5.
It's why our copy is equal to 5.
Does that make sense?
Does anyone need me to go through
that again, or more slowly?
You want me to go
through it one more time?
OK.
We're going to redraw it again.
When we start, we all agree we have
some chunk of memory that's a variable
x that we set equal to 5.
We don't control where it is in memory.
So this spot is just
arbitrarily assigned.
Good there?
OK.
Then we initialize a pointer to an int.
That's why it's allowed to point to
x because we have an int in here.
We have another chunk of
memory because this pointer
is a variable just like anything else.
It's arbitrarily assigned
some space in memory.
And what it stores is the address of x.
Ampersand means address of x.
So what is the address of x?
>> AUDIENCE: It's zero--
SPEAKER 1: 0x04.
So then-- last one.
We have some copy-- again
just another variable.
So let's assign some arbitrary place.
And we dereference our pointer.
The star means go to the
address stored in my pointer.
Tell me what's there.
So the address stored
in our pointer is 0x04.
So we go to that address.
It's pointing to that address.
What's inside this memory block?
It's a five.
So that's what we assign our copy.
Everyone good?
Cool.
Again-- pictures.
>> So tracking the values here-- I'm
going to let you guys think about this.
We can draw another picture.
But I want you to try and reason
through this on your own for a minute.
>> Since they didn't give
us an example address,
I'm just going to do ampersand x--
which should help drive it home.
Ampersand means address.
>> So in the first one, everyone
go with the first line.
Some x set's five-- some
random slot in memory.
Int star pointer is equal
to the address of x, right?
Int star pointer creates
this block, calls it pointer,
and assigns it to the address of x.
I'm terrible at ampersands.
>> Now what we're doing is we say
OK, dereference our pointer.
So we go OK, what's in our pointer?
It's ampersand x.
Go to ampersand x and reassign it.
>> So now, ampersand x is going to be 35.
So basically, when you're
dereferencing, you go OK.
You're going to be drawing
pictures like this.
your arrows over where it is.
So go to this slot in memory and either
give me that value back, or alter it.
In this case, because we're at this
value, we're assigning it to be 35.
Whereas in the last
one, if you notice, we
were assigning what was
in here to something else.
>> So they have this awesome table.
It's not that bad.
You guys work on it.
I'm going to draw it out on the board.
We're going to fill it out together, OK?
So grab some paper, grab
a partner, start working.
I'm going to get a
bigger piece of chalk.
Because it's going to be a lot.
OK.
PROFESSOR: OK.
Let's start with the first row.
We'll start there, then you guys
can maybe work through some more.
OK.
a equals b times c so what is a?
It's not a trick question, I promise.
>> STUDENT: 4 times 5.
>> PROFESSOR: 4 times 5.
20.
So what's b?
STUDENT: 4.
>> PROFESSOR: And c?
STUDENT: 5.
PROFESSOR: 5.
And then this is just going to
be ampersand a, ampersand b,
ampersand c, right?
Not bad.
It's simple enough.
OK.
So the next one.
A equals a times c, in case
anyone was unfamiliar with that.
Is everyone familiar
with the times equals?
OK, all this means-- this is
shorthand for a equals a times c.
You can also do it with division,
with addition, with subtraction.
You can do a equals, or a plus equals c
means a equals a plus c, a minus equal
c would be a equals a minus c.
It's just syntactic sugar.
>> So, in this case, a is equal to
a times c would give us what?
Again, not a trick question.
>> STUDENT: 100.
>> PROFESSOR: 100.
Does anything else change?
No.
Maybe I will finally get
better at my ampersands.
>> STUDENT: OK, sorry, how did you get 100?
PROFESSOR: OK.
So a is equal to a
times c, so a times c.
STUDENT: Oh, you're using
a for the previous--
PROFESSOR: Yes.
So these are our most recent values.
These are what you should be
using as we move down, OK.
So, b is the only thing changing, right?
So let's fill in everything else.
B. What is b going to be?
To be or not to be.
So what is this doing?
What is the star pa doing?
>> STUDENT: Code to the location of pa.
>> STUDENT: No, not quite.
So this is a d reference.
>> STUDENT: So b is handed value of pa.
>> PROFESSOR: Yeah, so pa is
the address of a, right?
So it's saying go to where a is
stored and give it that value.
So what is b?
STUDENT: 100.
PROFESSOR: 100.
Perfect.
OK, so pc is what's changing.
Everything else stays the same.
What is pc going to be?
Simple assignment.
Pc is equal to pa, and what is pa?
>> STUDENT: Ampersand a.
PROFESSOR: Perfect.
Now we're getting interesting.
OK, let's break this one down.
First, what's b times c, because that's
the easy part of this one, right?
B times c is--
>> STUDENT: 500.
>> PROFESSOR: Yeah, so
what is this one doing,
if it's star pb, what's changing?
>> STUDENT: What's in the--
PROFESSOR: What's in b?
STUDENT: What's in the space
that pb is pointing to.
PROFESSOR: And pb is pointing to--
STUDENT: B.
PROFESSOR: B. So the only
thing changing is b, right.
So b times c, 500.
So that's what changes now.
Cool.
Lovely.
You guys are doing great.
All right, breaking this one down.
C is changing, right?
So we can fill in everything else.
Let's see.
OK.
We know that c is going to be the
product of two numbers, right?
What two numbers, though?
>> STUDENT: A and c?
>> PROFESSOR: So a is
right for the first one.
So we're d referencing p of a, right?
P of a points to a, so we know that
this is going to be 100 times what?
Times what does pc point to?
Points to a.
So 100 times 100 is 10,000.
Does that makes sense?
Cool.
Home stretch, guys, last row.
OK.
What's changing here?
>> STUDENT: A.
PROFESSOR: A. Perfect, so
everything else can stay the same.
OK.
And what is a?
So it's a times what?
This is star pb.
So star pb means here's
pb, pb points to b.
>> STUDENT: 500.
>> PROFESSOR: 500.
So we have 500 times 100.
That's 50,000.
Whew!
Look at that.
>> STUDENT: Why do we have
the &c for the last--
PROFESSOR: Sorry.
STUDENT: Oh, OK.
PROFESSOR: My bad.
Lots of writing.
Everyone good?
Not too bad, right?
Just takes a little
while to work through.
If you break it down,
understand what each part
is referring to-- as
with everything it's,
yes-- break it down to the little
problems and then recombine,
and you can do some awesome stuff.
There are the answers, but we did that.
Pointer arithmetic.
Ah.
My hands are all chalky.
So adding or subtracting
int adjusts the pointer
by the size of the type of pointer.
Remember how every type
has a different size?
So like a double or a long long is
eight and int is four but char is one.
>> So what you want to do
is-- one thing to remember
is just that how much your
pointer value actually changes
will depend on the
type of pointer it is.
Everyone good with this?
Can I erase it?
We're good?
Awesome.
>> So if we have some pointer
that-- this is going to be-- I'm
going to make it an int pointer.
It stores this.
If you were to say pointer
plus one, what it's going to do
is it's going to update
it by the size of an int
because that's the
type of pointer it is.
>> With C, everything is
very strict and regulated.
The int pointer is going to update by
the amount of space an int would take.
An int is four bytes.
>> So what would this turn into?
You're just adding four onto this.
Now your pointer would be-- OK.
>> So if it was a char and we did pointer
plus one, what would it be now?
If it started-- pretending we
started-- right now it's 0x08.
Let's now say that this was a
char pointer, and we added one.
What would it change to?
How many bytes is a char?
>> AUDIENCE: One.
>> SPEAKER 1: One.
AUDIENCE: So 0x09.
SPEAKER 1: So it would be nine.
So just something to remember.
Just when you add one, it's not
adding one unless it's a char.
It's adding how many
bytes the type that it is,
which is why we have
this equation up here.
So it's int times the size
of the type of pointer.
>> So we have the example here.
y was assigned to that value, 0x4,
when we did y plus equals one.
What's in it, what's
in x, doesn't change.
What does change is what's in y.
The address stored in y updated by four
because there are four bytes in an int
and it's an int pointer.
>> All right.
So now we have another exercise.
So the question is what will print.
Any ideas?
>> AUDIENCE: The number of
characters in happy cat?
SPEAKER 1: Exactly.
So like with your string.
Does everyone get that?
Do we want to walk through it?
>> Yes, OK.
So what we have here-- I
like this so much more.
I don't have to
[INAUDIBLE] ridiculously.
>> So we have our string here, happy cat.
Lovely.
We have some counter that
we're keeping track of.
So we have some char* pointer
that just is set equal to str.
What this is doing is it's
assigning some pointer
to the beginning of your string.
Because I'm sure, as it
was mentioned in lecture,
we've given you guys this
data type called string.
>> But really strings are just
an array of-- like char*.
It's a pointer to a bunch of characters
that are contiguous in memory.
So this just sets it
equal to any string is
identified by where
its first character is.
So this is just setting some point
equal to the beginning of the string.
Everyone good there?
Cool.
>> So this is dereferencing our pointer.
So it's actually going to
give us some value in here,
in our string that we're talking about.
And we're saying as long as
it's not null terminator.
So keep going until you get
to the end of the string.
Update your pointer by one.
So r, it will actually update by one
each time because this is a char,
the char*.
>> So it's going to go through.
It's going to update.
So the first time this runs,
it's going to be here at h.
It's going to update.
>> It'll be an a.
It'll be a p, y, and so on and so forth.
We'll update counter.
When it reaches the end, it
just prints how far it's gotten.
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: So It counts
the space as one, right?
OK.
>> SPEAKER 1: Think so.
Is that a question--
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: No worries.
This I do that.
All right, so one thing I
understand is that with an array,
you can also treat it as a
pointer because arrays are just
continuous spots of memory.
>> So you can treat it the same way.
You can manipulate them
with pointers, too.
So instead of doing, in this
case, the analogous thing
would be array 0 equals 1.
>> But in the same way that
a string is determined
by the start of where
its first character is,
an array is determined by
where its first element is.
Because we know, we're
guaranteed, that these
are going to be continuous
blocks of memory.
That's what allows us to do this.
We know they're continuous
blocks of memory.
>> So in this case, by dereferencing
just array, that tells us,
OK, go to the start of
your array, which is here.
So you can set it equal to one.
And in this case, whatever your array
type is, when you update it by one,
that's just like updating
it to the next index.
You can do that because you
know what's in your array.
So it knows how much to
update your pointer by,
what address to update it to so
that you're at the next slot.
>> So this is just a different way
of writing array 0 equals 1,
array 1 equals 2, array
bracket 2 equals 3.
It's just another way to think about it.
Because they are continuous
blocks in memory,
you can refer to them either
by the array notation--
which I personally
find easier-- but maybe
you need to manipulate it
strictly by memory addresses.
And this is the way you would do that.
Kind of more of like a
cool thing you could do
versus maybe not something you're
actually going to implement.
>> I use it in 61.
You guys probably don't need
to worry about it too much.
But if you're interested,
take 61 next year.
We're in the home stretch guys.
I know, it's long.
Dynamic Memory Allocation--
so we know that one
of things when we talked during
our first section together,
we looked at a swap
function where it was
outside the scope of our main function.
And we were passing in these values
that were effectively copies.
>> And once swap finished
executing, it just left a stack.
Remember, we have a
stack frame for swap.
It leaves and those
values leave with it.
And they were gone.
We couldn't do anything
with them and we were sad
because we can't swap our values.
>> But with C, as I mentioned, you
have a lot of power over memory.
So what you can do is you can
allocate things on the heap here
that will stay there until
you tell them otherwise.
>> They're like good children.
They stay there.
They don't leave.
They'll stay there until you're
like, OK, you can go away.
>> Whereas things on the stack, who--
they're like naughty children.
They'll just run away when you want
to be there and then they're gone.
You can't get them back.
>> So the heap is-- we're going to
talk about malloc and free, which
I'm sure you guys
heard about in lecture.
And that's basically a way
to have very persistent data.
So you can keep the data
around as long as you want.
Mhm.
>> AUDIENCE: Can you define heap and stack?
Are they like places to put things?
>> SPEAKER 1: So they're
basically just-- they're
the way we refer just to memory.
So heap is just places where
memory is allocated dynamically,
whereas stack refers
more to stack frames
that are more central to the
functions that are actually running.
You don't really have control.
>> The big difference, you have control
over the heap if you want to.
You have less control over the stack.
The stack depends on the
functions that are running,
and the order in which they are
run, and how things are returned.
Whereas with the heap, as
we'll see, you can say,
OK, I want this value to be
around until I tell you otherwise.
You are not allowed to get rid of it.
You're not allowed to override it.
You're going to keep it around
for as long as I tell you.
You get to be the boss in the heap,
whereas the stack-- maybe if you
like finagle your way
you can be the boss.
But not quite.
And it's really just memory.
It's just different ways
of referring to memory.
>> Cool.
So with that, how to
control your memory.
It's with malloc, which
you're going to get to use.
So it's just short
for memory allocation.
That's all it is.
There's a bunch of other cool
functions that have alloc at the end,
and they stand for different things.
>> So when you need storage that needs
to outlast your current function so
that when your current
function runs away,
you still have the data that you
got from it, you want to use malloc.
That'll initialize it on the heap.
And like I said and keep
saying, you'll keep it there
until you tell it otherwise,
which is the important thing here.
>> So one thing to notice, and
that's typically really important,
is that this sizeof
is super useful to use
because depending on the type
of machine you're running,
it may have varying amounts
of memory that it takes.
So you always want to use size of so
that you're not machine dependent,
so that your code will
run on any machine.
>> And that's just part
of writing good code.
If it works on one machine,
but not any of the others,
how useful was your program?
So you always want to
make sure and use sizeof.
>> AUDIENCE: So is that like the
size of 10 inches [INAUDIBLE]?
>> SPEAKER 1: This is the size of 10 ints.
yeah.
So size of ints will return
how much does one int take.
Or size of char, how
much does one char take.
And then how many blocks
of that do you want?
>> So in this case, we want something
that we can store 10 ints to.
And it will work regardless
of machine, which is cool.
So how many bytes will
that actually give you?
Quick math.
>> AUDIENCE: 40.
SPEAKER 1: 40.
Exactly.
So another big thing.
Pointer or malloc can return null.
>> So again, always check to
see if it returned null
before you try and do anything with it.
If you try and dereference
this pointer now,
it's just going to segfault
because you went and tried
to touch null when you shouldn't have.
So always check for null.
Again, all you can do.
>> It might return null.
It'll return null if you're either
out of space, or for whatever reason
it ran into some memory bug.
It sometimes just returns null.
So you just have to check for it.
That's all this slide is saying.
And then what we have
here is a call to free.
So in the same way that if you
open a file you must close a file,
if you malloc memory, you
must you free that memory.
And you guys will get
to do really cool stuff.
>> And there's a program you can run to
see if you're ever leaking memory.
But you don't want to leak memory.
It's really bad.
Just mess up things.
>> It's bad to do just like programming
wise for design efficiency.
But it's also just kind
of bad for your computer.
So just free things
when you malloc them.
>> You guys see the symmetries here.
Super simple.
Just free and then
whatever your pointer,
whatever the name of
your pointer is, and it
will take care of freeing it for you.
Cool.
>> Then we have this.
So we're just going to
walk through this program.
And then you guys are done.
>> So [INAUDIBLE] just main.
So we have some int* pointer.
So we have a pointer
that's going to hold ints.
And how many ints is it going to hold?
Just one.
Size of an int.
>> We check to see if
pointer is null because it
is, we want to say don't do anything.
It's bad.
So we print some error out of
memory, most often return 1,
as you guys are used to.
>> And then we have here, we
dereference our pointer.
So that means we're going to store
something at the location given to us.
Int* pointer, or malloc, returns the
address of where it set aside this
memory for you.
So it's basically
giving you like-- if you
think about a bunch of
houses in a neighborhood
that you want to put
your furniture in, malloc
is like OK, you get
to go to house three.
And it gives you the
address of house three.
>> So this right now, this
pointer stores an address,
stores the address of your house.
*ptr means, OK, I'm at my house.
Cool.
I need to get some integer.
>> So you're asking for someone
to give you furniture now.
So you get some int.
And it puts it in your pointer
where it's pointing to.
>> And then it just prints
out, you entered wherever.
And again, the reference.
So this is like you went to this
address and you saw what was there.
Cool?
>> And then of course we free our pointer.
Don't forget to free your pointer.
Don't forget to check for null.
You have two things you remember from
this, or that you should remember.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] stuff
like that, the char*s.
How come we never free those?
>> SPEAKER 1: Hm?
>> AUDIENCE: Are those like strings?
You said strings are
just like char*s, right?
So why don't we free strings?
>> SPEAKER 1: You only to
free if you're mallocing.
AUDIENCE: Oh, if you're mallocing.
SPEAKER 1: So malloc
and free are two things
that you should always have together.
f open, f close, two things
you should have together.
In both those cases, check for null.
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: So free is just
allowing something else
to be stored there after
this program has used it?
>> SPEAKER 1: It's just saying,
OK, I'm done with this.
You don't need to keep it around.
Otherwise your computer will
just like try and keep it there.
And then you can't-- it runs
into memory issues later.
You always want to free it because
it tells your computer, OK, I'm
done with this spot of memory.
You can have it back
for me to use later.
Cool?
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: So we used the %d just
because a double that's coming back,
or why is-- [INAUDIBLE].
>> AUDIENCE: Can you use %i?
>> SPEAKER 1: You can use %i.
Any last minute questions?
Go ahead.
AUDIENCE: I just have a quick question.
So the ptr variable, that's--
like, with the int* ptr = malloc,
that's just saying it's
pointing to a place in memory--
SPEAKER 1: Do you want [INAUDIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: --that's the
size of-- no, it's OK.
But it's just pointing to a place in
memory that's just like four bytes.
SPEAKER 1: Right.
So malloc the size of int says,
OK, I'm going to go run off,
find four bytes of memory for you.
When it finds that four
bytes of memory, it
gives you back the address
of where it starts,
and that's what stored
in pointer, or ptr.
Good.
You guys look less confused than most
people when I talk about pointer,
so I'm feeling pretty good right now.
>> All right.
As always, you guys should have all
gotten your pset2 grades by now.
I know there have been some wonky
things where it says, formula not valid
or something.
If you're getting that, all of
your grades are valid on my side.
So I can send you
screenshots of your grades.
Just let me know as well if you're
missing any grades or something
doesn't seem to make sense.
Come to me.
>> I've been super proud of you
guys already, so keep it up.
And have a good rest of your week.
I'm sure I'll see some
of you at office hours.