>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> SPEAKER 1: All right, everyone.
Welcome to your last section with me.
It's been quite the semester.
I can't believe this is, like,
week 12 or 11, something like that.
But because it's our last
section, we have lots of candy.
And I'm going to try and
prep you as well as I
can for your quiz on Wednesday.
So probably not the best way to,
like, end section with quiz review.
But we'll try and make it fun.
And there's always candy.
So hopefully, that'll make it better.
>> Your quiz is going to be pretty
much the same thing as Quiz Zero.
It's going to be the
same format, same length.
You'll be in rooms scattered
across campus, because there
are close to 900 of you, and we can't
all hold you in rooms like this.
So be sure to look at all of
the Quiz One documentation
online at cs50.harvard.edu
tonight or tomorrow night.
Make sure you know where you're
going, what you need to bring.
Really, you just need to bring yourself
and a pencil, and you should be fine.
The questions will be
very much the same.
There will probably be a couple
multiple choice, a couple short answer,
some coding, maybe some true/false,
matching sorts of things.
So you shouldn't be too
surprised by the format.
>> What can be surprising is the
length, which, in previous years,
has been much longer.
In my year, I don't have a single friend
that I remember finishing the exam.
There were like multiple
pages left blank.
So the length can be
kind of disorienting
just because in some years, it has
been much longer than Quiz One.
I have no idea what it's
going to be like this year,
but it's something to be aware of.
>> Additionally, the
difficulty-- people tend
to find Quiz One much more
difficult than Quiz Zero.
Again, you know, if
you're kind of walking
out feeling a little uneasy because
you didn't do as well as you thought
you would or you feel like you didn't
do as well as you did on Quiz One,
remember that there are probably a
lot of other people feeling that way.
I was definitely one of those people.
Quiz one, like, threw me for a loop.
And my friends have this great
picture of them at JP Licks
kind of with these huge
sundaes, being like, Quiz One,
and looking like they're in tears.
>> So it's a general feeling.
It's a tough test, it's a tough quiz.
Obviously, if you come out and you
feel like you rocked it, great for you.
But know that you're probably not--
you are almost most definitely not
alone if you walk out feeling like,
eh, probably could have gotten better.
It's tough.
Mm-hm.
>> AUDIENCE: How much is it worth
in relation to [INAUDIBLE]?
>> SPEAKER 1: It's worth the same.
Yeah.
But again, it's also going to be
affected by how the rest of the class
does, how your section does,
how you've improved over time.
Grading is a little bit of a black box.
So what the actual number
or percentage you get
is not necessarily like directly
correlated with the grade
you're going to get.
There's a lot of
factors that go into it.
>> So with that, we're going to
go through some quiz review.
I'm just going to run this
like last time for you guys.
I have all the answers
to Quiz One of last year.
So if you guys want to pull
that up on your own computers,
if you've taken this exam
before and you have questions,
I was thinking we could
just go through some
of the more difficult ones on that.
So we can talk about it, maybe
get a little more insight
into the intuition behind some of
these questions, how to approach them.
>> As well, like last time,
I have a 100-slide deck
that has basically all
of the slides that I
have prepared for previous
sections since your last quiz-- I
have in this deck.
So we can go through
pretty much anything
that we've talked about
beforehand that maybe you
want a little more clarification on.
We could do that first.
>> But otherwise, I'm super
happy just to kind of work
through these problems with you.
And I'm really here to
focus on what you guys think
would be most important to focus on.
Like, obviously, all of
this stuff is important.
Especially as we go through Quiz One,
I'll definitely point out things like,
oh, this might be something
you really want to know
or you want to have on your cheat sheet.
I'll be telling you things
as we kind of go through.
>> So on that note, are there any things
that you guys would like to go over?
Also, if I don't have it in my deck,
we can pull up something on the web,
or we can try and make
up an example on the fly.
But any concepts that you
guys are a little fuzzy on.
[? Brian, ?] did you have--
>> AUDIENCE: Oh, is it cumulative?
Like, is the stuff on Quiz
Zero going to be on here?
>> SPEAKER 1: It's cumulative,
but it's much more
of an emphasis on things
since your last quiz.
So obviously, you guys have
learned about variables, and loops,
and conditionals.
And it's not like those just
go away, because they're
obviously inherent to everything
else that we've learned now.
>> There might be a question
on the sorts, or there
might be a question
on different searches.
Or there might be a couple
questions on maybe something you
having to do with compiling
or different errors.
But if you've looked at
Quiz One from last year,
you'll notice that it is
very much focused on things
that have happened since your last quiz.
>> Why is that door always locked?
It really bothers me.
Because I always try to go through it.
>> So that's pretty much
how the quiz will be.
So are there any concepts that
you guys would like to go over?
Or we can jump right into
just looking at Quiz One
from last year and kind of going
through practice questions there.
We can also switch back and forth.
This is not a one-time sort of thing.
Any questions?
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: Could I ask a
question about another--
>> SPEAKER 1: Another one?
>> AUDIENCE: This is from another year.
>> SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
We can also do another year.
>> AUDIENCE: OK.
So on 2011.
>> SPEAKER 1: 2011.
Ooh, that was the year before me.
Let me pull this up.
>> AUDIENCE: I think.
>> SPEAKER 1: This aspect
ratio is throwing me off.
>> AUDIENCE: 11 and 12.
>> SPEAKER 1: 11 and 12.
OK.
Well, here, why don't we do this?
You guys-- everyone just take a couple
of minutes to look through quizzes.
And we'll compile a list.
And then we'll go through them.
All right?
While I get a bunch
of this stuff set up.
OK.
I'm just going to write
things down on paper.
>> 2011, 11 and 12?
I'm just going to change this display.
OK.
That's better.
This over.
All right.
>> Anyone else have any that
they'd like to start with?
Also, forgot to say, if you want more
of a bunch of people talking at you
and just giving you a crack
course in the last six weeks,
we are running a review
session from 7:00
to 8:30 tonight in Northwest
B103, which also happened
last time, where it's going to
be me, Hannah, Daven, with Gabe
and Rob kind of helping from the
sidelines of just kind of throwing all
the information that you might
want to have on your cheat sheet,
slash, know in general there.
AUDIENCE: That's also online, right?
SPEAKER 1: It's also online.
So you can also stay out of this
icky weather, go to your dorm,
and live-stream it if you'd like.
I'm sure a lot of
people-- I know I would
be doing that if I were in your shoes.
OK.
So why don't we start with--
while you guys-- hopefully,
you're looking through.
If not, I might just start working
through different things on Quiz One
from last year unless you
have specific questions.
>> We'll start with this
question here about stacks.
So does everyone remember
kind of what a stack is?
How we tend to-- can anyone just give
me a general description of a stack?
A type of data structure.
OK.
So it's one of the
data structures that we
expect you to be familiar with-- like
stacks, arrays, queues, so forth.
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: Like First
In, Last Out, something.
>> SPEAKER 1: It's First In, Last Out.
Exactly.
So a stack is exactly
what we tend to think
about when we think
of a stack of things.
So a stack of plates.
The first plate you put down
is going to be at the bottom,
and it's going to be the last
one that you remove at the end.
Because they stack up.
>> And you take the one out of the bottom,
typically, things crash and break.
So stacks you can think of
just like a stack of plates.
Or the example we always like to use
is in the D halls, you have the trays,
they're all stacked up,
and you take from the top.
So the last one in is the first one out.
OK.
>> So in the case here, we
see we have-- I wonder
if I can actually zoom in a little bit.
So we have this struct here.
Right?
So you have some struct that has
some int numbers of capacity.
So what do we think that represents?
This is an array with size CAPACITY.
>> So this really represents
our stack in general.
Our stack is really just an
array with some set number
that is its max, that is, its CAPACITY.
And then we have some int size, which
will track the size of our stack
throughout the course
of when we're using it.
OK?
>> In this case right here, we say that our
stack size has been initialized to 0.
So we have an empty stack right now.
And then we want to complete
the implementation of pop
such that it returns the int at the top.
And then if it's empty,
it returns negative 1.
OK?
So I want you guys just to think
about what we might do there.
What might be one of the first
things we'd want to check?
There's a great thing here.
Whenever it says-- if there's ever some
If statement, like "If stack is empty,"
or "If this returns null," or
"If this is whatever"-- sorry.
>> AUDIENCE: Write an If statement.
>> SPEAKER 1: Right.
You could write an If statement.
And that's probably one of the
first things you want to check.
OK.
Whenever they give you
kind of like a corner case
like this, that's typically
one of the first things
you're going to check in your code.
>> Also, something to
recognize for the quiz
is if you have an inefficient way
to do something, write it down.
Because we're not grading
you on design, we're
grading you on correctness for quizzes.
So even if you know that it's a super
bad way to do something but it works,
write it down, OK?
>> Literally, I've seen kids last year--
if you look at last year's one,
they're like, do the Mario pyramid.
And they literally just did "print,
hash, print, hash, hash, print, hash,
hash, hash."
But it's correct.
It does what we told it to,
so you can't take points off.
If you're down to the
wire, obviously, you
want to get a more elegant solution, and
the more elegant solution will probably
be less code, which means you probably
have a higher chance of being right.
But if you're like, you know
what, no, I don't have time, I
know this is a solution,
it's not the best, write it.
And you can even write on the
side, I know this is terrible,
but I know it works.
So just a heads-up.
OK.
>> So obviously, first thing
is this If statement.
So what do we think this If
statement is going to be?
And actually, let me open
up my great Sublime editor.
I'm going to code this and then
show you guys when it's done.
So int pop.
OK.
So if we have this int
pop void-- so obviously,
this is some function that takes in
nothing and returns an integer, right?
So it's just going to talk about
this stack that we've created.
>> So just translating this last
sentence, "if stack is empty,
pop should return negative
1," how might we do that?
So If what?
How do we know that the stack is empty?
It's just size equals 0.
Stack.size equals 0.
Also, I'm kind of writing blind here.
So if I make any typos-- oh,
also forgot to mention this.
>> Last week, I totally figured out
what our problem was with JavaScript.
Don't capitalize I
and D. You should only
capitalize I and get element by Id.
And that was the entire error.
So if you guys go back and
actually look through my code,
if you just make everything a
lowercase d, "forget element by Id,"
it will work.
So as I promised, I was very close.
I just capitalized something
I wasn't supposed to, which
I'm sure you guys had in your last PSET.
>> So if our size equals 0,
what are we supposed to do?
>> AUDIENCE: Return negative 1.
>> SPEAKER 1: Return negative 1.
Cool.
So now what do we do?
We want to pop something off.
Now this is the case
where we have something.
Our size is greater than 1
or greater than 0, right?
We actually have something there.
So what we want to do is we
want to return right here.
We're going to say we want
to return top of stack.
OK?
>> So how might we do that?
How do we return the top of the stack?
Remember, our stack is
just an array, right?
It has some capacity
that we've given it.
As we've put things on-- or actually,
we're going to write "push" after this.
If things are in there--
maybe a picture will help.
Hm, I like big chalk better.
>> So if-- and you can just
think of this as our stack.
So this is 0, 1, 2.
I don't know why my boxes
are getting smaller.
But there.
OK.
>> So this is some stack
with a capacity of 5.
And let's say we have something
here and we have something here.
So at this point, our
size is equal to what?
2.
And if we want to pop
something off of it,
that means we want to get
rid of this right here.
OK?
So how would we return this value?
>> AUDIENCE: Size minus 1.
>> SPEAKER 1: Right.
So size minus 1, or you
could do size minus minus.
But we can't just do size.
It's inside a struct, right?
So stack.struct.
or stack.size.
That's our index right there.
OK?
>> And then if we look
back at our struct here,
we notice that to
actually access the array,
we need to do stack.numbers
to actually access that array.
So that returns the top of the stack.
>> But something that-- if you guys look
at the answer key, this is all they
give you.
So this is it.
But I might argue that they're
miss-- ooh, not what I wanted.
I might argue that they're
missing something, because-- yes.
AUDIENCE: Decrease the size.
SPEAKER 1: Right.
We need to decrease our size now.
So what's tricky about
this is once you return
something, your function's
going exit, right?
So what we might do is actually
decrease our size first.
And then we can just do stack.size.
>> We can just use stack.size
as our index, couldn't we?
Because if stack.size
is 2, we decrement it.
And so it's 1, which
is our actual indice.
Once we get rid of this, we actually
only have one thing in our array.
So it does both.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
>> SPEAKER 1: Well, in this case,
we just returned the element
at the top that is at our
size that's at the top.
But we haven't done anything to the
size after we removed that element.
This hasn't changed our size yet.
This does actually
inherently change our size.
>> But to make it a little clearer,
you could do stack.size minus minus.
For me, it makes it, I don't know,
a little more clear that-- ah,
that you're actually changing
the size and returning it.
The other way was fine, because
you were changing and returning
at the same time.
But this is just another way to write
it that I wanted to show you guys.
Does that make sense?
Stacks, I think, are
much easier than queues.
[LAUGHS]
OK.
Did you have any specific questions
about 11 and 12, or just--
>> AUDIENCE: I think it was the stack.
>> SPEAKER 1: The stack size?
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah.
>> SPEAKER 1: Gotcha.
OK.
Yeah, you could do it in
one of these two ways.
OK.
>> So now we have the other one.
This is really weird, like
not having this on my screen.
So if we look here, we now want to
complete the implementation of push,
which actually puts something, goes
and inserts something into our queue,
or into our stack.
OK?
>> So if we notice, we
have a couple of things.
We have our great-- if all else,
whenever we have one of these,
you guys should at least get half
a point, because all you have to do
is convert this into C. And
they give you half of it.
So "if a stack is full
or it is negative,
then push should return false."
OK?
>> So we only want positive
integers to be on our stack.
All right?
And this is going to either
return true or false.
So we should [INAUDIBLE] bool.
OK.
So translating.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: Oh, thanks.
Yeah.
This is why I have you guys.
Int n.
Perfect.
Because we're putting
something on to our stack.
We actually need some number.
OK.
>> So just taking that last line that
they gave us, our kind of corner cases,
what do you think we have here?
Obviously, we're going to have some If.
OK.
So we said, If our stack is
full or if n is negative.
So probably easiest to start
with, so if n is less than 0
or-- remember your nice
AND and OR operators there.
>> How would we check to
see if our stack is full?
What happens?
>> AUDIENCE: Size equal CAPACITY.
>> SPEAKER 1: Exactly.
Perfect.
OK.
And what do we want to do there?
>> AUDIENCE: Return false.
>> SPEAKER 1: Return false.
Perfect.
So halfway there, right?
At the very least, you guys
will have half of this.
So let's think about this.
>> So this is the stack we start with.
We're trying to put
some element on here.
>> We have a size that's
equal to 2 right now.
We have a capacity that equals to 5.
And let's say we have
some n that's equal to 3.
So we need to input 3 into this space.
And we need to input it into index 2.
Right?
>> So how might we do this?
Trying to assign-- we
want to access our array.
So stack.numbers.
But at what indice would
we want this to be?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
Stack.size.
And we want that to equal n, right?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: I was actually
just looking at that.
I think that is wrong.
>> AUDIENCE: Don't you want the
space past the current size?
>> SPEAKER 1: Well, if we look here,
our size at this point is 2.
We want it to go into index 2,
because this is the top of our stack.
So I would say that it
should be stack.size,
and then you would increase stack.size.
Does everyone agree?
I think I agree with that.
You guys can argue
with me if you'd like.
Or not argue, but we can discuss this.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: Mm-hm, is where it's
open because of zero indexing.
So whereas in the first part,
I thought they were wrong,
and they were actually right, this
part, I actually think they were wrong.
I would say you should
definitely input it here.
I think we all agree
we have a size of 2.
That's exactly where we
want our new number to go.
So stack.numbers at
stack.size should equal n.
And then we would
increment the stack.size.
++.
And then what do we want to do?
There's one last thing we have to
do if we successfully inserted this?
Return true.
And now you're done.
So I feel like it was the whole minus
minus stack.size and stack.size ++ that
messed things up.
Ugh.
I keep-- I have this knee-jerk
tendency to always hit
Control, S, because I never
want to lose any of my work.
But I don't need to do that now.
OK.
So that was stack.
Cool.
>> Is there anything?
Did you guys find any
other questions that you'd
like to go over from previous quizzes?
If not, we can kind of start talking
through Quiz One from last year.
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: For the first
part, I didn't really
understand how you deleted the number.
Isn't it still there?
>> SPEAKER 1: The number's still there.
But what happens is that because you've
told it that the top of your stack
is here, when you go to add something
onto the stack, it'll just replace it.
>> AUDIENCE: Oh, OK.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So it's like he forgot and it's there
type of thing even though it's there.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] or anything?
SPEAKER 1: No.
Because we're in an
array, you don't have
to worry about-- you'll just
override it when you need it.
All right.
Any other questions?
If not, we're just going
to start working through.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Well, this one is on the 2013,
but just going through the SQL stuff.
SPEAKER 1: SQL?
OK.
So this is 26 through 29.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
SPEAKER 1: OK.
Lovely.
Let's pull those up.
Oh, look.
Did you guys enjoy the Steve
Ballmer talk, by the way?
It was pretty hilarious, in my opinion.
I love that every time I bring up CS50's
website during section, it's like, oh,
watch section.
And I'm like, mm.
>> AUDIENCE: Can we do it?
>> SPEAKER 1: We'll do it at the end.
How's that?
Because I know you guys
have always wanted to.
So we'll do it at the end.
One questions.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: It'll be a meta section.
AUDIENCE: It's like 5 seconds.
AUDIENCE: Really?
AUDIENCE: It's like 20 seconds.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[LAUGHTER]
SPEAKER 1: I like that
you've already done
it, which is what makes me happier.
OK.
26.
Actually, we're just going to
mirror this now, because I can't.
This is annoying.
OK.
Now I can see everything.
Lovely.
OK.
>> So obviously, this should bring back
great memories from [? CSG ?] Finance.
Half of you about have yours graded now.
The other half I will get to
very, very soon, I promise.
>> So we have some SQL table
that's Accounts here.
Probably similar to
your guys' user tables.
And we have some number
that was a PRIMARY key
and represents a
12-digit account number.
And balance is how much money they have.
And the default value is 100.
And they give them $100 any
time they open an account.
I wish my bank did that.
OK.
>> So we want to complete the schema by
specifying next to number in balance
the appropriate SQL type.
So what do you guys think would be
kind of like your knee-jerk reaction
for types for these two?
>> AUDIENCE: Int.
>> SPEAKER 1: An int.
OK.
And then for a balance?
Decimal.
OK.
So decimal's right.
Int is close.
Kind of the big thing is this
underlined 12-digit account number.
Whenever we have something
that's larger than eight digits,
they want you to use big
int, which I think is--
>> AUDIENCE: Is that just SQL?
>> SPEAKER 1: It's the only time I've heard
of it is SQL-- like using a big int.
It's just to give you a
little more precision,
making sure you're not
overflowing type thing.
In all honesty, I think this
is definitely one of the ones
where it's like, oh,
it's meant for people
who have a little more knowledge of SQL.
We never talked about
big ints in your PSET.
So it's kind of like I'm pretty sure
if you put int, it was half credit.
>> And as I said before, there are going
to be some questions that are just
meant to trip you up, so
that not everyone gets 100.
Because of course, there
are some people in CS50
who have been doing this for like
eight years, and you're like,
what are you doing?
But yeah.
>> Decimal for balance was the obvious one.
And then big int for number just because
of that, like, underlined 12-digit.
Whenever anything is in bold or it's
underlined, like, pay attention to it.
We're not doing that just because.
OK.
>> So "suppose that the bank imposes
a $20 monthly fee on all accounts.
With what query could the bank
deduct $20 from every account
even if it results from
some negative balances?"
So let's start simple.
We have four main commands
for SQL, which are?
Do you guys remember the four
big ones that I told you?
>> UPDATE, DELETE, SELECT, and INSERT.
Perfect.
Got it.
So what do we think might
be most useful for this one?
We are-- UPDATE.
Exactly.
So UPDATE, because we're looking
at accounts that already exist.
>> So remember our general
sort of thing is update.
And then what comes after UPDATE?
We have some table
that we're referencing.
So if I pull up Sublime again-- UPDATE.
So this is a general format.
So we have UPDATE table.
And then what's the next thing we have?
>> You can do WHERE.
And then we have some qualifier here.
And then what do we have next?
We have some SET-- something
equal to something.
Blah equals blah.
Updated blah.
Right?
So that's like the general
idea for some update.
OK?
>> So let's start filling this
in with what it should be.
So what table are we talking about?
Accounts.
And then in this case,
what's really cool
is are we talking about specific
users within our account,
or are we talking about all users?
We're talking about all users.
So in that case, we can just
delete this WHERE qualifier.
The WHERE is only when you want
to limit what you're changing.
If you want to change the entire
table, you can just drop that.
OK.
>> So now we're at our SET part.
What do we want to change?
>> AUDIENCE: Balance.
>> SPEAKER 1: Balance.
And we're going to-- how are
we going to change balance?
We have a $20 fee, right?
Minus 20.
And they said it's OK if
we have negative balances.
So in this case, you don't need
to do any further error checking.
OK?
That is literally all you have to do.
Cool?
OK.
>> So let's go through the next one.
"With what SQL query could the
bank retrieve the account numbers
of its richest customers with
balances greater than $1,000?"
If your bank and your richest customers
are just the ones with over $1,000,
I feel like you're
doing something wrong.
Like, how does a bank survive on that?
Like, that interest, not quite enough.
OK.
With this sort of thing, what do
you think, of our four functions,
do you think we're going to use?
SELECT.
Perfect.
OK.
So we're selecting some
identifier FROM table.
And then WHERE condition.
So as we go through
these, I'm just going
to give you guys a general refresher
on the general format of all of these.
>> So we're selecting some sort
of [? thing. ?] In this case,
this is going to be
typically some column.
So in our case, we have number, balance.
In your guys' case, maybe
it was ID, name, password.
Any of those columns, that's
typically what we're selecting.
>> So in this case here, which
kind of column, what identifier
are we pulling from our table?
What does it ask us for?
It asks us for our numbers, right?
The account numbers.
So remember, just number in this case.
If you guys ever had the error, that
bright orange box would come up.
And it was like, unexpected
row in, like, whatever.
That's because you called
your table wrong, right?
So be sure that you are
calling the column correctly.
>> So from table, our table
is called accounts.
Again, make sure you're
referencing your table correctly.
And then what's our condition here?
What are we looking for?
We want our rich people.
Yes.
So balance greater than 1,000.
There you go.
That's your query.
Not too bad, right?
OK.
>> So now for our last one.
With that, we're breezing through.
OK.
So now "with what query could
the bank close, i.e., delete"--
don't you love how they
just gave you DELETE--
"every account that has a balance of 0?"
I think we can all agree we're
probably going to be using DELETE.
I'm welcome to take any
discussion around that.
But I think it's pretty safe to
say that we could use DELETE.
>> So we're going to DELETE some
users from table, WHERE condition.
So same sort of thing as SELECT.
So in this case-- oh, sorry.
I should DELETE FROM.
Because DELETE will
delete the entire row.
So we don't need to talk about which
specific things about a user we're
deleting.
If we delete a user, we're
deleting everything about them.
>> So in this case, we just need to
fill in our WHERE and our condition.
So our table is just our accounts
table, as we've been doing.
And then what is our condition here?
>> AUDIENCE: Balance.
>> SPEAKER 1: Balance equals 0.
Correct.
All good.
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: So DELETE
inherently deletes everything.
So whereas with SELECT, SELECT takes in
certain columns that you want returned.
If you wanted everything about
a user returned, you use star.
Star says, return to me
everything from this user.
Or if you put WHERE star, that
means just give me everything.
>> But DELETE inherently has that.
So if you say, DELETE from
accounts where balance equals 0,
it's going to go through.
And everywhere that balance is
equal to 0, it inherently does that.
It'll delete everything.
The star is more for--
with SELECT or UPDATE,
it's talking more about the individual
fields corresponding to a user.
>> So when you do SELECT
star from table WHERE ID
equals 1, that returns to you
everything about the user with ID 1.
If you were to do SELECT number
or SELECT ID comma name from users
WHERE ID equals 1, that
just returns their number
or their ID and their name.
OK?
>> So we use star in that case to
give us everything about a user.
And DELETE inherently does that.
It doesn't just delete the ID,
or just the name, or whatever.
Yeah, no.
It just deletes the entire user.
So we don't have to worry
about the star there.
>> If you wanted to delete
everything, you could do that,
and this'll just drop everything.
But typically, you
don't want to do that.
But if you ever want to delete
everything, you could do that.
OK.
>> Have you guys found any other questions?
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: Could you do 26?
>> SPEAKER 1: 26 we just did.
AUDIENCE: Oh, 25, sorry.
SPEAKER 1: 25.
OK.
25.
Oh.
They're doing JavaScript.
Oh, I can't believe it.
I'm going to mess us up again, guys.
OK.
We got this.
We're going to make this work.
Ah, jQuery.
Fun.
OK.
>> So we are going to complete the
implementation of the web page
in such a way that if they visit,
input their name, and submit the form,
they have this great alert
window that is going to appear.
So anything with alerts, we know that
we're going to have to use JavaScript.
Yay, JavaScript.
And if they fail to input a
name before submitting the form,
no alert should appear.
So you can use jQuery,
but you don't have to.
>> So I'm going to let you guys work
on this just for a couple minutes.
Think about it.
And then we will code it.
Slash I am going to try and think of the
best way to explain this answer to you.
All right.
We'll get it set up.
OK.
>> So we're just going
to walk through this,
because I know jQuery
is a little confusing.
JavaScript.
It's a little out there.
So what we're going to do is
[INAUDIBLE] actually solved
this problem with jQuery.
So if you remember,
jQuery is just a library
that's just built on top of JavaScript.
It's meant to make your
life a little bit easier.
>> I would definitely, if
you have time, look over
a little bit of the
documentation for jQuery.
But it's very similar to JavaScript.
It's got similar paradigms, where you
use this dot operator to call functions
on objects that you have.
>> So what we have here is for jQuery,
you should always have this sort
of wrapper, which is the
$(document).ready(function) function
in parentheses here.
OK.
So this might be something
you want on your cheat sheet.
Because at the very least, you can
have the wrapper for your jQuery.
And it'll at least get
you part ways there.
>> So in the same way that we
talked a lot about JavaScript,
and we would start by looking
at what we're trying to edit
or what we're trying to change.
And that would typically be the
first thing that we'd put in.
So in this case, if we go back to this
here and we look at our form here,
we have this inputs,
right, this id of inputs.
And we know that based
on our question, we
are either going to throw
an error if this is empty,
or we're going to put
this into an alert, right?
So probably safe to say that we're
going to be dealing with inputs here.
>> jQuery is very similar in that if we
think back to CSS, anything with an ID
we look at with a hash.
Anything with class we
looked at with a dot, right?
So in the same way here, what
we're talking about is inputs.
We saw that inputs is
an ID within our form.
So we're going to refer to it as such.
Inputs.
OK?
>> So when in doubt, even
if you have nowhere,
if you're really unsure about how to
approach this, A, have this wrapper.
So start there with
the wrapper for jQuery.
B, make sure that you know
what you are changing.
And when in doubt,
put that in something,
and do dot, whatever you think
you should be doing with it.
>> AUDIENCE: What is the wrapper?
>> SPEAKER 1: The wrapper
is this first line.
So this says, wait until
my document is ready.
Then start messing with things.
OK?
So we know we're messing with inputs.
So we're like, OK, inputs is our form.
That's our ID.
So that's what we're
going to be looking for.
And we want to see what happens
when this form is submitted, right?
>> So as we might think,
we have some .submit.
So .submit just says, OK, this form
that we've referenced with hash inputs,
when it's submitted,
execute something else.
So we're going to have some function.
Notice we have anonymous functions here.
We have an anonymous function here.
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: Will it always be .submit,
or is it just because in the HTML,
we made the button type Submit?
>> SPEAKER 1: It should be .submit, because
it's some form that we are submitting.
Because this .submit doesn't necessarily
correspond to what the button is like
to call.
But the fact that it's a
form that we're submitting.
OK.
>> So notice anonymous
function here that says--
AUDIENCE: I don't really
understand anonymous functions.
SPEAKER 1: So anonymous
functions, they're
just functions that don't have a name.
So instead of having some main function
that calls-- we could say, If document
ready, then we would call inputs.
And then, When submitted, call--
like, If so-and-so submitted,
we'd call some other function.
An anonymous function
just doesn't have a name,
and it will just execute
within these sorts of things.
>> So in this case, what this says
is, When our document is ready,
execute this function.
This function is composed
of everything within here.
And then the next layer in is, OK,
when inputs is submitted, execute this.
It's just a way of denoting
what should be executed when.
It's literally just a
function that doesn't
have a name, so they tend to
be nested into each other,
because you can't call them by name.
OK?
Literally, an anonymous function
is just a function without a name.
That's it.
Just a way to encapsulate
different things
that we want executed at specific times.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: The vent?
Where?
>> AUDIENCE: In the
parentheses after function?
>> SPEAKER 1: After functions.
Which one?
>> AUDIENCE: Both.
If you put, like, event, or if
you put an argument in there,
would it be wrong?
>> SPEAKER 1: In this case, I suppose
you could put an argument in there.
But because we don't need an
argument, there shouldn't be.
Like, it's the whole,
like, you should only
have things that are
necessary sort of thing.
In the same way that if we had any
function that has int main void-- like,
with int main void, you
could do int arg v, whatever.
But if you don't need those, you
shouldn't have them in there.
Same thing.
Emma, did you have a question?
OK.
Cool.
So what we have so far is when our
document's ready, execute this.
Now we're looking at
when it's submitted.
So now we actually have sort
of the meat of our thing.
So we need to get the value that the
user submitted, whether that be a name
or empty.
And then we need to either return
this alert or throw an error.
Either way.
>> So how do we declare a
variable in JavaScript?
Var.
So let's say, var name
equals-- or actually, we'll
do value since I think it's name.
OK.
So we have some value here that we
want to pull from our inputs form.
So in the same way that
we kind of did inputs,
can anyone tell me what we
might be calling within here
if we wanted to get
the name from the form?
And if we look back at our form here,
we notice that we have an ID of name.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: You don't have
to think of it as an array.
You don't need to worry about that.
So we just have some name.
And then because JavaScript and things
are weird, we can't just do "name."
We actually have to call
some function that gives us,
like, the value of that identifier.
OK?
So that is just .val.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: OK.
So with JavaScript, this sort of
thing right here just goes through.
And you could think of this as-- it's
like almost a getElementById, where
getElementById would actually
return the full thing to you.
The $("#name") is just like,
OK, I have it, I can access it,
but if you actually want it
to return the value to you--
>> AUDIENCE: Is it like a pointer?
>> SPEAKER 1: It's kind of like a pointer.
You could think of it as
kind of like a pointer.
Like, it says, OK, I
know how to get there,
but to actually get the value out of
it, you have to explicitly ask for it.
And unfortunately, obviously, we don't
do too much with JavaScript and jQuery.
>> So it's going to come down to how much
you guys-- what you happen to know,
what you happen to have seen, and what
you can kind of logically guess at.
Because some of these things, you
could probably get halfway there.
But to get it completely right,
I think this problem probably
had one of the lowest scores.
AUDIENCE: Like, for example,
for [INAUDIBLE] inputs,
why don't you have to put val there?
SPEAKER 1: For this one?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
Because this is kind
of like, as we said,
some pointer, and this is me referencing
it and actually getting us the value.
>> AUDIENCE: Whereas [INAUDIBLE]?
>> SPEAKER 1: For inputs,
inputs is just some--
it's like we're just
looking at it as a whole,
and this .submit tells
us what we need to know.
jQuery and JavaScript is weird.
I know.
I know, guys.
There's a reason I don't
do web programming.
Just kidding.
I haven't had enough exposure to it.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] CSS.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> SPEAKER 1: OK, that's CSS.
CSS is just, like, make things pretty,
it's not like let's deal with data.
There's a difference there.
OK.
So now hopefully, this part-- also, for
a problem like this, where you may not
know the syntax, you could be like,
OK, you could have some var value
and be like, assume I
got the value correctly.
And then you could probably
write this next part.
This next part will probably
seem much more easy,
or it would make logical
sense to you guys.
>> Whereas what we've written so far,
I know I would be like, umm, yeah,
I don't know that on the quiz.
You can totally write psuedocode
and then break into real code
when you-- it's kind of like math.
If you've ever had some
multi-part problem where
you don't know how to
get past the first step,
but everything else
relies on that first step,
you just say, like, assume x equals 4.
And then you run with it, right?
>> You can do the same thing with code.
So you could say, assume
I got the value right.
Then do this next part here.
Because this part actually
should be pretty logical.
>> So we need to check
if our value is empty.
Or if it's some name,
actually give an alert.
So what might we want to check?
We want to have some If.
What do you think our If is going to be?
We need to check to see if value
is-- if it's not an empty string.
>> Perfect.
Exactly.
OK.
So if that's the case,
what do we want to do?
We want to throw some alert, right?
So it's just alert.
And then whatever we want inside.
So what are we supposed
to have inside our alert?
>> AUDIENCE: "Hello."
>> SPEAKER 1: Comma.
And then do you guys
remember how to concatenate?
>> AUDIENCE: Plus.
>> SPEAKER 1: Plus.
So we want to have plus.
And then we need another plus
for our exclamation point.
Cool.
OK.
Otherwise, what might we want to do?
We don't want to do anything, right?
So we just return false.
Not what I want to do.
OK.
>> And then these, of
course-- what's important
is to remember to close
your anonymous functions.
So if you notice, we have some
function here that ends here.
So we need to close this
first one and add a semicolon.
And then this one here has to
do with this anonymous function,
so we close it there.
That knee-jerk reaction of saving.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: Is there a reason that--
just in all the examples in JavaScript
that I've seen, we have
the first curly braces
on the same line as the function?
>> SPEAKER 1: That's stylistic.
Yeah.
And actually, if you take 61, we
do all our curly braces that way.
Huh?
>> AUDIENCE: If we did do that on
the PSET, is that bad for style?
>> SPEAKER 1: No.
We have explicitly told
you guys to do this.
But actually, this is kind
of the dominating convention
in a lot of C classes and
JavaScript and jQuery.
So obviously, I'm sure--
and actually, if I
were to do this problem completely
blind without having looked at it,
there is probably very few
ways I would have gotten this.
>> I might have been like, OK, maybe I
need to grab something that's an input.
And I think having the
knowledge that, like,
OK, if I want to get something
from a form that has an ID,
I refer to it in this way,
I'd probably get that.
I might get this.
But really, the only thing that I think
I would really get is this right here.
>> So it's kind of important to
know, as with any difficult test,
you kind of choose your battles, right?
If you know that you're not going to get
that first part for jQuery, as I said,
assume that you have this value
and do what you can with it.
And if you have time, go back
and try and fill in the pieces.
But don't let a question like
this really bog you down.
Because what?
This was one question on
jQuery out of the entire exam.
So yes, it'd be great if you got it.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] you
are welcome to use jQuery.
SPEAKER 1: You are
welcome to use jQuery.
AUDIENCE: OK. [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: How would you not use it?
I would have to look
up all my JavaScript.
It's actually much easier,
I think, to use jQuery,
because jQuery actually reduces the
amount of JavaScript you write probably
by, like, half.
So our code would probably be
twice as long without that.
So if you recognize-- the biggest
thing to take away from this problem
are the patterns.
If you're accessing
something from a form,
you're going to use quotes, hash,
whatever you're trying to access.
If it's being submitted, you want
to use something like a .submit.
You're probably going to use
an anonymous function in there.
If you actually need the value of
something, you're going to do quotes,
hash, whatever that field is, .val.
And recognizing patterns
like that are going
to be far more useful than
really knowing the nitty gritty.
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: So if the
user submits their name
and it runs through that statement, will
it go down and return false after this?
>> SPEAKER 1: No, because the alert,
you can think of it like a return.
Yeah.
So it'll exit.
>> AUDIENCE: Could you
[? place ?] the parentheses
of submit, parentheses, something?
>> SPEAKER 1: I did, I believe.
This one's closed right here.
And then this one gets closed down here.
>> AUDIENCE: Oh, there.
All right.
>> SPEAKER 1: Obviously, little,
little syntactic things
like that, we'll probably
just circle it and be like,
don't forget your parentheses.
But yeah.
OK.
Do we have another one
that we would like to do?
Did you guys get the binary tree one?
Do we want to go over that one?
I feel like binary trees
and DOMs should be points
that you guys get pretty easily.
I would not want you
to lose points on that.
OK.
>> Let's do this DOM here.
I wish I had my Surface so I
could just draw on the screen.
That's what I used to do last year.
OK.
So as I mentioned, we talked
about DOM, Document Object Model.
They're probably going to give you
some little bit of snippet like this
and ask you to create a tree for it.
And this just all has to do
with running through the tags.
So let's try and do this.
>> Also, as per usual, if you guys
do these quizzes, as I highly
recommend that you do as practice,
any of them that you're like,
I really don't get what's
going on here, just, of course,
send me an email with a question,
and I will explain as best I can.
OK.
>> We have some document, and we have HTML.
So then we're just analysing
the tags here, right?
So what do we see comes-- what are
the two subheadings under HTML?
Especially because
they're indented properly?
Head and body.
Ah.
Lovely.
So then let's start here with head.
What's underneath head?
What's our next tag?
Title.
And then within title, quiz.
OK.
>> So literally, it's just
walking through the tags, OK?
So then if we have
body, as we go through,
body has three things within it, right?
It's got three divs.
Every div gets its own little box.
And what's in the first div?
[INAUDIBLE]
And then the next one is middle,
which I'm just going to abbreviate.
And then the last one is bottom.
>> So really, it's just walking through.
And because we're going to give
you HTML that is properly indented,
you can literally just run through
and be like, OK, here is the HTML.
So this is the outermost
corner, or furthest left,
so that has to be its own thing.
These are on the same indention.
>> So we know that head needs to
be at the same level as body,
but underneath HTML.
It's what we have here.
Head and body are siblings,
but they're under HTML.
And then we just go into each of these.
So head has title, which
has quiz, as we see here.
And then in this case, we have
body, which has these three lines.
So these are all
siblings all under body.
OK?
So hopefully when you see
something like this, you're like,
yes, I just get to draw a tree.
It's gonna be great.
OK.
So wanted to make sure
you guys knew that.
>> So why don't we go to
32 with our binary tree?
Because once you understand a binary
search tree, it's really not that bad.
So Everett, can I erase-- I
mean, these are all online, too.
So if you have any questions.
>> Lost a little space there, but it's OK.
So binary search tree is
just a way to organize data
not in an array, where
the root is always greater
than the left child and the root is
always less than the right child.
OK.
>> So we have this great search tree here.
We have these numbers, 34,
59, 20, 106, 36, and 52.
And we need to organize
them in such a way
such that the root is greater
than everything on the left side
and it is less than
everything on the right side.
And typically, what you
want to do is try and find
something about in the middle.
With binary search trees, you might have
to play around a little bit with it.
>> But in this case, let's just
assume that we know this first one.
So 36 is our first one here.
Typically, I would try
and choose something
about in the middle that'll
probably yield the best results.
So now we know that everything on
this side needs to be less than 36.
But also, what you could see is
that we have two spots over here.
So if we know that we need two
numbers that are less than the root,
then you could just order these
and choose the third number.
OK.
>> So why don't we start with this side?
So if we know that everything on
this side needs to be less than 36--
but if we look at this one,
we know that this number
has to be less than this number, right?
Because this number here
is on the right side.
And remember, just as in our larger
tree, everything on the right
needs to be larger than the root.
In this way, we know that
whatever is in this needs
to be larger than whatever's here.
OK?
>> So we have two choices
for these two bubbles.
We have 32 and 34-- or sorry.
20 and 34.
So how do you think
we might put these in?
If this one has to be
bigger than this one,
that means we want to
have 20 here and 34 here.
OK.
>> So in the same way, we look
at this kind of sub tree.
And we say, OK, we have not 36.
We have 106, 52, and 59.
Right?
In this case here, we
know that this one needs
to have one thing that's greater than
it and one thing that is less than it.
Right?
So if we put these in order, it's just
about finding that middle value again.
So our middle value is 59.
So then we say, OK, what's less than 59?
Well, that's 52.
And what's greater than 59?
Well, that's 106.
OK?
So it's just a bit like a puzzle.
It typically helps, especially
in small trees like this,
if you just order it, if you
know how many are on the left
and how many are on the
right, that can just
allow you to choose what
should be at your root.
And then you can kind
of work from there.
Mm-hm.
33?
Sure.
OK.
So we want to create a node
or a binary search tree.
And let's look at what might be in it.
And I think this will
actually be our last problem.
Ah.
OK.
>> This is like what we can
think of as a node, right?
We have some value, and we
know that it will either
have left and right children.
Binary search tree-- that means
that it has, at most, two children.
OK?
Let's think about the way we
defined a linked list, right?
>> We had some int that
represented the value.
We had some pointer that represented
what it was going to next.
Binary search tree is very similar.
We still have some value,
n, that we give it, right?
And then I drew these very
explicitly with arrows,
because they are effectively pointers.
OK?
>> So n is typically what?
It's some value.
What do we typically designate it as?
An int.
So we have some int n, or int value,
or whatever you'd like to call it.
And then we have the left
child and the right child.
Right?
And we know that what they're
point-- what are they pointing to?
They're pointing to other nodes, right?
So how would we declare a node pointer?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: Mm-hm.
And we're going to have
two of those, right?
And then we can literally
do left for the left child
and right for the right child.
Actually-- sorry.
Because we need struct.
>> So struct is because we haven't
finished declaring a node yet.
So node is within here.
It's kind of like a
recursive definition, right?
So when we are within
this definition, we
haven't finished declaring
node as the structure,
so we have to do struct
node just to say, yes,
we are in fact referring
back to ourself type thing.
That like once it's
created, it'll be fine.
>> So how big do you guys think this is?
What's the size of this structure?
12.
Why?
Precisely.
And in fact, one of the
first questions one Quiz One
is about sizes, which is why I asked.
All right.
>> We are going to end, because the
DCE will yell at me if we don't.
But if you guys have any questions,
of course, email me, let me know.
You guys are going to rock it.
I'm super excited.
You guys will be done as
of Wednesday, and then
you'll get to work on your final
projects, and it's going to be awesome.
>> I will be here next
week from 4:00 to 4:30
if you guys want to come
pick up your quizzes.
If you want to find me some other time
or just coordinate a different time,
feel free to let me know.
Otherwise, this is our last section.
So it was great to see you guys.
Please take more candy.
And good luck on your quiz.