>> SPEAKER 1: Hey everyone!
Welcome back to section.
So glad to see so many of you both here,
and everyone who's watching online.
So, as usual welcome back.
I hope that you all had a lovely
weekend, full of rest, relaxation.
It was beautiful out yesterday.
So, I hope you enjoyed the outdoors.
>> So first a couple of announcements.
Grading.
So, most of you should have gotten an
email from me about your Scratch Pset,
as well as grading for Pset 1.
So, just a couple things.
Be sure to use check50 in style50.
These are meant to be
resources for you guys,
to make sure that you're getting
as many points as you can
without needlessly losing them.
So, things like style
are very important.
We are going to take off for it.
Some of you may have already
noticed that from your Pset.
And check50 is just a
really easy way to make sure
that we're actually returning what
needs to be returned to the user,
and that everything's working properly.
>> On the second note, make sure your
uploading things to the correct folder.
It makes my life just a
little bit more difficult
if you upload Pset 2 into Pset 1
because when I download things,
they don't download correctly.
And I know it's a little wonky
in a system to get used to,
but just be super
careful, if only for me,
so that when you're getting emails
at like 2 A.M. and I'm grading.
If not cause I have to look
all around for your Pset.
Cool.
>> I know it's early, but I
totally got taken off guard
by an essay that's due this Friday, that
my professors were just like, oh yeah.
Remember, you have an
essay due on Friday.
So, I know no one likes
to think about midterms,
but your first quiz is on October 15th,
which October is starting this week.
So, it might be sooner
than you expected is all.
So that you're not thrown off guard when
I mention next week's section that oh,
your quiz next week, I thought
I'd give you a little bit more
of a heads up now.
>> So, your problem set, number three.
How people have read the
spec out of curiosity?
OK.
We got a couple.
Kind of down from last
week but that's OK.
I know it was beautiful out.
So Break Out.
Definitely after you get done
today read your spec at least
try like downloading
distribution code and running
like the first initial
thing that they ask you to.
Because we are using
distribution code and a library
that we've only been using-- --It's only
the second time we've done this Pset,
crazy things can happen
with your appliance,
and you want to find that
out now versus later.
>> Because if it's Thursday night or it's
Wednesday night and for some reason
your appliance just doesn't
want to run with the library
or with the distribution
code, that means
you can't even start doing the coding.
Because you can't check
to see if it works.
Your not gonna be able
to see if it compiles.
You want to take care of those early in
the week, when you can still email me
or one of the other TFs,
and we can get those fixed.
Because those are issues
that are going to stop you
from making any real progress.
It's not like one bug, that
you can just kind of skip over.
If you're having issues with your
appliance or distribution code,
you really want to get that taken
care of sooner rather than later.
So even if you're not gonna actually
start coding, download the distribution
code, read the spec, make sure
everything's working there.
OK?
If you can just do that, I
promise your lives will be easier.
And so you're probably going
to do it right now right?
OK.
So, any questions there?
Any logistic things?
Everyone's good?
OK.
>> Disclaimer for those of
you in the room and online.
I'm going to be trying to switch
between PowerPoint in the appliance
because we are going
to be doing some coding
today by popular demand of the anonymous
suggestion poll I sent out last week.
So, we will be doing some coding.
So, if you guys also want
to fire up your appliances,
and you should have got an email
from me, with a sample file.
Please feel free to do that.
>> So, we're going to talk about
GDB, which is a debugger.
It's going to help you
kind of figure out where
things are going wrong in your code.
It's really just a way for you to step
through your code as it's happening,
and be able to print out variables
or see what's actually happening
under the hood verses your program
just running, it's like faulting,
and you're like, no idea
what just happened here.
I don't know what line it failed at.
I don't know where it went wrong.
So, GDB is going to help you with that.
Also, if you decide to
continue yes, and take 61,
it will really, really be your
best friend, cause I can tell you
because I'm going through that class.
>> We're going to look at binary
search, which if you guys remember
the great phone book example
spectacle from class.
We'll be implementing that, and
walking through that a little bit more,
and then we're going through four
different sorts, which are Bubble,
Selection, Insertion, and Merge.
Cool.
So, GDB as I mentioned, is a debugger.
And these are kind of the big
things, the big functions or commands
that you use within GDB, and I will walk
you through a demo of it in a second.
>> So, this is not just
going to stay abstract.
I'll try and make it as concrete
as possible for you guys.
So, break.
It'll either be break
like, some number, which
represents a line in your program,
or you can name a function.
So, if you say break main,
it will stop at main,
and let you walk through that function.
>> Likewise, if you have some external
function like Swap or Cube,
that we looked at last week.
If you say break one of those,
whenever your program hits that,
it'll wait for you to
tell it what to do.
Before it will just execute so you
could actually step inside the function
and see what's going on.
So, Next, just skips over the
next line, goes over functions.
Step.
These are all little abstract.
So, I'm just going to run through them,
but you'll see them in use in a second.
>> Step into a function.
So as I was saying,
like with Swap, it would
allow you to actually as if you're
like physically stepping inside,
you can mess with those variables, print
out what they are, see what's going on.
List will literally just print
out the surrounding code.
So, if you kind of forget
where you are in your program,
or you're wondering
what's going on around it,
this will just print out a segment
of like five or six lines around it.
So, you can get oriented
about where you are.
>> Print some variable.
So, if you have the key like
in Caesar, that we'll look at.
You can say Print Key at any point.
It'll tell you what the value is so
that, maybe somewhere along the way,
you overwrote your key.
You can actually tell that because
you can actually observe that value.
>> In the locals, just prints
out your local variables.
So, anytime you're within a loop,
and you just want to see like, oh.
What is my I?
What is this key value
that I initialize here?
What is the message at this point?
It will just print all
of those, so that you
don't have to individually
say, Print I. Print Message.
Print Key.
And then Display.
What that does is as you
step through the program,
it'll just make sure that it's
displaying some certain variable
at every point.
So that you also-- --it's
kind of a shortcut where
you don't have to keep going like, oh.
Print Key or Print I. It just
will automatically do it for you.
>> So, with that, we're going
to see how this goes.
I'm going to try and switch
over to my appliance.
See if I can do this.
All.
We're just going to mirror it.
There's nothing crazy
on my laptop anyways.
OK.
This needs to be this one.
It's so tiny.
Let's see if we can do this.
>> OK.
Alice is obviously struggling
here just a little bit,
but we'll get it in a momento.
OK.
We are just going to increase this.
Can everyone kind of see that?
Maybe a little bit?
I know it's a little small.
You can't quite figure out
how to make this larger.
If anyone knows.
Does anyone know how to make it larger?
OK.
We're going to roll with it .
Doesn't matter anyways because it's just
that's the code that you guys should
have.
>> What's more important
is the terminal here.
And we have here Why is it so small?
Settings.
Oh.
True Ike.
How's this?
Out of there.
Is that better for everyone?
OK,.
Cool.
>> You know when you're in a CS
class technical difficulties
are kind of part of the--
So, let's clear this.
OK.
So, right here in section,
which we had here.
Caesar is an executable file.
So I made it.
So, one thing to realize with GDB is
that it only works on executable files.
So, you can't run it on a dotsy.
You have to actually make
sure that your code compiles,
and that it can actually be run.
>> So, make sure that if it doesn't
compile, get it to compile,
so that you can kind of run through it.
So, to start GDB, all you do,
Gloria type GDB, and then just the
file that you want.
I always misspell Caesar.
But you want to make sure
since it's an executable,
ti's dot flash so that
means you're going
to run CSI you're going to execute
this files either with the debugger.
OK.
So, you do that, you get
this kind of gibberish.
It's just all things about debugger.
You don't really have to
worry about it right now.
And as you see, we have this
open parens, GDP, close parens,
and just kind of looks like
our command line, right?
>> So, what we want to do--
--So, the first thing
is we want to choose
a place to break it.
So, there is one bug
in this Caesar program
that I introduce, that
we're going to find out.
It What it does is it takes the input
Barfoo in all caps, and for some reason
it doesn't change A. It just leaves
it alone, Is everything else correct,
but the second letter
A remains unchanged.
So, we're going to try and
figure out why that is.
So, the first thing you typically
want to do whenever you start on GDB
is figure out where to break it.
>> So Caesar is a pretty short program.
We just have one function, right?
What was our function in Caesar?
There's only one function, Main right?
Main is a function
for all your programs.
If you didn't have Main, I might
be a little worried right now,
but I hope you all had Main in there.
So, what we can do is we can
just break Main, just like that.
So, it says, OK.
We set our breakpoint one there.
>> So, now the thing to remember is Caesar
takes one command line argument right
and we haven't done that anywhere yet.
So, what you do is when
you actually go to run
the program, any program that you're
running in GDB that needs command line
arguments, you're going to input
when you first start running it.
So, in this case, we do
Run with a key of three.
And it will actually start.
>> So, if you see here, we have
If RC is not equal to 2.
So if you guys all have
that file that I sent out up
you'll see that that's like the
first line our main function, right?
It's checking to see if we have
the correct number of arguments.
So, if you're wondering
if RC is correct,
you can do something just like Print RC.
RC is two, which is
what we expected, right?
>> So, we can go Next,
and continue through.
So, we have some key there.
And we can print out our key
to make sure that's correct.
Interesting.
Not quite what we expected.
So, one thing to realize
with GDB also, is
that it's not until you actually hit
Next, that the line that you just saw
is actually executed.
So, in this case Key
hasn't been assigned yet.
So, Key is some garbage value
that you see on the bottom there.
Negative $120-- --It's one billion
and something odd things right?
It's not the Key that we expected.
But if we hit Next, and then we
try and Print key, it's three.
>> Everyone see that?
So, if you get something
that you're like, wait.
This is completely
wrong, and I don't know
how this would happen because all I want
to do is assign a number, a variable,
try hitting Next, try printing
it again, and see if that works.
Because it's only going to execute and
actually assign something after you
hit Next.
Make sense to everyone?
Uh huh?
>> SPEAKER 2: When you random
numbers what does that mean?
>> SPEAKER 1: It's just random.
It's just garbage.
It's just something that your
computer will randomly assign.
Cool.
So, now we can move through, and so
now we have this plain text GetString.
So, let me just introduce what
will happen when we hit Next here.
Our GDB kind of disappears, right?
That's because GetString
is now executing, right?
So, when we saw plain text equals
GetString, open parens and parens,
and we hit Next, that has
actually executed now.
So, it's waiting for
us to input something.
>> So, we're going to input our food which
is what it's failing as I told you
and that just says that it's
finished executing, that the closed
bracket means it's
exiting out of that loop.
So, we can hit Next, and now, as I'm
sure you're all familiar from Caesar,
this is, what's this line going to do.
It's for Int I equals 0, N equals
Strlen, plain text, and then
I is less than n, I, plus, plus.
What is this loop going to do?
Open your message.
Cool.
So, let's start doing that.
>> So, should this condition
match, for our first one?
If it's a B, it's plain text I. We
can get information about our locals.
So, I is zero, and if six, which
we expect, and our key is three.
All that make sense, right?
Those numbers are all
exactly what they should be.
So, hum?
SPEAKER 3: I have
random numbers for mine.
SPEAKER 1: Well, we can check-- --we
can chat about that in a second.
But you should be getting this.
So, if we have a capital
B for our first one,
this condition should catch it, right?
So, if we hit Next, we see
that this If actually executes.
Because if you're following
along in your code,
this line here, where plain text I
is replaced with this arithmetic,
only executes if the If
condition is correct right?
>> GDB is only going to show you
things that are actually executing.
So if this If condition wasn't met, it's
just going to skip to the next line.
OK?
So, we have that.
This bracket means it's
closed out of that loop now.
So, it's going to start again.
Just like that.
So, that we can get info
about our locals here,
and we see that our first
letter has changed, right?
It's now an E, as it should be.
So, we can continue on.
>> And we have this check.
And this check should work, right?
It's A. It should be changed
three letters forward.
But if you notice, we
get something different.
So in this case up here, it caught
it, and so this line executed,
which modified our B.
But, in this case here,
we have that it just skipped it,
and went to the [? L siff. ?]
So something's going on there.
What that's telling you is that,
we know that it should catch here,
but it's not.
Can anyone see what our
problem is in that line?
It's a very minute thing.
And you could also look at your code.
It's also line-- forget what line it is
in there-- but it's in the [INAUDIBLE].
Yes?
>> SPEAKER 4: It's on the greater than
page if you read it in the book.
SPEAKER 1: Exactly.
So, the debugger couldn't tell
you that, but the debugger
could get you down to a line
that you know is not functioning.
And sometimes, when especially
later in the semester, when
you're dealing with a hundred, a
hundred few lines of code, and you
don't know where it's failing,
this is a great way to do it.
So, we found our bug.
You can fix it in your file,
and then you could run it again,
and everything would work perfectly.
And the biggest thing is
this can seem like, OK.
Yeah.
Cool.
You knew what you're looking for.
So, you knew what to do.
>> GDB can be super helpful because you
can print out all these things that you
wouldn't.
It's much more useful than PrintF.
How many of you use
like PrintF statements
to figure out where a bug was, right?
So, with this, you don't
have to keep going back,
and like commenting in
PrintF, or commenting out,
and figure out what
you should be printing.
This actually just allows you to
step through, print out things
as you're going through, so, you can
observe how they change in real time,
as your program is running.
>> And it does take a little
bit of getting used to.
I would highly recommend just kind
of being a little frustrated with it
for right now.
If you spend an hour over the
next week learning how to use GDB,
you will save yourself
so much time later on.
And literally. we tell
this to people every year,
and I remember when I took the
class, I was like, I will be fine.
No.
Pset 6 came on and I was
like, I'm gonna learn
how to use GDB because I don't
know what's going on here.
>> So if you take the time so
use it on smaller programs
that you're going to be
working on, like working
through something like
Visionare, like this.
Or if you want extra practice, I'm sure
I could come up with buggy programs,
for you to debug if you'd like.
>> But if you just take some time to get
used to it, just play around with it,
it will really serve you well.
And it's really one of
those things that you just
have to try, and get your hands dirty
with, before you really understand it.
I really only understood it once
I had to debug things with it,
and it's much nicer to have an idea of
how to debug sooner rather than later.
OK.
Cool.
I know that's kind of like
a crash course in GDB,
and I will definitely work on getting
these to look bigger next time.
Cool.
>> So, if we go back to our PowerPoint.
Is this going to work?
Awh.
Yes.
OK.
So, if you ever need any of
those again, there's the list.
So Binary Search, which everyone
remembers the great spectacle of David
ripping phone books in half.
I don't really get the
phone books anymore,
because like where do you
get phone books these days?
I really do not know.
The Binary Search.
Does anyone remember
how Binary Search works?
Anyone at all?
Yeah?
SPEAKER 5: You know when
you look at which half
it would be in, Based on that,
and get rid of the other half.
>> SPEAKER 1 Exactly.
So, Binary Search, it's kind of a--
--we like to call it divide and conquer.
So, what you'll do is
you'll look in the middle,
and you'll see if it matches
what you're looking for.
And if it doesn't, then you try to
figure out, is it going to be left
half or the right half.
So, this might be if you're looking
at something that's alphabetized,
you see, oh.
Does Allison come before M?
Yes.
So, we're going to
look at the first half.
>> Or it could be like with numbers.
Anything that you can
compare, it can be sorted.
You can use binary search on.
So, anyone remember this
graph or what this is?
It's Asymptotic Complexity.
So, this graph just
describes how long it
takes you to solve a problem as
you increase the number of things
that you're using.
>> So, we have N, which is linear time.
If N over two, which is slightly
better, still grows super fast.
And then we have Login, which is
what we consider Binary Search.
If we notice, as your problem
gets much and much larger,
the time it takes you to solve it
doesn't really increase that much.
It's like comparable
here in the beginning.
You're like, OK.
Anything here doesn't really
matter which one we use,
but you get out to a million, a billion.
You're trying to find some-- --you're
trying to find a needle in a haystack.
>> I think you want this problem.
You want this complexity, not
linear because for all you
know your gonna be searching through
each individual needle, thing of hay,
trying to look for your needle.
And that's not too fun in my opinion.
I like fast.
I like efficient.
And as hardworking students you
guys are, you know work smarter,
not harder type thing, how you
can make up these algorithms.
>> So, we're going to walk
through just a quick example.
I think you guys should have
a hand on Binary Search,
but in case anyone is a little
fuzzy, want to reinforce it,
we're going to just go
through an example here.
So, we're looking for if
the array contains seven.
>> So, first thing we do is
look in the middle, right?
And also you're going to be coding
Binary Search in just a second.
So, it's going to be fun.
So we look in the
middle little arrays 3.
Does 3 equal 7?
Doesn't.
It's six.
So, is it less than
or greater than seven?
Less than.
Yes.
Nice job guys.
I feel I like I should
have candy because I
want to throw it out into the yards.
It's what I am going to do next week.
It will keep you guys sharp.
>> So, we throw away that
first half, right?
it was less than.
we know that everything
on that left hand side
is going to be less than what
we're actually looking for.
So, there's no need to
pay attention to it.
Just forget about it.
So, now we look at our right hand side,
and we look at the middle over there,
and now it's nine.
So, 9 is-- --Everyone?
Greater than what we're
looking for, right?
So, we're going to throw
away everything to the right.
Like that.
Now, all we're left with is one.
So we check, is this one what
we're looking for? it is.
We found what we wanted.
So we're done.
Bilinear Search.
>> And if you notice, we
had seven inputs there.
It only took us like three times,
but if you're doing like a billion,
you guys know how many steps it would
take if we had four billion things?
Any guesses?
It's 32.
32 steps to find something
in a four billion
element array because of powers of two.
So two is to 32, is to four billion.
>> So pretty crazy how you're still within
like a fairly small number of steps
to find something in
four billion elements.
So on that note, we're
going to code this
so you guys can actually
kind of see how this works.
All right, so you guys can code.
I'm going to let you guys
talk for a little bit.
Get to know people around you, which is
what someone wanted from last section.
>> So get to know the people around you.
Talk for a little bit.
And all I want from you
guys right now is just
try to create an outline of pseudocode.
OK?
Whoa.
All I want from you guys is you're
just going to fill in this while case.
So I have set these upper
and lower bounds which
represent the beginning
and end of our array.
And you are going to actually
loop through and figure out
what we're doing within this while loop.
>> So if you can figure out-- I have
a hint there-- what are the cases
that we have here?
So if you want to figure out the
cases, we will pseudocode those
and then we'll actually code them.
And it's going to be, I
think, hopefully it'll
be a little easier than you expect.
Because it's not that much code,
actually, which is really cool.
>> Mm-hm?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]?
INSTRUCTOR: Yes.
There was something
to find in the middle.
>> STUDENT: So we can use that.
OK.
>> INSTRUCTOR: Perfect.
So that's the first thing we need to do.
So find the middle.
Great.
So do you have an idea of how we might
actually find the middle with code?
>> STUDENT: Yeah.
n over 2?
INSTRUCTOR: So n over 2.
So one thing to remember is that
your upper and lower bounds change.
We keep constricting the part
of the array we're looking to.
So n over 2 will only work
for the first thing we do.
So taking upper and lower into account,
how might we get that middle element?
Because we want the middle
between upper and lower, right?
Mm-hm?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> INSTRUCTOR: So we have some middle.
And it'll be upper plus lower over 2.
Awesome.
There we go.
One line down.
You guys are on your way.
So now that we have our
middle, what do we want to do?
Just in general.
You don't have to code it.
Yes.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]?
INSTRUCTOR: So it's plus because you're
finding the average between the two
of them.
So if you think of them as kind
of increasing in from the sides,
think about it as you approach
the middle, you want like that.
So if you were on either side of the
middle, and we have like 5 and 7.
When you add them together you
get 12, you divide by 2, is 6.
>> Sometimes it's hard to
explain why that works,
but if you work through
an example sometimes,
it'll help you figure out if
it should be plus or minus.
Yes.
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
exactly in the middle
if they had a case where
there's a lot of smaller numbers
and like one large number?
>> INSTRUCTOR: So all you need
is the middle of the array.
So if you had a bunch of small numbers
and then one really large number
at the end, it doesn't matter.
All that matters is that
they're sorted, you just
want to look at the middle of
the array because you're still
slicing your problem in half.
Cool.
So now that we have the
middle, what do we do next?
>> STUDENT: Compare.
INSTRUCTOR: The compare.
So compare middle to value_wanted.
Cool.
So you see up here we have
this value we want up here.
Remember this is an array.
So middle refers to the index.
So we want to do values of middle.
Don't forget if you want
to compare, double equals.
You do single equals you're
just going to reassign it,
and then, of course, it's
going to be the value you want.
So don't do that.
>> So we're going to see if
the values at the middle
is equal to the value we want.
Don't forget your braces.
Dropbox should go away.
So what do we do in this case?
If it's what do we want to return?
We're trying to say.
>> STUDENT: Print off.
>> INSTRUCTOR: Well, we
don't want to print off.
So this is a bool here, so we
want to return true or false.
We're saying, is this number
an [? RRA? ?] So if it is,
we just return it true.
If I can spell true.
>> STUDENT: Why wouldn't you return zero?
INSTRUCTOR: So you could
return zero if you wanted.
But in this case because
our function returns a bool,
we need to return either true or false.
STUDENT: When you're
saying boolean expression,
can you set it equal to false?
Like if I want to say, if this condition
is not met, like is upper equals false.
Will it understand if you just
put false on the other side?
INSTRUCTOR: Yeah.
So actually if you're
ever doing something
like is upper or is lower,
that returns true or false
and it's actually bad style to
say equals equals true or equals
equals false.
You want to use that result
as itself as your check.
Not what I wanted.
That's what I wanted.
So in the case of you're asking
about something like save this in c.
>> So if we have int main (void)
and something like this.
And you have if is upper
of some input and you're
asking if you can do
something like this?
Right?
STUDENT: I was trying
to do it [INAUDIBLE].
Because if it's--
INSTRUCTOR: Right.
So you want this to be false, right?
STUDENT: Yeah.
INSTRUCTOR: So in this case you
want it to execute if it's not true.
So the cool thing you do there is this.
So remember exclamation
point negates things?
It says [INAUDIBLE] means not.
So if we look at just
this part here, you'd
say that evaluates to
false as you want it to.
Not false is true which
means this would execute.
Does that make sense?
STUDENT: Yeah.
INSTRUCTOR: Awesome.
OK.
So we could just return
true in this case.
So now we have two other
cases in this case.
What are our two other cases?
Let's just do it this way.
So let's start with else
if values at the middle
is less than the value we want.
So our value in the middle is less
than the value that we're looking for.
>> So which bound do you
think we want to update?
Upper or lower?
Upper?
So which side of the array
are we going to be looking at?
>> STUDENT: The lower.
>> INSTRUCTOR: We are we going
to be looking at the left.
So else if little value is less.
So your middle value here
is less than what we want.
So we want to take the
right side of our array.
So we're going to
update our lower bound.
So we'll reassign our lower.
And what do you think lower should be?
STUDENT: The middle value?
INSTRUCTOR: So the middle value--
STUDENT: Plus 1.
INSTRUCTOR: --plus 1.
Can anyone tell me why
we have that plus 1?
>> STUDENT: [? No value ?]
is more equal to it.
>> INSTRUCTOR: Right.
Because we already know that
our middle value is not equal to
it and we want to exclude it
from all subsequent searches.
If you forget that plus 1, this
will like loop indefinitely.
And you'll just be caught in an
infinite loop and then you'll segfault
and things go bad.
So always make sure that you're not
including the value that you just
looked at.
So we take care of that with a plus 1.
>> So now we have our last condition
which I always for safety sake
you can check here, else if value at
the middle is greater than the value
we want.
That means that we want
the left hand half.
So which one are we going to update?
Upper.
And what is this one going to equal?
Middle minus 1 because,
of course, we want
to make sure that we're not
looking at that middle value again.
And then we have it.
That's it.
That's all binary search is.
It's not that bad, right?
It's like 10 lines of
code with white space.
So very powerful, very useful, you will
be using it in one of your later psets.
Maybe not this one, but later.
So learn it.
Love it.
It will treat you well.
So does anyone have any
questions on binary search?
Yes.
>> STUDENT: Does it matter
whether your n is even or odd?
>> INSTRUCTOR: No.
Because we cast it to the middle as
an int, it will just truncate it.
So it will stay an integer and it will
eventually sort through everything.
So you don't have to worry about that.
Everyone good?
Awesome.
Cool.
So, you guys got this.
Slideshow.
So as we were talking about, I know
David mentioned complexity runtimes.
>> So in the best case, it's just
one, which we call constant time.
Can anyone tell me why that might be?
What type of scenario would that entail?
Mm-hm.
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] first--
INSTRUCTOR: So the middle being the
first element that we come to, right?
So either an array of one or
whatever we're looking for just
happens to be smack dab in the middle.
So that's our best case.
You get into real problems, probably not
going to reach [INAUDIBLE] that often.
What about our worst case?
Our worst case is log n.
And that has to do with the whole
powers of two thing that I talked about.
>> So in the worst case it would mean
that we had to chop the array down
until it was an element of one.
So we had to chop it down in half
as many times as we possibly could.
That's why it's log n because
you just keep dividing by two.
So assumptions, things you
need to know if you're ever
going to use a binary search.
Your elements must be sorted.
They have to be sorted because
that's the only way you
can know if you are able
to throw out half of it.
>> If you had this jumbled bag
of numbers and you're saying,
OK, I'm going to check the middle
number and the number I'm looking for
is less than that, I'm just going
to arbitrarily throw out one half.
You wouldn't know if your
numbers in that other half.
Your list has to be sorted.
As well, this may be
going ahead a little bit,
but you need to have random access.
You need to be able to just
go to that middle element.
If you have to traverse
through something
or it takes you extra steps
to get to that middle element,
it's not log n anymore because
you're adding more work into it.
And this will make a little
more sense in two weeks,
but I just kind of wanted to preface,
give you guys an idea of what's
to come.
But those are the two
important assumptions
that you need for a binary list.
Make sure it's sorted.
That's the big one for
you guys right now.
And on that we can go into
the rest of our sorts.
So four sorts-- bubble,
insertion, selection, and merge.
They're all kind of cool.
If you guys decide to take CS 124,
you'll learn about all sorts of sorts.
And if you're an XKCD fan, there
is a really cool comic about
like really ineffective sorts, which I
highly recommend you going to look at.
One of them is like panic sort, which
is like, oh no, return random array.
Shutdown system.
Leave.
So geeky humor is always good.
>> So does anyone remember kind
of like just a general idea
of how bubble sort works.
You remember?
>> STUDENT: Yeah.
>> INSTRUCTOR: Go for it.
>> STUDENT: So you're going through and
if it's bigger, then you swap the two.
>> INSTRUCTOR: Mm-hm.
Exactly.
So you just iterate through.
You check two numbers.
If the one before is bigger
than the one afterwards,
you just swap them so that in
this way all of the higher numbers
bubble up towards the end of the list
and all the lower numbers bubble down.
>> Did he show you guys the cool
sound effect sorting video?
It's kind of cool.
So as Robert just said, the algorithm
that you just step through the list,
swapping the adjacent values
if they're not in order.
And then just keep repeating
until you don't make any swaps.
So not bad, right?
So we just have a quick example here.
So this is going to sort
them in ascending order.
So when we go through the first
time, we look through eight
and six are obviously not
in order, we swap them.
>> So look at the next one.
Eight and four not in order.
Swap them.
And then eight and two, swap them.
There we go.
So after your first pass, you
know that your largest number
is going to be all the way
at the top because it's just
going to be constantly
larger than everything else
and it's just going to bubble
up all the way to the end there.
Does that makes sense to everyone?
Cool.
>> So then we look at our second pass.
Six and four, switch.
Six and two, switch.
And now we have a few things in order.
So for every pass that we
make through our entire list,
we know that like that many numbers
at the end will have been sorted.
So we do a third pass,
which is one swap.
And then on our fourth
pass, we have zero slots.
And so we know that our
array has been sorted.
>> And that is the big
thing with bubble sort.
We know that when we
have zero swaps, that
means that everything
is in complete order.
It's kind of how we check.
So we are also going to code bubble
sort which also is not that bad.
None of these are that bad.
I know they can seem a little scary.
I know when I took
the class, even when I
was teaching the class for
the first time last year,
I was like, how do I do this?
It makes sense in theory, but
how do we actually do this?
Which is why I also want to walk
through code with you guys here.
So I have a pseudocode
for you guys this time.
So just keep this in mind as
we're about to transition over.
So we have some counter that
keeps track of our swaps,
because we need to make sure
that we're checking that.
And we iterate the entire array
as we just did with this example.
If the element before is larger than
the element after where we're at,
we swap them and we increment our
counter because as soon as we swap,
we want to let our counter know that.
Any questions there?
Something seems funny over here.
STUDENT: Do you set the counter to zero
every time you go through the loop?
Don't you keep going
back to zero every time?
INSTRUCTOR: Not necessarily.
So what happens is we go through here.
So do while, remember, this
will execute once without fail.
So it's going to set the
counter equal to zero,
then it's going to iterate through.
As it iterates through,
it will update counter.
As it updates counter, when it's done,
when it's reached the end of the array,
if our list hasn't been sorted,
counter will have been updated.
>> So then it checks the condition and it
says, OK, is counter greater than zero.
If it is, do it again.
You want to reset so that when you
go through, counter is equal to zero.
If you go through a sorted
array, nothing changes,
this fails, and you
return the sorted list.
Does that makes sense?
STUDENT: It might in a little bit.
INSTRUCTOR: OK.
If there's any other
question that comes up.
Yes.
>> STUDENT: What would the function
be for swapping the elements?
>> INSTRUCTOR: So we can actually write
that if we're going to right now.
Cool.
So on that note, Alison is going
to switch back to the appliance.
It's going to be fun.
And we have our nice
bubble sort thing here.
So I already did cycling
through the array.
We have our swaps that
are equal to zero.
So we want to swap adjacent
elements if they're out of order.
So the first thing we need to
do is iterate through our array.
>> So how do you think we might
iterate through our array?
We have for and i equals 0.
We want i to be less
than n minus 1 minus k.
And I'll explain that in a second.
So this is an optimization here where,
remember how I said after every pass
through the array we
know that whatever's on--
>> So after one pass we
know that this is sorted.
After two passes we know
that all this is sorted.
After three passes we
know that's sorted.
So the way I'm iterating
through the array here,
is it's making sure to only go
through what we know is unsorted.
OK?
That's just an optimization.
You could write it naively just
iterating through everything,
it would just take longer.
With this four loop it's
just a nice optimization
because we know that after every full
iteration through the array here,
like every full loop here, we know
that one more of these elements
will be sorted at the end.
>> So we don't have to worry about those.
Does that makes sense to everyone?
That cool little trick?
So in that case, if
we're iterating through,
we know that we want to check if
array n and n plus 1 are in order.
OK.
So here's the pseudocode.
We want to check if array n
and n plus 1 are in order.
So what might we have there?
It's going to be some conditional.
It will be an if.
>> STUDENT: If array n is
less than array n plus 1.
INSTRUCTOR: Mm-hm.
Well, less than or greater than.
STUDENT: Greater than.
Then we want to swap them.
Exactly.
So now we get into what's the
mechanism for swapping them?
So we went through this briefly,
a type of swap function last week.
Does anyone remember how it worked?
So we can't just reassign them, right?
Because one of them will get lost.
If we said A is equal to B and then B
is equal to A, all a sudden both of them
are just equal to B.
>> So what we have to do is we
have a temporary variable that's
going to hold one of ours while
we're in the process of swapping.
So what we have is we'll have some int
temp is equal to-- you can assign it
to whichever one you want, just
make sure you keep track of it--
so in this case, I'm going to
assign it to array n plus 1.
So that's going to hold whatever
value is in that second block
that we're looking at.
>> And then we can do is we can go
ahead and reassign array n plus 1,
because we know we
have that value stored.
This is also one of the big
things-- I don't know if any of you
had issues where if you switch two
lines of code suddenly things worked.
Order is very important in CS.
So make sure you diagram
things out if possible
as to what's actually happening.
So now we're going to
reassign array n plus 1,
because we know we
have that value stored.
>> And we can assign that to array
n or in this case array i.
Too many variables.
OK.
So now we've reassigned array i
plus 1 to equal what's in array i.
And now we can go back and
assign array i to what?
Anyone?
>> STUDENT: 10.
>> INSTRUCTOR: 10.
Exactly.
And one last thing.
If we have swapped it now,
what do we need to do?
What's the one thing
that's going to tell us
if we ever terminate this program?
What tells us that we
have a sorted list?
If we don't perform any swaps, right?
If swaps is equal to
zero at the end of this.
So whenever you perform a swap, as we
just did here, we want to update swaps.
And I know there was a
question earlier about can you
use zero or one instead
of true or false.
And that's what this does here.
So this says if not swaps.
So if swaps is zero, which is-- I always
get my truths and my falses mixed up.
We want us to evaluate
to true and it's not.
So if it's zero, then it's false.
If you negate it with a
[? bang ?] it becomes true.
So then this line executes.
>> Truths and false and
zeros and ones get crazy.
Just if you slowly walk
through it it will make sense.
But that's what this little
bit of code here does.
So this checks to see
have we done any swaps.
So if it's anything besides
zero, it's going to be false
and the whole thing is
going to execute again.
Cool?
>> STUDENT: What does break do?
>> INSTRUCTOR: Break just
breaks you out of the loop.
So in this case it would
just like end the program
and you would just
have your sorted list.
STUDENT: Amazing.
INSTRUCTOR: I'm sorry?
STUDENT: Because previously we
used written 1 over written zero
to present that if
that will work or not.
>> INSTRUCTOR: Yeah.
So you can return zero or 1.
In this case, because we're not actually
doing anything with the function,
we just want it to break.
We don't really care about it.
Brake is also good if
it's used for breaking out
of four loops or conditions that
you don't want to keep executing.
It just takes you out of them.
It's a bit of a nuance thing.
I feel like there's
a lot of hand waving,
like you'll learn about this soon.
>> But you'll learn about this soon.
I promise.
OK.
So does everyone get bubble sort?
Not too bad.
Iterate through, swap things using a
temp variable, and we're all set there?
Cool.
Awesome.
OK.
Back to the PowerPoint.
Any questions in general
about these so far?
Cool.
Mm-hm.
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] int main usually.
Do you have to have that for this?
>> INSTRUCTOR: So we were just looking
just at the actual sorting algorithm.
If you had it within
like a larger program,
you would have an int main somewhere.
Depending on where you
use this algorithm,
it would determine what's
being returned by it.
But for our case, we're strictly
looking at how does this actually
iterate through an array.
So we don't worry about it.
>> So we were talking about best case and
worst case scenarios for binary search.
So it's also important to do
that for each of our sorts.
So what do you think is the worst
case runtime of bubble sort?
You guys remember?
>> STUDENT: N minus 1.
INSTRUCTOR: N minus 1.
So that means there are
n minus 1 comparisons.
So one thing to realize is
that on the first iteration,
we go through, we compare
these two-- so that's 1.
These two, three, four.
So after one iteration we
already have four comparisons.
When I'm talking about runtime and n.
N represents the number of comparisons
as a function of how many elements
we have.
OK?
>> So we go through, we have four.
The next time you know we don't
have to take care of this.
We compare these two,
these two, these two,
and if we didn't have that optimization
with the four loop that I wrote,
you would be comparing in here anyways.
So you would have to
run through the array
and make n comparisons n
times, because every time we
run through it we sort one thing.
>> And every time we run through
the array, we make n comparisons.
So our runtime for this is
actually n squared, which
is much worse in our
log end because that
means if we had four
billion elements, it's
going to take us four billion
squared instead of 32.
So not the best runtime,
but for some things,
you know, if you're within
a certain range of elements
bubble sort may be fine to use.
>> OK.
So now what is the best case runtime?
STUDENT: Zero?
Or 1?
>> INSTRUCTOR: So 1 would
be one comparison.
Right.
>> STUDENT: N minus 1?
>> INSTRUCTOR: So, yeah.
So n minus 1.
Whenever you have a concept like n
minus 1, we tend to just drop it off
and we just say n because you have
to compare each of these-- each pair.
So it would be n minus 1, which we
we'd just say is approximately n.
When you're dealing with runtime,
everything is in approximates.
As long as the exponent is
correct, you're pretty good.
>> That's how we deal with it.
So that the best case is n, which
means that the list is already sorted,
and all we do is run through
and check that it's sorted.
Cool.
All right.
So as you see here, we
just have some more graphs.
So n squared.
Fun.
Much worse than n as we see, and
much, much worse than log 2n.
And then you also get into log logs.
And you take 124, you get into
like log star, which is like crazy.
So if you're interested,
lookup log star.
It's kind of fun.
So we have this great chart.
Just a heads up, this a
wonderful chart to have
for your mid-term because we
long to ask you these thins.
So just a heads up, have this on your
mid-term on your nice cheat sheet
there.
So we just looked at bubble sort.
Worst case, n squared, best case, n.
And we're going to look at the others.
>> And as you can see, the only
one that really does well
is merge sort, which we'll get into why.
So we're going to go to the
next one here-- selection sort.
Does anyone remember how
selection sort worked?
Go for it.
>> STUDENT: Basically go through
an order and create a new list.
And just as you're putting elements
in, put them in the right place
in the new list.
>> INSTRUCTOR: So that sounds
more like insertion sort.
But you're really close.
They're very similar.
Even I get them mixed up sometimes.
Before this section I was like, wait.
OK.
So what you want to
do is selection sort,
the way you can think
about it and the way
I make sure I try not to get
them mixed up, is it goes through
and it selects the
smallest number and it
puts that at the beginning of your list.
It swaps it with that first spot.
They actually have an example for me.
Awesome.
So just a way to think of it-- selection
sort, select the smallest value.
And we're going to
run through an example
that I think will help because
I think visuals always help.
So we start out with something
that is completely unsorted.
Red will be unsorted,
green will be sorted.
It will all make sense in a second.
>> So we go through and we iterate
from the beginning to the end.
And we say, OK, 2 is
our smallest number.
So we're going to take 2 and we're going
to move it to the front of our array
because it's the
smallest number we have.
So that's what this is doing here.
It's just going to swap those two.
So now we have a sorted
part and an unsorted part.
And what's good to remember
about selection sort
is we're only selecting
from the unsorted part.
>> The sorted part you just leave alone.
Mm-hm?
>> STUDENT: How does it know what is
the smallest without comparing it
to every other value in the array.
INSTRUCTOR: It does compare it.
We like skipped it.
This is just general overall.
Yeah.
When we write the code I'm
sure you'll be more satisfied.
But you store this first
element as the smallest.
You compare and you
say, OK, is it smaller?
Yes.
Keep it.
Here is it smaller?
No?
>> This is your smallest,
reassign it to your value.
And you'll be much happier
when we go through the code.
So we go through, we swap it, so then
we look at this unsorted portion.
So we're going to select three out.
We're going to put it on at
the end of our sorted portion.
And we're just going to keep doing
that, doing that, and doing that.
So this is our kind of pseudocode here.
We'll code it up here in a second.
But just something to walk
through on a high level.
You're going to go from
i equals 0 to n minus 2.
That's another optimization.
Don't worry too much about it.
So as you were saying.
As Jacob was saying, how do we
keep track of what our minimum is?
How do we know?
We have to compare
everything in our list.
>> So minimum equals i.
It's just saying in this case
the index of our minimum value.
So then it's going to iterate through
and it goes from j equals i plus 1.
So we already know that
that's our first element.
We don't need to compare it to itself.
So we start comparing it to the next
one which is why it's i plus 1 to n
minus 1, which is the
end of the array there.
And we said if array at
j is less than array min,
then we reassign where
our minimum indices is.
>> And if min is not equal to i, as
in where we were back over here.
So like when we first did this one.
In this case, it would start at
zero, it would end up being two.
So min would not equal i in the end.
That lets us know that
we need to swap them.
I feel like a concrete example
will help much more than this.
So I'll code this up with you guys
right now and I think it'll be better.
>> Sorts tend to work that way in that
it's often better just to see them.
So what we want to do is
we first want the smallest
element in its position in the array.
Exactly what Jacob was saying.
You need to store that somehow.
So we're going to start here
iterating over the array.
We're going to say it's our
first one just to start with.
So we are going to have int
smallest is equal to array at i.
>> So one thing to notice, every
time this loop executes,
we are starting one step further along.
When we start we look at this one.
The next time we iterate through,
we're starting at this one
and assigning it our smallest value.
So it's very similar to bubble sort
where we know that after one pass,
this last element is sorted.
With selection sort,
it's just the opposite.
>> At every pass, we know that
the first one is sorted.
After the second pass, the
second one will be sorted.
And as you saw with the slide examples,
our sorted portion just keeps growing.
So by setting our smallest one
to arrays i, all it's doing
is constricting what
we're looking at so as
to minimize the number
of comparisons we make.
Does that make sense to everyone?
Do you need me to run through that
again slower or in different words?
I'm happy to.
OK.
>> So we're storing the
value at this point,
but we also want to store the index.
So we're going to store the
position of the smallest
one, which is just going to be i.
So now Jacob is satisfied.
We have things stored.
And now we need to look through
the unsorted part of the array.
So in this case this
would be our unsorted.
This is i.
OK.
>> So what we're going to do
is going to be for a loop.
Whenever you need to
iterate through an array,
your mind could go to for a loop.
So for some int k
equals-- what do we think
k is going to equal to start with?
This is what we set as our smallest
value and we want to compare it.
What do we want to compare it to?
It's going to be this next one, right?
So we want k to be initialized
to i plus 1 to start.
>> And we want k in this case we
already have size stored up here,
so we can just use size.
Size being the size of the array.
And we just want to
update k by one each time.
Cool.
So now we need to find
the smallest element here.
So if we iterate through, we
want to say, if array at k
is less than our smallest value--
this is where we're actually
keeping track of what's
the smallest here--
then we want to reassign
what our smallest value is.
>> This means that, oh, we're
iterating through here.
Whatever value is here is
not our smallest thing.
We don't want it.
We want to reassign it.
So if we're reassigning it, what do
you think might be in this code here?
We want to reassign
smallest and position.
So what is smallest now?
STUDENT: Array k.
INSTRUCTOR: Array k.
And what is position now?
What's the indices of
our smallest value?
It's just k.
So array k, k, they match up.
So we wanted to reassign that.
And then after we found our smallest,
so at the end of this for loop
here we have found what our smallest
value is, so we just swap it.
In this case, like say our
smallest value is out here.
This is our smallest value.
>> We just want to swap it here, which is
what that swap function at the bottom
did, which we just wrote up
together a couple minutes ago.
So it should look familiar.
And then it will just iterate
through until it reaches all the way
to the end, which means that you
have zero elements that are unsorted
and everything else has been sorted.
Make sense?
A little more concretely?
The code help?
>> STUDENT: For a size, you never
really define it or change it,
how does it know?
>> INSTRUCTOR: So one thing to
notice up here is int size.
So we're saying in this sort-- sort
is a function in this case-- it's
selection sort, it's passed
in with the function.
So if it wasn't passed
in, you would do something
like with the length of the array
or you would iterate through
to find the length.
But because it's passed
in, we can just use it.
You just assume that the user
gave you a valid size that
actually represents
a size of your array.
Cool?
>> If you guys have any trouble with these
or want more practice coding sorts
on your own, you should
go to study.cs50.
It's a tool.
They have a checker that
you can actually write.
They do pseudocode.
They have more videos and slides
including the ones I use here.
So if you're still feeling a
little fuzzy, try that out.
As always, come talk to me, too.
Question?
>> STUDENT: Are you saying the
size is previously defined?
INSTRUCTOR: Yes.
Size is previously defined up
here in the function declaration.
So you assume that it's been passed in
by the user, and for simplicity's sake,
we're going to assume that the
user gave us the correct size.
Cool.
So that's selection sort.
Guys, I know we're learning a lot today.
It's a dense data for section.
So with that, we are going
to go to insertion sort.
>> OK.
So before that we have to do
our runtime analysis here.
So in the best case,
granted since I showed you
the table I already
kind of gave it away.
But best case runtime, what do we think?
Everything sorted.
N squared.
Anyone have an explanation
for why you think?
>> STUDENT: You're comparing through--
INSTRUCTOR: Right.
You're comparing through.
At every iteration, even though
we're decrementing this by one,
you're still searching through
everything to find the smallest one.
So even if your smallest value
is here at the beginning,
you're still comparing it
against everything else
to make sure it's the smallest thing.
So you'll end up running through
approximately n squared times.
All right.
And what's the worst case?
Also n squared because you're going
to be doing that same procedure.
So in this case, selection
sort has something
that we also call expected runtime.
So in the others, we just know
the upper and lower bounds.
Depending on how crazy our
list is or how unsorted it is,
they vary between n or n squared.
We don't know.
>> But because selection sort has the same
worst and best case, that tells us that
no matter what type of input we
have, whether it's completely
sorted or completely
reverse sorted, it's
going to take the same amount of time.
So in that case, if you
remember from our table,
it actually had a value that
these two sorts don't have,
which is expected runtime.
So we know that whenever
we run selection sort,
it's guaranteed to
run an n squared time.
There is no variability there.
It's just expected.
And, again, if you want to learn
more, take CS 124 in the Spring.
All right.
We've seen this one.
Cool.
So insertion sort.
And I'm probably going
to blaze through this.
I won't have you guys code it.
We'll just walk through it.
So insertion sort is kind
of similar to selection sort
in that we have both an unsorted
and sorted part of the array.
>> But what's different is that
as we go through one by one,
we just take whatever number
is next in our unsorted,
and correctly sort it
into our sorted array.
It'll make more sense with an example.
So everything starts as unsorted,
just like with selection sort.
And we're going to sort this in
ascending order as we have been.
So on our first pass
we take the first value
and we say, OK, you are
now in a list by yourself.
>> Because you are in a list
by yourself, you are sorted.
Congratulations for being the
first element in this array.
You're already sorted all on your own.
So now we have a sorted
and an unsorted array.
So now we take the first.
What happens between here
and here is that we say,
OK, we're going to look at the
first value of our unsorted array
and we're going to input it in its
correct place in the sorted array.
>> So what we do is we take 5 and
we say, OK, 5 is greater than 3,
so we just insert it right
to the right of that.
We're good.
So then we go on to our next one.
And we take 2.
We say, OK, 2 is less
than 3, so we know that it
needs to be at the
front of our list now.
So what we do is we push 3 and 5 down
and we move 2 into that first slot.
So we're just inserting it into
the correct place it should be.
>> Then we look at our
next one, and we say 6.
OK, 6 is greater than
everything in our sorted array,
so we just tag it on to the end.
And then we look at 4.
4 is less than 6, it's less
than 5 but it's greater than 3.
So we just insert it right into
the middle between 3 and 5.
So to make that a little
bit more concrete,
here is kind of the
idea of what happened.
So for each unsorted element, we
determine where in the sorted portion
it is.
>> So keeping in mind the
sorted and unsorted,
we have to traverse through and figure
out where it fits in the sorted array.
And we insert it by shifting the
elements to the right of it down.
And then we just keep
iterating through until we
have a completely sorted list
where unsorted is now zero
and sorted takes up the
entirety of our list.
So, again, to make things even
more concrete, we have pseudocode.
>> So basically for i is
equal to 0 to n minus 1,
that's just the length of our array.
We have some element that is equal to
the first array or the first indices.
We set j equal to that.
So while j is greater than
zero and the array, j minus 1
is greater than the
element, so all that's doing
is making sure that
your j really represents
the unsorted portion of the array.
>> So while there is still things
to sort and j minus one is-- what
is the element her?
J was never defined here.
It's kind of annoying.
OK.
Anyways.
So j minus 1, you're checking
the element before it.
You're saying, OK, is the element
before wherever I am-- let's
actually draw this out.
So let's say this is
like on our second pass.
So i is going to be equal
to 1, which is here.
>> So i is going to be equal to 1.
This would be 2, 4, 5, 6, 7.
All right.
So our element in this case
is going to be equal to 4.
And we have some j that's
going to be equal to 1.
Oh, j is decrementing.
That's what it is.
So j is equal to i, so what this is
saying is that as we move forward,
we're just making sure
that we're not over
indexing this way when we're trying
to insert things into our sorted list.
>> So when j is equal to 1 in this case and
array j minus one-- so array j minus 1
is 2 in this case-- if that's
greater than the element,
then all this is doing
is shifting things down.
So in this case, array j minus one
would be array zero, which is 2.
2 is not greater than 4,
so this doesn't execute.
So the shift doesn't move down.
What this does here is just
moving your sorted array down.
In this case, actually, we
could do-- let's make this 3.
So if we're to walk through with
this example, we're now here.
This is sorted.
This is unsorted.
Cool?
So i is equal to 2, so
our element is equal to 3.
And our j is equal to 2.
So we look through and we
say, OK, is array j minus one
greater than the element
that we're looking at?
And the answer is yes, right?
4 is greater than 3 and j
is 2, so this code executes.
>> So now what we do an array at
2, so right here, we swap them.
So we just say, OK, array
at 2 is now going to be 3.
And j is going to equal
j minus 1, which is 1.
That's horrible, but
you guys get the idea.
J is now equal to 1.
And array j is just going to be
equal to our element, which was 4.
I erased something I shouldn't
have or miswrote something,
but you guys get the idea.
>> It move at n.
And then if this were, it would loop
again and it would say, OK, j is 1 now.
And array j minus 1 is now 2.
Is 2 less than our element?
No?
That means that we've
inserted this element
in the correct spot in our sorted array.
Then we can take this and we say,
OK, our sorted array is here.
And it would take this number 6 and be
like, OK, is 6 less than this number?
No?
Cool.
We're fine.
>> Do it again.
We say 7.
Is 7 less than the end
of our sorted array?
No.
So we're fine.
So this would be sorted.
Basically all this does
is it's saying take
the first element of
your unsorted array,
figure out where it goes
in your sorted array.
And this just takes care
of swaps to do that.
You're basically just swapping
until it's in the right spot.
The visual image is that you're
moving everything down by doing that.
>> So it's like half bubble sort-esque.
Check out study 50.
I highly recommend trying
to code this on your own.
If you have any issues or you want to
see sample code for an insertion sort,
please let me know.
I'm always around.
So worst case runtime
and best case runtime.
As you guy saw from the table I already
showed you, it's both n squared and n.
>> So kind of going off of what we talked
about with our previous sorts, worst
case runtime is that if
it's completely unsorted,
we have to compare all of these n times.
We do a whole lot of comparisons
because if it's in reverse order,
we're going to say, OK, this
is the same, this is good,
and this one will have to be compared
against the first one to be moved back.
And as we get toward
the tail end, we have
to compare, compare, and
compare against everything.
>> So it ends up being
approximately n squared.
If it's correct then you
say, OK, 2, you're good.
3, you're compared to 2.
You're good.
4, you just compare to the tail.
6, compare to the tail, you're fine.
So for every spot if it's already
sorted, you're making one comparison.
So it's just n.
And because we have a best case runtime
of n and a worst case runtime of n
squared, we have no expected runtime.
>> It just depends on the
chaos of our list there.
And again, another
graph and another table.
So differences between sorts.
I'm just going to breeze through, I
feel like we've talked extensively
about how they all kind
of vary and link together.
So merge sort is the last one
I shall bore you guys with.
We do have a pretty colorful picture.
So merge sort is a recursive algorithm.
So do you guys know what
a recursive function is?
>> Anyone want to say?
You want to try?
So a recursive function is just
a function that calls itself.
So if you guys are familiar
with the Fibonacci sequence,
that's deemed recursive because
you take the previous two
and add them together
to get your next one.
So recursive, I always think
of recursion as like a spiral
so you're like spiraling down into it.
But it's just a function
that calls itself.
>> And, actually, really quickly I
can show you what that looks like.
So recursive here, if we look, this is
the recursive way to sum over an array.
So all that we do is
we have sum function
sum that takes a size and an array.
And if you notice, size
decrements by one each time.
And all it does is if x is equal to
zero-- so if the size of the array
is equal to zero-- it returns zero.
>> Otherwise it sums this
last element of the array,
and then takes a sum of
the rest of the array.
So it's just breaking it down
into smaller and smaller problems.
Long story short, recursion,
function that calls itself.
If that's all you got out of this,
that's what a recursive function is.
If you take 51, you will get very,
very comfortable with recursion.
It's really cool.
It made sense at like
3 AM one night out.
And I was like, why
have I never use this?
>> So for merge sort, basically
what it's going to do is it's
going to break it down and break it
down until it's just single elements.
The single elements are easy to sort.
We see that.
If you have one element, it's
already considered sorted.
So on an input of n elements,
if n is less than 2,
just return because that means
it's either 0 or 1 as we've seen.
Those are considered sorted elements.
>> Otherwise break it in half.
Sort the first half, sort the second
half, and then merge them together.
Why it's called merge sort.
So we have here we'll sort these.
So we keep having them
until the array size is 1.
So when it's 1, we just return
because this is a sorted array,
and this is a sorted array, and that's
a sorted array, we're all sorted.
So then what we do is we
start merging them together.
>> So the way you can
think about merging is
you just remove the smaller
number of each of the sub arrays
and just append it to the emerged array.
So if you look here, when we have
these sets we have 4, 6, and 1.
When we want to merge these,
we look at these first two
and we say, OK, 1 is smaller,
it goes to the front.
4 and 6, there's nothing to compare
it to, just tag it on to the end.
>> When we combine these two, we just
take the smaller one of these two,
so it's 1.
And now we take the
smaller of these two, so 2.
Smaller of these two, 3.
Smaller of these two, 4, 5, 6.
So you're just pulling off these.
And because they've
been sorted previously,
you just have one
comparison each time there.
So more code here, just representation.
So you start at the middle and
you sort left and the right
and then you just merge those.
>> And we don't have code
for merge right here.
But, again, if you go on
study 50, it'll be there.
Otherwise come talk to me
if you're still confused.
So cool thing here is that best case,
worst case, and expected runtime
are all in log n, which
is far better than we've
seen for the rest of our sorts.
We've seen n squared
and what we actually
get here is n log n, which is great.
>> Look at how much better that is.
Such a nice curve.
So much more efficient.
If you ever can, use merge sort.
It will save you time.
Then again, as we said, if
you're down in this lower region,
it doesn't make that
much of a difference.
You get up to thousands
and thousands of inputs,
you definitely want a
more efficient algorithm.
And, again, our lovely table of all
sorts that you guys learned today.
>> So I know it's been a dense day.
This isn't necessarily going
to help you with your pset.
But I just want to make a disclaimer
that section is not just about psets.
All this material is fair
game for your midterms.
And also if you do continue on with CS,
these are really important fundamentals
that you would need to know.
So some days will be a
little more pset help,
but some weeks will be
much more actual content
that may not seem super
useful to you right now,
but I promise if you continue
on will be very, very useful.
>> So that's it for section.
Down to the wire.
I did it within one minute.
But there you go.
And I will have donuts or candy.
Is anyone allergic to
anything, by the way?
Eggs and milk.
So donuts are a no?
OK.
All right.
Chocolate no?
Starburst.
Starbursts are good.
OK.
We're going to have
Starburst next week then.
That's what I'll get.
You guys have a great week.
Read your spec.
>> Let me know if you have any questions.
Pset two grades should be
out to you by Thursday.
If you have any questions
about how I graded something
or why I graded something the way I
did, please email me, come talk to me.
I'm a little crazy this
week, but I promise
I will still reply within 24 hours.
So have a great week, everyone.
Good luck on your pset.