[MUSIC PLAYING]
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
All right, everyone.
Welcome back to section.
So our agenda for today is going
over much more web dev stuff.
I don't know how many of
you have seen your psets
since it was released
earlier this morning.
I would as how many
people have read the spec,
but seeing as how you've had all
of, like, seven hours to look at it
and it's a Monday and
you've probably had class,
I'm going to assume that
most of you have not.
If you have, extra kudos.
>> You're basically helping
implement a simple web
server in C, which is a brand new pset,
so you guys get to be the Guinea pigs.
It's going to be a fun, wild week,
but I think it'll be a lot of fun
and it'll be a really
good experience actually.
So to prepare you for
that, in section today,
we're going to go chmod, TCP/IP, and
then a little bit of HTML and CSS.
>> At the end, we'll actually code
up a simple web page together
to help you guys kind of get
more familiarized with that.
And then if you haven't picked up
your quizzes, they're in front,
but I'm pretty sure everyone
here has their quiz.
And also on that note,
solutions aren't up yet,
but as soon as we finish-- like, the
last few people taking their quizzes--
they will be up.
If you have any questions
in the meantime,
feel free to email me personally.
I will respond with your individual
questions, as I always do.
>> So on that note, chmod.
So basically all you
need to know about chmod
is that it's used to change
file permissions, right?
So it's just some systems call it a
change permissions, as it says here.
And if you ever want to see
what permissions a file has,
instead of just doing
ls, you could do ls -l.
l stands for long.
>> So you'll do long lists
of everything, and it
will give you much more detailed
information about each of your files.
And you'll see something-- I'm
going to skip ahead for a second--
but you'll see something similar to
that top line there for each file.
And we'll go through what that means.
>> So basically, to change
your file permissions,
you just want to use chmod.
You can think of it as any other
UNIX call like ls or cd or whatnot.
It's just kind of another like call.
>> So we do chmod and then we'll
have three digits typically.
There are a couple ways to do
it, one of which we'll go over.
But typically, you'll have three
digits ranging from 0 to 7 each time.
>> So one thing is that there are
three different permissions
that we can give each file.
And it's readable, which is
represented by r, which will make sense
in a little bit; w, which is
writable; and executable, which is x.
I know that the e one, executable,
maybe not the most sense, but we
represent it with x.
>> And then what happens is each of these
also have the number representation.
So we have 1, 2, and 4.
And basically what happens is
each of these three numbers
here corresponds to a
different set of users
that those permissions pertain to.
>> So you can think of that first
number corresponds to the actual user
or the owner of the file, the second
number will correspond to the group,
and the last one refers
to the world, OK?
So what happens is remember
those numbers-- r is 4, w is 2,
x is 1, right?
This-- if you sum these up,
that gives you that first number
that we might input in our chmod.
>> So in this case, what
would this number be?
It'd be 4 plus 2 plus
1, which is a 7, right?
And in this case, these
don't have anything,
so this right here would
translate to chmod 700, OK?
And what that does is it grants all
of these permissions to your user.
>> So this means our user
can do whatever they want.
They can read this file.
They can execute this file.
They can write to this file.
But group and the world, no
permissions whatsoever, OK?
>> So another way to write that, we can
do chmod of three digits, each of which
corresponds to whatever the sum or that
specific group is, specific subset.
Or we can do actually another thing.
Hold on.
We can do something with these here.
>> How many of you saw an example
where it was like to chmod a plus x?
Did you see that in lecture, I think?
So a stands for all.
It means give it to all users,
which I forgot to put here.
>> But a plus x, if we
notice here, if we do
to chmod-- what group we're
talking about plus the permissions
we want to give them.
So this can be a plus or a minus.
Plus adds permission.
Minus takes away permission.
Pretty intuitive, I think.
>> So a plus x means chmod.
So change the permissions of all people
if this is an a-- add permissions.
And x-- that means what permission
are we granting everyone.
Read, write, or execute?
>> AUDIENCE: Execute.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Execute.
So we are giving all users
permission to execute this file, OK?
So what if we wanted to do
that with the numeric form?
So remember with numeric,
we want three numbers.
>> AUDIENCE: 4.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: What was that?
AUDIENCE: 4.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Not 4.
AUDIENCE: 0, 0, 4.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Well, we want
to give it to all users, right?
So we're going to have
a number in each slot.
That's going to be the
same number in each slot
because we just want to give
everyone executable permissions.
So executable is 1,
but on the right track.
>> So if we did chmod 111 that would
be the equivalent of chmod a plus x.
Does that make sense to everyone?
We're going to go through
a couple of examples.
>> So the big takeaway
here is a's not on here,
but a just means give it to all users.
u is if you just want
to give or take away
a specific permission from
the user or the owner.
g is for the group,
so that middle digit.
And then others you can think of
as the world, that last digit.
>> So with that, we'll go to an example,
because I feel like examples always
make these things easier to understand.
So rwx-- we went through this--
could also be represent as 700.
That's the example we looked
at more of the picture.
So chmod 444 on some file
would give what permissions?
You were really close.
AUDIENCE: Readable to all.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Readable.
So readable to everyone, right?
And then what's another way to do that?
If we want to do chmod with either
r's or w's, plus and minuses,
what would that call look like?
It would be chmod what?
>> AUDIENCE: a plus r.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: a plus r on the 5.
OK, so this is the same as this,
just two different translations
of the same thing.
So with that, we have these.
So I want you guys to try and write
these kind of in their opposite way.
>> So with chmod 555,
what would it be like?
Would it be a plus or u plus or whatnot?
For u plus x, give me the three numbers.
And then tell me about what permissions
we're actually granting and to who?
>> So I'll give you guys two
minutes to work on that.
Feel free to talk with each other.
For those of you who came in a little
late, there is candy and shirts.
We have three shirts left, and
we have Kit Kats and Starbursts.
So feel free to come grab
some in this little interlude.
>> Also, the last one is tricky.
It's two chmods for the last one.
Actually, let me close that door
while you guys are working on that.
Candy's always necessary
on a Monday afternoon.
>> OK, so chmod 555.
What's another way we could write that?
Any ideas?
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: a plus rx.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: r plus rx.
Do you want to explain why it'd be rx?
>> AUDIENCE: Because you have
5, so that's 4 plus 1,
so that's read plus
executable, and it's for all.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Right.
So just to reiterate, 5 here
we know as the sum of 4 and 1,
because each number in our trio is the
sum of the permissions for that subset,
right?
Either the user, the
group, or the world.
So in this case, we know that
5 has to be formed by 4 and 1.
>> And 4 and 1 correspond to
readable and executable.
We are giving it to everyone,
so we can do chmod a plus rx.
And obviously, we just went
through the questions there,
so now this file is executable
and readable to everyone.
>> So what about the second one?
What might the number for that one be?
Any ideas?
Go ahead.
>> AUDIENCE: 100 [INAUDIBLE].
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: 100.
Exactly.
So do you want to explain why 100?
AUDIENCE: Because it's for the
user, so it's in first position.
And then x executable is 1.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Exactly.
So we are granting executable
permissions to just the user.
So in this case, it would be 100.
And I have all the answers
up on the next slide in case
you're writing lots of things down.
>> OK, so this next one is actually done
with two chmods, you could do it.
So does anyone have
any idea how you might
get chmod 640 rewritten
in the other way?
You can change the user first and then
you can change the group is my hint.
>> So if we were just changing the
user, which is this first one here,
what might our call be?
So user is u, right?
So chmod u plus what?
Mmhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: rw.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: rw.
Right, for read and write, because read
is 4, w is 2, those sum together as 6.
So we get chmod u plus rw,
and we get our first 6 there.
>> So then to get the 4, we now want
to change our group settings.
So we're going to do chmod g plus what?
What's a 4?
>> AUDIENCE: r.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: r.
Precisely.
So we're giving the owner
read and write permissions
and we're giving the group read
permissions, which we have all up here.
Mmhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: If you can write something,
does it imply you can execute it?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: You
can write to something--
I don't believe that it
implies you can execute it.
Cool.
So that's all that we just went through.
So on this next one, it's
just kind of common cases
that you want to keep in
mind for your problem set.
These are typically the permissions
that we like you to use.
>> So for 711, that gives
us, of course, user
all permissions, which
tends to make sense.
And then it's executable by the
group in the world, which makes sense
if you have some directory, you
want to be able to traverse into it.
People need access.
>> For any non-PHP file, you're going
to use 644, which would do what?
What does that imply, or what
permissions does that give?
So the owner can what?
AUDIENCE: Read and write.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Read and write.
And then group and others
can just read, right?
And then chmod 600 for any
PHP files that you use,
your owner, again, can
read and write to it
but everyone else is
just kind of blocked off.
>> So this will actually
be more useful when
you get to your problem
set next week where
you're actually building a website.
So if you ever run into
any strange problems
where it's not loading
properly, maybe you
need to add an executable
permission, or maybe you need a read
or write permission.
Little things that tend to trip people
up, but that's kind of like the go-to
when you start next week's pset.
And I would give you more
hints on this week's pset,
but I have yet to look at it since
it was released this morning.
But you email me, I will have looked
at it by the time I respond tomorrow.
>> So now, is everyone good with chmod?
Any lingering questions?
Pretty straightforward.
Just kind of keeping track of what
read, write, and execute numbers are
is probably the hardest part.
>> So with TCP/IP, all these protocols,
kind of like with your data structures
last week, it's much more
important to kind of get
a higher level intuition of them.
This is not CS143 where we're going
to ask you to implement a network,
so you'll be fine if
you don't understand
the nitty gritty of all the protocols.
What's important to understand is
kind of like what they represent
and why they're important.
>> So TCP/IP, of course, it is the
Transmission Control Protocol
or Internet Protocol, which is
basically just a set of laws basically
or standards that tell data
how it should be handled,
how it should be packetized,
transmitted, and received.
So it basically, just as it
says here, increases the chances
that data gets where
you want it to get to.
>> I'm sure if you guys went to
lecture or watched it online,
he has-- I don't know
if he did it this year,
but I know last year, he had a
demo where he had a picture of Rob
and he split it up into
four and put it in envelopes
and tried to get it across Sanders.
And you can kind of
think of it that way.
It's just a set of rules that
tell data how to get someplace
and lets you know if
you are missing data,
in the same way that if you are
taking multiple pages of notes
and you label them with page 104, page
204, and you go back to study later
and you are missing something--
you can't find page 304-- you know
something's wrong, so you
can look through your notes
again or ask someone to resend you
the lecture notes from that day.
The same way with data on the internet.
If I'm asking for
something from some server
and it needs to send
it in multiple packets,
probably going to number
it in some way, let
me know how many I should have received,
and tell me, oh, this is one of 10
or this is one of 10,000.
That way when I go to reassemble
all the pieces together,
I know if something's missing
and I can ask for that again.
Does that make sense?
Just a set of rules.
At its basis, set of rules, OK?
>> So we also talked a
little bit about ports.
This is really just a standard that
lets you know what type of data
is being transmitted in these packets.
If we go with our
envelope example, we don't
know that it's a picture of
Rob in there unless we write it
on the outside of our envelope.
So ports are basically the same thing.
It's just a way to figure out what
type of data is being transmitted.
>> So we have all of the
most common ones here.
So 21-- these are also kind
of like good things to know.
It's kind of an easy quiz question.
Be like, what does port 80 do?
Or, what does port 443 do?
So good things to know.
>> So we have here, 21 is file
transfer protocol, so just
the rules that govern file transfer.
25, something that we all
use far too much, is email.
53 is the domain name
system, which is basically
just kind of a lookup for the
IP address of a domain name.
>> So I'm pretty sure it was
mentioned in lecture, if you
go to something like
google.com, it has an IP address
that's associated with it.
It's not actually google.com.
And so 53 is the port
that actually takes
care of kind of translating it
into that IP address for you.
And then 80 and 443 are very common.
You either have your web page or
you have your secure web page,
which a lot of web pages are
transferring over to now.
>> So that's kind of high level
overview of transfer protocol.
I don't see much more in depth.
It's kind of cool stuff
if you're interested.
There's plenty of resources.
Wikipedia actually is
a pretty good page.
So I was looking at it
just a little while ago,
so I would highly recommend
looking at it if you're interested
or take 143 in two years because
I think it's every other year.
>> So on the end of this, we're
talking about web pages and HTTP,
which is actually our next topic for
today before we go into HTML and CSS
and you can actually code up a web page.
It'll be fun.
We'll have pictures of
bunnies and it'll be great.
>> So HTTP, as you can see here,
is one of the lovely acronyms
for this week, which is
Hypertext Transfer protocol.
So again, it's just
another set of rules that
governs hypertext
transfer, in this case.
So best way to learn
about this is just kind of
to break it down into
these individual words
because there are a lot of
words on the screen there.
>> So we're going to start with hypertext.
So "hyper," you can think of
"above," like super-type thing.
So it's really just text taken to the
next level, so it's like super text,
like the next text.
So it's basically just
text that gives us
more information than
normal text does, OK?
>> So in this case here, this is hypertext.
This tells us that we have
some link that we're going to,
which is cs50.net, which
is now cs50.harvard.edu.
These slides are a little old.
And it's going to display
it as this, as a hyperlink,
and then a really cool website.
>> So it's text, which is a little
bit of really cool things in there.
So you can link things and you can
insert images and you can style things.
And the most familiar thing that you
guys probably have with hypertext
is HyperText Markup Language, HTML,
which of course is all of the web
that we see around us, granted
with some CSS style thrown in.
>> But if anyone was
really big with MySpace,
I'm sure you all used HTML
all the time to create
those perfect profiles, right?
I feel like that might be an
outdated reference now, but whatever.
Just a little-- you guys
aren't that much younger.
Some of you are older than me.
MySpace was still a
thing when I was young.
I'm not that old.
>> Anyways, HTML just a form of hypertext.
So hypertext is just
text with added features.
So transfer protocol is probably
the more iffy thing to explain.
Obviously, transfer--
just transfer of data.
So either between the client, like
your web brother, and a server.
So basically just the
way the internet works.
>> So the exact request of
how these work, we're
actually going to look at an
example request and response.
But how we request
information from a server
and how the server responds to us is
what this transfer protocol governs.
So the request and the response have
to follow these specific set of rules.
It's standardized so that no matter
where you're using the internet,
it always works the same, OK?
>> Again, protocol, set of rules.
It's just a normal
interaction in the same way
that Professor Malan talks about
if someone extends their hand,
you know that it's common courtesy to
reach yours out and shake their hand.
That's a protocol, right?
>> So I give some standardized request,
which is I want to shake your hand,
and you give some standardized
response, which is either no thanks
or you could try and shake my
hand or maybe you're going to try
and fist bump me.
And we don't have a protocol for that.
It breaks down.
But if everyone follows the
same protocol, of course,
it goes much more seamlessly.
People get to know each other.
Everyone's happy.
>> So in the world of the web,
everyone follows the same rules--
slightly better than social standards.
But with that, we'll look
at an example request here.
So there's this little
key here on bottom
that tells you the different colors,
what they're supposed to mean.
>> So white is just like your method
request and protocol version--
so method request, version.
And then this is some
field name and the value
of that field, which we will
go into very, very shortly.
So this is an example request.
This is like me extending out,
wanting to introduce myself.
>> This is what the client
or what your web browser
would be sending to your server.
So this is a get request, so it's
asking for something from the server.
And it's, of course, HTTP
and it's version 1.1.
>> So the rest of this here is what we call
the header, and its extra information
that gives us a better idea of
what we're actually asking for,
or information that we want to give
the server that might be pertinent.
So User-Agent gives some more
description on-- for example, here,
curl/7.24.0 is actually going to tell
the server that we're using Google
Chrome as our browser.
So if you ever hear
about people who talk
about making an app responsive
to multiple browsers,
this is something that they
would use because if you
don't know what browser
the request is coming from,
you can't tailor the data to that.
So in this case, user
is just giving this kind
of identifying information
about what browser
your user is currently using, OK?
>> So then we also have host, which is
where we're actually wanting to go to.
In this case, we want to go to
apple.com, buy some cool new iPads
or something, maybe cute
lights at our dorm rooms.
And name value at the end is just
a filler, just a general thing
for you guys to see.
It doesn't actually
correspond to anything here.
>> So you can have as much or as
little as you want in each case.
Most of the time, these are optional.
It just depends on what
you need from the browser,
from your user in order to
properly give the request.
Or it depends on what your user
actually wants to give up to the server.
So you may have many, many
of these header field names
or you might just have a couple.
As with so many things
I've said in this section,
it really depends on the context
of how you're using this.
>> So does that makes sense to everyone?
This is just an example of
a request, headers, whatnot.
OK, so with that, we have some response.
>> Again, we have our status code, protocol
version, and then field name and field
value as always.
So our protocol version
and our status code is 200.
OK, which means that,
yes, everything went well.
Here's what you want.
>> The server type, the content
type-- it tells us, OK, you're
going to get some text HTML.
Here is the length of it and here's
what you should do with the connection.
OK, so again, depending
on the data you're
asking for, depending on what the
server wants to return to you,
you may have more of these field
names, you might have less.
Totally context dependent.
>> And as far as this status
code here, of course,
200 is not the only one
you could have, right?
We have lots of status codes.
Does anyone remember any of the
others that we mentioned in lecture?
A lot of them start with 4.
>> AUDIENCE: 404.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: 404, which is?
>> AUDIENCE: File not found?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: File not found.
Exactly.
So what about 403?
AUDIENCE: Forbidden.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Forbidden.
So what do you think
that means with chmods?
>> AUDIENCE: It means that you
don't have permission to read it.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Exactly.
In some way, you don't have
permission to access it, right?
So 404, 403.
There's a really funny
one that we always
introduce every year that
I should have put up here,
like 413, which is I'm a teapot.
You can google this.
It's funny like, that is code
413 and it's I'm a teapot.
Which I don't know why you would
ever need that on the internet,
but I digress.
AUDIENCE: Maybe you're a tea pot.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Maybe
the server is a tea pot.
Who knows?
All right, so we're about to
transition into real coding.
I feel like you guys are going to
get out of here pretty quickly.
>> AUDIENCE: Why does it
say "server: twice?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Hm?
Server twice?
That is a good question.
I am not sure.
I will find out and
I will email you all.
>> OK, any other questions besides that?
Good?
Cool.
>> HTML and CSS, and now we
get to all the fun parts.
So as I mentioned before, HTML
is probably one of the things
you guys are most familiar with.
So we have HyperText Markup Language.
>> The best way to learn this-- I don't
have any prepared slides or anything
for you guys with HTML.
It's really about learning the syntax.
And if you were in the MySpace
day, you would have this down.
>> So really, the biggest thing is
just to practice and experiment.
One of the great resources I would
highly recommend using is W3Schools.
So just W, 3, and then Schools.
They have a lot of
resources on HTML, on CSS,
and they actually have a
split screen sort of thing
where they'll give you example code.
You can fiddle with it,
change it, and press Update,
and it'll show you what it
actually does to the web page.
>> So I would highly recommend using that.
It's pretty cool.
You won't get seg faults
here when things go wrong.
If you manage to get
a seg fault with HTML,
do let me know because I'm
going to be real intrigued.
But it's really cool because
you can change things,
you can see them updated live.
And I think you'll get a much
more intuitive grasp of HTML
if you actually just spend some
time experimenting with it.
So that's why I said,
practice and experiment.
>> Google, from here on
out, will probably be
one of your best resources and friends.
Or Bing-- I'm working at Microsoft,
so maybe I should say Bing.
But pretty much anything
is just going to be syntax,
so understanding what the tags are,
understanding-- at least with CSS--
how to change certain attributes.
It'll be super useful.
>> So even though we don't
have any prepared things,
we do have kind of some best practices
that we want you guys to try and abide
by-- or rather, you should
abide by until further notice.
So close all your tags.
Hopefully everyone has-- you know what,
if this doesn't make sense right now,
I promise it will make sense
when we're coding up the page.
But close all your tags.
So if you ever have some
header that's bracket,
H1, bracket, make sure that
whenever you're done with that,
you close that header.
Validate your page with W3 Validator.
If you don't close your tags,
you can get unexpected behavior.
It'll say that your page is invalid
if you run it through this validator.
So when in doubt-- and especially
on this week's and next week's
pset-- in the same way that we ask
you to use check 50 and style 50,
you could think of this
as one of your checks, OK?
>> So if it does not pass the W3 Validator.
That is something we will dock you on.
Or I'm telling you right
now, I will dock you on.
So make sure it validates.
It's not hard.
You just paste in your code
and it'll either say good job
or you're missing
something in the same way
that style 50 tells you
where you're messing up.
>> And then one last thing
is you want to separate
your markup, which is all that HTML
or your text, and your styling.
So we'll do an example
of that right after this.
So HTML and CSS should be separate.
And we're going to be talking about
MVC, which is Model View Controller,
next week.
You guys should probably
learn about that in lecture
tomorrow if you had
already learned it today.
>> And it's just kind of
a paradigm that we tend
to use when creating web
pages to separate things out.
You can think of it in the same way
that we tend to separate functions in C
where we hash to find things.
It's just a way to
make your life easier.
It separates out attributes or code that
you would be using over and over again,
but in this way, it kind
of keeps it nice and neat.
And if you want to change
one thing, you change it once
and it's changed everywhere else.
So it's more for your
ease and flexibility.
>> So with CSS, it's very similar
to HTML, but instead of tags
that I mentioned just now, we
use what's called selectors.
And they basically just kind
of associate a certain tag
in HTML with different attributes.
And when I say attributes, I mean
things like font color, font style,
the color of the background,
the color of your text.
Those sorts of things.
Like if it's centered,
if it's off to the right,
if it's inverted-- all
of these cool things.
Any stylistic things
that you do to your text,
this is what I mean with attributes.
>> And then two main things to know is that
selectors-- two of the main factors--
are ID, which is unique.
You can only use that for one thing.
Otherwise, it's going to yell at you.
And when we define it
in a CSS file, it will
be hash ID and then
what attributes we want.
I promise we're going to
go through an example.
It'll make a lot more sense.
>> Class can refer to multiple blocks.
So you can have your
first and third paragraph
have the same sort of attributes if
you associate them with the same class.
And when we define them
in CSS, we do a dot class,
with class being whatever
you want it to be named.
>> So I know this is right
now very abstract.
That's why we're going to code.
I know you guys love
that, and you all are
going to help me because
this is your web page.
This is our section's web page, guys.
So are there any questions before I
turn off the PowerPoint, or anything
you want me to scroll back
to before we start coding?
>> AUDIENCE: When you say match tags,
do you mean selectors or tags?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: You can
think of them as the same thing.
It's just different words.
I mean, like selectors.
But selectors also map to tags.
So you can think of them as
effectively the same thing.
I promise it's going to make
more sense when we code.
Anything from the
PowerPoint or any questions
right now before we actually
create our section's page?
Everyone ready?
Cool.
>> So I have one started.
Let me increase the font for you guys.
OK, so right now, we just have a
bare bones web page right here.
>> We have some HTML.
We have some header, which we
see here as example web page.
Some title, some font.
These are tags, OK?
So when I mean close your tags, we see
here this bracket head is your opening
tag, and this bracket
/head is closing it, OK?
>> So you could think of this as
your braces in your if conditions
or your for loops.
If you have one at the beginning,
you want one at the end.
It will still work most of the time
if you don't have a closed tag,
but best practice is close your tags.
>> So in this case, let's change this.
We're going to have section seven.
"Section Webpage."
So I'm just going to change this.
>> And if we go over here and we
reload-- gotta save and reload--
we notice that up here
it changed, right?
Cool.
So this changes the title.
This is whatever's on your tab.
>> So this is kind of
looking kind of boring.
I don't know about guys.
I think we want something else here.
>> So what we can do is the
header is just there.
Let's do some sort of body.
So we have some body here.
I always do open and
close my tags to start,
in the same way that I do braces.
Ah.
Wait, what?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Ah.
You guys got me.
Good job.
Gold star.
>> OK, so we have some body here.
And now let's start adding some text.
So you have a couple different
options for adding text.
We have things like headers.
We have just normal text.
So let's just start with a header.
Actually, if you guys want
to pull up W3 School's HTML,
you can kind of look around
and if there's anything
particularly that you want to try out
with this web page, we can do that.
So in this case, let's just do some h1.
So h1 is like the highest header.
It will give you something
that is very large and bold.
>> And in this case, what do we want
for the first text on our web page?
Anything.
You guys are going to create this.
I'm just going to type.
AUDIENCE: Welcome.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Welcome.
OK, so if we save it and we reload,
we have a great big welcome.
So just so you can see the
differences, let's do something on H6.
What do we want right here?
Right?
>> OK, so just so you can
see the difference.
Yeah, Sublime.
So if you notice, h1, very, very large.
h6, like bold, but much smaller,
and you have everything in between.
So you could have h2, h3, h4.
And these are just headers,
so if you're trying
to create a web page that
has different sections,
maybe you want to use
headers in there somewhere.
>> Cool.
So we'll add some more
things in our body.
I see that it would be kind
of cool if we had a picture.
I feel like everyone could use maybe
a cute bunny picture right about now,
so we're going to find
a bunny picture first.
>> I don't know if you guys have any
preferences on which one we want.
Do you have any preferences?
This one here?
Down.
OK.
That one it is.
Good choices.
>> OK, so we're going to view our image.
Look at that.
Look at that adorable thing.
How could you be sad
on a Monday with this?
>> So we're just going
to copy the image URL.
And what we want to do is, let's just
say we have some p for paragraph.
We're going to say "Look
look at the cute bunny.
d'awwww."
I love my bunnies.
I have a bunny at home.
I miss my bunny.
So what we're going to do--
I don't know if you guys want
to google this-- but with HTML,
how might you include an image?
Literally, if you google
"include image HTML,"
why don't you guys tell me
what this tag should be?
>> AUDIENCE: img source--
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: img source--
AUDIENCE: --equals--
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: --equals--
AUDIENCE: --quote-- yeah.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Perfect.
Lovely.
See, MySpace generation, right?
AUDIENCE: Neopets.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Neopets.
Oh, OK.
Wow.
It's been crazy.
OK.
>> So make sure I get this right.
Cool.
So this should be here.
And then if we reload, we have our
bunny on the page Isn't this adorable?
>> This is so cute.
You chose a great, great photo.
I'm digging it.
>> OK, so we have this adorable bunny now.
We were able to add an
image, just like that.
So basically if there's any image
you want to add to your web page,
you can add it just like this.
Another thing would be if
you have the image stored
in the same folder as
this file, you can just
write whatever the name of that image
is instead of having a web link.
>> It would still be in quotes.
It would just be like
if we had named this--
if this picture had been saved
in the folder with this HTML file
that I'm editing and it
was called bunny.jpg.
We could also do that
and it would show up.
However, I don't have this saved in
the file and I want to keep the bunny,
so we're going to keep the link.
>> AUDIENCE: What is rabbit.org?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: rabbit.org.
It's an appropriate--
look, you can adopt it.
Adoption.
bunny.jpg.
I want to adopt this bunny.
Oh, god, it's so cute.
>> OK, so we've added headers.
We've added a picture.
Obviously, we added
some text here, right?
If we wanted to add other
texts, we'd go like this.
So this is another paragraph.
>> And we say "this is another paragraph."
Also, I'm a horrible speller,
so I may misspell things.
Just FYI.
>> So we have another
paragraph here, right?
So maybe you want to do something
a little more interesting than just
have all your text, like right aligned.
Maybe you want to center your text, OK?
>> So if someone wants to use those
handy computers in front of you
and tell me how you're
going to center this text,
>> AUDIENCE: p align.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So
p align equals "center."
He's killing it, guys.
Y'all need to step up.
And we have "This is centered."
And now we have something centered.
>> In the same way, if you
want it left aligned,
you could do align equals
left, align equals right.
Totally up to you.
If I did right here, then this
should-- now it's right aligned.
>> AUDIENCE: Allison?
By image source, why isn't
there close of the img source?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Sorry.
This one should be
there Now you're good.
Now we're good.
AUDIENCE: Don't you have
to close it there, or not?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Well, so img
source, this one is just-- with image,
it's just seen as one element, whereas
if you notice for the rest of these,
we have some tag then information that
it pertains to and then a closing tag.
But with image, everything's
just sort of self-contained.
Cool.
So you guys know how to create a
header, you know how to input text,
you know how to put an image
in now, you can align things.
>> Another thing that you
might want to be able to do
is to create a list in CS-- we're
kind of going into next week's pset.
The stuff that we
typically teach this week
goes really well with
next week's pset, so we're
kind of mixing, overlapping things here.
But it'll be useful for next week.
>> So if we wanted to create some
list, how might we do that?
You can't answer this time.
Someone else has to.
It's not hard, guys, promise.
Google "unordered list HTML."
What was that?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Right.
So do we want ordered or unordered?
Let's do an unordered.
So we have some ul, which
stands for Unordered List.
And what do we have for each element?
Does it needs its own tag?
Can we just start writing things?
>> AUDIENCE: li.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: li.
So what is our list going to be?
What do we want here?
We just do names.
Just do Jacob.
>> AUDIENCE: Rabbit foods.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Rabbit foods.
OK I like this.
Rabbit foods.
>> OK, so we have carrots.
I like this rabbit theme.
I'm digging it a lot.
AUDIENCE: Actually, I thought
that Jacob would be a legit.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Jacob?
Jacob is rabbit food.
If you saw Jacob's
photo from office hours,
you might have thought he got
attacked by a killer rabbit.
>> AUDIENCE: I have a rabbit now.
I have a killer rabbit now.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
Are you kidding me?
>> AUDIENCE: I'll bring it next section.
I have it.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
This is ridiculous.
Anyway.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah, my proctor
has a rabbit as well.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: I want a rabbit.
OK, whoever brings a real rabbit to
the next section, total brownie points.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: Oh, it's not real.
It's a stuffed rabbit.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Oh
yeah, we can close these.
Looks rad.
AUDIENCE: Does it actually matter?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It doesn't.
With most of these things,
you don't close the tag,
99% of the time nothing bad's going
to happen, but it's good style, too.
So Jacob.
And we have lettuce.
AUDIENCE: For links,
it's really important.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Hm?
AUDIENCE: For hyperlinks.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: For hyperlinks.
Yes, hyperlinks need it.
OK, so let's see here.
And we have the close of our list.
And we look at that.
We have all-- Jacob, right there.
Rabbit food.
Reminds me of Bunnicula.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: I'm bringing back
all the old school references today,
aren't I?
Just all the old school references.
Should have brought like
Gogurts or something for snacks.
>> AUDIENCE: Or Gushers.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Oh.
OK.
I'll see if I can track
down Gushers for next week.
I think I can do that.
I think we might have
some in the office.
>> OK, so we've covered a lot of different
things you can do with HTML, right?
And as you can probably see, it's
nothing-- hopefully, not too intim--
if it is, I don't mean
to belittle anyone.
If you're having trouble,
please come talk to me.
>> But most of it is just
looking at the syntax, right?
If you want an unordered list,
if you want some sort of list,
if you want to align something or
format something, it's all about just
kind of looking up the
syntax for HTML, right?
And one thing that's
pretty cool actually
is if you go to-- let's see,
what's a nice website that we like?
Anyone have any favorite websites
that are OK to bring up online?
You know what, let's just do CS50.
That's nice and safe, right?
>> OK, so CS50 here.
Oh look, there's a section right now.
If you like the way it looks.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: We are not
going to do meta section, guys.
It's not happening.
It would be cool, but
we're not going to do it.
>> So what do you could
do if you like the way
this works is you can always right
click on any web page that you like
and you can do View Page Source.
It will bring up all the HTML.
And this is actually a really good
way to style your own web page.
Go to a web page that you
really like and look at the HTML
and figure out how they did it.
>> And literally, as long
as you cite things,
as long as you're not just
stealing from people, it's OK.
Especially for CS50
[? finance ?], we are
kind of expecting you to get
inspiration from other website.
So feel free.
Look through websites that
you think are really pretty
and figure out how they use
HTML and CSS to do these things.
>> So as you see here, there's obviously
like links and we have a class here.
We have a link here.
We have a list.
We probably have some
pictures in here somewhere.
>> We've got some cool style here.
This is the next thing
we're going to do.
So style, whenever you see these
style brackets, it's CSS basically.
Ben, did you have a question?
>> AUDIENCE: What is div?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: div
is just a-- what is div?
AUDIENCE: Division.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Division.
Yeah, it's just like
separating different elements.
OK, so here is what we're
going to go into next.
So this may not be the best
style because, if you notice
we have HTML and style in the same page,
and we actually want to separate those,
OK?
And actually, let me
open up my right one
because this is supposed to be
the PDF, so we have style.css.
>> So what we can do here is these
are cool things like some fade
and we could try and do that, but I feel
like I would mess that up on the fly,
so I encourage you guys to
go try that on your own,
but I'm not going to do it right now.
So if you guys, remember,
if you ever hit problem set,
something swoops in from the side.
It has to do with the fade and
the transition and whatnot.
>> AUDIENCE: And that's all CSS and HTML?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: All CSS and HTML.
Yeah.
So you can do a lot of really
cool things with CSS and HTML.
So with our awesome
bunny web page here, we
are going to do a little
bit of CSS styling with it.
>> So if you ever have a style
sheet, which we have here,
you can just call style.css.
You can call it whatever you want.
What's important is that we're going
to reference it in our web.html here.
>> So what we're going to do is
we-- so I don't mess this up--
we are going to link
these two files together.
So in the same way-- I'm going
to draw an analogy to C here.
In the same way that if you have
some library-- and we have cs50.h--
our compiler links it.
This is just an explicit
link on our part.
So in the same way that we do
hash include some file, what
I'm about to write is just the
HTML/CSS equivalent of that.
>> We are just saying, OK, this web page
is going to use this stylesheet, OK?
So we have link rel equal to stylesheet.
And then we have type, css.
And then href equals.
>> OK.
So all this did here is you can
think of this as the same thing
as a hash include.
Obviously it looks a little more
complicated, but in all cases,
it's effectively the same thing.
So this is just some linking of a
style sheet, it's of type text/css,
and the name of it is style.css.
>> What's important to know
is that the web page
that I'm working right now-- web.html
and style.css-- are in the same folder.
Because in different folders,
you need to give the actual root
to it or the path to it.
But in this case, we're keeping it
super simple and it's going to be here.
So if we do that, I have some
things already queued up here.
>> So we have some body, which is going
to have our background color, which
right now is light blue.
We can change it if we want, but
if I remember this correctly,
it should just change it to light blue.
And now we have a light blue background.
And we had here-- can anyone remember
which one is hash ID or class?
>> AUDIENCE: ID.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: ID.
Cool.
So what we want to do
is which of these fonts
or which-- do we want "Look at
the cute bunny" to be purple?
I think we want that to be purple.
I'm pretty down with that being purple.
>> So what you do is you do
ID equals-- in this case
I said, what, pretty color here.
We reload.
All of a sudden, it's purple.
OK, so with ID, remember
it needs to be unique,
so I should never be using
this ID anywhere else.
But with class, as we have
here with a pretty font,
I should be able to use
that anywhere I want to.
>> So let's do this one here.
So we can say class equals pretty font.
And if we look now, we have
this cool pretty font here.
So maybe I want to do both.
OK, I actually don't know if this is
going to work but I want to try it.
And this is how you learn CSS and HTML.
You're like, you know
what, I want to try this.
I'm not sure if it's going to work.
Let's see if it works.
>> And look at that.
Now it's in purple and
it's a pretty font.
OK, so you have all these
different things you can do.
Do you have a question?
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Well, just like the colors
you're using are words.
Is there a way to do colors
with the hexadecimal RGB?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: You can also
do it with hexidecimal, I believe.
Yeah.
But it's kind of nice if you
don't want to look them up.
You can just be like, purple or blue.
AUDIENCE: Let's hope they
know what that means.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Right.
So let's make this read or chartreuse.
Why would you ever choose chartreuse?
It's an interesting color.
>> OK, so obviously we can see we
can change things however we want.
If you wanted to create-- let's say
we wanted to create another class.
What might you guys want to change?
If you pull up W3Schools'
CSS documentation,
I leave the floor to you guys.
We can try and do something cool with
this in the last couple of minutes.
Because I've kind of given you a
crash course on a lot of cool things
that you can do.
But in the end, as I said, if you
just experiment, you'll learn a lot.
>> AUDIENCE: Did you look up that font?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah,
I looked up that font.
So like literally, I
went to-- what did I do?
I did CSS font list, and
then I did font stack,
and then I was like, look, here
are all the cool fonts you can do.
And there was this one, so
I copied it to my clipboard.
And then I was like,
OK, cool, there we go.
All done.
>> AUDIENCE: So you do have to make sure
that CSS knows what that font is.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: What's it say at the end?
Cursive?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Cursive.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Background image.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Background image.
OK.
So you want to tell me how to do this.
I leave this to you.
I'm just typing up here now.
The wheel is in your hands.
>> AUDIENCE: OK
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK.
What am I doing?
>> AUDIENCE: Doing-- I know what
comes after the curly brace.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK.
So probably in body, I
would assume, because we're
doing with the background image.
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah, let's do that.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK.
AUDIENCE: OK, so background
colon, and then we
need a URL address of that image.
Maybe pseudo-code that for now, perhaps.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: What
would you like me to--
AUDIENCE: I'm thinking like a GIF.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: A GIF?
That's going to be interesting.
OK, what am I googling here?
>> AUDIENCE: No, that's your choice.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Why
don't we-- if it's a bunny,
I feel like we should have a
nice grassy lawn or something.
>> AUDIENCE: Meadow.
A meadow.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: A meadow?
OK.
AUDIENCE: Or Rachel Maddow.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
This one looks pretty.
Oh, that's tiny, though.
We need a good size image.
Let's see.
Oh, look.
That's a pretty meadow.
You know what, I like this one.
Let's copy this one.
>> AUDIENCE: OK, so I think it's
the URL, open parentheses.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK, URL.
>> AUDIENCE: Then the address.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK.
Is that all we need?
>> AUDIENCE: Close parentheses semicolon,
and then space, background hyphen
attachment colon fixed, and curly brace.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK.
Let's see if that works.
It's going to be pretty cool if it does.
I'm real excited right here.
It didn't work.
I wonder why.
AUDIENCE: Maybe the URL
has to be in quotations.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Maybe.
And this is how we learn, guys.
>> AUDIENCE: Can we have background
color and background image?
>> AUDIENCE: No.
One supersedes the other.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: I dunno.
Let's see.
Let's check it out and see.
>> AUDIENCE: Oh, maybe, yeah.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK, this is
obviously-- I [INAUDIBLE] here.
So OK.
AUDIENCE: Background attachment.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Ah.
>> AUDIENCE: OK, I don't know.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It
looks like it should work.
Are you sure it's colon after the URL?
>> AUDIENCE: No, it's semicolon.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It's semicolon.
AUDIENCE: Did I say colon?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: You said a colon.
AUDIENCE: Oh no.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: There you go.
AUDIENCE: Oh, wait, now
we can't read the text.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Now
you can't read the text,
but we have the background image.
Mmhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: Does HTML
support dynamic content?
Like, could you resize that picture
depending on the window size,
or is that a CSS--
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
So CSS has to do that.
So if you guys are interested
in learning advanced CSS,
I am co-teaching a
seminar on CSS on the 7th.
And I promise it will
be much more in depth
and do much more cool
things in this section.
And my co-teacher is like
total front end web dev master.
So it'll be pretty cool if you want
to learn about all the cool things
that CSS can do.
>> But what we have here with
his background attachment
fixed-- so it's some fixed size--
but you can actually dynamically--
if you ever see web pages, as
most good web pages will do,
when you adjust the
size of your browser,
it adjusts the background or how much
is showing or reformats things, right?
So that's what we call
relative positioning.
>> And CSS can actually grab how big your
browser width is or how tall it is,
and you can position things
according to the relative sizes
versus absolute sizes.
And that's obviously more advanced
CSS, but that is something you can do.
If you want to learn
more, come to my seminar.
>> So that is something you can do.
And CSS can actually
do-- CSS and JavaScript,
which we'll get into next week--
can allow you to dynamically change
pages without having to
reload them all the time.
And you get to do some
pretty cool stuff.
>> So is there another thing
that you guys might want to do
or anything you want to explore?
We have 10 minutes left.
We can also leave early, but if
you want to do some more web stuff,
we can, but I'm not
going to force you to.
But we can also just eat candy.
AUDIENCE: Highlight the text
white so you can read it.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK.
So in this case, we want some p.
AUDIENCE: Should we do it in the
body so it applies to the whole page?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
Yes, we can actually.
That's a good idea.
So we have-- do you
know what we should be?
I don't know if we can do text color.
I was going to try and
create another class here.
>> AUDIENCE: How do you get so
that it has the suggestions?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So
if you guys are interested,
this is another text
editor called Sublime.
You should be able to
install it on your appliance.
Sometimes it gets a little tricky.
If you want help with that,
I'm super happy to help you
with it, because gedit is great and
it's awesome because you can compile it
on the bottom, but I really
like Sublime because it's pretty
and it does do things
like auto-complete.
>> So you can definitely feel free to
let me know if you want to do that.
If you just google "Sublime
text," it typically
has instructions on how to install
on various operating systems.
It is really cool, I
think, in my opinion.
So p.
I think I can just do text-- or
we can just do color is "white."
There.
>> So what I did here is that I
didn't change all the text.
But p here is just a
tag that we have, right?
This paragraph tag.
So I just created a CSS element that
said, OK, anything with this tag
p, make the color white.
>> So if you noticed, it made
this white and this white.
It didn't make our list white because
it's not associated with that.
You could go through and you could say--
>> AUDIENCE: Do background color.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Background color?
>> AUDIENCE: Background to pipe in
color where you put the p tag.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK.
You want it white?
AUDIENCE: Mmhmm.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK.
There you go.
AUDIENCE: That's weird.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
Pretty cool, right?
So if you just mess around,
you're going to learn a lot.
And it can be pretty cool.
I think it's definitely more
gratifying than sometimes
because you don't have to wait
for your program to compile.
You can just hit Refresh
and you're like, oh, look,
it worked, or oh, I'm
probably missing something.
And that's something that's really
cool about this next part of the class,
is it's definitely, I
think, easier to check
as you go along the way versus
having to write these long programs
and wishing and praying
that it works at the end.
>> So with that, I think
you guys all seem good.
If you have any questions, as always,
come talk to me, come let me know.
I will be right outside
for the next 15 minutes
if you want to chat about
anything and everything.
>> So I hope you guys--
good luck with this pset.
The deadline is Friday at noon
because it was released late.
So I will probably be seeing
a lot of you guys on Thursday,
but hopefully not.
Maybe you'll have it done by then.
I'd be super proud.
>> But if not, I will see you Thursday.
You can also use a late date, which
extends it to Saturday at noon.
But I don't-- huh?
>> AUDIENCE: Halloween.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU:
It's Halloween, a, and b,
I don't think there will
be office hours on Friday.
So really do try and get it done by
Friday so that we can all celebrate
Hallow weekend.
All right, I'll see you guys next week.