ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Hey, everyone.
Welcome to section.
Today is just going to be all quiz
review for your quiz on Wednesday.
I hope everyone remembers that
they have a quiz on Wednesday.
And if you didn't, well,
now you've been reminded.
So Wednesday make sure you show up
for class or other accommodations as
necessary.
You guys are going to be awesome.
It's going to be great.
And I'm going to do everything I can
to help prepare you today for your quiz
now.
And also in case you don't know,
there is a course wide review session
today at 7 o'clock in
Northwest labs room B103.
You can see me again for an encore as
I will lead part of that review session
also.
So if you can't get enough of me
now, you can come again tonight.
>> All right, so first things first.
Just some quiz tips before we
actually dive in to reviews.
So as with any exam, practice
will definitely help you out.
There are exams from the past
six or seven years on there,
so that's a lot of practice
material for you guys to have.
And in fact, today is really just
going to be going over any topics
that you guys have questions on as well
as working through practice problems
from quiz zero.
So I'll throw up quiz zero
from last year on here,
and we can work through any problems
that you guys would like to.
>> So practicing.
You're going to start doing that today.
Code on paper.
So yeah, if everyone
could actually get out
paper, that'll be great,
because you're not
going to have your computer on the
exam and writing out code by hand
is often much more difficult
than you might expect.
You're used to just
seeing it and typing it,
and you have your compiler to
help you out when you have errors,
but you don't get that on the exam.
So it's really important to actually
be able to write out the code,
and that muscle memory of doing
it by hand will really help you.
>> So we're getting a little close.
It's Monday.
Your exam is on Wednesday.
But if you have time,
definitely take one
of the exams from last year or the
year before under the time constraint
of an hour and a half.
Just knock out an hour
and a half of time,
and sit yourself down, and
just work through the problems
as if you were actually
taking it, because one
of the biggest things that we hear about
the quizzes is that they are very long.
It is a lot of material.
There are a lot of questions,
and most people may not finish.
I know that I totally did not finish
my quizzes when I took the class.
>> On that note, as a less
comfortable section,
understand that this course is meant
to cater for people of all levels.
The whole reason we have you split
less comfortable, somewhere between,
and more comfortable is to
kind of make it more fair.
And if you are less comfortable, it's
not necessary per se to get everything.
Like if you were getting
everything, you would probably
be in the more comfortable section.
So obviously don't beat yourselves up
too hard if you can't finish the exam.
Take it from me, I didn't do it.
I'm still a concentrator.
I'm still helping teach the course.
You'll be fine.
All right.
And lastly, get some sleep.
Obviously with any exam
we always say this.
Cramming the night before
and not getting any sleep
does not-- maybe if that
works for you, go for it.
But for the vast majority of
people, getting some sleep,
letting your brain rest and recover
before coming in for the exam
will really help you.
Also there will almost
surely be candy at the exam,
so you have to look forward to.
You guys are going to do great.
It's going to be fine.
And now in the next hour and a half I
will try and prep you as best as I can.
>> So I have slides from basically
all sections up to now.
I'm not going to go through
all of them because that is not
feasible in an hour and a half as well
as working through practice problems.
So instead I have a list of topics.
These are all the things
that we could quiz you on.
If there's anything
that really jumps out
that you want to go over, that you
want me to go over conceptually,
I can try and give
you an overview there.
Or if you want to jump right in to
doing practice problems together,
we can do that.
It's up to you guys.
There aren't that many of you.
So it's whatever you guys like to do.
I want to be the most
helpful toward you guys.
So I'll let you just look.
>> AUDIENCE: One thing is
the chart that we keep
saying about the stack and the heap.
Just the whole idea behind
that and what that means.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah, OK.
This is all the way at the
end, so let me scroll through.
>> AUDIENCE: We don't have to
do it now, but whatever.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Was there
anything-- this one.
Is this kind of fuzzy for people?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I second that.
And can we also do buffer overflow?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Buffer overflow?
OK.
So buffer overflow is pretty
easy just to talk about.
It's basically buffers you think about
some array memory that you have, right?
We typically talk about
buffer overflow when
you're not checking how much
the user is putting in, right?
And the idea being
with buffer overflow is
they are putting in far
too much data for the space
that you've allotted for them, right?
>> So if you say, give
me some message, we're
assuming that they're going to give
us a reasonable length message.
Maybe a couple lines, whatnot.
So we don't check.
Instead they feed us in an
entire book that's a message,
and it overflows the amount of
space that we've allocated for this.
And what happens is it might overwrite
places that it's not supposed.
>> So I know Professor Malan said
something about buffer overflow attacks.
So that's where the user will input
some massive amount of data in the hopes
that he overwrites past
the end of your buffer
and replaces something-- I wonder
I we have those slides in here.
I don't think we have
those slides in here.
But basically he overwrites
some portion of memory
that allows him access
to parts of your computer
that you wouldn't
normally have access to.
>> Biggest thing with
buffer overflow is just
to understand that it
happens when you aren't
checking how much your
user is putting in.
When you aren't kind of
safeguarding against that.
And at its simplest
thing, it's just your user
inputting a massive amount
of data in an attempt
to overwrite some security
portion of your memory.
That's all it is.
>> So this here, stack and heap.
Basically all this is is just
a representation of memory
and where things are stored.
That's really kind of
all you need to know.
The biggest things that
you need to know are
that-- let me see if
there's a better-- here.
So this is the stack here.
>> So stack has to do with
all of your functions
that you're calling at any given time.
And what's important to remember
going off of last week with malloc
is that you don't really have
necessary control over it.
It all depends on when certain
functions are executing.
And when they are executing, they
have what are called stack frames
that go up here.
>> So it all kind of happens
without any real input from you.
You write your program,
and you let it run,
and the stack kind of takes
care of itself as it needs to.
So if in main you're calling
cube, that will be passed up here.
It'll create a frame.
But there's nothing you explicitly do
to create that stack frame other than
write the function to begin with, OK?
>> What is kind of under your
control is the heap with malloc.
So whenever you malloc something,
you are taking memory from the heap.
And that is memory that you
have, for lack of a better word,
explicit control over,
because remember with malloc
it's basically there
until you say otherwise.
For those of you who
watched section last week,
it's there until you tell it to go away.
It will be there unless
otherwise told not.
So the heap is just something
you can think of as memory
that you have control over.
And those are just the
two different big things.
>> Other than that, you shouldn't have
to worry too much about stack and heap
questions or typically more just
if you have local parameters
or a function would it be
on the stack or the heap.
Obviously in this case
it would be the stack.
If you're mallocing something,
where is that coming from?
The heap.
If you look at practice quizzes, those
are generally the type of questions
that they have.
>> You don't have to worry
too much about it.
You get into more explicitly
about stack and heap
later on or in other CS classes.
So just having kind of a
general idea of what this is
will be good, which I
just kind of went over.
Any other topics?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Can you go over
pointers again really quickly?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Pointers?
Do you want conceptual
overview of pointers
or do you practice with pointers?
AUDIENCE: Kind of like the syntax.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: The syntax?
Yeah.
OK, we're getting there.
Yeah, so this is just kind of something
when you have a recursive function,
every time that recursive function is
called, it just adds other stack frame.
Pretty much an example
of how you don't really
have control over the
frames on your stack.
>> OK, pointers.
All right, so creating pointers.
Remember, it's just type star.
So whatever type of data that
you're going to be pointing to.
So this would be a pointer to an int.
This would be a pointer to a char.
This would be a pointer to a float.
So it's basically whatever
you want it to be pointing to,
star is how you declare the pointer, OK?
>> But then obviously gets a little
tricky when you have pointer
or you have star whatever.
So the big difference is
when you're declaring--
so we have some-- so
this takes some int star.
So this is some pointer
calls x to an int, right?
So remember what this does
is this calls the system x.
And this is going to
have some address, right?
So let's just say this is our address.
Pointers hold addresses.
So what this says is that at this
location, we are storing an int.
>> So another way we can think of
this is that this is some int.
We haven't really assigned it to
anything yet, but it's just an int.
So we can do is if we do star x
equals 5, this becomes a 5, OK?
This says go to whatever x is
pointing at, so go to this address
and make it equal to 5.
So we assign 5 to this address, right?
>> And then if you do this,
this gives us the address of.
This is the address of operator.
So what is the address of x?
We don't know.
We haven't assigned it an address.
We could say it's some-- now we gave
it an address, so the address is 4.
And actually if we go through something
like this, kind of what we did.
So working through here-- I find
it helps if you draw out pointers.
If you're on your exam, I
highly recommend drawing boxes.
>> So this first one, int x equals 5.
This just means we have some
place in memory that is 5, right?
And our table here tells us
that it's at address 0x04.
And then we create some pointer.
So let's break this down one at a time.
So this creates some
box to an int, right?
It's going to hold
some address of an it.
So this is some pointer.
And this chalk is really small.
So we have some pointer here.
And our table tells us
that is address is 0x08.
Cool.
And we are assigning
it to the address of x.
>> Remember, pointers hold addresses, OK?
So if we want to hold x, we have
to use the address operator, which
is the ampersand, to get the address
of x, which in this case, 0x04.
And then if we have
some int copy, this just
creates some other box that
holds an int called copy.
And if we assign it to this--
so this is referencing it.
So it says go to whatever
address pointer holds.
Pointer holds this address,
so we'd go over here,
and we say, OK, what's in it?
It's 5.
So copy becomes 5.
Make sense?
>> What if I tried to assign
this to just pointer.
What does pointer actually equal?
It would just be whatever
pointer contains, right?
And then what if I did this?
What would copy be now?
>> AUDIENCE: 0x08.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yep, the
address of our pointer.
Any part of that that
needs to be re-explained?
Cool.
There is definitely a very
fun problem on quiz one
that we can over that
gives you more practice.
The guys from last week can
tell you it wasn't that bad.
We got through an entire
chart, and everyone did great.
>> OK, so that's overview
of syntax of pointers.
Biggest thing is understanding how
to create them, do referencing,
and address of, OK?
Cool.
Any other topics before
we dive into practice.
Also if we're going through
the practice problems
and there's something you want a
refresher on, we can do that too.
Do you have something?
>> AUDIENCE: Structs and linked lists.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Structs
and linked lists, OK.
So structs.
We actually are going
over this tonight too.
OK, so structs.
Structs are basically
just a way for you to hold
multiple values of different types.
So with an array we are
constricted to one data type.
Our array either has to just be numbers,
or just be chars, or just be floats.
>> But maybe you need to
contain more than that.
Maybe you need to hold-- if
you're talking about a student,
you're going to have their house, their
ID number, their age, where they live,
right?
And all of those are
different sorts of types.
So you can't store
those all in an array.
>> So what you can do is you
can create a struct, which
you can think of as your
own personal data type.
So instead of just having ints
and instead of just having floats,
you can have a type student that
has all of these fields in it.
So the way we initialize
our structs is-- actually
since my writing is terrible, we
are going to transition to typing.
Woo.
>> OK, so if we want to create a struct--
I'm just going to it down here.
Disregard the in main whatever
which we will use later.
So the way you want to do
it is with typedef struct.
And let's just call this student
because that's what I was using.
OK, so typedef means you're
defining a new type, OK?
There are nuances into when you do
just a struct versus a typedef struct.
For all intents and
purposes, you guys are just
going to assume they're
approximately the same and just
use typedef struct for now.
It'll become way more apparent in your
next P set what those differences are,
but I don't think you need to
worry about that right now.
I would much rather you
know how to create one,
access it, and assign [? value. ?]
>> A new type of struct, and
we are calling it student.
So after we're done creating this,
for all intents and purposes,
you will have a type called student.
And you can think of it just as a type
like an int, or a float, or a char.
It's just another type, OK?
>> So in this one, what do we have?
We have maybe a name.
So maybe we want a string name.
And we have maybe an int that's an ID.
And we have another in
that's phone number.
And we have some-- let's see.
What else might we have?
We'll have some string at his house.
All things that a student has.
>> So this creates a struct now.
So how might we create a student?
If we have some variable that is
going to talk about Walker here,
so we have-- we're just
going to call this walker.
He needs a type.
What's your type?
AUDIENCE: Student.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Student.
So this just creates an object you can
think of that has all these things.
You just created a walker student.
So now we need to be able
to assign all these, right?
So does anyone remember how
we access within a struct?
AUDIENCE: Period.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Period Exactly.
So if we wanted to assign
him a name, we could do that.
Obviously this would
be-- this part here would
be within main, so
actually let me do this.
Declare this above main so
that we can use it within main.
So now I want it to do ID,
and we'll just do some there,
and then we'll assign a house.
Bam.
Cool.
>> So now should we ever need to access
anything later on-- maybe we--
if we ever need to access anything,
let's just do an int copy ID.
And I want to copy
Walker's ID into this.
How might I do it?
You need to access within the walker
struct to [? go to that ?] [? E ?].
And the same way that we
assigned it up here, how
might we access it when we want to
give that value to something else?
AUDIENCE: Walker.id.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah, exactly.
So that's pretty much all
you need to know for structs.
You just need to think of
them as another variable.
Basically a create your
own variable type, OK?
You use it to declare
variables in any way.
Here walker is still a variable.
It just has a type student now instead
of a type int, or a type string,
or a type char.
If there was an easy way to talk
about structs, it is literally just a
create your own data type
that allows you to group
all these different
kind of data together.
Does that makes sense?
OK.
That and accessing with dots.
Pretty much all you need.
>> OK, where did my PowerPoint go?
Here it is.
Well this is weird.
Aha.
OK, cool.
Any other things or do we
want to head to practice?
Practice?
OK.
Awesome.
I'm going to exit this.
If at any point during
practice questions,
I'm happy to revamp
and go through things.
So I have quiz zero up here.
If you guys want to pull
it up on your computer,
just like take five
minutes to browse through.
Maybe choose some top
questions you want to go over.
If you guys can't decide, we'll just
slowly start working through them,
but I'm sure there are going to be some
questions that you are particularly
eager to talk about and have
me work through with you all.
So just go ahead and take five minutes.
Scroll through.
And this is the quiz from 2013.
>> AUDIENCE: Zero?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah, quiz zero.
We're not doing quiz one stuff.
We'll do that in a couple weeks.
Also for those of you who
came in late, we have candy,
so do you guys want candy?
>> AUDIENCE: Sure.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: I'm just
going to pass around.
Hey, if you guys get here
early, you get more candy.
That's fine.
Ben, do you want candy?
You want some of these?
There's also Snickers if
anyone wants Snickers.
I'll leave them here and here.
Feel free.
Do you want anymore?
AUDIENCE: All set.
Thank you.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: And I had a nice
little pile there at the beginning.
You guys get to take the quiz and
I get to have a quiz grading party.
It's chaos.
900 exams.
It's going to be so much fun.
Going to be great.
I'm pretty sure that's one
of the biggest staff bonding
nights of the year.
Has anyone done quiz zero from
last year yet out of curiosity?
>> AUDIENCE: Parts of it.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Parts of it, OK.
Did you have questions on any of them?
AUDIENCE: I already
went to office hours.
Thank you though.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Well, hopefully
it's still kind of helpful.
When did you go to
office hours for that?
AUDIENCE: My TF had them this afternoon.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Oh.
Who's your TF?
AUDIENCE: Fred [? Wujaya ?].
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: There are so many TFs.
So many.
All right.
Anyone have any to start that I can
jot down that we want to work on?
I assume the pointers
one with the table.
Go for it.
>> AUDIENCE: Maybe the switch one.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So number 12?
I assume number 8 and 9 are probably
ones people want to go over.
>> AUDIENCE: And 10 and 11.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: And you guys know
you get one page of notes, right?
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah, so what are
we allowed to put on that.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: You're allowed
to put anything you want.
And it can be typed.
As far as I remember, ours were typed.
>> AUDIENCE: You can do
back and both sides?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah, both sides.
So something like the heap and
[? back end ?] heap, your running
times.
Useful.
Maybe little things about
pointers to remind you.
Syntax for things.
Having just like a skeleton
program can be super useful.
I know that I always forgot exactly what
I was supposed to write for int main,
because I always just copy
paste from my previous P set
or it's already there, so
I never really wrote it,
so having that can be super useful.
>> OK, so why don't we
start with number 8 then?
All right.
OK.
So consider the program below.
So obviously when we see
pointers, it's probably
a good idea to start drawing, right?
I want to know where all my
big pieces of chalk went.
This is kind of annoying.
>> So we have here some swap function
that's going to take in two pointers.
So in this case, they
should actually be switching
things versus our original swap
function that only took in copies.
So what it's going to do
is-- let's start with main,
because that's where 1 is.
>> So we have some int x 1.
We have some y that's equal to 2.
And then we have some swap
that's going to take those.
And let's see what do we have here.
And in our table-- oh boy.
How am I going to do this?
I'm going to draw my table over here.
Barely making it there.
Barely making it.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
And they give us that 1 is 1, and 1 2.
Cool.
Awesome.
So 3.
And there's [? a 1. ?]
>> All right.
And then address of x is 0x123.
And y is Ox127.
Cool.
All right.
I want you guys work on this
for just like-- work on it
with the people around you.
I wish I had said that
while I was setting up.
Work on it.
Try and work on it by
yourselves for a couple minutes,
and then I will work on it with you.
Because the only way you're really
going to learn is by doing it yourself.
No worries.
Good luck.
>> OK, why don't we slowly
start working through this.
So everyone gets after line one, x is 1.
After line two, x and
y are 1 and 2, right?
Cool.
So line three is where things
get interesting of course.
>> So what we've done here
is we have now swapped.
We say that x and y have those points,
or they have the address of x and y,
right?
So in this case, three,
what is the value of a?
a had been passed in, has been given
the value of the address of x, right?
>> AUDIENCE: 1?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So we add it to the x?
What's x's address?
>> AUDIENCE: 0x123.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Exactly.
But what is a actually pointing to?
If we were to dereference a,
what value would it give us.
AUDIENCE: 1.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It would
give us 1, because what
we're saying is go to this
address, tell us what the value is.
So what would be b?
>> AUDIENCE: 0x127.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Exactly.
So it's the address of y.
And then what [? dereference? ?]
AUDIENCE: 2.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK, so now four.
We said a is equal-- well now we've
done int temp is equal to star of a.
So what changes?
There's only one thing
that changes here.
What is it?
>> AUDIENCE: Temp.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: The temp.
So we can rewrite all of these.
A good strategy for these
is just figuring out
what changes, because most often
there's only one thing that's
going to change at any given point, OK?
So we've assigned temp.
>> Now our next point, five, we
have made star a equal to star b.
So what changes now?
>> AUDIENCE: Star a.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Star a, so
everything else stays the same.
And what does star a equal?
>> AUDIENCE: 2.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: 2.
Lovely.
Awesome.
OK, and then now we have
start b is equal to temp.
So the only thing changing is star b.
Everything else stays the same.
And what is star b equal to now?
And you've completed the table.
Because now at the end, if we say x
and y, we know that at this point--
we know that when we
changed star a to 2,
what that did is it said OK, at
address 0x123 here, change it.
Now this was 2.
And then at this point,
we said OK, go to star b.
So go to the address at
0x127 and make it a 1.
So now at the very end when
we actually return for main,
we actually have that x is
equal to 2 and y is equal to 1.
Everyone good with that?
OK, cool.
Number 9.
You guys work on this.
I'm going to set up a board
so we can draw through it.
It'll be a blast.
The big tables can be
really scary, I know.
But if you just take them one row at
a time, they get a lot less scary.
All right.
>> So you know that this will have
gone through main first, right?
Initializes x and y and
then tries to swap them.
So even swap is above, real way it
goes is that we're going through main,
and then it's calling
up to swap, all right?
So everyone knows that.
>> So which one do you
guys want to start with?
Is anyone really sure
about one of these?
Or even partially sure?
Why don't we start with x?
What do we think x is?
>> AUDIENCE: 1.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: 1.
So then why is 2.
And that's because the
big distinction here
is that we are only
passing copies in, right?
We're not passing by reference.
So even at the end of
this program x and y
have stayed the same, because they
are just copies in the swap function.
They don't actually change, right?
>> So what about a, b, and temp?
>> AUDIENCE: a is b.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: a is b.
So in this case, a was
x, which is 1, right?
So here, let's walk through it.
So at the beginning, a and
b are 1 and 2 and undefined.
So originally temp gets
assigned to a, so temp is 1.
a is equal to b, So we get
2, and b is equal to temp.
Now we get 1.
>> AUDIENCE: In the previous one it
swapped ampersand x and ampersand y.
What exactly does that mean?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So that means that
you're passing by reference.
So that means you're actually
passing in the addresses of where
x and y are stored.
AUDIENCE: But you're not
swapping the address.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: You're not
swapping the addresses.
You're swapping what's within them.
Like what's at that address,
and that's why it works.
Versus in this program here what
you're doing is you're creating copies.
So you have x and y that exist
as their own variables out here.
But then when you pass
them into swap, it's
as if you're creating
this whole other set.
So you're never actually
touching x and y.
>> AUDIENCE: If ampersand x is what is at
the address of x, what would star x be?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Ampersand x is what's at
the address of x, then star-- well,
in this case, x is not a pointer.
AUDIENCE: Oh, OK.
So you only do this
because it's not a pointer.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Right.
You can only do star of
something that's a pointer.
Maybe you could do it to things that
aren't, but the compile that you
do that crazy things would happen.
And I'm not exactly
sure what would happen.
You can always take the
address of something,
but you can't dereference
something that's not a pointer.
If that makes sense, that's
a good distinction to have.
>> So not too bad, right?
The tables are hopefully
getting slightly less scary.
All right.
Ah, the fun ones.
So now, writing your own code.
So I'm going to let you guys work
on this for about four minutes,
and then we can talk
about ways to approach it.
Feel free to talk to people around you.
Also this is interesting.
It's like an all girls
section right now.
Pretty exciting.
Except for Chang.
But Chang is not really part of section.
Awesome.
Perfect.
So I will give you a couple hints.
In the case where you have
more than one character, where
you have something else
like 123 or 1000 something,
you need to be able to loop
through and convert each of those.
So there's a couple
ways you could do that,
but you're definitely going to have
a for loop somewhere in there to loop
through them, which is
kind of like the giveaway
with even if you call strlen,
which is kind of like oh
maybe you want to use the length
of the string in some way.
>> All right.
So what do you guys think might be
one of the first things we want to do?
There's a couple cases in here
we need to account for, right?
Either we have something that's null.
What do we have?
Cases.
Null.
We have the case that it has
something other than 09, right?
So let's say it has letters.
Or we have the case that's valid.
Three cases to think of.
So which one do you think might be
the easiest one to take care of first?
AUDIENCE: Null.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: The case is null.
So what would we do there?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah.
And what do I want to do?
>> AUDIENCE: Return 0.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Exactly.
Awesome.
OK.
So now case that it has letters
and the case that it's valid.
We can actually take care
of this within one loop, OK?
So one way to do it-- what might be
a simple way to check if it's valid.
We would have to go through
each letter and do what?
>> AUDIENCE: Check if it's in--
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Right, you can check
if it's between 0 and 9, right?
And then in the case
that it's valid, we're
going to end up iterating through
our string anyways, right?
So why don't we try and
combine them into one.
We're going to iterate
through out string, and as we
do that, we're going to first
do a check to see if that letter
or if that character is valid.
If it is, we're going to perform the
operation that we need to convert it.
Otherwise it'll return 0, right?
>> So before we do that, we
probably want some variable
that we can return at the end
that's going to be our actual value.
So we're going to initialize
some value to be 0.
And that's just how we start.
So I'm going to get rid of this.
So how are we going to
iterate through this string.
AUDIENCE: For loop.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: A for loop.
So what's our for?
>> AUDIENCE: i is 0.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Mm-hm.
And what are we iterating until?
>> AUDIENCE: str length of s.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: OK, now remember
there's a better way. [INAUDIBLE].
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah, we can do n equals.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Exactly.
>> AUDIENCE: i is less than n.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: And why
would we want to do that?
Do you remember the reason?
AUDIENCE: We have to recalculate it.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Becasue this way you
only have to calculate strlen once.
If you do i is less than strlen
s, that's means it recalculates
the length every time
you run the for loop,
which isn't a huge cost
of energy, but it's
better practice to try and
do things like that once.
Unless maybe you have a crazy string
that's changing at every iteration.
But if it's staying the same, save it.
All right.
And then i plus plus.
Awesome.
We are on our way.
AUDIENCE: Really quickly.
First, so let's say we just
did i less than strlen of s,
are they grading us on design
at all or just correctness?
They're not.
We are grading on correctness
for quizzes as far as I know.
I cannot make a full on
guarantee, but for the most part,
vast majority is correctness, because
you're under a lot of time constraint.
Design typically means
you have time to think
about the elegance of your situation.
>> OK, so we're iterating through.
So we need to either check to
see if this character is valid
or if we can perform our
normal [? a to i ?] function.
We can worry about what
that is in a second.
So why don't we take--
if anyone can think
about a way to check to
see if this is valid.
We know it's going to be
some if condition, right?
And remember this is
in ASCII, so how might
we see if it's not 0,1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, or 9.
AUDIENCE: If alpha.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So if alpha would
only let us know if it's a letter.
And if they give us a symbol, it's
still not quite going to check.
So if you pull up your ASCII
table, we know that 0 through 9
are in one segment.
Tell me the numbers that they
correspond to if possible.
AUDIENCE: 40.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So the range is like 40--
AUDIENCE: Maybe.
48 to 57.
I'm not sure.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: 40 to 57?
>> AUDIENCE: 48, I think.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: 48 to 57.
So we know that those ASCII
symbols-- if the ASCII value is not
between 48 and 57,
it's not valid, right?
So could we use that to
our advantage possibly?
How are we going to get
this letter, first off?
How are we accessing
this this character?
>> AUDIENCE: s bracket i.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Mm-hm.
Because we can think of
strings as arrays, remember.
So what do we want to say?
We want to say if this
is-- I'll give you a hint.
It's a less than.
What to you think it
needs to be less than?
AUDIENCE: 57?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: 47, right?
But it also represents that as you a 0
in single [? spokes ?], because that's
the character 0.
You could also put 47.
Having the ASCII table, as
you see, is just something
you should have on your quiz sheet.
>> So if this is the case, if it's a
less than 0-- not necessarily and.
It's only either going to be
less than or greater than 9.
So can you fill out this last for me?
So or s of i is what, Rhea?
>> AUDIENCE: Greater than 9.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: There.
Does that make sense to
everyone, how we got there?
These problems, they're like once you
see the solutions, it's like oh, OK.
And this is why practice will help you.
OK, so we return 0.
Lovely.
All right.
Otherwise what do we want to do?
This is the interesting part
where it's a little more
like math versus CS in my opinion.
Does anyone have an idea
of how we might do this?
So the important thing to
realize is the first character
we're taking is going to be
the highest order digit, right?
So if we're looking at converting
123, the first time we iterate
is going to be 1, but we need
that to be 100 by the end, right?
So one thing you can do is that
with every subsequent digit
you take, you multiply your value by 10,
so that by the time you reach the end,
everything has been
shifted upwards, right?
>> So the first time you run
it, you have 1 as your value.
Second time you run it, you
multiply your value by 10.
It will update it so that it's now
10, and you add on your next value.
And then you multiply that by
10 and add on your next value.
And this is why they say this
is much more like testing
a math algorithm versus
CS, but I digress.
I don't write the quizzes.
>> So one thing we can do is we
say value times equals 10.
So this is going to shift
your digit once every time.
And then we just want to add.
We want to add in what
we just got, right?
So how do we actually convert our
ASCII character into the number
that it represents?
>> So we know that 0 is equal to 47, right?
So if 0 is 47, what
would we have to do to it
to actually make it be an int of 0?
>> AUDIENCE: It's 48.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: 48?
Sorry.
We would subtract 48, right?
Remember ASCII math?
We can treat them just
like normal numbers.
If you treat them like numbers,
they become numbers effectively.
So if we have s of i, which let's
say in this case is equal to 0.
So s of i in this case
would be the ASCII--
the ASCII int for it would be 47.
So we could subtract-- or 48.
You could do that, is one way.
Does anyone know a better
way we could do 48?
We just said 0 is-- go into
the ASCII you could do quote 0.
So does it kind of make
sense how this works?
>> AUDIENCE: At this point, is the value 0
because even if you multiply it by 10,
you're starting out with zero,
so should it be switched?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So in this case, you
want to multiply it before you add,
because in this case, yes, it would
still be-- my pointer is missing.
The value in this case, the first
time we run it will be zero.
So you're just adding
on that first digit.
What's important is the next time
you iterate, you want to shift it up
before you add your next digit on.
Does that clarify for you?
OK.
>> Sometimes you're going to
get weird more mathy things.
If you had most of
this, you're still going
to get-- you're going to do pretty well.
Partial credit is a very
big thing on CS50 quizzes.
So write what you know.
If you got everything
except for here, you're
still going to do
really well the problem.
Because you're showing,
OK, I almost know.
I know that I need to iterate through.
I know what I need to check for.
I just don't quite
get how to convert it.
You're going to be OK.
Yes, you're going to
lose a couple points,
but you're still going to get a
good number of points for something
like that if you're
missing these two lines.
I would be like OK, this person
knows what they're doing.
Math is hard.
So I would say you'd be fine.
>> OK, so you guys ready to
try strlen with pointers now
that you guys are pointer masters?
So I'll let you guys work
on that for a little bit.
If anyone needs a refresher.
So you want to use pointer
arithmetic, and then if s is null,
your implementation should return 0.
Things like this that make you
really happy to just call strlen
at the end of the day.
I think this one might be a little
easier than the last one, which
is good.
I'll give you guys another minute,
and then we'll work through it.
And then we get to go to switches.
>> OK, ready guys?
Maybe a little bit.
So I've given you your
two options, right?
Either check for null and return 0 if
it is, or actually compute the length.
So who wants to write check for null?
Go for it.
>> AUDIENCE: If parentheses s
equals equals null return 0.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Lovely.
I love when half your problem
is just checking for null.
I know with you guys last
week I was like check for null
literally every time.
OK, so--
>> AUDIENCE: If return 0 is only one line,
do we still need the curly bracket?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: You don't technically
need them as long you're consistent.
It's good practice just
to get in the habit
of using curly braces,
but technically no.
You don't need them for one line.
We just tend to recommend it
for people starting to program.
>> So now what might we want to do here?
So now we know that our string is valid.
We want to keep compute the length.
What's probably the first
thing we want to do?
>> AUDIENCE: Create an
int that's the length.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Exactly.
AUDIENCE: And we want to set it to?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: 0.
Perfect.
All right.
Now what do want to do?
This is really the bulk of it.
Go for it.
>> AUDIENCE: So you probably do a for loop.
And then since when you call s you're
getting the address of the first thing,
you would start with i equals 0.
And then as long as x
plus i isn't back slash 0.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: The null terminator.
AUDIENCE: The null terminator.
Then you add one to length.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Yeah.
OK, so lets turn that
into very concrete code.
But that is the perfect idea.
That's exactly what we're doing.
We're going to be iterating
through with the pointer.
So what we want to do
is instead of an int
here, because we're
not referring to an it.
We're referring to the start of a
string, that start being some address,
right?
>> So we want a pointer.
So we're going to have some char star,
because it corresponds to our s, right?
So this is some point we're initializing
to the start of the string, OK?
So let's just call it i.
If it's the start of the string,
what's it going to be assigned to?
Not 0.
We want it to be the
start of our string.
What represents the start of
our string that was given to us?
>> AUDIENCE: Just s.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: s.
So this creates some new pointer that
represents the start of our string, OK?
Another way to think of it
is like here's our array.
That's our string, s.
So let's say this is the
first spot, and this is 0x4.
04.
This is our s, which holds that address.
And we just created another one called
i that just refers to the same thing.
So they're both just pointing
to the start of our string.
This is just a graphic representation.
>> So now what we want to
do is we want to iterate
our condition for iterating
through our string.
Now shopping.
Got to shop, guys.
Is we want to keep updating until
we reach the null terminator, right?
So what might that look like?
Do we want i, or do we want
star i is the question?
Is the null terminator an address
or something located at an address?
Located at an address, right?
>> So we need dereference whatever is
here, because this is just some address.
To actually get to the start
we need to dereference this
so that we actually get
what's in this first place.
So if we do star i, what
don't we want it to equal?
AUDIENCE: Back slash?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: There.
Does that make sense to everyone?
We need to go into our string and
make sure that it's not the end.
And then we can just update like this.
Normal updating.
So as long as these are
met, what do we need to do?
>> AUDIENCE: Length plus plus.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Mm-hm.
And then after the for loop
terminates, what do we want to return?
AUDIENCE: Length?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Length.
There you go.
Obviously the meat of this one
is understanding this for loop.
Does everyone get how that worked?
I'm happy to go over it again.
>> AUDIENCE: The second
part, so the star i there,
that's the address of the first--
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It's not the address.
It's what's at.
AUDIENCE: That's actually in there.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: That's
what's actually in there.
So this is saying-- let
me make this better.
So this is 0x04, and I'm just going
to say I'm going to make this my name.
OK.
Yes, I know I have quiz review tonight.
Lots of quiz review.
So let's say this string
is my name, Allison.
Little messy, but it's there.
And s represents the location
of where the string starts,
so I'm going to make this
real-- this is the address of a,
where the string starts, right?
>> So what we do here is we want to
use pointers to iterate through.
So we create some pointer, i, that also
is equal to the start of the string.
And at each point, we want to
continue going through the array
here until we hit the null terminator.
So we always want to check what's
at each of these addresses.
>> So we dereference i, so that
the first time we do it we
say, OK, what's at address 0x04?
It's an a.
OK, we're good.
Increment length.
Move on to the next one.
So i-- remember pointers increase by the
size of whatever they're pointing to.
So in this case, since it's
a char, it'll update by one.
So now we're going to look at 5,
which means it's going over here.
So it says OK, go to 0x05.
What's in there?
It's an l.
And it'll keep doing that
until it hits this one.
And it says OK, what's in
whatever address this is?
The null terminator, OK.
Exit.
And just return length.
Because you need what's actually at
that address, not the address itself.
>> There are very few places where
you actually need the address.
Most of the time when
you're using the and it's
when you are first
assigning a pointer or when
you're passing it into another function.
OK, everyone good there?
Kind of?
OK.
>> So it looks like we've
got about 12 minutes left,
so we'll go on to
maybe our last problem,
and then there's any
concepts that have come up
in the meantime we can
quickly go over that.
>> So switching gears is the last
problem here, switch statements.
So your job is to rewrite this
so that it behaves the same
but doesn't use switches.
Chalky hands.
So any questions about this off the bat?
None?
OK.
Does everyone understand that if the
case doesn't have anything after it,
it means that it should
follow the next step?
So case 1 and 2 in this case
do the exact same thing.
Sometimes a point of confusion.
>> All right.
Anyone have any ideas?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: So you can
just do if statements.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Mm-hm.
So what's our first one?
>> AUDIENCE: If n equals equals 1,
and the 2 lines for or n equals
equals 2, then print small.
And then can you do else if?
Or can you just do an if?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: You can do else if?
>> AUDIENCE: Would it matter if you do if?
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So it does.
Does anyone-- so, you
will get the same output
if you use just ifs versus
if you use else ifs.
Can you guys think of the reason
why you might want to use an else
if versus a lot of ifs?
Has to with efficiency.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: It would check
all the ifs every time.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: So even if
it hit this first one,
it would go on check every other one.
So you want to use if else ifs in cases
where only one of them will ever apply.
So mutual exclusion is
what we tend to say.
If you have a bunch of ifs, it means
that maybe more than one of them
matters, and maybe more than
one of them can be true.
And you want both of them
to execute if they're true.
If you only want one of them to work
in these mutually exclusive cases,
you want to use else if, because
it all has to do with efficiency.
Your code is just better designed
if it adheres to this practice.
So in this case we'll have an else if.
And this would be?
>> AUDIENCE: n equals equals 3.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Perfect.
Print medium.
And then in our last
case, what do we have?
Else or else if?
AUDIENCE: Else.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Do we want-- You want
else if because we have concrete cases.
It's not kind of a catch all.
If you had a default in a switch--
remember in switches you can have case,
and then you have default.
If you had a default, that's kind
of your else statement there.
But if it has only cases,
that means you need
to check to see if it's each of those.
So in this case, it would the 4 or 5.
We want a print off.
It's large.
And there you go.
And that would be your program.
>> So in this case if we
had a default something,
we would have an else in
whatever it wanted us to do.
So that is a good distinction
to know, to understand.
Does that help with switches for you?
Perfect.
All right.
>> We have about eight minutes left.
Do you guys have any
other high level concepts?
Questions in general?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: I had a
question about one of them
that was about the random
number generator on quiz zero.
ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: Oh, that one.
That one is another one where
it is more math than-- yes.
The solution to that-- even I when
I see it, I'm like what is this.
>> AUDIENCE: It was number 7.
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: It's strange in my opinion.
So basically you want
to use drand48, which
will give you some
number between 0 and 1.
And you want to use it so
that you somehow get a--
and it's much more of a math problem
to me than I think a CS problem.
>> The way that you do it-- and
sometimes it will just be like that.
Again, these are the
cases where it's kind
of like write what you
can and partial credit.
So if we want a return,
we know that we're
going to be using drand48
in some way, right?
So why don't we just jot that down.
We're using it in some way.
The way that they have
you guys use it is
like this, which I will try and explain.
>> So basically what happens here
is because it's between 0 and 1,
what you're doing is you're multiplying
by-- this is very much a math question.
Just full disclaimer, this is
completely a math question.
What you're doing is
because of 0 and 1 and you
want it to be within
this range, you actually
figure out how large
the range is, and then
you basically scale it up,
which is what this is doing.
>> b minus a gives you that range, the
difference between those numbers.
You can multiply between 0
and 1, and then adding a just
means that your scaling it up
so that it's between a and b,
which I didn't really like this problem.
As I said, this quiz
is meant to encompass
people who are less comfortable,
somewhere in between,
and more comfortable.
So if they made it so
that it was something
that everyone at the less
comfortable place would get,
we would have far too many
people scoring perfects,
and the more comfortable would be bored.
>> So they always have these
kind of brain teaser questions
that are meant to be a little harder
that take some creative thinking.
When you see them,
don't get too stumped.
I would definitely say flip
through your quiz first.
Tackle the problems
that you know you can,
because there's no use getting stuck
on a problem when there are three
or four or five on the page
after that you can easily do.
>> AUDIENCE: Why exactly do you
multiply it by the range?
>> ALLISON BUCHHOLTZ-AU: You multiply the range that
you know-- it's like how much after a
do you want?
So you can think of, because it
returns a number between 0 and 1,
you can think of it as a percentage.
So it's basically saying if we have
our number line here, a is here,
and b is here.
You're like how much past a is it?
Is all we're doing.
So you're just asking for the
percentage of this range, which
is what it's giving you.
And then you basically just
scale it up by adding a.
It's a math brain teaser.
>> If there was any last minute advice, I
would say flip through the questions,
figure out which ones you
know that like, oh I got this.
Almost surely they're going to
be questions that you won't know
or that you're going to have time
for, so hit your strengths, OK?
You guys are going to great.
There are a lot of
questions for a reason,
so that you have time to
kind of have the opportunity
to demonstrate what
you're really good at.
So it's OK if you're
not good at everything.
Play to your strengths.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: So is this going to
return something that's truncated?
Yes, it will, because drand
returns between 0 and 1.
It'll return an int,
because it'll truncate
when we add a or multiply by it.
Cool.
Any last minute questions?
>> You guys are going to do great.
You're Going to be fabulous.
And even if not, there will
be candy here next week.
And I'll love you.
I'll love you guys regardless.
All right, everyone, good luck.
Have a great time.
You're going to be fine.
And you know what?
In two days it's going
to be over, whereas I
have two midterms on Thursday, so
at least you guys will be done.
All right, I'll see you guys next week.