[MUSIC PLAYING]
SPEAKER 1: All right.
Everyone welcome back to section.
I hope you all are successfully
recovered from your quiz
from last week.
I know it's a little bit crazy at times.
As I was saying before, if you're
within the standard deviation,
don't really worry about it, especially
for a less comfortable section.
That's about where you should be.
>> If you did great, then awesome.
Kudos to you.
And if you feel like you need
a little bit more help, please
feel free to reach
out to any of the TFs.
We are all here to help.
>> That's why we teach.
That's why I'm here every Monday for you
guys and at office hours on Thursdays.
So please feel free to let me know
if you're worried about anything
or if there's anything on the quiz
that you'd really like to address.
>> So the agenda for today is
all about data structures.
Some of these are just going to be just
to get you familiarized with these.
You may not ever implement
them in this class.
Some of them you will,
like for your speller pset.
>> You'll have your choice
between hash tables and tries.
So we'll definitely be going over those.
It's going to be definitely more of kind
of a high level section today, though,
because there are a lot of them, and if
we went into the implementation details
on all of these, we wouldn't
even get through linked lists
and maybe a little bit of hash tables.
>> So bear with me.
We're not going to be doing
as much coding this time.
If you have any questions about it
or you want to see it implemented
or try it for yourself,
I definitely recommend
going to study.cs50.net, which
has examples of all of these.
It'll have my PowerPoints
with the notes that we
tend to use as well as some programming
exercises, especially for things
like linked lists and binary
trees stacks and cues.
So little more high level, which
might be nice for you guys.
>> So with that, we'll get started.
And also, yes-- quizzes.
I think most of you who are in
my section have your quizzes,
but anyone comes in or some reason you
don't, they're right here in the front.
>> So linked lists.
I know this kind of goes
to back before your quiz.
That was the week before
that we learned about this.
But in this case, we'll just
go a little bit more in depth.
>> So why might we choose a
linked list over an array?
What distinguishes them?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: You can expand a linked
list versus an array's fixed size.
SPEAKER 1: Right.
An array has fixed size whereas a
linked list has a variable size.
So if we don't know how
much we want to store,
a linked list gives us a great
way to do that because we can just
add on another node and add on
another node and add on another node.
But what might be a trade-off?
Does anyone remember the trade-off
between arrays and linked lists?
Mmhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: You have to
go through all the way
through the linked list
find an element in a list.
In an array, you can
just find an element.
>> SPEAKER 1: Right.
So with arrays--
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: With arrays, we have
what's called random access.
Means that if we want what is
ever the fifth point of a list
or the fifth point of our
array, we can just grab it.
If it's a linked list, we have
to iterate through, right?
So accessing an element in
an array is constant time,
whereas with a linked list it would
most likely be linear time because maybe
our element is all the way at the end.
We have to search through everything.
So with all these data
structures we're going
to be spending a little more time on,
what are the pluses and negatives.
When might we want to
use one over the other?
And that's kind of the
bigger thing to take away.
>> So we have here the
definition of a node.
It's like one element in
our linked list, right?
So we're all familiar
with our typedef structs,
which we went over in review last time.
It was basically just creating
another data type that we could use.
>> And in this case, it's some node
that will hold some integer in.
And then what's the second part here?
Anyone?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
It's a pointer to the next node.
So this should actually be up here.
This is a pointer of type
node to the next thing.
And that's what they
encompasses our node.
Cool.
>> All right, so with search, as we were
just saying before hand, if you're
going to search through,
you have to actually iterate
through your linked list.
So if we're looking for the number
9, we would start at our head
and that points us at the beginning
of our linked list, right?
And we say, OK, does this
node contain the number 9?
No?
>> All right, go to the next one.
Follow it.
Does it contain the number 9?
No.
Follow the next one.
>> So we have to actually iterate
through our linked list.
We can't just go directly to where 9 is.
And if you guys actually want to
see some pseudo-code up there.
We have some search function here
that takes in-- what does it take in?
What do you think?
So easy one.
What is this?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: The number we're looking for.
Right?
And what would this correspond to?
It's a pointer to?
>> AUDIENCE: A node.
>> SPEAKER 1: A node to the list
that we're looking at, right?
So we have some nodes are pointer here.
This is a point that's going to
actually iterate through our list.
We set it equal to list
because that's just
setting it equal to the
start of our linked list.
>> And while it's not NULL, while
we still have things in our list,
check to see if that node has
the number we're looking for.
Return true.
Otherwise, update it, right?
>> If it is NULL, we exit our
while loop and return false
because that means we haven't found it.
Does everyone get how that works?
OK.
>> So with insertion, you
have three different ways.
You can prepend, you can append
and you can insert into assorted.
In this case, we're
going to do a prepend.
Does anyone know how those
three cases might differ?
>> So prepend means that you put
it at the front of your list.
So that would mean that no matter
what your node is, no matter
what the value is, you're going
to put it right here in front, OK?
It's going to be the first
element in your list.
>> If you append it, it's going
to go to the back of your list.
And insert into assorted means you're
going to put actually into the place
where it keeps your linked list sorted.
Again, how you use
those and when you use
them will vary depending on your case.
If it doesn't need to
be sorted, prepend tends
to be what most people
use because you don't
have to go through the entire list
to find the end to add it on, right?
You can just stick it right in.
>> So we will go through an
insertion 1 right now.
So one thing that I'm going to
highly recommend on this pset
is to draw things out, as always.
It's very important that you update
your pointers in the correct order
because if you update them
slightly out of order,
you're going to end up
losing parts of your list.
>> So for example, in this case, we're
telling the head to just point to 1.
If we just do that
without saving this 1,
we have no idea what
1 should point to now
because we've lost what
the head pointed to.
So one thing to remember
when you're doing a prepend
is to save what the
head points to first,
then reassign it, and then update
what your new node should point to.
In this case, this is one way to do it.
>> So if we had done it this way
where we just reassigned head,
we lose basically our
entire list, right?
One way to do it is to have 1 point to
next, and then have head point to 1.
Or you can do kind of like the
temporary storage, which I talked about.
>> But reassigning your
pointers in the correct order
is going to be very, very
important for this pset.
Otherwise, you're going to have a hash
table or a try that's just going to be
only part of the words that you
want and then you're-- mmhmm?
AUDIENCE: What was the temporary
storage thing you were talking about?
SPEAKER 1: The temporary storage.
So basically another
way you could do this
is store the head of something, like
store it the temporary variable.
Assign it to 1 and
then update 1 to point
to whatever head used to point to.
This way is obviously
more elegant because you
don't need a temporary value, but
just offering another way to do it.
And we actually do have
some code for this.
So for linked list, we
actually have some code.
So insert here, this is prepending.
So this enters it at the head.
>> So first thing, you need to
create your new node, of course,
and check for NULL.
Always good.
And then you need to assign the values.
Whenever you create a new node, you
don't know what it's pointing to next,
so you want to initialize it to NULL.
If it does end up pointing to something
else, it gets reassigned and it's fine.
If it's the first thing
in the list, it needs
to point to NULL because
that's the end of the list.
>> So then to insert it, we see here we
are assigning the next value of our node
to be whatever head is,
which is what we had here.
That's what we just did.
And then we're assigning head to point
to our new node, because remember,
new is some pointer to a node,
and that's exactly what head is.
That is exactly why we
have this arrow accessor.
Cool?
Mmhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: Do we have to
initialize new next to NULL first,
or can we just initialize it to head?
>> SPEAKER 1: New next
needs to be NULL to start
because you don't know
where it's going to be.
Also, this is kind of
just like a paradigm.
You set it equal to NULL just to make
sure that all your bases are covered
before you do any reassignment so that
you're always guaranteed that it will
be pointing to a specific value
versus like a garbage value.
Because, yeah, we assign
new next automatically,
but it's more just like a
good practice to initialize it
in that way and then reassign.
>> OK, so doubly linked lists now.
What do we think?
What's different with
doubly linked lists?
>> So in our linked lists, we can
only move in one direction, right?
We only have next.
We can only go forward.
>> With a doubly linked list,
we can also move backwards.
So we have not only the
number that we want to store,
we have where it points to next
and where we just came from.
So this allows for
some better traversal.
>> So doubly linked nodes,
very similar, right?
Only difference is now we
have a next and a previous.
It's the only difference.
>> So if we were to prepend or append-- we
don't have any code for this up here--
but if you were to try and
insert it, the important thing
is you need to make
sure you're assigning
both your previous and your
next pointer correctly.
So in this case, you would
not only initialize next,
you initialize previous.
If we're at the head of the list, we
would not only make head equal new,
but our new previous should
point to the head, right?
>> That's the only difference.
And if you want more practice with
these with linked lists, with inserting,
with deleting, with insert
into an assorted list,
please check out study.cs50.net.
There's a bunch of great exercises.
I highly recommend them.
I wish we had time to go through them
but there's a lot of data structures
to get through.
>> OK, so hash tables.
This is probably the most
useful bit for your pset
here because you're going to be
implementing one of these, or a try.
I really like hash tables.
They're pretty cool.
>> So basically what
happens is a hash table
is when we really need speedy
insertion, deletion, and lookup.
Those are the things that we're
prioritizing in a hash table.
They can get pretty big,
but as we'll see with tries,
there are things that are much bigger.
>> But basically, all a hash
table is a hash function
that tells you which bucket to put each
of your data, each of your elements in.
A simple way to think of a hash table
is that it's just buckets of things,
right?
So when you are sorting things by
like the first letter of their name,
that's kind of like a hash table.
>> So if I were to group you guys is
into groups of whoever's name starts
with A over here, or whoever's birthday
is in January, February, March,
whatever, that is effectively
creating a hash table.
It's just creating buckets that
you sort your elements into
so that you can find them easier.
So this way when I need
to find one of you,
I don't have to search
through each of your names.
I can be like, oh, I know that
Danielle's birthday is in--
AUDIENCE: --April.
SPEAKER 1: April.
So I look in my April
bucket, and with any luck,
she'll be the only one in there and
my time was constant in that sense,
whereas if I have to look
through a whole bunch of people,
it's going to take much longer.
So hash tables are really just buckets.
Easy way to think of them.
>> So a very important thing about
a hash table is a hash function.
So the things I just talked about, like
your first letter of your first name
or your birthday month,
these are ideas that
really correlate to a hash function.
It's just a way of deciding which
bucket you're element goes into, OK?
So for this pset, you can look up
pretty much any hash function you want.
>> Doesn't have to be your own.
There are some really cool ones out
there that do all sorts of crazy math.
And if you want to make your
spellchecker super fast,
I would definitely
look into one of those.
>> But there are also the
simple ones, like compute
the sum of the words, like
each letter has a number.
Compute the sum.
That determines the bucket.
They also have the easy ones that
are just like all of the A's here,
all of the B's here.
Any one of those.
>> Basically, it just tells you which
array index your element should go into.
Just deciding the bucket--
it's all a hash function is.
So here we have an example which is
just the first letter of the string
that I was just talking about.
>> So you have some hash that's just the
first letter of your string minus A,
which will give you some
number between 0 and 25.
And what you want to do is
make sure that this represents
the size of your hash table--
how many buckets there are.
With many of these
hash functions, they're
going to be returning values that might
be far above the number of buckets
that you actually have
in your hash table,
so you need to make
sure and mod by those.
Otherwise, it's going to say,
oh, it should be in bucket 5,000
but you only have 30
buckets in your hash table.
And of course, we all know that's
going to result in some crazy errors.
So make sure to mod by the
size of your hash table.
Cool.
So collisions.
Is everyone good so far?
Mmhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: Why would it
return such a massive value?
>> SPEAKER 1: Depending on the algorithm
that your hash function uses.
Some of them will do
crazy multiplication.
And it's all about getting
a even distribution,
so they do some really
crazy things sometimes.
That's all.
Anything else?
OK.
>> So collisions.
Basically, as I said earlier,
in the best case scenario,
any bucket I look into is
going to have one thing,
so I don't have to look at all, right?
I either know it's there or it's
not, and that's what we really want.
But if we have tens of thousands of
data points and less than that number
of buckets, we're going to have
collisions where eventually something
is going to have to end up in a
bucket that already has an element.
>> So the question is, what
do we do in that case?
What do we do?
We already have something there?
Do we just throw it out?
>> No.
We have to keep both of them.
So the way that we
typically do that is what?
What is the data structure
we just talked about?
AUDIENCE: Linked list.
SPEAKER 1: A linked list.
So now, instead of each of these
buckets just having one element,
it's going to contain a linked list of
the elements that were hashed into it.
OK, does everyone kind of get that idea?
Because we couldn't have an array
because we don't know how many things
are going to be in there.
A linked list allows us to
have just the exact number that
are hashed into that bucket, right?
>> So linear probing is
basically this idea--
it's one way to deal with a collision.
What you can do is if, in this
case, berry was hashed into 1
and we already have
something there, you just
keep going down until
you find an empty slot.
That's one way to handle it.
The other way to handle
it is with what we just
called-- the linked
list is called chaining.
>> So this idea works if
your hash table you think
is much larger than
your data set or if you
want to try and minimize chaining
until it's absolutely necessary.
So one thing is linear
probing obviously means
that your hash function
isn't quite as useful
because you're going to end up using
your hash function, getting to a point,
you linear probe down to
some place that is available.
But now, of course, anything
else that ends up there,
you're going to have to
search even further down.
>> And there's a lot more
search expense that
goes into inputting an element
in your hash table now, right?
And now when you go and try and find
berry again, you're going to hash it,
and it's going to say,
oh, look in bucket 1,
and it's not going to be
in bucket 1, so you're
going to have to traverse
through the rest of these.
So it's sometimes useful,
but in most cases,
we're going to say that
chaining is what you want to do.
>> So we talked about this earlier.
I got a little ahead of myself.
But chaining is basically that
each bucket in your hash table
is just a linked list.
>> So another way, or more technical
way, to think of a hash table
is that it's just an array
of linked lists, which
when you're writing your dictionary
and you're trying to load it,
thinking of it as an
array of linked lists
will make it much easier
for you to initialize.
>> AUDIENCE: So hash table
has a predetermined size,
like a [INAUDIBLE] of buckets?
>> SPEAKER 1: Right.
So it has a set number of
buckets that you determine--
which you guys should
feel free to play with.
It can be pretty cool
to see what happens
as you change your number of buckets.
But yeah, it has a
set number of buckets.
What allows you to fit as
many elements as you need
is this separate chaining where you
have linked lists in each bucket.
That means your hash table
will be exactly the size
that you need it to be, right?
That's the whole point of linked lists.
Cool.
>> So everyone OK there?
All right.
Ah.
What just happened?
Really now.
Guess somebody's killing me.
>> OK we're going to go into
tries, which are a little crazy.
I like hash tables.
I think they're really cool.
Tries are cool, too.
>> So does anyone remember what a try is?
You should have gone over
it briefly in lecture?
Do you remember kind of how it works?
AUDIENCE: I'm just nodding
that we did go over it.
SPEAKER 1: We do go over it.
OK, we're really going to go
over it now is what we're saying.
>> AUDIENCE: That's for a retrieval tree.
>> SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
It's a retrieval tree.
Awesome.
So one thing to notice here is that we
are looking at individual characters
here, right?
>> So before with our hash function, we
were looking at the words as a whole,
and now we're looking more
at the characters, right?
So we have Maxwell over here and Mendel.
So basically a try-- a way to think
about this is that every level here
is an array of letters.
So this is your root node here, right?
This has all the characters of the
alphabet for the start of every word.
>> And what you want to do is
say, OK, we have some M word.
We're going to look for Maxwell, so
we go to M. And M points to a whole
other a array where every
word, as long as there
is a word that has A
as the second letter,
as long as there's a word that
has B as the second letter,
it will have a pointer
going to some next array.
>> There's probably not a
word that MP something,
so at the P position in this
array, it would just be NULL.
It would say, OK, there is no word
that has M followed by a P, OK?
So if we think about it, each
one of these smaller things
is actually one of these
large arrays from A through Z.
So what might be one of the things
that is kind of a drawback of a try?
>> AUDIENCE: A lot of memory.
>> SPEAKER 1: It's a ton of memory, right?
Each one of these blocks here
represents 26 spaces, 26 element array.
So tries get incredibly space heavy.
>> But they are very fast.
So incredibly fast but
really space inefficient.
Kind of have to figure
out which one you want.
These are really cool for your pset,
but they do take up a lot of memory,
so you trade off.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Would it be possible
to set up a try and then
once you have all the
data in it that you need--
I don't know if that would make sense.
I was getting rid of all the
NULL characters, but then
you wouldn't be able to index them--
>> SPEAKER 1: You still need them.
>> AUDIENCE: -- the same way each time.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
You need the NULL characters to let
you know if there's not a word there.
Ben did you have something you want?
OK.
All right, so we're going
to go a little bit more
into the technical detail behind
a try and work through an example.
>> OK, so this is the same thing.
Whereas in a linked list, our main
kind of-- what's the word I want?--
like building block was a node.
In a try, we also have a node,
but it's defined differently.
>> So we have some bool that
represents whether a word actually
exists at this location, and then
we have some array here-- or rather,
this is a pointer to an
array of 27 characters.
And this is for, in this case, this
27-- I'm sure all of you are like, wait,
there are 26 letters in the alphabet.
Why do we have 27?
>> So depending on the
way you implement this,
this is from a pset that
allowed for apostrophes.
So that's why the extra one.
You'll also have in some
cases the null terminator
is included as one of the
characters that it's allowed to be,
and that's how they check to
see if it's the end of the word.
If you're interested, check out
Kevin's video on study.cs50,
as well as Wikipedia has
some good resources there.
>> But we're going to go through just kind
of how you might work through a try
if you're given one.
So we have a super simple one here that
has the words "bat" and "zoom" in them.
And as we see up here,
this little space here
represents our bool that
says, yes, this is a word.
And then this has our
arrays of characters, right?
>> So we are going to go through
finding "bat" in this try.
So begin at the top, right?
And we know that b corresponds to
the second index, the second element
in this array, because a and b.
So approximately the second one.
>> And it says, OK, cool, follow that into
the next array, because if we remember,
it's not that each of these
actually contains the element.
Each one of these arrays
contains a pointer, right?
It's an important distinction to make.
>> I know this is going to be-- tries are
really hard to get on the first time,
so even if this is the
second or third time
and it's still kind
of seeming difficult,
I promise if you go watch
the short again tomorrow,
it'll probably make a lot more sense.
It takes a lot to digest.
I still sometimes am
like, wait, what is a try?
How do I use this?
>> So we have b in this case,
which is our second index.
If we had, say, c or
d or any other letter,
we need to map that back to the index
of our array that that corresponds to.
So we would take like rchar and we just
subtract off a to map it into 0 to 25.
Everybody good how we
map our characters?
OK.
>> So we go to the second one and we
see that, yes, it is not to NULL.
We can move on to this next array.
So we go on to this next array here.
>> And we say, OK, now we
need to see if a is here.
Is A null or does it
actually move forward?
So a actually moves
forward in this array.
And we say, OK, t is our last letter.
So we go to the t at the index.
And then we move forward
because there's another one.
And this one says basically that, yes,
it says that there is a word here--
that if you follow this
path, you have arrived
at a word, which we know is "bat."
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Is it standard to have that
as index 0 and then have a sort at 1
or to have at the end?
>> SPEAKER 1: No.
So if we look back at our
declaration here, it's a bool,
so it's its own element in your node.
So it's not part of the array.
Cool.
So when we finish our word and we're
at this array, what we want to do
is do a check for is this a word.
And in this case, it would return yes.
>> So on that note, we know that "zoo"--
we know as humans that "zoo" is a word,
right?
But are try here would
say, no, it's not.
And it would say that because we
haven't designated it as a word here.
Even though we can traverse
through to this array,
this try would say that, no,
zoo isn't in your dictionary
because we haven't
designated it as such.
>> So one way to do that--
oh, sorry, this one.
So in this case, "zoo" is not
a word, but it is in our try.
But in this one, say we want it
introduce the word "bath," what happens
is we follow through-- b, a, t.
We're in this array, and
we go to search for h.
>> In this case, when we
look at the pointer at h,
it's pointing to NULL, OK?
So unless it's explicitly
pointing to another array,
you assume that all the pointers
in this array are pointing to null.
So in this case, h is pointing
to null so we can't do anything,
so it would also return
false, "bath" is not in here.
So now we're actually
going to go through
how would we actually say
that "zoo" is in our try.
How do we insert "zoo" into our try?
So in the same way that we started with
our linked list, we start at the root.
When in doubt, start at
the root of these things.
>> And we'll say, OK, z.
z exists in this, and it does.
So you're moving on to
your next array, OK?
And then on the next one,
we say, OK, does o exist?
It does.
This again.
>> And so on our next one, we've said,
OK, "zoo" already exists here.
All we need to do is set this equal
to true, that there is a word there.
If you had followed everything
up to before that point,
it's a word, so just
set it equal to such.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: So then does that
mean that "ba" is a word also?
>> SPEAKER 1: No.
So in this case, "ba" we would get
here, we would say is it a word,
and it would still be no.
OK?
Mmhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: So once you is it a
word and you say yes, then it
will contain to go to m?
>> SPEAKER 1: So this has to do
with-- you're loading this in.
You say "zoo" is a word.
When you go to check--
like, say you want to say,
does "zoo" exist in this dictionary?
You're only going to search for "zoo,"
and then check to see if it's a word.
You're never going to move
through to m because that's not
what you're looking for.
>> So if we actually wanted to
add "bath" into this try,
we would do the same thing
as we did with "zoo,"
except we would see that when we
try and get to h, it doesn't exist.
So you can think of this as trying
to add a new node into a linked list,
so we would need to add another
one of these arrays, like so.
And then what we do is we just set the h
element of this array pointing to this.
>> And then what would we want to do here?
Add it equal to true
because it's a word.
Cool.
I know.
Tries are not the most exciting.
Trust me, I know.
>> So one thing to realize with tries,
I said, they're very efficient.
So we've seen they
take up a ton of space.
They're kind of confusing.
So why would we ever use these?
We use these because they're
incredibly efficient.
>> So if you're ever looking
up a word, you are only
bounded by the length of the word.
So if you're looking for a
word that is of length five,
you're only ever going to have to
make at most five comparisons, OK?
So it makes it basically a constant.
Like insertion and lookup
are basically constant time.
>> So if you can ever get
something in constant time,
that's as good as it gets.
You can't get better than
constant time for these things.
So that is one of the
huge pluses of tries.
>> But it is a lot of space.
So you kind of have to decide
what's more important to you.
And on today's computers, the
space that a try may take up
maybe doesn't affect
you that much, but maybe
you're dealing with something
that has far, far more things,
and a try just isn't reasonable.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Wait, so you have 26
letters in every single one?
>> SPEAKER 1: Mmhmm.
Yeah, you have 26.
You have some is word marker and then
you have 26 pointers in every one.
And they're point--
>> AUDIENCE: And every 26,
do they each have 26?
>> SPEAKER 1: Yes.
And that's why, as you can
see, it expands quite rapidly.
All right.
So we're going to get into trees, which
I feel like is easier and will probably
be a nice little reprieve
from tries there.
So hopefully most of you
have seen a tree before.
Not like the pretty
ones outside, which I
don't know if anyone
went outdoors recently.
I went apple picking this weekend,
and oh my gosh, it was beautiful.
I didn't know leaves
could look that pretty.
>> So this is just a tree, right?
It's just some node, and it
points to a bunch of other nodes.
As you see here, this is
kind of a recurring theme.
Nodes pointing to nodes is kind of
the essence of many data structures.
It just depends on how we
have them point to each other
and how we traverse
through them and how we
insert things that determines
their different characteristics.
>> So just some terminology,
which I've used before.
So root is whatever is at the very top.
it's where we always start.
You can think of it as the head also.
But for trees, we tend to
refer to it as the root.
>> Anything at the bottom here--
at the very, very bottom--
are considered leaves.
So it goes along with the
whole tree thing, right?
Leaves are at the edges of your tree.
>> And then we also have a couple of
terms to talk about nodes in relation
to each other.
So we have parent,
children, and siblings.
So in this case, 3 is the
parent of 5, 6, and 7.
So the parent is whatever is
one step above whatever you're
referring to, so just
like a family tree.
Hopefully, this is all a little
bit more intuitive than the tries.
>> Siblings are any that have
the same parent, right?
They're on the same level here.
And then, as I was
saying, children are just
whatever is one step below
the node in question, OK?
Cool.
So a binary tree.
Can anyone hazard a guess on one of
the characteristics of the binary tree?
>> AUDIENCE: Max two leaves.
>> SPEAKER 1: Right.
So max of two leaves.
So in this one before, we had this one
that had three, but in a binary tree,
you have a max of two
children per parent, right?
There's another
interesting characteristic.
Does anyone know that?
Binary tree.
>> So a binary tree will have everything
on the-- this one isn't sorted--
but in a sorted binary tree,
everything on the right
is greater than the parent,
and everything on the left
is less than the parent.
And that has been a quiz
question before, so good to know.
So the way we define this,
again, we have another node.
This looks very similar to what?
Doubly
>> AUDIENCE: Linked lists
>> SPEAKER 1: A double linked list, right?
So if we replace this
with previous and next,
this would be a doubly linked list.
But in this case, we actually
have left and right and that's it.
Otherwise, it's exactly the same.
We still have the element
you're looking for,
and you just have two pointers
going to whatever's next.
Yeah, so binary search tree.
If we notice, everything on the
right here is greater than--
or everything immediately
to the right here
is greater than, everything
here is less than.
>> So if we were to search through, it
should look very close to binary search
here, right?
Except instead of looking
at half the array,
we are just looking at either the left
side or the right side of the tree.
So it gets a little simpler, I think.
>> So if your root is NULL,
obviously it's just false.
And if it's there, obviously it's true.
If it's less than, we search the left.
If it's greater than,
we search the right.
It's exactly like binary search,
just a different data structure
that we're using.
Instead of an array,
it's just a binary tree.
>> OK, stacks.
And also, it looks like we
might have a little bit of time.
If we do, I'm happy to go
over any of this again.
OK, so stacks.
Does anyone remember what stacks--
any characteristics of a stack?
>> OK, so most of us, I think,
eat in the dining halls--
as much as we may not like to.
But obviously, you can think of a stack
literally just as a stack of trays
or a stack of things.
And what's important
to realize is that it's
something-- the characteristic
that we call it by-- is LIFO.
Does anyone know what that stands for?
Mmhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: Last in, first out.
>> SPEAKER 1: Right, last in, first out.
So if we know, if we're stacking things
up, the easiest thing to grab off--
and maybe the only thing we can grab
off if our stack is big enough--
is that top element.
So whatever was put on
last-- as we see here,
whatever was pushed
on most recently-- is
going to be the first
thing that we pop off, OK?
>> So what we have here is
another typedef struct.
This is really just like a
crash course in data structure,
so there's a lot thrown at you guys.
I know.
So yet another struct.
Yay for structures.
>> And in this case, it's some pointer
to an array that has some capacity.
So this represents our stack
here, like our actual array
that's holding our elements.
And then here we have some size.
>> And typically, you want to keep
track of how big your stack is
because what it's going to allow
you to do is if you know the size,
it allows you to say,
OK, am I at capacity?
Can I add anything more?
And it also tells you
where the top of your stack
is so you know what you
can actually take off.
And that's actually going to
be a little more clear here.
>> So for push, one thing, if you
were ever to implement push,
as I was just saying, your
stack has a limited size, right?
Our array had some capacity.
It's an array.
It's a fixed size, so we need to
make sure that we're not putting more
into our array than we
actually have space for.
>> So when you're creating a push
function, first thing you do is say, OK,
do I have space in my stack?
Because if I don't, sorry,
I can't store your element.
If I do, then you want to store
it at the top of the stack, right?
>> And this is why we have
to keep track of our size.
If we don't keep track of our size,
we don't know where to put it.
We don't know how many things
are in our array already.
Like obviously there are ways
that maybe you could do it.
You could initialize everything to NULL
and then check for the latest NULL,
but a much easier thing is just
to say, OK, keep track of size.
Like I know I have four elements
in my array, so the next thing
that we put on, we're
going to store at index 4.
And then, of course, this means that
you've successfully pushed something
onto your stack, you
want to increase the size
so that you know where you are so
that you can push more things on.
>> So if we are trying to pop
something off the stack,
what might be the first thing
that we want to check for?
You're trying to take
something off your stack.
Are you sure there's
something in your stack?
No.
So what might we want to check?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: Check for the size?
Size.
So we want to check to see if
our size is greater than 0, OK?
And if it is, then we want to decrease
our size by 0 and return that.
Why?
>> In the first one we were
pushing, we pushed it
onto size and then updated size.
In this case, we're decrementing size
and then taking it off, plucking it
from our array.
Why might we do that?
So if I have one thing on my stack,
what would be my size at that point?
1.
>> And where is element 1 stored?
At what index?
AUDIENCE: 0.
SPEAKER 1: 0.
So in this case, we
always need to make sure--
instead of returning
size minus 1, because we
know that our element is
going to be stored at 1 less
whatever our size is, this
just takes care of it.
It's a slightly more elegant way.
And we just decrement our
size and then return size.
Mmhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: I guess just in general,
why would this data structure
be beneficial?
>> SPEAKER 1: It depends on your context.
So for some of the theory,
if you're working with-- OK,
let me see if there is a beneficial one
that is beneficial to more than outside
of CS.
With stacks, any time you need
to keep track of something that
is the most recently added is when
you're going to want to use a stack.
>> And I can't think of a good
example of that right now.
But whenever the most recent
thing is most important to you,
that's when a stack
is going to be useful.
I'm trying to think if
there's a good one for this.
If I think of a good example in the next
20 minutes, I will definitely tell you.
>> But overall, if there's anything,
like I said most, where most recent
is most important, that's
where a stack comes into play.
Whereas queues are kind of the opposite.
And all the little dogs.
Isn't this great, right?
I feel like I should
just have a bunny video
right in the middle of
section for you guys
because this is an intense section.
>> So a queue.
Basically a queue is like a line.
You guys I'm sure use this everyday,
just like in our dining halls.
So we have to go in
and get our trays, I'm
sure you have to wait in line
to swipe or get your food.
>> So the difference here
is that this is FIFO.
So if LIFO was last in, first
out, FIFO is first in, first out.
So this is where whatever you put
on first is your most important.
So if you were waiting
in a line-- can you
imagine if you went to
go get the new iPhone
and it was a stack where the
last person in line got it first,
people would kill each other.
>> So FIFO, we're all very familiar
with in the real world here,
and it all has to do with actually
kind of recreating this whole line
and queuing structure.
So whereas with the stack,
we have push and pop.
With a queue, we have
enqueue and dequeue.
So enqueue basically means
put it onto the back,
and dequeue means take
off from the front.
So our data structure is a
little bit more complicated.
We have a second thing to keep track of.
>> So without the head, this
is exactly a stack, right?
This is the same structure as a stack.
The only thing different now is we
have this head, which what do you think
is going to keep track of?
>> AUDIENCE: The first one.
>> SPEAKER 1: Right, the
first thing that we put in.
The head of our queue.
Whoever's first in line.
All right, so if we do enqueue.
Again, with any of
these data structures,
since we're dealing with an array,
we need to check if we have space.
>> This is kind of like me telling
you guys, if you open a file,
you need to check for null.
With any of these stacks
and queues, you need
to see if there's space because we're
dealing with a fixed size array,
as we see here-- 0, 1 all up to 5.
So what we do in that case is check
to see if we still have space.
Is our size less than capacity?
>> If so, we need to store it at
the tail and we update our size.
So what might the tail be in this case?
It's not explicitly written out.
How would we store it?
What would the tail be?
>> So let's walk through this example.
So this is an array of size 6, right?
And we have right now, our size is 5.
And when we put it in, it's going
to go into the fifth index, right?
So store at tail.
>> Another way to write tail would just
be our array at index of size, right?
This is size 5.
Next thing is going to go into 5.
Cool?
OK.
It gets slightly more complicated
when we start messing with the head.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Does that mean that we
would have declared an array that
was five elements long and
then we're adding onto it?
>> SPEAKER 1: No.
So in this case, this is a stack.
This would be declared
as an array of size 6.
And in this case, we
just have one space left.
>> OK, so one thing is in this
case, if our head is at 0,
then we just can add it at size.
But it gets a little trickier
because actually, they
don't have a slide
for this, so I'm going
to draw one because it's not
quite that simple once you
start getting rid of things.
So whereas with a stack
you only ever have
to worry about what the size is
when you're adding something on,
with a queue you also need to make
sure that your head is accounted for,
because a cool thing about queues
is that if you're not at capacity,
you can actually make it wrap around.
>> OK, so one thing-- oh,
this is terrible chalk.
One thing to consider is the case.
We'll just do five.
OK, so we're going to
say the head is here.
This is 0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
>> The head's there, and
please have things in them.
And we want to add something in, right?
So the thing that we need to
know is that the head is always
going to move this way and
then loop back around, OK?
>> So this queue has space, right?
It has space in the very beginning,
kind of the opposite of this.
So what we need to do is we
need to calculate the tail.
If you know that your
head hasn't moved, tail
is just your array at
the index of the size.
>> But in reality, if you're using a queue,
your head is probably being updated.
So what you need to do is
actually calculate the tail.
So what we do is this formula
here, which I'm going to let you
guys think about, and
then we'll talk about it.
So this is capacity.
>> So this will actually
give you a way to do it.
Because in this case, what?
Our head is at 1, our size is 4.
If we mod that by 5, we get 0,
which is where we should input it.
>> So then in the next case,
if we were to do this,
we say, OK, let's dequeue something.
We dequeue this.
We take out this element, right?
>> And now our head is pointing here,
and we want to add in another thing.
This is basically the
back of our line, right?
Queues can wrap around the array.
That's one of the main differences.
Stacks, you can't do this.
>> With queues, you can
because all that matters
is that you know what
was most recently added.
Since everything is going to be added in
this leftward direction, in this case,
and then wrap around, you can
continue putting in new elements
at the front of the array
because it's not really
the front of the array anymore.
You can think of the beginning of the
array as where your head actually is.
>> So this formula is how
you calculate your tail.
Does that makes sense?
OK.
OK, dequeue, and then
you guys have 10 minutes
to ask me any clarifying questions
you want, because I know it's crazy.
>> All right, so in the same way--
I don't know if you guys noticed,
but CS is all about patterns.
Things are pretty much the
same, just with tiny tweaks.
So same thing here.
We need to check to see if we actually
have something in our queue, right?
Say, OK, is our size greater than 0?
Cool.
>> If we do, then we move our head, which
is what I just demonstrated here.
We update our head to be one more.
And then we decrement our
size and return the element.
>> There is much more concrete
code on study.cs50.net,
and I highly recommend going
through it if you have time,
even if it's just a pseudo-code.
And if you guys want to talk through
that with me one on one, please let me
know.
I'd be happy to.
Data structures, if
you take CS 124, you'll
know that data structures get very
fun and this is just beginning.
>> So I know it's hard.
It's OK.
We struggle.
I still do.
So don't worry too much about it.
>> But that is basically your
crash course in data structures.
I know it's a lot.
Is there anything that we
would like to go over again?
Anything we want to talk through?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: For that example, so
the new tail is at 0 over that?
SPEAKER 1: Yes.
AUDIENCE: OK.
So then going through,
you'd have 1 plus 4 or--
>> SPEAKER 1: So you were saying,
when we want to go do this again?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
So if you were figuring out-- where are
you calculating the tail from in that?
>> SPEAKER 1: So the tail
was in-- I changed this.
So in this example here, this was
the array we're looking at, OK?
So we have things in 1, 2, 3, and 4.
So we have our head is equal to 1 at
this point, and our size is equal to 4
at this point, right?
>> You all agree that's the case?
So we do the head plus the size, which
gives us 5, and then we mod by 5.
We get 0, which tells us that 0 is
where is our tail, where we have space.
>> AUDIENCE: What's a cap?
>> SPEAKER 1: The capacity.
Sorry.
So that is the size of your array.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] before
we return the element?
>> SPEAKER 1: So we move the
head or return the moment?
So if we move one, decrement the size?
Hold on.
I definitely forgot another.
Never mind.
There is not another formula.
Yeah, you would want to return
the head and then move it back.
>> AUDIENCE: OK, because At this
point, the head was at 0,
and then you want to return
index 0 and then make head 1?
>> SPEAKER 1: Right.
I think there's another
formula kind of like this.
I don't have it on the top my head as
I don't want to give you the wrong one.
But I think it's perfectly valid to
say, OK, store this element-- whatever
head's element is-- decrement your
size, move your head over, and return
whatever that element is.
That's perfectly valid.
OK.
I feel like this is not
like the most-- you're not
going to walk out of here
like, yes, I know tries.
I got it all.
That's OK.
I promise.
But data structures are something that
it takes a lot of time to get used to.
Probably one of the hardest
things, I think, in the course.
>> So it definitely takes
repetition and looking at-- I
didn't really know linked lists
until I did far too much with them,
in the same way that I didn't
really understand pointers
until I've had to teach it for two
years and do my own psets with it.
It takes a lot of reiteration and time.
And eventually, it will kind of click.
>> But in the meantime, if you have kind
of a high level understanding of what
these do, their pros
and cons-- which is what
we really tend to emphasize,
especially in the intro course.
Like, why would we use
a try over an array?
Like, what are the positives
and negatives of each of those?
>> And understanding the trade-offs
between each of these structures
is what's much more important right now.
There may be one crazy
question or two that's
going to ask you to implement push or
implement pop or enqueue and dequeue.
But for the most part, having that
higher level understanding and more
of an intuitive grasp is
more important than actually
being able to implement it.
>> It'd be really awesome if all of you
could go out and go implement a try,
but we understand it's not necessarily
the most reasonable thing right now.
But you can in your pset, if you want
to, and then you'll get practice,
and then maybe you'll
really understand it.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: OK, so which ones are
we meant to use in the pset?
Do I need to use one of them?
SPEAKER 1: Yes.
So you have your choice.
I guess in this case, we can
talk about the pset a little bit
because I ran through these.
So in your pset, you have your
choice of tries or hash tables.
Some people will try
and use bloom filters,
but those technically are not correct.
Because of their probabilistic nature,
they give false positives sometimes.
They're cool look into, though.
Highly recommend looking
at them at least.
But you have your choice
between a hash table and a try.
And that's going to be where
you load in your dictionary.
>> And you'll need to choose
your hash function,
you'll need to choose how many
buckets you have, and it will vary.
Like if you have more buckets,
maybe it'll run faster.
But maybe you're wasting a
lot of space that way, though.
You have to figure it out.
Mmhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: You said before that
we can use other hash functions,
that we don't have to
create a hash function?
>> SPEAKER 1: Yes, right.
So literally for your hash function,
like google "hash function"
and look for some cool ones.
You are not expected to build
your own hash functions.
People spend their
theses on these things.
>> So don't worry about building your own.
Find one online to start with.
Some of them you have to
manipulate a little bit
to make sure return types match up
and whatnot, so in the beginning,
I would recommend using something
really easy that maybe just
hashes on the first letter.
And then once you have that working,
incorporating a cooler hash function.
Mmhmm?
>> AUDIENCE: Would a try be or
efficient but just harder to, like--
>> SPEAKER 1: So a try, I think,
is intuitively hard to implement
but is very fast.
However, takes up more space.
Again, you can optimize both of those in
different ways and there are ways to--
AUDIENCE: How are we graded on this?
Does it matter--
>> SPEAKER 1: So you're graded normal way.
You're going to be graded on design.
Whichever way you do, you want to
make sure it's as elegant as it can be
and as efficient as it can be.
But if you choose a try or hash
table, as long as it works,
we're happy with that.
And if you use something that hashes
on the first letter, that's fine,
like maybe like design-wise.
We're also reaching the
point in this semester--
I don't know if you
guys noticed-- if you're
pset grades decline a little bit
because of design and whatnot,
that's perfectly fine.
It's getting to a point where your
programs are getting more complicated.
There are more places
you can improve on.
>> So it's perfectly normal.
It's not that you're
doing worse on your pset.
It's just we're being harder on you now.
So everyone's feeling it.
I just graded all your psets.
I know everyone is feeling it.
>> So don't be worried about that.
And if you have any questions about
prior psets or ways you can improve,
I try and comment the specific
places, but sometimes it's late
and I get tired.
Are there any other things
about data structures?
I'm sure you guys don't really
want to talk about them anymore,
but if there are, I'm happy to
go over them, as well as anything
from lecture this past
week or last week.
>> I know last week was all review, so
we may have skipped over some review
from lecture.
Any other questions I can answer?
OK, all right.
Well, you guys get out 15 minutes early.
>> I hope this was semi-helpful at least,
and I will see you guys next week,
or Thursday office hours.
Are there requests for snacks
for next week, it's the thing?
Because I forgot candy today.
And I brought candy last
week, but it was Columbus Day,
so there were like six people who
had four bags of candy to themselves.
I can bring Starbursts
again if you like.
Starbursts?
OK, sounds good.
Have a great day, guys.