>> AMILA: Let's tackle Caesar.
In Caesar, we allow the user
to encode a secret message.
So let's dive right in and look
at our to-dos for this problem.
So first, we get the key from the user.
Then we get the plaintext
that they want to encode.
After that, we encipher it for them,
and finally we print their ciphertext.
>> So let's start with an example.
Say you wanted to encode the
entire alphabet with a key of two.
Well, your entire alphabet would
just be shifted to letters.
So A would encode to C, B to
D, C to E, so on and so forth,
until you get to X, which encodes to Z
or zed, depending on where you're from.
Then Y would then shift all the way,
wrap around the alphabet to get to A,
and then finally the last letter of the
alphabet, Z, zed, would encode to B.
>> You got that?
Let's look at some examples.
The first example here is very similar
to what we just explained above.
So if I encode some section of the
alphabet, A through L, by a key of two,
then I just get my entire
alphabet shifted two letters.
>> Then, in my next example,
the key is still two,
so you should still know
which letters to expect.
But here it's a phrase.
This is CS50.
So you'll notice that I
preserve the case of my letters,
so any upper case letters are also
upper case letters in the ciphertext.
And any lowercase
letters in the plaintext
are also lowercase
letters in the ciphertext.
But I keep the letters
and any exclamation marks
or any other punctuation the same.
>> So now that we have a sense
for how the program works,
feel free to go run some more
examples of your own, if you wish.
Let's start with getting
the key from the user.
Traditionally, with
other problems, we've
been accustomed to getting
any numbers that we
need by prompting the user
with the function getint.
But this time we're actually going
to use the command line argument
and a new function called atoi.
>> When you run the main
program in C, then it
takes in two parameters--
int argc, which
is the number of arguments
passed in, and then
argv, an array of strings which contains
the list of all of the arguments
passed.
You don't explicitly have
to declare these variables.
They're computed for
you by the compiler.
Correct usage for this would be
for argc to be two in this case,
because the user has to pass in
the call to the program, ./caesar,
and then the key,
whatever number they wish.
So that means that argc must be two
in order for a valid use of Caesar
to be executed.
>> So let's look at an example.
Say I've already written and
compiled a program called blastoff.
So if I ran in the command line
./blastoff Team Rocket, well, then,
argc would be three because I
passed in three distinct arguments.
Then argv would look like this.
It's an array, and it would
contain each of the three strings.
./blastoff in the first index, team
in the next, and rocket in the last.
>> Let's talk about arrays for a sec.
Arrays are data structures that hold
multiple values of the same type.
This can come in handy when we
have lists of integers or strings.
Just remember they have
to be the same type.
In computer science, we
love counting from zero,
so remember that arrays
are also zero-indexed.
So the first element of my array
is going to be at index zero.
So in this case, when I have
an array of length four,
then the last index of the
last element of my array
is actually going to be
at index three, not four.
Because remember, we
start counting at zero.
>> Here's an example of how you
might create an array of your own.
So say I wanted to store my
three favorite dog names.
Then I would create an array of strings.
So I would declare the type, string, and
then put the name of the array, dogs,
and then in those square
brackets put the size
of the array-- in this case, three.
>> So my first entry is going
to be dogs at index zero,
and that's going to be Milo.
Then dogs at index one
is going to be goofy,
darling Mochi, and then the last
entry, the third entry at index two,
is going to be cute, sweet Elphie.
You'll notice that the format
for filling in this array
is very much like how you might
declare any other variable where
you have the variable name followed by
the value that you want stored in it.
The only difference in
this case is that you
have to remember to put the index
of the value in square brackets.
And there we have our
three favorite dogs.
>> But alas, it's time
to get back to Caesar.
Remember that correct usage for the
user is going to be passing in not only
the name of the program ./caesar, but
also the key that they want to shift
their plaintext by.
So that means that argc must be two.
They must pass in two-- no more, no
less than two command line arguments.
>> Now, what about argv?
Well, we already know that the
array is going to be of length two,
but what's contained in each element?
Well, the first element
is going to be ./caesar,
and then the next element is going to
contain the key that the user typed in.
Now, if they used it correctly
for the usage of Caesar,
then they're going to type in a number.
But even though the character
that they type is a number,
it's of data type string.
>> So how do we convert that
string to an integer?
So say I have num, a string,
containing the string 50.
If I want to convert that
to an integer, then I simply
declare a new variable, an
integer i, calling atoi.
I pass in my string variable, num, and
then i will then contain the number 50.
Make sure to check the man
pages for the atoi function
to check which library it's
in, as well as what value it
will return if the string passed
in doesn't contain all numbers.
>> So now that we've gotten
the key, the next step
is to get the plaintext from the user.
Now, this is going to
be less complicated
than navigating around the
command line arguments.
All we have to do is call
the getstring function
to prompt the user to give
us a string, but remember
to check the specifications for how we
might want to prompt the user for that.
>> Now we come to the
heart of the problem--
how to encipher the plaintext.
Well, first, let's talk about how
to encipher one character at a time,
and then we'll address how to
iterate over the entire plaintext.
I've written some pseudocode
for the Caesar problem.
I encourage you to
write your own as well.
It might not look identical to
mine, and that's OK, but as long
as the general idea is the same.
>> The first three steps
we've already done.
We've gotten the key from
the command line argument,
we've turned that key
into an integer, and we've
prompted the user for the plaintext
that they want to encipher.
So then the next big chunk
is that for each character
in the plaintext string,
if it's alphabetic,
we want to preserve
its case and shift it.
By preserve case, what I
mean is that all upper case
letters should remain upper
case and all lowercase letters
should remain lowercase.
So then after we shift those,
then we print the ciphertext.
>> Here are three functions that are going
to come in handy for this problem.
Remember up above when I gave the
example for shifting this is CS50?
Remember that the 50 and the
exclamation mark didn't shift?
So how can we tell whether we
need to shift a letter or not?
Well, "is alpha," if
you pass it a character,
will return true if that character
is a letter and false otherwise.
To help you with
preserving capitalization
are the functions "is
upper" and "is lower."
>> These two functions also take
in a single character as input
and return you a Boolean,
either true or false
depending on whether that character
is upper case or lower case.
Because "is upper" and "is
lower" are Boolean functions,
meaning that they return you a Boolean,
you can use these in your conditions.
So here's a snippet of code that only
prints a letter if it's upper case.
So I've declared my character
letter to be the upper case zed
and then if "is upper" returns
true, then I print that letter.
>> Going back to our simple example of
shifting the alphabet by a key of two,
how do we actually get that to work?
Well, it turns out that characters
and integers are very closely related.
Each character has an
integer value associated
with it found in the ASCII chart,
where each character's ASCII
value is displayed.
So an upper case A corresponds
to an ASCII value of 65
and a lowercase a to
an ASCII value of 97.
>> Feel free to look up
any ASCII chart online
to see these values for yourself.
So what this means is that we can
take the character of upper case A,
add the integer two to it, and then get
the character upper case C as a result.
That's because 65, the ASCII
value for capital A, plus 2,
gives us 67, which corresponds
to the character of upper case C.
>> Unfortunately, things
won't quite be so simple.
We have an equation that
we have to consider.
Here it tells us that the ith ciphertext
letter corresponds to the ith plaintext
letter, plus the key--
all of that, modular 26.
Why is that the case?
Let's go back to our example from
before, where capital A, plus 2,
gives us capital C.
>> So applying the equation that
the specification gives us,
then let's take capital A
plus 2 and mod that by 26.
So capital A, when I put it in
those single quotation marks,
allows me to treat it as
an integer, so that allows
me to cast it to its ASCII value, 65.
65 plus 2 is 67.
67 mod 26 gives us 15,
but that doesn't really
make sense because we know that the
capital C ASCII value is 67, not 15.
So how do we reconcile that?
>> Well, here I'd like to posit the
notion of an alphabetical index.
So we've already talked about how
each character has its ASCII value,
but I'd like to say, well, let's
think about each character also having
an alphabetical index,
where A for instance,
as the first letter of the alphabet,
has an alphabetical index of zero.
So now let's apply the
same equation as before,
but using an alphabetical index.
>> So A is zero, as we've defined.
So then taking zero plus two, mod 26,
that's two, mod 26, which gives us two.
And well, in terms of
an alphabetical index,
C is the third letter in the
alphabet, so that would correspond
to an alphabetical index of two.
So it seems that using the
alphabetical index in this case
actually gives us the correct result.
>> So now let's check to
see if the equation works
with an alphabetical index.
Y's alphabetical index is 24 as the
second to last letter in the alphabet.
So then 24 plus our
key of two gives us 26.
26 mod 26 gives us 0, which, lucky for
us, is the alphabetical index for A.
So hopefully that's proof enough that
the alphabetical index method works.
If not, feel free to try out
some examples of your own.
>> In order to properly wrap around the
alphabet and apply the Caesar equation,
then we know that we need to
deal with alphabetical indices.
But we start with ASCII
values, and only then
do we then convert to
the alphabetical index.
From there, in order to print, we need
to deal with the ASCII values again.
So we need to figure out how to
go from ASCII to alphabetical
and from alphabetical to ASCII.
>> So I leave it to you to figure out
the pattern between a character
and its alphabetical
index and its ASCII value.
Now, remember that even though
this table right on the slide
shows the capital letters, we also
have to consider whether or not
a different pattern applies
for the lower case characters.
>> So now that we've figured out
how to shift a single character,
then all we have to do is scale that
up to go across the entire plaintext.
So the plaintext is a string.
Lucky for us, a string is really
just an array of characters,
so in order to access every character
of a string, all you have to do
is to use array notation.
Say I have a variable of type
string called "text='this is CS50.'"
>> Well, then, in order to
access each character,
all I have to do with
the variable text is
to say well, text at index zero, that
corresponds to capital T. Text at index
one corresponds to the lower case h.
Another useful function is
the string length function.
So passing in a string to
that function will return
an integer, the length of that string.
>> Now that we've talked about
all these different elements,
let's put them back together.
So return to either my pseudocode
code or your pseudocode
and go through and make sure that you
know how to do every single thing.
Getting the key using argc and argv,
turning the key into an integer, a
to i, prompting for plaintext,
getstring, and then iterating
over every character in
the plaintext string,
preserving the case of each character
and shifting that character by the key,
ensuring that you're
wrapping around the alphabet,
finally printing that ciphertext.
My name is Amila, and this was Caesar.