SPEAKER: Now that we've
created our dictionary,
it's time to implement check,
which will check whether a given
string is in our dictionary or not.
Check is going to be a
case insensitive function.
That means that whether or not
the word that you're checking
contains uppercase letters or lowercase
letters or a mixture there of,
it's going to return true as long
as any combination of those cases
is found in the dictionary.
Then finally, we're
going to let you assume
that the strings that you're passed in,
will only have alphabetical characters
or apostrophes.
So no need to worry about cases with
any numbers or other characters.
The premise of check is
that if the word exists,
then you'll be able to find it in
your dictionary data structure.
I'm going to follow the
same order as I did in load,
so we're going to talk about
linked lists and hashtables first.
And then, we'll talk about tries.
In a hashtable dictionary, which
bucket would the word be in?
Remember that.
A hashtable is simply an array of linked
lists where each element of the array
is a node pointer.
So then, once we know which
linked list to search,
we're going to use the
string case comparison
function to compare those two strings.
So how do we search that bucket
for our word or in other words,
traverse a linked list?
Well let's assume first,
that I've declared
a node pointer, called head, that points
to the very first node in a linked
list.
Then I declare another node
pointer, called cursor in this case,
that points to the very same node
that the head pointer points to.
Notice here, that when I
created the cursor pointer,
I didn't malloc any space.
That's because I'm
not making a new node,
I'm simply creating a
pointer that will point
to preexisting nodes in my linked list.
So then, we have a
loop that will execute
as long as the cursor is not null.
Within that loop, you have
space to do some process,
some repeated process on every single
node, whether it is change the value
or calculate something or in
this case, compare strings.
After you've done that,
then you can reassign cursor
to whatever that node is pointing to.
And then, continue your loop
until cursor points to null.
Now how do we traverse a try?
Well for each letter in
the input word, then we'll
go to the corresponding element
in children in that try.
If it's null, then that
means the word is misspelled.
But if it's not, then we
can move to the next letter
until we reach the
end of the input word.
Now even if we've successfully followed
every single letter down our try,
then that doesn't necessarily
mean that our input
word is a word in our dictionary.
The final step that we'll need to do
is to check whether the Boolean is
word is true or not.
If true, we can return true.
If false, then that's an invalid word.
Now that you know how to
traverse your data structure,
you can get to checking.