>> Zamyla Chan: Let's check your credit.
In this problem, we'll prompt the user
for an input of a credit card number.
Then we'll run that credit card
number to see if it's valid.
If so, we'll print the company
that that credit card belongs to.
Otherwise, we'll tell the user
that that card is invalid.
>> Let's jump right in with
prompting for user input.
The credit card number is
of data type long_long,
so the CS50 library function
get_long_long will be quite useful.
But this function ensures that
the user inputs any integer.
So any positive integers, negative
integers, or zero is all fine.
So up to you to further
validate whether or not
the user has given us a valid
credit card type number.
>> Now that we have a credit card
number from the user, then
we need to calculate the checksum.
So credit card checksums
are calculated as follows.
Starting from the second to last digit,
we multiply every other digit by 2.
Then we add those
products' digits together.
From that we add the
sum of the digits that
weren't multiplied by 2 to that
previous sum that we calculated.
Finally, if that number ends
in 0, then the number is valid.
>> Let's go through an example
and take this step by step.
So our first step is to start
from the second to last digit
and multiply every other digit by two.
Now, if I stored the credit card
number in a variable called CC number,
then modding that by 10 would
give me the very last digit.
So how might you access
the second to last digit?
>> OK, so once we've accessed
the second to last digit,
then we'll iterate through
multiplying every other digit by 2.
Once we have that, then
we'll take those products
and add those products' digits together.
So here I have single
digits, so that's fine.
But then once I get to my last
number-- 7 multiplied by 2--
I add the 1 and the 4 to give me 27.
From there, we add that product--
27-- to the sum of the digits that
weren't multiplied by 2.
>> So here I've highlighted all
of those numbers in orange.
Once we add those digits, then
we get our final checksum number.
So we validate it by making
sure that the last digit is 0.
If the checksum does not end in
0, then the credit card number
is definitely invalid.
Otherwise, let's go on to
check the company identifiers
and the credit card number length.
>> We've provided a list
of three companies,
along with that, the number of integers
that their credit card numbers have.
Then the first two digits that
those cards might start with.
So up to you to keep track of the
first two digits of the credit card
and the number of integers in that card.
And with that, you've
finished the problem.
My name is Zamyla, and this was Credit.