ZAMYLA CHAN: Let's play a game.
In the game of fifteen,
we have a tile set
that we allow the user
to move around the tiles
until the numbers are
arranged in the correct order.
How do we do this?
The game is a little involved.
So in fifteen.c, you'll find
a lot of distribution code.
In that distribution code, it accepts
and parses the command-line arguments,
creates the board, and
then enters the game play
by checking to see where the game is
won and exiting if it is, and otherwise,
getting input from the user to
see which tile should be moved,
and calling that function.
So what do we actually have to do?
Well, within fifteen.c, you'll
find calls to four functions--
init, draw, move, and won.
And that's our job to implement.
Init stands for initialize, where
we initialize the 2D integer
array that will represent our board.
Now, this board is going
to be of dimensions d,
given by the user, where that dimension
is less than the game's given maximum.
We've encountered 1D arrays
already, so what are 2D arrays?
Well, they're not all that different.
We can just represent
2D arrays as grids.
Here, I've initialized a
new 2D array called grid.
You'll see that I put two indicators
for the dimension, as opposed
to one in a one-dimensional array.
So I'm going to declare every
single element of this grid
explicitly, where grid 0, 0 is 8,
and grid 0, 1 is 7, grid 0, 2 is 6.
You'll see that the indicator
for the row comes first,
and then the index for
the column comes second.
So now proceeding to the next
row, then the first index
in all of my declarations
is going to be 1.
So indeed, we have grid at 1, 0
set as 5, grid at 1, 1 set as 4,
and grid at 1, 2 set to 3.
Moving on to the last row, I have grid
at 2, 0 equal to 2, and grid at 2,
1 equal to 1.
Now, in the physical version
of the game of fifteen,
it's actually made up of tiles, whereby
the player moves those tiles around
in order to move the tiles
into correct descending order.
So in our digital version
of the game of fifteen,
we also want a blank
space for that user.
So we're not going to
display a number there.
But knowing that this is an integer
grid, we have to put an integer there.
But we're not going to display it.
So it's up to you to choose which
one makes most sense to you.
So to recap, for initialize, we want
to initialize the board, a 2D integer
array, with the starting state
of the game of fifteen board,
where board at index i, j represents
the tile at row i and column j,
and the numbers for these tiles start
in descending order-- left to right, top
to bottom.
So what does the pseudocode look like?
Well, to iterate over the entire grid,
then for each row and each column,
we want to set the value for the tile.
It might look something like
this-- a nested for loop.
Here, integer i iterates
over the rows, and integer j
iterates over the columns.
And within that, we
set the tile's value.
Now, unfortunately, it's
not quite so simple.
In order for the game of fifteen
to be completely winnable,
then there are certain
cases with certain numbers
of tiles when you actually have to
swap the 2 tile with the 1 tile.
The rule is that whenever the
dimension, d, is even, you swap 2 and 1.
So in the case that we already
talked about with d being 3,
we don't need to worry about that.
But when d is 4, for
instance, then we actually
have to switch the 1 and the 2 tile.
So make sure you include a case in
order to check whether d is even or not.
I'll give you a hint.
Modulo might come in handy.
Now that we've initialized our board,
it's time to go on to drawing it.
Now, if we follow the same pattern as
we did when we initialized the board,
then we'll iterate over the board in the
same exact order as we initialized it.
So let's iterate over the rows
first, and then the columns,
and then print the tile's value.
Now, since this is a
visual game, we want
to make sure that the users can sort
of see where the tiles end and begin,
and when the rows end and begin.
So let's print a new line and
perhaps some other characters
to indicate when tiles
and rows begin and end.
We're almost done with
the draw function, which
will print the current
state of the board
whenever the draw function is called.
All that's left is to
ensure proper formatting.
So for this, we'd like
you to print a blank space
before any single-digit numbers.
That way, single-dingle numbers
and double-digit numbers
will look the same.
For this, all you have to do is
modify your original printf statement
for printing an integer, except
instead of a %i, let's add a %2i.
That way, we'll ensure
that a space is printed
before any single-digit numbers,
and no space before a double digit.
Then the very last thing
to do in this draw function
is to make sure that the user can
visually see where the blank tile is.
For this, we're representing
it with an underscore.
The board is a 2D array of integers.
And an underscore
definitely isn't an integer.
So how do you reconcile the two?
Well, I propose that as you're
iterating over your board
and printing those values,
you include a condition where
you make sure to print an underscore
on lieu of whatever other integer you
stored in that blank tile location.
So now that we've drawn our
board, it's time to move it.
In move, you want to
implement the functionality
where the user has already given you
the tile number, not the tile location.
So your first job is to
find that tile location.
Try to see if you can do this
in a nice, iterative manner.
So then next, we want to edit the
board array to move that tile,
but only if the move is legal.
A legal move in the game
of fifteen is to move
any tile that's above,
below, to the left,
or to the right of the blank tile.
So in this case, the 8, the 5, and
the 2 are all legal tiles to move,
but not the 7, because that
one's diagonal to the blank.
Once we found that, we swap
the tile and the blank tile.
So even though we searched
for that 8 tile before,
we're always going to
need that blank tile.
So I suggest that you keep
track of where the blank is
using two nicely named variables.
Great.
So now the user can
move any valid tiles.
The last thing to do is to check to
see whether they've won the game.
The fifteen.c file calls won.
And won returns true if the game
is won, and false otherwise.
The rule for the game
of 15 is that the game
is won when the tiles are in increasing
order left to right, top to bottom.
So how do we check this?
Well, let's iterate over the
board and check each value.
And if any value is incorrect,
then we'll return false.
And then the user has to
keep on playing the game.
But once we've checked all the
values, then we'll return true.
The user has won, and so
have you, because you've
completed the game of fifteen.
My name is Zamyla, and this was fifteen.