>> Let's get greedy.
In greedy, our job is to play
the role of a greedy cashier.
The user will tell us how
much change we owe them,
and then our job is to calculate
the minimum number of coins
that we can use to make
that amount of change.
>> Let's start with an example.
Say the user requires $0.32 back.
We could do this by giving
them 32 pennies, one cent each.
Or I could also use five coins-- by
giving them three dimes, $0.10 each,
and two pennies, $0.02 each.
But could we use even
fewer coins to make that?
>> The whole tactic in greedy--
to be a greedy cashier--
is to use the largest coin possible.
So whenever we have
quarters we'll use them.
And then once those run out,
we'll use dimes, $0.10 each.
Then nickels, 5 cents each, and
then down to pennies, one cent each.
By using the largest coin
possible whenever we can,
we ensure that we use the fewest number
of coins possible to make the change.
>> So let's walk this through.
The user needs $0.32.
So we ask ourselves,
can we use a quarter?
Well, yes we can.
So now we only know them
$0.07, and we used one coin.
>> Can we use another quarter?
Well, no.
$0.07 is less than $0.25, so we proceed
to the next largest coin available.
Dimes are $0.10, and
again, we can't use dimes.
Because dimes are worth $0.10, which
is more than the amount of change owed.
>> We go to nickels.
And, yes indeed, $0.05 is less than
$0.10-- so we can use a nickel.
So now we only owe the user $0.02,
and we've so far used two coins.
We can't use another nickel.
So then we proceed to the last coin at
our disposal, which are the pennies.
>> And can we use penny?
Well, yes-- and we end up using two
pennies for a total of four coins.
>> Once you're finished, the
program will look like this.
Once the user runs the
greedy program, they'll
be prompted to give the amount of
change in dollars that they're owed.
And then your program will output
the minimum amount of coins
that the greedy cashier would use
to make that amount of change.
>> So now let's break this
down into our subtasks.
First we're going to prompt our
user for an amount of change.
And, as with any user input, we want to
make sure that we validate that input
and ensure that we can use that
input for the rest of our program.
Then we're going to always
use the largest point possible
and keep track of the coins used.
And finally, print the final
number of coins that we used.
>> So let's talk about prompting.
The amount must make cents,
and this is in dollars.
And so for dollars, we're going
to use the float variable type.
Now whenever you ask a user for input,
you want to make sure that it's valid.
And so here we like to take advantage
of the do-while loop construct.
>> A do-while loop will execute the
body of the loop at least once.
So this comes in handy.
We know that we need to prompt the
user at least once for a float.
Now if that float is valid.
That's great.
We move on.
But if not, the loop will ensure
that we get a proper float
by repeating continuously until
the user gives us a valid value.
>> Now for the do-while
loop condition, we need
to consider what it means
to have an invalid float.
So for the context of
this problem, probably
it makes sense just to
accept positive values.
>> So moving on-- we've obtained a
value in dollars from the user.
But we're dealing with coins,
which are entirely in cents.
$1 is equivalent to 100 cents.
So a good thing to do is to
convert those values into cents.
>> Now when converting from a float
to an integer, so dollars to cents,
we want to make sure that we're careful
about floating-point imprecision.
So that means that-- say
my dollar value-- my float
value-- was an even $2, there still
may be some stray numbers in there.
So we want to make sure that not only
do we multiply by 100 to get the cents,
but we also round it off.
>> So now we have the amount
of change owed to the user.
We originally obtained it in dollars,
and now we've converted it to cents.
So now we can proceed with the heart of
the greedy algorithm, which is always
using the largest coin possible.
While we're doing this,
it's essential that we also
keep track of how many coins are
going to be returned to the user
as well as the remaining
change owed to the user.
>> The program will look
something like this.
After you get the amount of
dollars and convert that to cents,
then you'll enter a loop.
While quarters can be
used-- that is to say
while the amount of change owed to the
user is greater than or equal to $0.25,
you'll use a quarter.
>> Now what does using a quarter entail?
Well, one-- you'll increase the coin
count to be returned to the user.
And second you'll decrease the current
amount of change owed back to the user
by $0.25.
>> After repeating that until
quarters can no longer be used,
proceed to the next largest
coin-- in this case dimes, $0.10.
So you'll enter that loop until
you can no longer use dimes.
Then proceed to the next
largest coin, nickels.
After nickels can no longer be used,
use the remaining amount in pennies.
And finally, print the
number of coins used.
>> Another way that you can
approach the greedy problem
is to use the modulo approach.
Modulo is an operator
that returns the remainder
of the division between two numbers.
Say I had 50 mod 5.
Well, 5 is a factor of 50,
so the remainder will be 0.
50 mod 10-- well, 10 is also a factor
of 50, so the remainder is also 0.
50 mod 50-- well, any number mod itself
isn't going to have any remainder.
>> What about 50 mod 49?
Well, 49 only goes into 50 once.
So the remainder is going to be 1.
53 mod 50 is going to
give you a remainder of 3.
>> So how can we use modulo
and perhaps some division
to implement our greedy algorithm?
Well, we still want to stay true to the
heart of the greedy algorithm-- that
is using the largest coin possible.
>> So let's ask ourselves if we can use any
quarters to return $0.32 to the user.
Well, 32 mod 25 gives
us a remainder of $0.07.
So that tells us that we can definitely
use one quarter with $0.07 remaining.
>> Can we then use any dimes?
Well, no-- because $0.07 mod
$0.10 gives us a remainder of 7.
10 doesn't go into 7 at all.
>> Then can we use nickels?
Well $0.07 mod 5 cents
gives us two remaining.
And lastly, can we use any pennies?
2 mod 1 gives us 0,
which is ultimately what
we want because then that
means that we've returned
to the user all of the change owed.
>> So now you have two possible ways of
implementing the greedy algorithm--
one with loops and one with a
combination of modulo and division.
So finally, we just need to
print the final number of coins.
>> If I wanted to tell you that I had
3 pets and this value was hardcoded,
then I could just use a
simple print test statement.
But our value is actually
stored in a variable.
So how do you print the
values stored in variables?
>> For this we take
advantage of placeholders.
Say I had already declared
an initialized integer n.
Then later on if I wanted to print that
value, then I would write the string.
And instead of that value I would use
a placeholder for that integer-- %i.
Then after the string, I have a
comma, followed by the variable
that I want to print.
And later on, when it prints,
it'll print the value of n.
>> I could also use a placeholder
for a float, for instance.
If I wanted to tell you how
much cash I have in my pocket,
then I could say I have %f dollars.
And later on when it prints, then n will
take the place of that place holder.
I could also, for instance, use several
placeholders for several variables.
So as long as I list
them in order, then I
can tell you how many
dogs and cats I have.
>> Now we know how to prompt the
user for an amount of change,
ensure that that input
is valid, and then we
have two possible ways of implementing
the greedy algorithm of always using
the largest coin possible.
Because we've kept track of
how many coins we're using,
we can then print that value at the end,
telling the user how many coins they're
getting back.
>> My name is the Amayla, and this is CS50.