ZAMYLA CHAN: Hello, world.
My name is Zamyla.
And I will be your walk-through
lead for these CS50 problems.
In each walk-through, I'll go for
what's required for the problem,
I'll go over what the
list of to-dos are,
and I'll provide more of a high-level,
algorithmic way of getting started,
give you a few hints,
a few snippets of code.
And hopefully, you'll be well on
your way to completing the problem.
>> So for today, let's
talk about hello, where
we're going to write our
very first C program.
What we need to do is first
navigate to our workspace,
where we're going to create a
file and save it as hello.c.
I've already written
a bit of code already.
I've included the standard
io library, and then
I just created my main function.
>> What I'm going to do is I'm going
to write printf Hello, world!
with a backslash n for a nice,
new [INAUDIBLE] formatting,
and a semicolon to end.
After saving our program,
let's go to our terminal,
where we're going to compile it
by typing the command make hello.
It compiles correctly.
And so we can go ahead and run
our executable file ./hello.
>> And there we get Hello, world!
Hello, world!
My name is Zamyla, and this was hello.