ZAMYLA CHAN: In the
initials problem, we're
going to prompt the user for their
name and then print their initials.
To prompt for the name, we'll use the
get string function found in the CS 50
library, and you're allowed to
assume that this string will only
contain letters and spaces-- so no
numbers and no other characters.
Then, once you have the
string, you'll iterate through.
>> If, say, I was using
this program, then I
might type my name perfectly--
Zamyla Chan with a capital Z
in the beginning, a space, and then
a capital C to start my last name.
So you'd simply iterate
through the string,
getting the first character, and then
the first character after a space
and printing those out.
>> But say you had a slightly
sloppier user, Milo Banana, who
doesn't type in uppercase and
might include some extraneous space
characters.
Well, then when you
iterate through the string,
you'll have to check to make sure
that you're not printing out a space,
but rather, his proper
initials, capital M,
capital B. To print out capital letters,
you can use the toupper function.
And with that, you finished the problem.
>> My name is Z. C., and this was initials.