>> ZAMYLA CHAN: In the
initials problem, we're
going to prompt the user
for their name and then
print the initials from that name.
To prompt the user for the name,
we'll use the get_string function
found in the CS 50 library.
>> You're allowed to make
two assumptions-- one,
that the string will be comprised
of only letters and spaces-- so
no numbers, no other characters.
You're also allowed to
assume that there's only
going to be a single space
between letters, between names.
>> So once you have that string, then
let's go to print the initials.
In this example, say I
were to be a perfect user.
Then I'd type in my name with
a capital Z and a capital C,
with a single space in between.
So your program would
calculate the first letter
and then the first letter after
a space, and print out ZC.
>> But for instance, say Mile
Banana is at the keyboard.
Well, he might be a
little bit sloppier than I
am and only type in lowercase
letters and include an extra space
in front of his first name.
But your program should
have the same exact output,
with a capital MB without any spaces.
>> Finally, whenever you've
determined the characters to print,
make sure that you print them as
uppercase using the toupper function.
>> My name is ZC, and this was initials.