ZAMYLA CHAN: Let's start
by creating our dictionary.
For each word found in
the dictionary text file,
we'll want to store it in the
dictionary's data structure.
And it's up to us to create a
representation for our dictionary,
whether it be a linked
list, hash table, or try.
If you choose to implement
your dictionary as a try,
then you can fast forward
in this video, because we're
going to be talking about linked
lists and hash tables now.
Hash tables can be thought
of as an array of buckets,
where a hash function will
give us the bucket that a given
key or value belongs to.
Let's look at an example.
Over my years working with CS50, I've
accumulated a lot of CS50 Stress Balls.
So much so that I'm having
trouble organizing them all.
I've numbered them in the
order that I've received them.
So, in total I have
10 CS50 Stress Balls.
Now, I want to tidy up my room.
So I put them all inside of a box.
Say I wanted to reminisce
about my very first CS50 fair.
Then I would go to my
box of stress balls
and I would sift through to
find the ball with the number 1.
Now, I could be very lucky and I
could find this ball right away.
Or I could spend some time
sifting through this box
to find the right ball.
Instead, I decide to make this
process a little bit easier.
And instead of putting all of
my stress balls into one box,
I put them into two, one
for odds and one for evens.
So now I have a reliable
method of sorting my stress
balls into two groups.
So now, say I wanted to find
the stress ball numbered 1.
Then I would be able to
discard the evens box
and just look in the odds box.
And with half as many balls as
before, then it's more likely
that I'll find that ball a lot faster.
What I essentially did, here,
was create a hash table.
In this case, my hash table is small
with only two buckets, my two boxes.
And my hash function, in this case,
checks the number of the ball.
And if that number is
odd, then that means
that the ball belongs in the odd
box, and otherwise in the even box.
So, whenever I'm sorting my
stress balls or looking for it,
I know which box it'll belong to.
Now, I hate to break it to you, but I
have way more than just 10 CS50 Stress
Balls in my closet.
So, let's say I'm looking
at just my first 20.
Well then, I can do the same process
as before, and sort all of the odds
into the odd box and all of
the evens into the even box.
But now I'm faced with the
same problem as before.
With 10 stress balls
per box, it might get
a little bit more difficult to find
the ball that we're looking for.
So, I might decide that instead
of just having two boxes,
I'm going to sort my
stress balls into four.
With this organization, I have one box
for balls numbered 1 through 5, another
for 6 through 10, another for 11
through 15, and then my last box for 16
through 20.
So, here I have a nicely
balanced hash table.
By that, I mean that I have the same
number of keys-- or in this case,
stress balls-- per box-- bucket.
You can see how it might be unbalanced
if instead of having these four
boxes, like so, I had created
three boxes, one for balls 1
through 5, another for 6 through 10,
and then another for 11 through 20.
So what we've learned is that a hash
table is simply a collection, an array,
of buckets.
And the number of buckets that we have
can change, as does the hash function,
depending on what we're dealing with.
Now in this case, we don't have physical
boxes to sort our stress balls into.
What we're going to deal
with is linked lists.
A hash table is simply
an array of linked lists.
Now you'll see this slide pop up a lot,
because it's a really important concept
to remember.
Linked lists are comprised of nodes.
The first component of
the node is its value.
Now the data type of this value
depends on what kind of node
you're dealing with.
In the previous example
with my stress balls,
then the value would be an integer.
But in this case when we're
dealing with words, then
the value is going to be a different
type, most likely a char array.
The second component of a node
is a pointer to another node.
This is important
because in a linked list,
we have our first node,
which then contains a pointer
to the node following it, which contains
a pointer to the node after that,
so on and so forth, until the
very last node in the list
contains a pointer to null.
So when we're dealing
with linked lists, it's
very important not to lose any links.
So I find it very useful to
draw schematics like these,
or even physically take hold of
things and make sure that you
don't lose any links prematurely.
So how do we incorporate
linked lists into hash tables?
Well, as I said before, hash tables
are just arrays of linked lists.
So here, in this case, I
have an integer hash table.
So every node contains an integer
value as well as a node pointer.
And I have four buckets.
Try and figure out if you can see what
the hash function for this might be.
Now, say I have three values that I
want to insert into my hash table.
Then what I'll do is I'll take each
node at a time, hash the value,
figure out which bucket or
which linked list it belongs to,
and insert it there.
Now that we've got a nice
grasp of these concepts,
let's take a look at some code.
So how do we go about creating nodes?
Well, we'll start by allocating enough
space in memory to store our node.
To do that, we'll use
the malloc function.
Malloc will need to know how
many bytes to allocate in memory.
So then we'll use the size
of function to calculate
the size in bytes of a node.
Once we have that, malloc
will give us the pointer,
which indicates a spot in memory
where it's reserved for our char
array and a pointer to a node.
So the key takeaway here is that
whenever we're creating a node,
we actually just want to
malloc a node pointer.
So if, say I wanted to
create another node, node 2,
then I would do the same thing again.
Allocating another spot
in memory for that node.
Now I want to set the
values for these nodes.
So node 1 and node 2 are
actually node pointers.
So I'll use arrow notation in
order to access the word variable.
And then I can set those
two words, hello world.
These are just two independent nodes.
How do I link them?
Well, I'll simply access
the next variable for node 1
and point that to node 2.
Great.
So now we have a linked list of size 2.
Remember that a hash
table is simply an array
of linked lists, where each element
of the array is a node pointer.
So your hash table might
look something like this.
You define your struct for a node.
And then you create an
array of nodes, the same way
that you would create an array
of any other variable type.
Here, my hash table has 50 buckets.
But depending on the hash function you
decide, it could be a different number.
Now that we've created our
dictionary as a hash table,
then it's time to populate the
hash table with nodes containing
words found in the dictionary.
How do we do this?
Well, let's look at the fscanf function.
This piece of code will
take the dictionary file--
in this case it's called
file-- look for a string,
and then put that string
into a variable called word.
And it will execute this loop until the
end of the dictionary file is reached.
Now what goes inside of this loop?
Well, we know that for
every word that we scan,
we want to malloc a node for it.
Now whenever we create
a node, we always want
to check to make sure malloc succeeded.
But what happens if
you run out of memory?
Well, malloc will return null.
So whenever we make a
new node, you always
need to check to make sure
that the pointer to that node
doesn't return null.
If it does, then you need
to unload your dictionary
and return false so
that speller will quit.
But if it succeeds, then you
can proceed and copy that word
into your node by using
the function string copy.
OK.
So now we have a new node with a value
that we scanned in from the dictionary.
Let's go on and insert
that into a linked list.
Remember I said that
it's really important
to maintain all links
in your linked lists,
and make sure not to let go of any
links until you know it's safe.
Let's look at an incorrect
way of doing this.
Say I wanted to insert my new node
into the very beginning of my list
and put that first.
Well, if I have a node
pointer, called head, pointing
to the very first element in my
linked list, then I might say,
well, head now points to new node.
But this won't do because then
I lose the link to the A node.
And then I lose the entire list.
Let's look at a correct way to do this.
Knowing that we're inserting new
node into the very beginning,
and that becomes the
first value, then that
means that new node should point
to whichever node was previously
the first value in the list.
So let's point new node next to the
pointer that head's pointing to.
Now that we have two pointers
holding on to that A node,
we can safely reassign the
head pointer to new node.
And there we have a linked list.
So now we know how to take a word
from the dictionary and take that word
and put it into a node, and take that
node and put it into a linked list.
So next we need to
decide, well, how do we
know how to put which word
in to which linked list?
Because remember, a hash table is
simply an array of linked lists.
Well, how did we know which box
to put which stress ball in?
We used a hash function.
The hash function, in this
case, will take a string.
And from that string it
will calculate an index,
the index corresponding
to which bucket--
which element in the hash
table-- that word belongs to.
Now hash functions all
have to be deterministic.
What I mean by this, is that the same
value needs to map to the same bucket
every time.
So in the stress ball example, when
I had the number 1 stress ball,
I knew that with my hash
function every time it
would indicate that I'd have
to put it in the odd box.
So same with our spell checker.
Every single time that
I hash the word apple,
it should give me the very
same index, whether or not
I'm putting it into the dictionary for
the first time or checking it later.
Once you've made your hash function,
then you can hash your words.
The word that you want to hash is
contained within your new node, arrow,
word.
So hashing that will give you the index
of whichever bucket in your hash table
you should put that word in.
From there, you insert
into the linked list.
How do you do that?
Well, I've already given
you the tools to do so.
Knowing that a hash table is
simply an array of linked lists
and that each element of
an array is a node pointer,
pointing to the very first
node in that linked list.
Another way to represent the dictionary
data structure is with a try.
Now in tries, we're also going
to make them up with nodes.
But in this case, the nodes are
going to be different than the nodes
that we used in the hash table.
Every node for a try contains
an array of node pointers,
one for every single letter in the
alphabet and the apostrophe character.
Notice, here, how I included the
apostrophe character with a backslash
in front of it?
That way I allow the
apostrophe to parse correctly.
Now each element in that array
will point to another node.
And then if that is
null, then that means
that the letter that
that array belongs to
is not the next letter of any word
in any sequence in the dictionary.
Now just because a letter is
contained within the path of the word
doesn't mean that it's the end of
a valid word in the dictionary.
So every node will also
indicate whether it's
the last character of a
valid word in the dictionary.
So how do we represent this in a struct?
Well, we'll have our Boolean indicating
whether the node is a word or not.
And then I'll have my
array of node pointers.
In this case, I'm calling it children.
Finally, in order to keep track of
the top or the beginning of your try,
we're going to have another node
pointer, in this case, called root.
Scanning through the dictionary one word
at a time will iterate through the try
as follows.
Given that each element
in the children array
corresponds to a different
letter, we'll check the value
at the appropriate index of children.
Now, if that node is null, then
we'll malloc a new node for it
and have children at
that index point to it.
But if it's not null, then that
means we've already created the node.
So we can then move to that
node and continue the process.
Finally, once we reach the
end of the dictionary word,
we'll set the is word Boolean to true.
Let's go through an example, storing
fox into an empty dictionary.
The word fox begins with the letter f.
So for the letter f, we're
going to malloc a new node.
We're going to put this
at children on index 5.
That's because f is the
sixth letter of the alphabet.
So once we've done that, then
we proceed to the next letter.
Well, o comes after f.
So then from that f node, we'll
then access the corresponding node.
In this case, children at index 14.
And then we'll do the same thing for x.
Finally, here I indicate,
by shading the box
in green, that is word is set to true.
Now that we've loaded
fox into our dictionary,
let's go to the next valid
word in our dictionary, foo.
Now foo starts with the letter f.
We've already created a node for that.
So we don't need to create a new one.
We progress to the second
letter of this word, o.
And we've also already created an o
node that follows the first f node.
So then the only node that we need to
create is the last o in the word foo.
Remember that whenever you make a new
node, you have to allocate space for it
in memory and make sure to check
whether or not malloc returns null.
Now if it doesn't, and if you
succeed in creating a node,
then you've reached the end of the word.
So we can set is word to true.
Let's go on and enter another
word into our dictionary, dog.
I start with the letter d.
And d is the fourth
letter of the alphabet.
So then I access children at index 3.
From there, I create another
node for the letter o.
Notice that this node is going to be a
new node, because the letter o in dog
follows the letter d, not the
letter f as we previously created.
So then, completing the
chain for the word dog,
I then create another node for the
letter g, and then set is word to true.
Now let's say, the next word that
I need to enter is the word do.
Well, do is a substring of dog.
So I won't need to
create any more nodes.
What I'll need to do is navigate down
to that o and set is word to true.
So following this chain, you
could either end a valid word
at do or advance to dog.
And there you have it.
Whether or not you've implemented
as a hash table or a try
or perhaps a linked list,
you've created your dictionary.