ZAMYLA CHAN: It's a me, Zamyla.
Today in Mario, we're going to be
drawing the half pyramid for Mario
to climb up.
>> So let's talk about our
to-do's for this problem.
We're going to want
to prompt and validate
the user for a valid input of how
high they want Mario's pyramid to be.
And then, we're going to draw it.
So let's get started with prompting and
validating the user for their input.
>> We can make use of the
CS50 Library Function
get int that will ensure that
the user inputs an integer.
Any positive integers, negative
integers, number 0 are all fair game.
Otherwise, the user will be prompted to
retry until they input a valid integer.
Now although get int does
a lot of the work for us
in ensuring that the
user gives us an integer,
we still need to apply some
additional constraints on that.
After all, we can't have Mario climbing
a half pyramid of height negative 12.
>> In addition to that, the
problem specification
says that we can only
allow Mario to climb
a pyramid of heights between 0 and 23.
OK, so that means that we need
to continuously prompt the user
to give us a valid
number and only continue
once they've given us a valid height.
How do we do that?
>> Well, continuous processes give us
the idea of loops-- doing something
repetitively.
One loop in C as a while
loop that will continuously
execute the body of the loop as long as
the given condition evaluates to true.
As soon as that condition
evaluates to false,
the program will proceed to
whatever comes after that.
So while loops are one way of
ensuring that we continually
prompt the user for a valid input.
And once they give us a valid input,
we'll proceed to whatever comes next.
We know that we're going to ask
the user for input at least once.
So now we come to a sister of the
while loop, which is the do while loop.
>> Do while loops will execute the
body of the loop at least once.
So without checking the condition,
it will execute the body of the loop.
And then check the condition to see
whether it needs to repeat itself.
This comes in handy when
we're validating user input.
We know that we're going
to ask them at least once.
So a do while loop might
look something like this.
We have an integer n.
And inside of the do
while loop, we immediately
prompt the user for an integer.
If n is invalid, then we'll prompt them
again and again and again until they
give us that valid integer.
Finally, once n is a valid input, we'll
proceed to the rest of our program.
>> So let's go back to the spec and check
what the conditions for a valid input
is going to be.
The valid heights are going to
be between 0 and 23, inclusive.
So invalid heights are going to
be less than 0 or more than 23.
So remember to design
your condition carefully,
knowing that the condition
for the do while loop
should be while n is invalid.
Now this isn't going to be a
simple single Boolean expression.
We're going to have to combine
two different expressions
to make our whole condition.
>> So let's just look at a truth table I've
already given you the hint that we're
going to be dealing with two Booleans.
So here's a truth table where I
have two Booleans-- Boolean 1 and 2.
So we have the option to evaluate
bool1 and bool2 or bool1 or bool2.
And will only be true if both
Booleans evaluate to true, whereas all
or will be true as long as one of
the two Booleans evaluates to true.
OK, so take a moment, pause this
video and digest this truth table.
I'll be right here waiting.
When you come back, see
if you can piece together
a Boolean expression for your
condition of n being an invalid input.
>> So now that we have
valid user input, let's
go ahead and talk about how we
might draw the half pyramid.
Here in this simple text editor,
I've drawn a left aligned pyramid.
But we know that we need our
pyramid to be right aligned.
So how might I do this?
Well, I might try to push
everything to the side
by just putting a little
character in between.
And then, for the next
line, I'm going to put
some more characters to push it along,
and further-- so on and so forth--
until I have the right aligned pyramid.
So we do have a right align pyramid, but
it doesn't look so great with the dots.
But we still want to
maintain that nice spacing.
So I'm going to literally
insert some spaces.
>> Instead of three dots, I'll
put one, two, three spaces.
On the second line.
I'll put one, two spaces.
And on the penultimate
line, just one space.
And here I have a right aligned pyramid.
From doing the example in the text
editor, we have an idea for the pattern
that we'll use to draw the half pyramid.
For every row, what we did
is we type some spaces,
and then typed some
hashes, and then typed
the Enter key, which
is creating a new line.
So now that we have that, let's go
one step further and find a pattern.
>> So I'm going to say, for the
interest of this example,
we're dealing with a height of 8.
The first row is going to have two
hashes that follows seven spaces.
The second-- three hashes, six spaces.
Third row-- four hashes, five
spaces-- so on and so forth
until we get to the NTH row.
So then, I ask you for the NTH row,
how many hashes are we going to have
and how many spaces?
So it's up to you to figure out a
formula to represent how many hashes
and how many spaces are needed for
the NTH row when you have some height.
>> Now when you're figuring this out,
be careful how you're indexing.
What I mean by this is that
in everyday life all of us
start counting, usually by 1.
But in CS50 and in computer science
in general, we are 0 indexed.
So the first row would be
n of 0 as opposed to 1.
Be careful of this when you're
trying to figure out your pattern.
So now let's go back to how
we're going to draw our pyramid.
For every row, we're going to want to
print the spaces, print the hashes,
and then print a new line.
The hint here is the
word "for" every row.
In C, we have a construct
called a for loop,
which is comprised of an
initialization, a condition, an update,
and the body of the loop.
>> Say I wanted to say, hello
world, 50 times, my for loop
would look something like this.
I initialize my integer to 0.
The condition is that I is less than 50.
And then my update is just
incrementing I by one every time.
We can also use for loops
to iterate over things.
Notice here how we haven't
hard coded a number,
but rather placed the variable
height instead into the condition.
So what I'm doing here is I'm iterating
over every row of the pyramid.
I can do something for each
row inside the body of my loop.
>> What are we doing inside
the body of the loop?
Well, as we already said, we're printing
spaces and we're printing hashes
and we're printing a new line.
So my outer for loop
will look like this.
I iterate over every row
of the pyramid, using,
in this case, height as the variable
that stores the height of the pyramid.
Inside the body of that loop, I'm
going to print spaces repeatedly, print
the hashes repeatedly,
and then print a new line.
>> So now, using all of the concepts that
I've talked about in this walk-through,
you should be able to prompt the
user for input, validate that input,
and then draw the half pyramid.
>> My name is Zamyla, and this is CS50.