ZAMLYA CHAN: Let's save
the day with Recover.
In Recover, we provide
you with a memory card,
but we've accidentally deleted
all of the photos on it.
So your job is to recover
all of those JPEGs
so that we can see those pictures again.
Now, this might seem a little bit
daunting, especially because there's
no distribution code to work off of.
But grab your pen and paper, get
ready to draw some concepts out.
We're going to get this done.
Let's break this up
into manageable pieces.
So first, I'll talk about how
to open the memory card file.
Then we'll talk about how all JPEGs have
a distinct header, so we can use this
to find the beginning of a new JPEG.
Once you've done that, we'll open the
JPEG and write 512 bytes at a time
until we reach the end of that
JPEG and the beginning of another.
From there, we also need
to detect once we've
reached the end of the memory card.
First things first, let's
open the memory card file.
Using the fopen function,
you can do this.
But always remember to check
the return value of fopen
to ensure that you didn't
get some null value.
So once we open the file, let's
find the beginning of a JPEG.
Let's talk about JPEGs.
JPEGs are just sequences of
bytes, just like any other file.
What makes JPEGs extinct is that
they start with a distinct header.
The first three bytes are always
going to be the same for any JPEG,
and then there's a variety of options
for the last byte of that header.
You can find these details in
the problem's specification.
Now, JPEGs will be stored
side-to-side on the memory card,
and each block is 512 bytes.
This is going to be really important,
and we'll take advantage of this.
Throughout this problem
you might find it
useful to draw for yourself
your conception of a JPEG.
Here's just one of the ways
that I might draw it out.
Here every box represents 512 bytes.
So from the beginning
of the file, each block
is 512 bytes until I reach the
beginning of a JPEG, indicated
by a starred block.
From there you'll see that all
of the JPEGs follow continuously,
each 512 block at a time,
until I reach my end of file.
To read into our memory card,
we'll use the fread function, which
takes in four parameters-- first,
the pointer to a struct that
will contain the bytes
that you're reading;
second, the size of
each element to read,
and then the number of elements
to read; and finally, the file
pointer that you're reading from.
So how might we do this
for the memory card?
In the beginning, we'll start reading
in 512 blocks at a time, every time,
checking to see whether the first
four bytes indicate a JPEG header.
If not, we don't need to worry
about that block and we can proceed
to the next block of 512
bytes, checking that to see
if the header is that of a JPEG.
We continue this process until
we reach the first 512 block,
where the first four bytes
do indicate a JPEG header.
From there we know that
we found our first JPEG.
And from there on out,
all of the blocks,
side-by-side, will belong to JPEGs.
So we continue reading in,
building up this red JPEG,
in this case, until we
reach another block which
indicates the header for a JPEG.
So we know that the red JPEG has ended,
so we can close that and then start
a new one.
We continue this process,
reading 512 blocks at a time,
until we reach a block that indicates
the beginning of a new JPEG.
In which case, we close the previous
one and open the next, all the way
until we reach the end
of the memory card file.
So how do we read into the file?
Well, we've already talked
about the fread function,
but there are actually
two ways to do this.
We know that we want to
read in 512 bytes at a time,
but we could either read in one block of
512 bytes or 512 blocks one byte each.
Think about this for a second as we
talk about the rest of the problem,
and we'll come back to this slide later.
Let's go back to identifying JPEGs.
So we know, per the problem's
spec, that each JPEG
starts with a distinct header.
We can definitely check the
first three bytes easily,
but then when it comes
to the last byte, we
have so many options that writing a
condition for checking the header could
get pretty messy pretty quick.
So instead I propose that we
use a bitwise AND operator.
Say you've read in 512 bytes
into an array called buffer.
Well, then, you can use this code
to check whether the first four
bytes of buffer correspond to a JPEG.
If this code returns as
true, then you found a JPEG.
All right, so now that we found
the beginning of a JPEG, let's
talk about opening it.
The file names, per the
spec, need to be formatted
with three digits dot J-P-G, named in
the order in which they were found,
starting at zero.
So make sure that you're keeping track
of how many JPEGs you found thus far.
We'll use the sprintf function to
create a file name for our new JPEG.
Once we have that, we can
open, using fopen our new file,
making sure to include
writing permissions.
So once we've created the new
JPEG and opened that file,
then we need to write 512 bytes at
a time until a new JPEG is found.
How do we write those files?
In order to write the 512
bytes into our new file,
we'll use the fwrite function,
which takes in four parameters.
The first is a pointer to the struct
that contains the bytes that you're
reading from, then the
size and number of bytes,
and lastly, the file pointer
that you're writing to.
So in this case, the first parameter
will be where the 512 bytes are,
and then the out pointer will be our
new image file that we've just created.
So now we know how to
read into a memory card
and then how to write
into a JPEG image file.
So the next step is to figure
out, well, when do we stop?
Let's go back to the
representation of the memory card.
As we've discussed already, we'll
be reading 512 blocks at a time,
checking the header every time, until
we reach the start of a new JPEG.
Once we find that, we continue
building on 512 blocks at a time.
Let's fast forward to the end, where
we've already identified our last JPEG,
indicated by these pink blocks here.
We read in 512 bytes at
a time until we reach
the end of a file, which will
be less than 512 bytes long.
OK, so knowing that the very last
time that we try to read in 512 bytes,
we'll actually get
something shorter than that.
Then let's go back to our two
options for fread parameters.
When we're reading into
the memory card file,
either we could read in 512 blocks,
one by each, or, in the second case,
read in one block 512 bytes long.
So which one do we choose?
Well, fread will return how many
items of size size were read.
And ideally, this will return the number
that we asked for, until it doesn't.
So with that hint, try
to see if you can come up
with a condition for when we've
read in successfully our 512 bytes,
and then figure out a condition for
when we've reached the end of a file.
So let's bring all these pieces
together and make some pseudocode.
First we want to open
the memory card file.
Then, repeating until we've
reached the end of the card file,
we'll read 512 bytes in.
Then we'll ask whether we're
at the start of a new JPEG.
If we are, then we'll ask whether
we've already found a JPEG.
If we haven't, then that means that
we'll start our very first JPEG.
But if we already have
found a JPEG, then that
means that we need to close the
previous file and then open our new one.
Now, say we've read 512
bytes in and we haven't
reached the start of a new JPEG.
Well, then we ask ourselves, well,
have we already found a JPEG or not?
Because if we haven't, then
that means that we can simply
discard those 512 bytes and then
go to the start of our loop.
But if we have already
found a JPEG, then that
means that those 512 bytes belong
to the currently opened file.
Finally, once we've reached the end of
the memory card, we can exit the loop
and close any remaining files.
Now we're almost done.
The only thing that I ask is
that you take pen and paper
and draw out your own representation
and your own schematic of how the memory
card works and how those
blocks are laid out.
It's really important
to understand that,
and then writing the code
will be that much easier.
My name is Zamyla, and this was Recover.