ZAMYLA CHAN: Let's enlarge
our C repertoire with resize.
In resize, we're given an
infile bitmap, and our job
is to create an outfile file that scales
that bitmap by n, a user-given number.
OK, so let's break this down.
Today, we'll talk about how to open
the in-file, then create an outfile
and update that outfile's
header information.
Then we'll read into the infile
scan line, pixel by pixel,
resizing horizontally as we go.
It's going to be really
important to talk about padding
and understand exactly where to put
it in, and when to skip over it.
Finally, we'll talk about resizing
the file vertically, as well.
Now this is a lot to do, but luckily,
we have a good starting point,
because copy.c actually implements
a lot of this functionality.
Copy.c will open a file, update
the header information, then
it will read each scanline--
pixel by pixel from the infile--
and then write those pixels
into the outfile scanline.
So even though it doesn't
necessarily resize the file for us,
it's a great place to start.
So let's copy the code
from copy.c into resize.c.
All right, so now that
we've done that, we
want to update the outfile
header information.
So let's talk about bitmaps for a sec.
Bitmaps are simply an arrangement
of bytes, just like any other file
you'll encounter.
It's just a matter of how we
interpret this arrangement of bytes.
So take a peek inside
bmp.h for more information.
With a resize bitmap, we'll
have an updated header.
So what's changing in the header?
Well, our file size is
changing, our image size,
and of course, the width
and height of our file.
So what are those variables, exactly?
Well, within the bitmap
info header, we have
biWidth, which indicates
the width of the image
in pixels, not including padding.
More on padding in a sec.
Then we also have
biHeight, which represents
the height of the image in pixels.
Last in the bitmap in full
header we have the biSizeImage,
which is the total size of the image
in bytes, including pixels and padding.
Then we move to the bitmap file
header, where bfSize includes
the total size of the file in bytes.
So this includes pixels,
padding, and the headers.
So the bfSize can be
calculated by adding
the size of the image from
the bitmap info header,
and adding that to the size
of those headers in bytes.
OK, so when we scale the
image by n, what's changing?
Well, pretty obviously,
the width and the height
are both going to be scaled by n.
But what's happening to
biSizeImage, and bfSize?
Up to you to figure that out.
So now that we've dealt with the header,
let's start looking at the pixels.
So to read into the
infile scanline, copy.c
calls the function fread,
which takes in four parameters.
The first is a pointer to the struct
that will contain the bytes that you're
reading, and then the size
of each element to read,
then the number of those elements to
read, followed by the file pointer
that you want to read those from.
So now that we know how to read
into the scanline for the infile,
let's talk about resizing.
We're going to tackle
resizing horizontally first.
For this, essentially what we need
to do is for each pixel in the row,
we want to write it n times.
So for an n of 2, I'll go to my
orange pixel and write that twice.
Then proceed to my red
pixel, write that twice.
And finally my blue pixel,
I'll write twice, as well.
We call upon the function fwrite to
write those pixels into our outfile.
Fwrite takes in four
parameters-- the pointer
to the struct that contains
the bytes you're reading from,
then the size and number of
the elements you want to write,
and finally, the destination of
those files as a file pointer.
Now that we've talked about
resizing horizontally,
it's time to get to the padding.
In a bitmap, each pixel is
represented with three bytes.
Now the length of each
scanline of a bitmap
must be a multiple of four bytes.
Now, if the number of pixels
is not a multiple of four,
then we'll need to include padding,
where padding its just zeroes.
Here's an example where
I have four RGBtriples.
Each triple is comprised of three bytes.
So four triples, three bytes
each, that's equal to 12 bytes.
Because that's a multiple of
four, I don't need any padding.
Now say I have five
RGBtriples-- five triples times
three bytes each equals 15.
Not a multiple of four.
So I need to add one
unit of padding in order
to reach a multiple of four bytes.
If I have, say, six
triples, then I'll need
to add padding, as well, but a
different amount than last time.
In this case, two zeroes.
Finally, in this example, if I have
three triples, than 3 times 3 is 9.
So in order to bump it up, I need
to add three units of padding.
It's really important to
understand the concept of padding.
Don't worry about the equation,
I've provided it here,
and you can also find it in
the problem specification.
You'll notice that the padding takes
into account the size of an RGBtriple,
as well as the width of the image
in pixels, found in the bi header.
Because we're resizing the
outfile, the outfile and the infile
will have different widths.
So the padding will most
likely be different.
The other important fact to remember is
that padding isn't an RGBtriple-- so we
won't be f-reading, or f-writing it in.
Instead, to write padding,
will use the fputc function,
which takes in a character to write, and
then the file pointer to write it to.
So in this case, we'll be putting in
a 0 for the padding into our outfile.
Let's look at an example using
any n equals 2 for simplicity.
At the first pixel, we'll
resize horizontally,
so we'll write that
twice into the outfile.
Moving on to the second triple,
we'll also write that twice,
resizing horizontally.
Now you'll notice here that while
the infile requires padding,
the outfile doesn't.
The infile only has two pixels,
which results in six bytes--
so it needs two units of padding
to reach a multiple of four
bytes for the scanline.
Whereas, the outfile has
four triples, so that
results in a multiple of
four bytes for that scanline
without needing any padding.
The key takeaway here
is that the padding
may very well be different
from the infile to the outfile.
Looking back to the
equation for padding,
we know that this
depends on the biWidth.
But recall from earlier, we
know that biWidth is going
to be changing from the old to the new.
So perhaps we need to
calculate how the padding is
going to change, but also keep track
of both the old and the new padding.
With that said, let's go
back to some pseudocode code.
Now this is pseudocode code just
for resizing horizontally-- it's
not going to be the final
algorithm for your entire problem.
But to resize horizontally for each
row, and for each pixel in the row,
we want to write to the outfile n times.
Then we want to write the outfiles
padding, once we finish that row.
But then skip over the
infiles padding so that we
reach the next row in the infile.
Try to see if you can implement resize
by simply stretching by n horizontally
first.
Then we can move on to
resizing vertically.
In resize, every pixel
is repeated n times.
That's the horizontal
resizing component.
But then every row is
also repeated n times.
So say I have an n of
three, and a single pixel.
Than that pixel is going to be
repeated three times in a row,
then that row is going to be
repeated three times, as well.
All right, so now let's move on to
a more complex example with more
than one pixel needed to resize.
I'll go to my first pixel and write
that twice, then go to the next,
write that twice, and then
the third, write that twice.
We've already achieved this
by resizing horizontally.
Resizing vertically entails
repeating that process another time,
so that we've repeated the row twice.
Only then will we move on to
the next row in the infile,
and repeat that same process.
There are two overarching methods
in which you can resize vertically,
and even within those methods, there
are multiple options for implementation.
So the first type of
method is a rewrite method,
in which you remember the pixels
that need to be written in the array,
and then write that array
as many times as needed.
Or there's the recopy
method, in which you go back
to the start of the original scanline,
and recopy that line as necessary.
I've mentioned a couple times
now seeking back or skipping
forward padding, lines, et cetera.
What I mean by this, is that we need
to move the file position indicator.
The file position
indicator is essentially
a cursor-- whenever
you fread into a file,
there is a cursor that keeps track
of where you are in that file.
If you ever want to
move that, then you call
upon fseek-- which takes in the
file pointer that you're seeking in,
the number of bytes that you
want to move the cursor, and then
finally, whether or not you want to
move relative to the current position
in the file, the beginning
of the file, or the end.
Now that you're equipped
with fseek, we can
talk about pseudocode
for the rewrite method.
Now remember that even
within the rewrite method,
there are multiple
ways to implement this.
So your pseudocode in
your implementation
might very well be different than mine,
and that's OK-- as long as it works,
and the basic premise is the same.
That for each row, we're going
to make a copy of the array
that we want to write, then for n times,
we'll write that array to the outfile,
and write the outfile padding.
Once we're done, we'll fseek
over the infile padding,
and then repeat for the next row.
Now we come to the recopy method.
In the recopy method, the infile cursor
starts at the beginning of a row.
Then for n minus 1 times, we'll want
to write the pixel scaling horizontally
to the outfile, and adding the
padding to the outfile as necessary.
Then once we've written that,
we'll send the infile cursor back
to the beginning of the row,
and repeat that process.
After we've done that n minus 1 times,
then we'll write the pixels once more,
scaling horizontally, adding
padding to the outfile.
Only then will we skip over the infile
padding, bringing us to the next row,
ready to repeat the process.
We're in the homestretch-- so let's just
wrap up and summarize, and make sure
that we're on the same page.
We want to open the infile
and create an outfile,
updating the outfile's header
information appropriately,
and keeping track of whichever
variables we need to from the infile.
Then, we'll read into
that infile scanline pixel
by pixel, resizing horizontally,
remembering to add padding,
and resizing vertically.
Now, I admit, my own code
didn't work perfectly
the first time that I tried resize.
And yours might not, either.
So if that happens, make
sure to put pen to paper,
draw out your pixels-- perhaps
a simple smiley, or just a box--
and follow through your own code
to make sure that the logic works.
And you might find your bug that way.
Good luck.
My name is Zamyla and this was resize.