ZAMYLA CHAN: Let's scale
things up with resize.
In resize, the user will
provide us with a float
by which they want to scale their infile
and the name for an outfile image.
It's up to us to parse that float
input, update the outfile's header
information, and then resize
our bitmap accordingly,
either making it smaller
or larger than before.
If we look at the
distribution code, then we'll
see that the implementation
of copy.c satisfies
a lot of similar functionalities
to that of resize.
copy.c will parse an integer
input, then open your infile
and outfile, updating the header
information for your outfile
and reading into the
infile scanline pixel
by pixel, writing those
pixels into the output file.
So perhaps our first step would
be to copy copy.c into resize.c.
But we need to parse
floats not integers.
So check out the sscanf
function and the atof function.
Also make sure to check
out corner cases, perhaps
taking a peek into CS50's own get
float function for more hints.
Then we need to update the
outfile's header information.
Now, bitmaps are simply an arrangement
of bytes just like any other file.
It's just a matter of how we
interpret this arrangement.
So take a look into bmp.h
for some documentation.
Essentially whenever
we have a new bitmap,
we'll need to update
the header information.
So what's changing when we're
scaling up or scaling down?
Well, the file size is going to change
as does the image size, the width,
and the height of our bitmap.
In the bitmap info header,
we have the biWidth,
which includes the width of the
image in pixels not including
padding, and the biHeight, the
height of the image in pixels.
We also have the biSizeImage, which is
the total size of the image in bytes
including the pixels and the padding.
Moving to the bitmap
file header, we have
bfSize which contains the total
size of the file in bytes.
So that includes pixels,
padding, and the headers.
So of these values, what's changing
when we scale our bitmap up or down
by a factor of f?
Well, biWidth and biHeight
will definitely scale by f.
So figure out how biSizeImage and
bfSize are also going to change.
Now that we've updated the outfile's
header information, let's talk
about resizing horizontally.
So say the user gave us a float of 2.
Well then, the algorithm
would be pretty simple.
For each pixel in the row, we
would write that pixel f times
into the outfile row.
Now what if instead of a whole number
float, the user gives us 1.5 or 0.5?
Well, it's impossible to write
a pixel a fraction of a time.
So let's adjust our thinking.
Instead, how about for
each pixel in the row,
we simply write the corresponding
pixel from the old row?
It would look something like this.
Here I have the same
three pixels as before.
Now we know that we
need to scale by 1.5.
So we know that the outfile row is
going to have four pixels in it.
So for each one of those
four pixels in the outfile,
I figure out what the
corresponding pixel is.
So see if you can figure out
what pattern I'm using here.
I'll use the same pattern
for a float input of 0.5.
With three pixels in
the original row, I'll
calculate that I'll need two
pixels in my outfile row.
So I'll calculate the
corresponding pixel as follows.
All right, so now that we've
figured out that pattern,
let's talk about the two
functions that we'll need to use.
To read into the file, we'll
use the fread function.
And then to write the
files, we'll use fwrite.
So the next thing that we
need to talk about is padding.
In a bitmap, every pixel
is three bytes long.
Now, a requirement for the bitmap image
is that the length of each scanline
must be a multiple of four bytes.
So if the number of pixels
is not a multiple of four,
then we'll need to add padding
where padding is just a single zero
character.
In this example, I have
4 pixels in my row.
Now, with 4 pixels 3 bytes
each, that equates to 12 bytes.
So I won't need to add any padding.
But instead, if I had 5 triples, then
5 times 3 is 15, not a multiple of 4.
So I'd need to add one
single padding character.
Then if I had six RGBtriples,
I'd add 2 characters of padding.
Finally, with 3 RGBtriples,
I'd add 3 units of padding.
I've included the
equation for padding here.
And it can also be found in
the problem specification.
Notice how padding depends
on width of the bitmap
and the size of an RGBtriple.
Now the size of the RGBtriple
is going to be constant.
So the only thing that might be
changing is the width of the bitmap.
So if the outfile and infile
have different widths,
then they may have a
different amount of padding.
Remember our discussion
about bitmap headers
where we calculated how the
old header information might
change for the outfile.
Well, because the padding is going
to be different for the infile
and the outfile, then we may also
need to keep track of that as well.
Now, why do we keep track of
both the old and the new padding?
Well, we'll need the old
padding because we'll
want to skip over the padding
in the infile using fseek.
And then we need to know how much
padding to add into the outfile.
And we'll use fputc to
put those characters in.
Now that we have a
firm grasp on padding,
we can resize our entire image.
So once we figure out which row should
be written, then let's seek to that,
draw the pixels into the outfile
and write the outfile's padding.
With that, we've resized our image.
My name is Zamyla.
And this was resize.