ZAMYLA CHAN: Let's find
the needle in the haystack.
Today in find.c we're going to
help implement a program that
prompts the user for
numbers to fill the haystack
and then searches the
haystack for a needle.
Now, find.c calls sort and
search, which are both functions
to find in helpers.c.
It's actually helpers.c
where we're going
to be doing our programming today.
So what do we have to do?
Well, first we need to
implement search, which
is a function that returns true if
the value is found in the haystack
and false otherwise.
And then we also have to do sort,
which sorts the values in the array
in incrementing order.
So first let's talk about search.
If you look at the
distribution code in helpers.c
you'll find a preexisting
linear search implementation
but we know that we can
do much better than this.
Linear search is in O(n) time,
which means that it's quite slow.
Instead of slowly iterating over
every element of the list up until n,
let's talk about binary search.
Now, linear search can search any
list, whereas binary search requires
that the list is sorted already.
But as long as you have a sorted list
then binary search operates in O(log n)
time, which is quite efficient.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here I've populated an integer array
of size nine with nine integers
and let's say we're
looking for the number 17.
Now in this example, if we
were to do a linear search
then it would take us 7 checks starting
from index 0 all the way till index 7
to find that number.
So let's see how we can implement
this using binary search
and find that needle a lot faster.
In binary search we start by
looking at the whole array.
So from the left side of the array to
the right side, we look at the entirety
and find the middle.
In this case, the
middle is that index 4.
The value is 10.
So the assumption under binary
search of the list is sorted.
So while 10 is not 17 and
because the list is sorted,
we know that we don't need to look at
the left half of the array anymore.
So similar to the way
that we just throw aside
one half of the phone book in
the beginning of this course,
we can just move our left
bound all the way to the middle
but we've already checked the middle so
we can get a little bit more efficient
and say, well since we've
already checked the middle
we know that's not part of the
array that we're looking for
so let's push they're bound to
just beyond where the middle was.
So now we have our left bound at index
5 and our right bound stays the same.
Let's calculate the middle and
we find, truncating the integer,
that the middle is at index 6.
So we check that value there, 16.
16 is not 17, in fact
it's less than 17, which
means that we can discard the left half
again and just look at the right side.
So then we move our left bound all the
way to index 7 and the right bounds
stays at 8.
Calculating the middle between
7 and 8 brings us to 7.
We check that value and
indeed we found our needle.
So let's talk about some
pseudocode for this.
Essentially, while
the length of the list
is greater than zero, that is
we still have things to look at,
we want to look at
the middle of the list
and if that middle is our needle if
the number is found then that's great
and we can return true.
Otherwise we want to either
search left or search right
depending on whether the number is
higher or lower than our needle.
And then finally, if
we've executed all of that
and we don't have any
more list remaining then
that means that we
return false because that
means that the needle is definitely
not in that particular haystack.
Congratulations.
You've implemented a fast search,
and now we can move on to sort.