ZAMYLA CHAN: Our challenge for sort
is to implement a sort in O of n time.
How might we do this?
Well, counting sort is one such example.
Counting sort will use key
values as indices for an array
and then uses that array to determine
the positions for the final array.
Now, counting sort does
depend on the assumption
that we have a known and
finite range of numbers
and that that range
isn't terribly large.
So counting sort ultimately
takes place in big O of n
plus k time, which resolves to O of n.
Let's look at an example.
Here I have an array of five integers.
And I know that my random integer
generator only generates numbers
from 0 all the way to 6, inclusive.
So I generate a counting
array, which will
count the number of entries for every
single integer within this range.
So I start at the very
first element of this array.
And I have the number 3.
So then I go to index 3 of my
counting array, and then I put a 1
there at that element.
I then go to the next element in
my array, 6, so I go to index 6
and I put a 1 there.
Progressing to the third element
of the array, I have the number 1.
So following this pattern, I go to index
number 1 and I increment the count.
So then, when I get to the fourth
element and I have the number 1,
I go to index 1 and I
simply increment the count,
indicating that so far I've
found two ones in my array.
So finally, after we
increment the count at 3,
we have enough information
in this counting array
to be able to fill in our original
array in incrementing order.
But I'll leave that to
you to figure that out.
My name is Zamyla, and this was fun.