ZAMYLA CHAN: Congratulations.
You've implemented a fast binary search.
And now we can move on to sort.
In the sort, you have the
option of implementing
a selection sort or a bubble sort.
So let's look at selection sort first.
In selection sort, we start by
going to the beginning of the array,
and then following through to
replace the beginning of the array
with the minimum value found.
How does that work?
Let's go through this example.
In this example, I have a
short list of five integers.
We're going to start by replacing
index 0 with the minimum value
that we find in this array.
So knowing that I start at 0, I'm
going to put my i index there.
Then I'm going to look
at the rest of the list.
So starting at index
1, I have the value 5.
Now, I haven't looked at any
other values in this array.
So for right now, let's say that
this value 5 is the minimum.
Then we progress to index 2, where
the value 2 there is less than 5.
So that becomes where
the new minimum is.
Progressing to index 3, we
find that 1 is less than 2.
So then that becomes the
location of the new minimum.
Going to index 4, we find that,
well, 4 is greater than 1.
So when we were at index 3,
we actually found the minimum.
So then now that we found that,
we switch those two values
from the beginning to
where we found the minimum.
So now we have an
array that's definitely
sorted for the very first value,
but not for the remaining four.
So then we advance our i indicator
for the remaining four in the list.
We don't need to worry
about that first value
because we know that
it's the minimum value.
So then we do the same
process as before,
where we search the
remaining three elements
in that list for the minimum value.
In this case, we find that it's actually
the first one we checked, at index 2.
So then what we do is we
switch the 2 with the 5.
So now the first two elements
of the list are sorted.
And now we look at the remaining three.
For the remaining three, we find
that the minimum is, well, 3.
And so we switch that with the
5, and continue that process
until we have a completely sorted list.
Now that we've gone through an example,
let's look at what the pseudocode looks
like.
So for i equals 0 to n minus 2--
that is, from the very first element
all the way to the penultimate one--
that is, not the last one, but the one
right before that-- we want to find
the smallest element from i plus 1
to n minus 1-- so from the
second element of the array
all the way to the end.
From there, I exchange the
smallest element with the element
that I had at i.
Now, by incrementing i
every time, essentially what
we do is we make sure that in order from
the beginning all the way to the end,
we find the minimum value of the array.
And that way, we have an array
sorted in incremental order.
We've finished talking about selection
sort, so let's talk about bubble sort.
In bubble sort, we iterate over a
list, comparing adjacent elements.
Now, if those elements are in the
wrong order, then we swap them.
This way, the largest element
will sort of bubble to the end.
That's how it gets its name.
And then we repeat
that for the whole list
until no elements have been swapped.
Then we consider the list
as successfully sorted.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here in my five-element
array, we're going
to start at the beginning
at index 0 and index 1.
Comparing these, I see that the
3 and 5 are, in fact, in order.
3 is less than 5.
So then I proceed to
compare index 1 and 2.
Now, 5 and 2 are out of order.
So I'm going to swap those.
And then I compare 2 and 3.
5 is greater than 1,
so I swap those again.
And then continuing on, I swap 5 and 4.
So you see how 5 started out at the
second element, and now is at the end,
being the largest element in the list.
Now that 5's bubbled through, I go
back to the beginning of my list.
I look at indices 0 and 1, and
find that 3 is out of order
because it's greater than 2.
So I swap those, and then continue on.
3 then bubbles through
to element 2, but find
that when we advance to comparing 3
and 4, those are actually in order.
So the 3 bubbled its way, but
not all the way to the end.
Now that 5's bubbled its
way to the end of the list,
we go back to the beginning again.
So we compare indices 0 and 1,
and find that 3 is larger than 2.
It's out of order.
So we swap those.
Then proceeding on, we compare 3 and 1.
And 3 is larger than 1,
so we swap that again.
So so far, 3's bubbled its way
from the beginning all the way
to the middle of the list.
But 3 isn't greater than 4, so
we actually don't swap those.
We don't need to make one last
comparison because 5 already
bubbled its way to the end of
the list in the first iteration.
So we can just go to
the beginning again.
We look at index 0 and index 1.
And we swap 2 and 1, and then proceed.
And we don't need to swap 2 and 3.
So then 3 is set.
Then comparing 1 and 2,
no swaps need to be made.
So then that means that we
finished sorting our list.
That was bubble sort.
And we already talked
about selection sort.
So there you have it.
Now you can sort an array
and do a binary search on it.
My name is Zamyla, and this was find.