How many words can a
spell checker check?
Well, let's find out with Speller.
Let's dive right into
the distribution code.
Speller.c will call load
on a dictionary file
and put it by the user,
where the dictionary contains
valid words, one per line.
Then, it calls check on
each word in a text file
that the user provided and prints
all of the misspelled words found
in that file.
Then, it calls size to determine the
number of words in the dictionary.
And finally, calls unload to
free up all of the memory used
while doing this process.
Our job is to implement the
four functions in dictionary.c.
Load, which loads the dictionary into
a data structure that we've created.
Check, which then checks
that data structure to see
if a given word is in the dictionary.
Size, which returns the number
of words in the dictionary.
And finally, unload, which frees
the dictionary from memory.