SPEAKER: Now that we've created
our dictionary data structure,
it's time to free up all of that memory
that we had previously allocated.
So how does one free a linked list?
It might look something like this.
Here I follow the same convention
that I've used throughout the walk
through where the node
pointer, called head,
refers to the very first
node in a linked list.
The code to free a linked list
might look something like this.
Here I assign a new node
pointer, called cursor, to head.
Remember that following the
convention of this walk through,
I've used head to refer to the node
pointer that points to the very
first element in a linked list.
For your hashtable, it might
be named something different.
Then I enter a loop that advances
as long as the cursor is not null.
Within that, I create a temporary node
pointer, initially pointing to cursor.
I advance the cursor and then
free that temporary node pointer.
What does that look like?
Well I leave it to you to
follow through this example,
erasing and creating arrows as necessary
to see how this method of freeing
will ensure that no
node is left un-freed.
If instead of a
hashtable or linked list,
you've decided to implement
your dictionary as a try,
then you'll unload from
the bottom to the top.
What I mean by this is that you can
travel to the lowest possible node,
from there you can free all
of those pointers and children
because you know they're not
linking to anything else.
From there, you can then
go up to the parent node
and backtrack upwards that way, freeing
all of the elements in each children
array until you hit the root node.
If you get stuck, remember
to take pen to paper
and draw out your try data
structure in whichever
schematic makes most sense to you.
And there, you can ensure that following
your code, you free all of the nodes
that you've ever created.
If you've chosen to go with
a try for a data structure,
then I challenge you to look at
recursion for an elegant implementation
of the unload function.
Finally, whether or not you've
chosen a hashtable or a try,
make sure to run
valgrind, which will check
to make sure that all of the memory
that you've allocated in your program,
you've also freed by the end.
If valgrind gives you the
OK, then you're good to go
and you've successfully
unloaded your dictionary.
My last couple tips to you
before you go out and code,
is to try make it easier
on yourself to debug.
Pass in a smaller dictionary
to speller instead.
By default, speller will run
with the large dictionary file.
But also, try passing
in the small dictionary
file provided in the distribution code.
Or you can even make your own
dictionary and your own input text file.
Perhaps, use the words that we talked
about today, fox, food, dog, and do.
Finally, pen and paper are
going to be your best friend.
Try drawing out your
dictionary as you create it,
load it, check it, and finally, unload.
My name is Zamyla, and this was speller.