>> Zamyla Chan: Let's step up our
game with the vigenere cipher.
The vigenere cipher is
very similar to Caesar,
except in Caesar we passed in
a single integer as our key.
In vigenere we're going
to pass in a keyword.
So, if I wanted to shift the
ciphertext this is CS 50 by ohai,
then that means that each letter in
ohai is going to serve as the key,
and I'm going to cycle over
that keyword for my shift
making the ciphertext
a lot harder to decode.
>> What does it mean to
shift by the keyword?
Well, the keyword is a string
where every letter corresponds
to some integer shift.
So, the o corresponds to a key of 14,
h to a key of 7, a has a key of 0,
so that wouldn't change anything,
and then i has a key of 8.
>> Say I ran vigenere A with the
plain text this is CS50 well,
that would simply give
me an unchanged string.
Notice that this is equivalent to
running Caesar with a key of zero.
In fact, running vigenere
with any single character
would be equivalent to running
Caesar with that same integer.
>> All right, so, since
they are so similar I'd
actually recommend that if you
want you can just copy your Caesar
code into your vigenere code.
Things will change,
but at least you have
some backbone that you can work with.
Because the TODOs are the same we want
to get the key, get the plain text,
encipher that plain text,
and then print that out.
>> Just like Caesar the key is going to
be passed in as the second command line
argument contained in argv index
1, but it's different this time
because it must be alphabetical.
So, we need to iterate over every
single character in that key
that the user passed in, and ensure
that every character is alphabetic
in order to continue.
>> Once we've done that, then we
can get the string from the user,
just as we did before.
And now, we come to the heart
of the problem for vigenere,
which is just like Caesar, how to
figure out the enciphering pattern
and equation, and encipher
the entire plaintext.
>> So, you'll notice that the
equation for the vigenere shift
is very similar to the Caesar one.
The only difference is that
instead of a single variable k
before, now k has a subscript,
indicating the jth letter of the key.
>> Let's walk through an example.
Say you wanted to pass a secret
message onto your crush, I like you.
Well, for your key you
choose something that your
know crush knows that you like, pandas.
All right, so how do we shift this?
>> Well, we have our plaintext index.
That's at the first letter and
so is the index for our key
which is at the p, the first
letter in our panda word.
So, shifting I by p gives us x,
then we advance the plaintext index.
This gets us to a space.
Now, the space character
is non alphabetic,
so that means that, that just
transfers right over to the ciphertext,
we put a space there, and we don't
advance the index for our key.
So, we're still at p at this point.
>> We advance to the next
index in our plaintext.
And now, because that is
a letter, the lowercase l,
we shift that by the
next index in our key.
Which is a, which is a zero
shift so that just becomes
an l in our ciphertext.
Then, we advance both the plaintext, and
the key index because it's alphabetic.
So then we continue that
until we get to the e in like.
>> All right, so you'll notice at this
point that, in terms of our key index,
we've reached the end of
the panda word, so what
happens when we get to the next
alphabetic letter in the plaintext?
Well, all that happens is we
wrap around to the beginning,
to the first index of our key.
So, then we shift that
y by p to give us n.
And then, we continue finishing encoding
our plaintext to get x lvne noh.
>> From this example, I
showed that we only advance
to the next letter in the keyword
if the character in plain text
is a letter so the isalpha
function will come in handy here.
And, just as in Caesar, we want to
preserve the case, isupper and islower.
So, add this little bit
in into your pseudocode.
>> So how do we figure out the key shifts?
Well, if you recall our discussion
on alphabetical indices in the Caesar
problem, it's very similar.
>> Where A corresponds to an ASCII
value of 65 but a shift of 0,
and then the last letter
in the alphabet, Z,
corresponds to a shift of 25.
You'll notice that the shift
is identical whether or not
the letter is upper case or lower case.
>> OK, so now that you
know how to figure out
the numerical shift that
corresponds to a single character
let's go back to our equation.
Because we have two different
subscripts here, i and j,
that's a hint that we want to keep track
of both our position in the plaintext
as well as our position in the keyword,
so those are two separate variables
that we want to keep a hold of.
>> Now, the position in our plaintext
is going to increase every time,
so that's going to be a
bit more straight forward
as opposed to the position the keyword,
which we know has to wrap around,
and sometimes increment,
sometimes stay the same.
So, how do we implement
the functionality
to wrap around the
index for the keyword?
>> I'm going to use the count off example.
Counting off is a popular way
to split people into groups.
Say I had 5 people and I wanted to
split them up into three groups,
well then I would start by counting off.
The first person would
say I'm team number one,
the next person would be team number
two, the third person team number
three.
Now, I only want three groups so
the fourth person would actually
start at the beginning and say,
well, I'm team number one as well,
and the next person
would be team number two.
And, from there, they can then
separate into their groups.
>> So, how might I use modulo
to help me implement
this count off wrap around function?
Well, the first person
number 1, mod 3 gives us 1.
2 mod 3 gives us 2,
and 3 mod 3 gives us 0.
>> The fourth person, number 4, mod 3
gives us 1, and then 5 mod 3 gives us 2.
So, you will notice that even though
the number of people that I have
increases, and is above
3, since I'm modding by 3
I always get numbers 0, 1, and 2.
I never get larger than 3.
So then, even if I had 10
people, then all of those people
would still be within groups 1, 2, or 0.
>> So, now we know that if we have a group
of 5 and we mod all of those by 3,
then we're never going to
exceed groups 0, 1, or 2.
So, we're never going to get a group
number that's equal to 3 or above.
So, even if I add five more
people, then all of them
would still be assigned to groups
0, 1, or 2 because I'm modding by 3.
I'm never going to exceed that cap.
>> OK, so let's see if we can apply
this concept of using modulo
to wrap around the
group numbers and apply
it to vigenere where we want
to use modulo to wrap around
the index for the keyword.
Even though we're incrementing
the index we always
want to make sure that we always
wrap around to the very beginning
never exceeding the
length of the string.
>> OK, so I know it might be
a little bit overwhelming.
There's a lot more to do in this p set.
So, make sure that you write out
a good pseudocode for yourself
that you understand and
that gets the job done.
Try and address every
single line independently
figuring out all the little
small pieces of the puzzle
before putting it together.
>> Make sure that you can get
the key from the command line
and ensure that it's alphabetic,
get the plain text from the user,
and then in enciphering, make sure you
know how to encipher a single letter,
and then progress to the whole string
with all of the wrap around functions.
Finally, you can print the ciphertext.
>> My name is a Zamyla,
and this was vigenere.