SPEAKER 1: Let's talk about water.
In this problem, we ask the user to tell
us how long in minutes their shower was
and then we calculate the equivalent
number of bottles of water
that their shower used.
>> So what are our to-do's
for this problem?
First, we're going to want
to prompt and then validate
the input that the user gives us.
Once we ensure that we
have valid user input,
we're going to calculate the
equivalent number of bottles of water
that the user had during
their shower, and then we're
going to tell them by
printing out that number.
>> So let's tackle our first
task, prompting and validating
the user input.
For this we've written a
function for you called
get_int located in the CS50 Library.
get_int ensures that the user inputs
an integer, so any positive numbers,
negative numbers, or
zero are all accepted.
But if the user inputs anything else,
so any combination of letters or numbers
or decimal numbers, then the
user will be prompted to retry
and the function won't accept anything
until the user gives them an integer.
>> So how do we use get_int?
If you open your workspace and
create a file named integer.c let's
type the following.
Hashtag include cs50.h.
This is necessary because get_int
is a cs50 library function,
so we must hashtag include
its declaration in order
to use the function.
And then in my main
function I'm just going
to simply call the function get_int.
>> So let's run this and see how it works.
I've already compiled it, so let's
just go ahead and run this program,
./integer.
Here I have a prompt and
here's where I input the value.
Say I put in just some integer,
50, the program excepts and quits
and that's that.
>> But say I run it again and
I input something else.
Perhaps, hello world.
That's not an integer so the
program will prompt me to retry.
Let's try again with
perhaps a decimal this time.
0.5, again, not an integer so
the program won't accept it
and it'll tell me to retry.
So let's give it another number.
The program accepts it,
quits, and we're done.
>> So now we have a function
that allows us and ensures
that the user inputs an
integer, but how can we
actually keep track of the
integer inputted by the user?
Well, all we'll do is store
this value in a variable, say n.
So if I declare an integer n,
and I set that value to get_int,
then n will then store whatever
value the user inputted.
>> All right, so now we've ensured that
the user will give us an integer
and we know how to keep track
of the integer, but remember,
integers are both positive and negative.
So it doesn't really make sense
in the context of this problem
that the user takes a shower
of say negative 12 minutes.
So we need to make sure that the user
actually gives us a positive integer.
Now we don't have just a
single function for that,
so we're going to have
to create that ourselves.
>> So we want to continually
prompt the user
until they give us a positive integer.
If I'm doing something continuously then
that's akin to a loop, a repetition.
So one of the constructs that we use
in c to implement repetition and loops
is a while loop.
So a while loop, as
shown here, will execute
whatever is in the body of the loop as
long as the given condition evaluates
to true.
As soon as that condition
evaluates to false, then
the program will proceed to whatever
comes after the body of the loop.
>> So while loops are going to
be really useful in CS50.
But in this particular
case, we know that we're
going to prompt the user at least
once and then only loop if necessary.
So here we come to a
special construct and that's
very similar to the while
loop called a do-while loop.
>> So a do-while loop executes the
body of the loop at least once
and then it checks to see
whether it should execute,
as opposed to a while loop,
which will check the condition
and then execute the body.
So in a do-while loop what we might
do is prompt the user for an integer,
and then check if it's invalid or not.
If it's invalid, then we'll
repeat the process asking the user
to give us another integer, and then
only when that integer is valid,
we'll continue to
whatever comes afterwards.
>> Now you'll notice that the
declaration of the integer n
is slightly different to what we
did before in the previous example
and this is because of scope.
If we had declared the integer n inside
of the body of the do-while loop,
then we wouldn't be able to access
that value of n outside of those curly
braces indicating the body of the loop.
But we do in fact want to access the
value of n later on in our program.
>> OK, so now let's talk about
what this condition should be.
We want to only reprompt the
user as long as n is invalid.
So think to yourself what an invalid
integer value would look like
and then create a Boolean
expression to express that.
>> We're almost finished with our subtask
of prompting and validating user input.
So let's make this a little
bit more user friendly
and give the user a little
bit more information
of what we're prompting them for.
So let's prompt the user, per the
spec, with the string minutes.
So using your printf statements, make
sure that you match this exactly.
>> All right.
So now we have a valid user
input, a positive integer
value for how many minutes
they spent in the shower.
So what's next is to calculate
the equivalent number of bottles.
What we're going to do here might
be very obvious to you at first,
and that's OK.
What we want to do is we
want to start practicing
the idea of detecting patterns and
developing formulae for the problem.
>> So we're told per the spec
that one minute in the shower
is equivalent to about
12 bottles of water.
So then two minutes would
be equivalent to 24,
and five minutes would
be equivalent to 60.
So now if you think
you've got it, then let's
see if you can come up
with a pattern or formula
to express if we have say, n
minutes, how many bottles of water
would that be expressed in terms of n?
>> Again, even though this
might be simple at first,
later on when we get to
more complicated problems
we're going to want to get into
the practice of identifying
patterns and developing formulae
to figure these things out.
>> In c you have access to
standard arithmetic operations,
addition, subtraction,
multiplication, and division.
So I'll leave it to
you now to figure out
how to express the
equivalent number of bottles
that the user consumed
during their shower.
>> All right, we're almost done.
We've prompted the user for their input,
we've ensured that it's valid input,
and then we've figured out how
to calculate the equivalent
number of bottles that they consumed.
So the last thing to do is to output
the equivalent number of bottles
and hopefully encourage
them to conserve some water.
>> Outputting the value will
be a printf statement.
If I wanted to tell you that I
have three pets, for instance,
I might use a printf statement
that looks something like this.
I have three pets, and a new
line for nice formatting.
>> Now we don't want to
simply hard code things.
Say the number of my
pets changes over time.
Then I'm going to make use of
placeholders in my printf statement.
So here my number is an integer.
So I'm going to make a placeholder
for an integer using %i.
I'm going to write the string,
and then after the string
I write a comma and then the
variable that I want to print.
So that value will be printed
in lieu of that placeholder, %i.
>> You can use placeholders, as
well, for floats with a %f.
You can also have multiple
placeholders in a string.
For instance, if I have some number
of dogs and some number of cats,
I put two placeholders here and then
my two variables in respective order.
>> So now that we know how to print
the values stored in variables,
the very last thing to
do is to ensure that we
print the value in the exact format
indicated in the specification.
With that, we've prompted the
user and validated their input.
We've then calculated the equivalent
number of bottles of water
that they consume during their shower,
and we've outputted that value to them.
And so, we've completed water.
>> My name is [? Zamila, ?]
and this is CS50.