>> FRED WIDJAJA: All right.
Hi, everyone.
Thank you welcome for
joining me at this seminar.
So today we going to be talking about
how to develop apps for Android,
and particularly, we're going to
be using Android Studio in order
to develop our apps.
>> So as you all may know.
Android uses Java, and so we'll be
going through a brief introduction
on Java itself.
So I know many of you only have
experience programming in C. So
that's totally fine, and that's
because Java is very, very
similar to C, with little differences.
>> So the types in Java are
fixed in the number of bytes.
So in C, we have shorts
and longs, and they
differ in number of bits
from machine to machine.
In Java, it's already set as a standard.
So bytes have eight bits, shorts
have 16 bits, and so on and so forth.
We also have chars, booleans,
and also floats and doubles.
So the way you program in
Java, it's very similar.
So for example, we have
for loops and while loops,
and if and else statements are
exactly the same as you would do in C.
>> All right, so the special thing about
Java is that it is object oriented.
Now, what are objects?
So if you look at the
things around you, you'll
notice that every real world object
has two common characteristics.
And that is that they have state
and they have some sort of behavior.
>> So for example, dogs
would have states which
are name, color, breed, maybe
if the dog is hungry or not.
And some behaviors that dogs would have
would be barking, or wagging a tail,
or fetching a ball.
So we can also apply this
to inanimate objects.
So for example, cars, they have
the model, year, max speed,
and so on and so forth.
And they have some behavior.
For example, accelerating, or
braking, or going in reverse.
>> So Java objects attempt to model
this by having fields and methods.
So fields are the states that
the Java object may have,
while method would represent the
behavior that a Java object would have.
So when I say methods
and fields, I really
just mean variables and functions.
They are exactly the same, except
that they apply to a certain object.
>> OK, so moving on to classes.
Java classes are like the
blueprints for an object.
They tell you what methods
it has, what fields it has,
and even here, we have something
called access modifiers which
we'll get to in a while.
So to declare a Java class, it's
very similar in syntax to a C struct.
>> Here we start off with public class Car,
and then we have an open brace and then
some number of fields that
you want the object to have.
And then here we have some methods,
and we also have a object constructor.
Now what this object constructor
does is it tells the object,
OK, I want to initialize this
object with some sort of fields.
>> So here, we want every Car
to have a model and a year.
So we have a constructor
just specifically
for the model and the year, and
this would set the model field
to a certain value, and
the year field as well.
>> Now about the access
modifiers I was talking about.
Here we have the public and
private access modifiers.
So you can think of this as
the RWX in your directories.
So they allow certain people
to read, and have access
to these fields and methods.
>> So if I say that model and
year and speed are private,
that means that other objects cannot
attempt to access this object's fields
there are private.
But when I set the access
modifier to be public,
now that means that other objects
are free to access and even
used the methods that are defined here.
>> So this is the basic
Car object that I have.
We have the accelerate,
break, and getSpeed methods.
To this point, is everyone clear on
Java objects and how to declare them?
Cool, all right.
So if you want to use the Java
object in a program itself,
then we can use this
new Car constructor.
So here we're saying we want to declare
a new object, which is of type Car.
And here it's applying
the model and year,
which we have defined in
this object right here.
>> So this is also another
object, if you notice.
It's a class for the
main program itself.
And we have this PSVM, or public
static void main, function,
and its the starting
point of your program,
similar to the main
function in your C program.
Here, we can access and
use the object's functions
using the dot and then the
function name notation.
And we can even specify
certain arguments or parameters
for that function.
>> OK, so now moving on to inheritance.
So real world objects may
share the same characteristics.
So for example, there's
different types of bicycles.
For example, mountain bike,
city bikes, or tandem bikes.
So they have this common
characteristic of being a bike.
>> And so bikes may have two wheels and
they may have a handlebar, maybe even
a tail light or something like that.
So Java gives us this
power to represent objects
that have certain common
characteristics through inheritance.
Now, what inheritance does, is it
passes on an object's fields and methods
on to a child object.
>> So for example, if I
have a car, and it has
the state of having four
wheels and one steering wheel,
then we can pass this on to
certain different types of cars.
For example, we have the
sedan, sports car, and an SUV.
Now, these three different
types of cars would still
have four wheels and one
steering wheel, but then they
may have certain
special characteristics,
such as having five seats and
a for a sedan, for example.
>> So to make use of this inheritance
feature, we use this extends keyword.
So remember back to the Car
object that I defined previously.
Now I define a Sedan object.
So this Sedan object would have the
same fields and functions, or methods,
that the Car would have.
But then, here I specify
certain additional functions,
for example, the set
number of passengers
and the get number of passengers.
>> Here, you may also notice
that we can override methods,
and that means we're just
replacing the behavior
to act differently in certain cases.
So, for example, I want to
set a max speed for our car.
And to do that, I check whether this
speed would go over the max speed.
And if it doesn't, then I call the
super class' accelerate method.
So this is the super.accelerate() calls
the super class' accelerate method.
>> Finally, we're going to
talk about interfaces.
So interfaces are a way to expose only
certain methods to the outside world.
So they're like a table
of contents, and you
can think of them as like
the C header files, just
like methods with empty bodies, and they
specify what the object or the class
has to have, or what methods
the object or class has to have.
>> So for example, if I
have a Bicycle interface,
and it has three different methods,
and here if I implement this interface,
then that means that this Bicycle
would need to implement the same three
methods that I defined in the interface.
>> Up to this point, any other questions?
All right, cool.
So this was a very brief
and quick tutorial on Java.
There's way more features and topics on
Java, that you can actually go through.
For example, there's
generics, there's data types,
there's even enums and stuff.
So if you want to learn more
about it, do follow these links,
and they'll teach you more about them.
>> OK, so, let's move on to the
actual meat of the seminar,
and that is actually
Android programming.
So before we actually
get to programming,
I want to talk about some jargon.
So an activity is
Android's way of saying
it's a single screen
within the application.
>> So, for example, if you have a Gmail
app, we have the view emails activity.
And then if you click
a certain email, that
will show another activity where
it's a view email activity.
And then we also have the compose
activity, or the edit message activity.
And so activities are
generally just a single screen
within the application itself.
>> Now, views are the components that make
up the screen, or the activity itself.
So they draw a certain
thing in your screen.
So for example, it could be a
text field, it could be a label,
it could be a checks box.
So it is many different types of views.
So now we have intents,
and that's a message
that is passed on to another activity.
And they contain information as to
what you want this activity to execute.
Finally, we have the
manifest file, and that
is an XML file that gives your phone
all the information about your app.
So that's includes the version, and
the activities that you will have.
>> OK, so let's start.
So we're going to be
using Android Studio.
So if you guys have this already
installed, feel free to follow along.
We'll try and start over from scratch.
And so I'm going to try
and create a new project.
And I'm going to call
my project Android 101.
And here we put the name of the
project in the application name field.
>> Company Domain, you don't
really have to worry about that.
This is just how Android
identifies your application.
So you have a domain name, you can type
in your domain name inside of there.
But if you don't, you can feel
free to type in anything you want.
So here I just type in frederickw.com.
>> And then, finally, I choose where
I want to store my project in.
And I'm going to just choose my desktop.
So Users, Frederick
Widjaja, and Desktop.
OK.
Then click Next.
Here, I'm going to choose the
minimum API to be supported.
So in this case, I'm
going to choose API 15.
And it's fine if you actually just
choose 4.4 which is the latest API.
Or 5, in fact.
But then you just need to worry about
which phones you're really supporting,
and which phones you're targeting.
Click Next.
>> OK, so we come to this
screen, and we're just
going to use create an
activity through this.
So I'm going to click blank
activity and then Next.
We're going to call it main
activity, I think that's fine.
Just going to call it,
press Finish right here.
Wait for it to load, and there we go.
>> So here we notice three
different folders.
We have the manifest folder
that contains our manifest.
If you open it, we'll see our package.
Or how Android identifies
your application
and then we have this
application tag, which
contains the title of our application
as well as the icon for the application.
>> We can actually run this
application straight.
So why don't we try and do that?
I'm going to use Genymotion.
If you brought your own phone, you can
link it up and run it if you want to.
But I'm just going to use an
emulator, and I'm going to start this.
Ooh.
Well I think that's
going to take a while,
so I think we'll just get straight
into explaining more about this.
So here we have the Java directory, or
where your source files are contained.
Here we have the main activity itself.
You can see that it
extends the activity class.
So our main activity is a screen
that will be in our application.
And then here we notice that a number
of functions are auto generated for us.
We have the onCreate function,
and that will be called whenever--
STUDENT: Do you mind
making the text larger?
FRED WIDJAJA: OK, sure.
I'll try and increase the font size.
Think that should be good.
That good?
>> STUDENT: Just a little bit
higher, like 20 or something.
>> FRED WIDJAJA: 20?
OK.
OK, all right.
So here we have onCreate
method that would
be called when our activity
is created in the [? show ?].
We have the
onCreateOptionsMenu, and we'll
see that there's actually
an action bar, and then
we can add certain menu items on to it.
And then here we have the
onOptionsItemSelected.
So this is like an event listener, so
whenever an option in our action bar
is clicked, this
function will be called,
and it will be passed with a
certain item that was clicked.
>> OK, I'm going to see--
that's not working well.
Let's try and start.
Oh dear.
OK.
This is worrying.
OK, so anyway.
Here we have the layout
for our activity itself.
This is our main activity, and here
we notice that there's the action bar.
And then we have this hello
world label, and we can actually
edit text right here.
If you go and scroll
down to the Hello World,
we can change it to whatever we want.
For example, it could be, Hi there.
Welcome.
And there we go, it changes.
Oh dear.
This style not working.
OK, that's worrying.
OK, anyway, we can move on without that.
So for now, let's try and
do some really basic stuff.
So here we going to have
a label, and then we're
going to have a text view--
sorry, not a text view,
we're going to have an edit text.
And that is a component
for you to type and stuff.
So we have a plain text, and then
we just add it onto our interface.
>> Here, I want to also add some margin
to the top so that it looks nicer.
So we're going to go on to the
properties, and then at the top margin,
we're going to add in 20 DPs.
So now, DPs are just a
unit of measure in Android,
and they stand for density
independent pixels.
So, as you may know, Android, there's
many different types of screens
and then they have
different screen densities.
So here it's just going to be
a density independent pixel,
so it's going to be same
throughout all the screens.
>> Going to extend this edit text, and
then I'm also going to add a button.
And it's going to say OK.
20 DPs.
OK.
So now we have three
different components.
And the way we can refer to
these in our main activity class
is by using this method
called findViewByID.
So I'm going to define some fields.
So we have in TextView,
so let's say helloText.
And then if you're using Android Studio,
you can use the shortcut alternate,
enter.
And click Import Class to automatically
import the corresponding classes
that we need.
And then here I'm going to add an ID to
this TextView and call it text_hello.
Now that we have defined
an ID for this TextView,
we can use this to refer to the
textview that we just defined.
So helloText equals
TextView findViewByID,
and then we specify the ID that
we want, which is r.ID.text_hello.
>> So this is very similar to JavaScript
and jQuery, where we can actually just
refer to certain elements
in the layout just
by using the ID that we have specified.
So in general, to access a
certain object or a certain field
in our layout, you're going to have
to use this findViewByID method.
And then we're going to do the same
things for the other two elements.
Here, I am going to
add the ID text_name.
Yes.
As well as for this one.
Button_ok.
>> Now what I want this to do is
when we click the OK button,
and we have inputted some sort
of name into the text field,
then it's going to update this
label to say, hi, name, welcome.
So, back in our main
activity class, we're
also going to try and refer to
those elements that we have to find.
>> So we have the EditText nameText.
Oops.
Enter and alternate, import class.
And then also the OK button.
Similarly, we're going to
do the same thing over here.
nameText equals EditText
findViewByID, r.ID.text_name.
And then the OK button.
findViewByID, r.ID, and then button_ok.
>> OK, so now we have all three
elements that we want to refer to.
So now I'm going to attach an
on-click listener to our button
to listen for user clicks.
To that we just use the
setOnClickListener event.
Now, here it's saying we need
to specify setOnClickListener,
and you can do that by just having a
new onClickListener, and press Enter.
>> And then you have this anonymous
class, or anonymous object.
And we also have this onClick
method, and that's basically
what it's going to be called
whenever our button's clicked.
>> So here, I want to get the name that
was input into an text field first So
String name equals to
nameText.getText().
Again, this is like the
Java syntax for referring
to functions within the object.
So nameText.getText, and then we're
going to convert it to a string.
Now we have the name that
was input by the user.
>> And then we're going to
generate a new string,
so it's going to be called hello.
I'm going to say, hi, name, welcome.
And finally, you want
to update the helloText.
So to do that, we simply call
helloText.setText(hello).
OK.
Oops.
>> I'm going to try and re-run Genymotion
one final time and see if it works.
If it doesn't, it's totally fine.
OK.
So I guess it doesn't work.
Actually, let me try and do this.
Could be this.
Genymotion.
OK.
All right.
Yes, it works.
OK.
That was frightening.
I did not mean to do that.
OK, so we have this Android emulator.
Let me turn this off.
So we have our Android emulator.
So we're going to try and
run this app that we made.
Just going to click the Play button,
and it's going to say, waiting for adb.
Oh, man.
Restart.
OK, I guess this still doesn't work.
OK, nevermind, then.
this is going to be a pity.
But so let's say that we want
to create a new activity,
and we're going to have a
picture in that activity.
To do that, we can just click
this File, and then New.
And then here we can select
Activity, and then Blank Activity.
Here, we're going to call
it maybe CatActivity.
>> OK, so now it generates two other files.
One is called
activity_cat, and the other
is called catActivity, which is a class.
So let's say that we want to add
a picture of a cat right here.
So when you do that, we're going
to use the ImageView class.
We're going to add it onto here.
And then set the margin to be 20 DP.
>> And now we're going to find
an image of a cat on internet.
So let's see.
Cat.
OK.
I guess this is fine.
So now we have our image.
So we're going to add
it into our project.
Can do this by right
clicking, and then-- we
can actually just open this,
go downloads, sorry, desktop.
Going to try and find it.
Cat.
Right here.
I'm going to copy it into my folder.
Now, it's going to ask me a few options.
Now, I just want this to
be in the drawable folder,
and that's going to be for all
different screen resolutions.
Alternatively, we can
actually just select
which screen resolution you
want this image to be in.
So going to select the
drawable folder, click OK.
Just going to name it cat.jpg.
>> OK, so, now it's added
into our image view.
we're going to have to use
this source right here,
and then we can use this dot dot dot
button, and select the cat image.
OK.
So now I want to make it such
that it's just the right size.
So I'm going to select this adjust
view bounds option right here,
and that automatically
sets it to the right size.
OK.
Now, to actually launch this
activity from our previous activity,
you're going to have to use
something called the intent.
So let's say I'm going to add another
button that launches the activity.
I'm going to add it here, right here.
And then it's going to
have the text activate it.
Oops.
OK.
>> Now, how do we actually open the
new activity within this activity?
So same deal as before.
We need to add an ID to this
button, and call it button_activate.
And then in our main activity, going
to have this new Button activateButton.
And then also use the
findViewByID method.
activateButton equals Button
findViewByID r.ID.button_activate.
>> OK.
And then we also going to
add in an onClickListener.
New onClickListener.
And then we're going to use
this thing called Intent.
Intent equals new Intent(this).
And then the name of the
activity that we want to show up.
So here in this, we're going
to have catActivity.class.
Sorry.
We're going to have to
specify @MainActivity.this.
So now the .this property is referring
to the current instance of the object
itself.
OK.
Up to this point, any questions?
All good?
All right.
>> And then if you want to start
the activity, it's pretty simple.
We just call the the
startActivity method.
And then we pass in the Intent
object that we have just defined.
Unfortunately, we
can't really show this.
I was hoping that we can actually run
this and show it along in the seminar,
but unfortunately not.
Oh, man.
I see.
Oh, we're going to try and kill ATB.exe.
OK.
Restart.
Did it work?
Oh, OK.
So now it's actually compiling.
Oh.
Unfortunately, there's
no devices running.
Let's try and restart my emulator.
Ah, there we go.
It appeared.
OK.
So I'm going to launch my
app on my Android emulator.
And we have the things
that we defined just now.
So we have the label, the text view,
the text field, and then button.
So I'm going to input
my name right here,
and there we go, it changed the text.
So if we type in Foo, it's
going to change to Foo.
>> And if I click the
Activate button, which
we have linked to actually launch a
new activity, hopefully this will work,
there we go.
It launches the new activity.
To go back, we can press
the Back button right here.
Or not.
Oh, there we go.
Oops.
That was bad.
OK.
>> So now that we have implemented
some basic stuff in Android,
we can try and do some
more complicated stuff.
So first, let's try and pass messages
from one activity to another.
So let's say we want to pass in
a name from the main activity
to the cat activity.
And a name would be
retrieved from this nameText.
>> OK, so first, we're going to
retrieve the name right here.
String name equals
nameText.getText().toString().
OK.
And then we can use this thing
called intent.putExtra(name),
and then it actually also wants
a key for this extra field.
>> So I'm going to define a new
key, we'll call it EXTRA_NAME.
So I'm going to use this
key, CatActivity.EXTRA_NAME,
and then pass in the name itself.
>> OK, so now we can actually retrieve
this within the new CatActivity.
To do that, we have to use the
intent equals getIntent method.
So now it's going to
retrieve the intent that
was used to call this new activity.
So if you want to retrieve the string
that we actually put inside the intent,
you can use an intent.getStringExtra
and then pass in the same key,
>> OK, so now let's say we you
want to change this field.
Change this field right here.
And let's make the font
size of this field larger.
So let's say I want this to be 20 DP.
OK.
And I'm going to add an
ID for this TextView,
and I'm going to call it text_cat.
Sorry.
>> And back in CatActivity,
same deal as before.
We're going to define some fields.
Here it's going to be
a TextView catText.
And then catText equals TextView
findViewByID, r.ID.text_cat.
OK.
And then back in here, I'm
going to set the text right
after we retrieve for
it from the intent.
setText(name).
>> OK, so let's try that out.
Click the Play button.
I'm going to use the same device.
Back in here.
So let's say I didn't input--
if we don't specify any name,
let's see what happens.
So now there's nothing that appears.
So we go back and input our name,
it's just going to say Fred.
So we can actually pass messages
from one activity to another.
OK.
>> So there's a bunch of other views
that you can use in Android.
So now we have progress bars, we have
list views, we have toggle buttons,
and if you really wanted
to learn more about that,
you can actually visit these web pages.
They contain many different resources.
So for example, the API
guide right here actually
gives you some code examples for
certain features in the Android library.
>> And a few tutorials I found useful
when learning about Android.
That's the official tutorial itself,
and also this other tutorial right here.
And finally, you can actually
use different libraries
for your Android application.
Now, these actually extend
the functionality of your app
without having to
really write much code.
The downside is, of
course, that you actually
have to learn the libraries yourself.
>> So for example, if you want to make
use of Dropbox cloud technology,
then you can use the Dropbox API.
Similar with the Facebook API.
And then there's actually a few
different other miscellaneous libraries
that you can use.
If you're trying to get, like,
JSON from a certain website,
then I think the Google JSON
library would be pretty helpful.
So now, that converts a JSON
formatted text into a Java object,
and vice versa.
>> And then there's Retrofit and Picasso.
And that's if you want to use--
that's for if you're using a rest API.
And Picasso, if you're using images
for your Android application.
All right.
Thank you very much,
and have fun coding.