JEFFREY LICHT: Hi there.
I'm Jeffrey Licht.
And I'm here to talk to you about the
Harvard Library and building tomorrow's
library today, I guess.
So the background here,
the pitch for this session
is essentially that there is
a lot of bibliographic data
available in the Harvard libraries.
And there is an opportunity,
through some of the tools
and a project that's being developed,
to get access to the information
and take it to places that the
Harvard Library isn't doing right now,
do new stuff with it, experiment
and play around with it.
>> So the entry point into this is an API
called the Harvard Library Cloud, which
is an open metadata server,
which I will talk about now.
So the background is that there is a
lot of stuff in the Harvard library.
We have over 13 million bibliographic
records, millions of images,
and thousands of finding aids, which
are essentially documents describing
collections, saying what
is in them, boxes of papers
and so forth that represent over
a million individual documents.
And there's also a lot of
information that the library has
about how the content is used that
could be of interest to people
who might want to work with it.
>> So all of the information
the library has metadata.
So metadata is data about data.
So when we talk about
the information that's
available through the library
cloud that's available,
it's not necessarily
the actual documents
themselves, not necessarily the full
text of books or the full images,
though that actually may be the case.
But it's really
information about the data.
>> So you can think of cataloging
information, call numbers, subjects,
how many copies of the
book there are, what
are the editions, what are the
formats, the authors, and so forth.
So there's a lot of information about
the information in the collection that,
in itself, is kind of inherently useful.
And though if you're
doing in-depth research,
you obviously want to get to the actual
content itself and look at the data,
the metadata is useful in terms of
both analyzing the corpus as a whole,
like what things are in the collection.
How do they relate?
It helps you really find other stuff,
which is really the main purpose of it.
The point of the
metadata and the catalog
is to help you find all
the information that's
available within the collections.
>> So this is an example of metadata
for a book in the Harvard Library.
So it's there.
And you can see it's
actually moderately complex.
And part of the value of metadata
within the Harvard Library system
is that it's been sort
of built up by catalogers
and assembled by people applying
a lot of expertise and skill
and thought to it over time,
which has a lot of value.
>> So if you take a look at this record for
The Annotated Alice, you can find out
you've got the title, who wrote it, the
author, and all the different subjects
which people have cataloged it into.
And you can see there's also, in
addition to a lot of good information
here, there's some duplication.
There's a lot of complexity that's
reflected through the metadata
that you have.
>> So one title of this book is
Alice's Adventures in Wonderland.
So this is an annotated
version of that book.
But it's also called The Annotated
Alice, Alice's Adventures
in Wonderland because
it's something which
Martin Gardner wrote
and annotated the book.
And there's a lot of great information
about logic puzzles and things
within Alice that you
probably didn't know about.
So you should go read it.
>> But you can see there's
a lot of detail here,
including identifiers, when it
was created, where it came from,
in terms of the Harvard
system, and so forth.
So this is a sample of
the type of metadata
that you might see for a book in
the Harvard Library collection.
>> This is something completely different.
So there is a system called
VIA Harvard, which basically
is cataloging images and objects of art
and visual things throughout Harvard,
and adding some metadata
to them, classifying them,
and, in some cases, providing
small thumbnail images
that you can take a
look at if you so wish.
>> So this is an example of the
metadata that you have for a plate
from, presumably, Alice in Wonderland.
And you can see there's
less metadata here.
It's just a different kind of object.
And so there's less information.
>> You mostly have the fact that, a call
number, essentially who created it,--
>> We don't know when it was created.
>> --and a title.
>> Another example.
This is a finding aid.
So there's a collection of Lewis
Carroll's papers at Harvard.
So this describes what
is in that collection.
So someone has gone through and
looked through all the boxes
and cataloged it, given some background,
written a summary of what's here.
And if you were to look
further at this, this
goes on for pages and pages
and pages, but will tell you
what letters and what
dates from what boxes
existed throughout the collection.
But this is something
that, if you're at Harvard,
you can go and actually physically look
up and, presumably, take a look at.
>> So this is all great.
This metadata's useful.
It's in the Harvard Library system.
There are tools online where you
can go and take a look at it,
and see it, and search it.
And you can slice it and dice
it in lots of different ways.
>> But it's really only available if
you are a human being sitting down
at your web browser or something or
your phone and navigating through it.
It's not really available in
any kind of usable fashion
for other systems or
other computers to use,
not with systems within
the Harvard Library,
but systems in the outside world,
just other people in general.
So the question is, how can we
make it available to computers
so that we can do more interesting
stuff with it than just
browsing it ourselves?
>> So why would you want to do this?
There are a lot of possibilities.
One is you could build a completely
different way of browsing
the content that's available
through the Harvard Libraries.
I'll show you one
later called Stacklife,
which has a completely different
take on looking for content.
>> You could build a recommendation engine.
So Harvard Library isn't in the
business of saying, you like this book.
Then go take a look at these 17 other
books that you might be interested in
or these 18 other images.
But that certainly could
be a valuable feature.
And given the metadata, it may
be possible to put that together.
You might have different needs in
terms of searching the content,
like maybe despite the tools that
are available that the library makes
available, you might want
to search in a different way
or optimize for a particular use case,
which maybe it's very specialized.
Maybe there are only a few
people in the world who
want to search the content
in this way, but it
would be great if we
could let them do that.
There's a lot of analytics
in just how people
use the content that would be really
interesting to know about, find out
what books are being used,
what are not, and so forth.
And then there's a lot of
opportunity to integrate
with other information
that's out there on the web.
So we have--
>> For example, NPR has
a book review segment,
where they interview
authors about books.
And so it would be great if you were
looking up a book in the Harvard
Library, and you say, OK, there's
been an interview with the author.
Let's go take a look at that.
Or there's a Wikipedia page, as an
authoritative, scholarly reference
about this book that you
might want to take a look at.
>> There are these types of sources
scattered throughout the web.
And bringing them together
could be a great use
to someone looking at the
content, looking for something.
But it's also not the
kind of thing you'd
want the library to be responsible
for going down and hunting down
all these different sources
and plugging them together
because they're changing continuously.
And what they think is important may
not be what you think is important.
>> And even more so, basically there's a
lot of stuff we haven't thought of yet.
So if we can open this up, more
people besides a half dozen or so,
who are looking at this on a
regular basis can think of ideas
and massage the data, and
do what they want with it.
>> So we want to make this
data available to the world.
Well, there are a couple complications.
One is that this metadata
is in different systems.
It's in different formats.
So there's some normalization
which needs to happen,
which normalization being the process of
bringing things from different formats
and mapping them to a single format
so that the fields will match up.
>> There are some copyright restrictions.
Oddly enough, the catalog entry
about a book is liable for copyright.
So even though it's just
information derived from the book,
it's copyrightable.
And depending on who actually
created that metadata,
there may be restrictions on who
can distribute it, similar to--
>> I don't know.
It may or may not be similar to
the situation of the song lyrics,
for example.
So we all know how that pans out.
So you need to get around that issue.
>> And then another piece is
that there's a lot of data.
So if I am someone who wants to work
with the data or has a cool idea,
dealing with 14 million
records on my laptop
could be problematic
and difficult to manage.
So we want to reduce
the barriers for people
to be able to work with the data.
>> So the approach that hopefully addresses
all of these concerns is two parts.
One is building a platform that takes
data from all these disparate sources
and aggravates it, normalizes,
enriches it, and makes
it available in a single location.
And it makes it available through
a public API that people can call.
>> So an API is an Application
Programming Interface.
And it basically refers to an
endpoint that a system or technology
can call and get data back in
a structured format in a way
that it can be used.
So it's not dependent
on going to a website
and scraping data off
of it, for example.
>> So this is the home page of
the Library Cloud Item API,
which is essentially its version two.
So it's the second iteration of
trying to make all of this data
available to the world.
So it's
http://api.lib.harvard.edu/v2/items.
And just to break this down
a little bit, what this means
is that this is version two of the API.
There's a version one, which
I'm not going to talk about.
But there is a version one.
>> And if you're calling this
API, you are getting items.
And part of the idea of an
API is an API is a contract.
It's something that is
not going to change.
So for example,--
>> And the reason is that if I
build some kind of system that
is going to use a library cloud API
to display books or help people find
information in unique ways,
what we don't want to happen
is for us to go change how
that API works, and suddenly
everything breaks on the end user side.
So part of if you're making API
available to the world, it's
good practice to put a
version number in it so people
know what version they're dealing with.
>> So if we decide we find a better way
of making this information available,
we might change that to
call that version three.
So everyone who is still using
version two, that'll still work.
But version three would
have all the new stuff.
>> So this is an API, but this
really looks like a URL.
And so what this is an
example of is what's
called a rest API, which is available
over just a regular web connection.
And you can actually
go to it in a browser.
>> So here I've just opened up Firefox and
gone to api.lib.harvard.edu/v2/items.
And so what I get here is
basically the first page
of results from the entire
set of items that we've got.
And it's here in XML format.
And it's also been
prettified by Firefox.
It doesn't actually have all of these
little expanding and contracting
doohickeys here.
This is sort of a nicer
version way to look at it.
>> But what this is telling us is
I've requested all the items.
So there are 13,289,475 items.
And I'm looking at the first
10, starting at position zero
because in computer science
we always start at zero.
And what I have here, if I just collapse
this, you'll see I've got 10 items.
>> And if I take a look at an item, I can
see that I've got information about it.
And this is in what's called MODS form.
And so I'm going to switch
back here for a moment.
OK.
>> So let's search for something in
specific because the first item that
happens to come up when you look
through the entire collection
is, by definition, random.
So let's look for some donuts.
Oh.
>> OK.
So doughnuts.
So we found there are 80 items in
the collection that reference donuts.
We're looking at the first 10 of them.
Now, you can see here the way that
I said I'm looking for donuts,
I just added something to
the query string of the URL.
So q equals donuts, which you can
see a little more easily here.
>> And this basically means there's
a spec for the API, which
defines what all of
these parameters mean.
And this means we're going to
search everything for donuts.
>> So the first item here we have
you can see the title is Donuts,
and there is a subtitle called An
American Passion, which is, I guess,
appropriate.
There are a lot of different--
Once you get to the point
of getting the data,
there are a lot of different
formats that you can get it into.
And there are different strengths
and weaknesses for all of them.
So this one, you can see
here, this form is very rich.
And it's standardized.
>> So there's a specific title
field, a subtitle field.
There's an alternate
title, An American Passion.
There is the name associated with it.
Type of the resource is text.
There's a lot of information
here in this format.
>> But there are a bunch
of different formats.
So what we were just
looking at is a format
called MODS, which stands for
Metadata Object Description Service,
potentially.
I'm actually not quite sure about the
S. But it's a fairly complex format.
It's the default format.
>> But it's the one that keeps
the richness of all the data
that the library has because
it's very close to what
the library uses internally.
It's a standard that is
used across the country,
across the world in academic libraries.
And it's very interoperable.
So if you've got a document
that is in MODS format,
you can give that to somebody else
whose systems understand MODS,
and they can import it.
So it's a standard.
It's very well defined, very specific.
And that is what makes it
interoperable because if someone says,
this is the alternate title of a
record, everybody knows what that means.
On the flip side, it's very complicated.
>> So if you take a look
at this record here,
if I just want to get the
title of this document,
of this book, which is probably Donuts,
An American Passion, parsing it out
is a little involved.
Whereas there's another
format called Dublin Core,
which is a much, much simpler format.
>> And so you see here, there's no
title, subtitle, alternate title.
There's just the title,
Donuts, An American Passion,
and another title, American Passion.
So when you're looking at what form
you want to get the data out of,
a lot depends on how
you're going to use it.
Are you using for
interoperability or do you
want something simple that
might be easier to work with?
>> On the flip side, a lot of the
details get sort of squished down.
You might lose the nuances of
what a particular field means
if you're dealing with Dublin Core,
which you wouldn't get with MODS.
So those are two of the formats
you can get out of the API.
And basically, we are keeping
it behind the scenes in MODS.
But we can give you it in MODS and
Dublin Core and anything else as well.
The other consideration when
you're looking in the data
is you can get it as either JSON, which
stands for JavaScript Object Notation,
or XML, which stands for
Extensible Markup Language.
And these data representations both
have exactly the same data, exactly
the same fields.
But they're just
syntactically different.
>> So this is a--
Well, let's just switch.
So this is our query for
donuts in XML format.
If I just switch this to be JSON,
I can see it looks different.
So now this is the same content,
but a different structure.
There are fewer angle brackets.
There's less verbose.
>> And this is a format that, if you
are working in the web environment,
you are most likely going
to want to use because one
of the nice things about JSON is
it's compatible with JavaScript.
So if I'm writing web app, I can pull
in JSON and just work with it directly.
Whereas with XML, it's a
little bit more complicated.
So again, these are both useful.
They just are different use cases
where people might want to use them.
OK.
So back to the API.
So we can search for--
>> I give an example of
searching for donuts.
We can also search just in a
particular field within here.
So instead of searching
the entire record,
I can just search the title field.
And so now there are 25 things that
have donuts in the title, one of which
is about restoring
wetlands in management
of the hole in the donut
program, which is probably
not necessarily what we're looking
for when we're searching for donuts.
>> You can also, when you're
dealing with an API--
>> Part of having an API is giving
people access to large data sets.
And there are a couple different
tools you can use to do that.
One is, very simply, you
can page through the data.
So just as if you do a query
through a web interface,
you can look at page one,
page two, page three.
You can do the same
thing through the API.
You just need to be
explicit in how you do it.
>> So for example, if I'm looking
at my first query here,
where I'm doing a search for things
with donuts in the title, I can say,
and limit equals 20, which means
give me the first 20 records, not
the first 10, which is the default,
because I want to look at 20 at a time.
Or I can say, set the
start equal to 20 and limit
equal 20, which will give
me records 21 through 40.
>> So I guess the thing
to take away here is
that we're using the query strings
to set parameters on the query.
And it lets you control
what you get back.
>> Another tool that you can use,--
>> And this is really helpful in
terms of exploring the data.
>> --is something called faceting.
So the term faceting is
not necessarily common.
But you've all seen it before.
If you take a look at
Amazon, for example,
and you do a search for
donuts in the books,
here they've got a series of books,
and they're grouped by category,
and you get the different categories,
and how many books in each category
show up.
>> So this is basically a facet.
You take all their books, the 1,800
books that match donuts at Amazon.
12 of them are in the
breakfast category.
21 in pastry and baking,
and so on and so forth.
>> So this is really a useful
tool for exploring the content
within the library as well
because when you look at a facet,
it gives you an idea of what subjects
exists, like what types of subjects
are most popular within your query set.
And it helps you drive off and explore.
So we can do the same thing.
>> If we want to use the
API and look at facets,
we add another parameter to
our friend the query string.
So facets equals a comma separated
list of what we want to facet on.
So one of the facets might be subject.
Another might be language.
And so if we run that query, we get--
It looks pretty much the same here.
But we've added to the end
of the list a set of facets.
So we have a facet called subject.
So this is telling us that if I look
at my 80 results from the donut query,
13 of them have the
subject United States.
Three have the subject donuts.
Three have the subject
of wetland restoration,
which may be our hole in the donut.
Two of them, the Simpsons,
and so on and so forth.
>> So this can be useful if you
want to narrow down your search.
It can help you do that.
Especially if you have
more than, say, 80 results.
>> Similarly, we also asked
for facets on language.
So if we look at our results, we see 76
of them are in English, four in French,
two in Spanish, two, I think that's
undefined or unknown, Dutch and Latin.
So I think the Latin
donut result, again,
has nothing to do with baked goods.
But there you go.
>> So this is sort of showing you
how you can pull the content back
from the API just through
web browser, which is great.
But it's not really what you would
normally be using in API for it.
So one example of how you
could actually do this is I've
written a super small program,
which, again, does my donut search
and selects a couple fields
and displays them in a table.
So this is very much the
same content that we just
saw with a few fields pulled out.
So list of titles, the
location of what the book
is about, the language,
and so on and so forth.
>> So how this actually happened, since
I guess we have to look at some code,
is--
>> What we have here is a simple HTML
page, which displays the text,
welcome to library cloud and
then displays a table of results.
And there are obviously no results in
the table when the page gets loaded.
But what we're doing
is, first of all, we
are loading a library called
jQuery, which is basically
a JavaScript library, which makes it
very easy to manipulate JavaScript
natively, HTML, and create web pages,
client-side logic and web pages.
>> So what we have here is jQuery
has a method called Get,
which essentially will go to
a URL, which, in this case,
is this familiar looking URL.
And will then get the content from
that URL and then run a function on it.
So we said go to api.lib.harvard/edu.
Search for donuts.
Give us 20 records.
And then run this function, which
I've selected, passing it the data.
And the data is the JSON that
got returned from the API.
>> And then we're saying, within that
data there's a field called item.
And if I go take a look back at
one of these results that's here,
there's something called--
>> Well, it's called item.
So that may be that.
And what it does is it
goes through each item
and then calls another
function on each item.
And that function basically
is taking the value
of the item, which is
essentially the individual record
and allows us to pull out the title,
the coverage and the language.
>> So we call a function on every
item that we got back from the API.
And if you just take a look
at this piece right here,
what we're doing is
we're creating a string,
which is essentially some HTML markup
around a table, with value.title,
which is the title of the
object, value.coverage,
which is the coverage,--
>> And we're doing a check
here to see who's undefined
and hiding it if it says undefined,
because we're not really interested
in that.
>> --and then the language.
And then what we're
doing is appending that
to the table that is
identified by this string here.
And how jQuery works
is what this is saying
is look for the table with idea
results and add this text to it.
And this is the table with idea results.
So what you end up
with is this page here.
And in order to view source--
Well, the source is not actually
updated when that happened.
So you can see the actual
results of the table here though.
>> So that's just a simple example of
doing a very basic query against the API
and displaying information in some other
form, and not doing anything too fancy.
Now, another example is like an
application written by David Weinberger
as a demo of this, which
essentially shows you
how you can mash up the results you're
getting from the library cloud API
with, say, Google Books.
>> And the thinking here is that I can
run a query against Google Books,
get a full text search, get some results
back, find out which of those items
actually exist in Hollis,
the library system,
and then give me links
back to those items.
So if I search for, it was
a dark and stormy night, I
get back a bunch of results
from Google, and then one result
which is A Wrinkle in Time.
And these are links to books that exist
within the Harvard Library system.
>> So I guess the point here is not
so much that this may or may not
be the way that you want
to search the library,
but it is a completely different
way that was not available to you
before, like you had no way of doing
full text searches on books that even
were part of the Harvard Library system.
So now this is a way
that you can do that.
And you can display them in
whatever format you want.
So the point here is, basically,
we're opening up new ways for people
to work with the data.
>> Another piece of library cloud is that
it helps expose some of the usage data
that the library has.
So if you go to the library,
and you're looking for books,
you don't necessarily
actually have an idea of,
for all the items in a
particular subject, what
are people in the
community, whether it's
defined as Harvard or the
country or your class,
what have they found most useful?
And the library actually has a
ton of information about what
is most useful because if a lot
of people are checking out a book,
that tells you something.
There must have been some reason
they want to check it out.
A lot of people put it on reserve.
>> If it's on the reserve list for a lot
of classes, that tells you something.
If faculty members are checking it
out a lot and undergraduates are not,
that tells me something.
Vice versa, that also
tells you something.
So it would be really interesting to
put that information out there and let
people use it to help them find
works within the library system.
The flip side of this is
there are some serious privacy
concerns because one of the
core tenets of the library
is we're not going to be telling
people what other people are reading.
And even if you are saying this
book was checked out four times
in a particular month,
that could be used
to link back to a particular
person by de-anonymizing data
and finding out who checked it out.
So the way that we can avoid--
The way that we can try to extract
some signal from all the information
without infringing
anybody's privacy concerns
is essentially we look at
10 years of usage data,--
>> So it's over a long period of time.
>> --and say, OK, let's see how
many times this work was used,
and by who over this period
of time, and then basically
give back a number, which we call
a stack score, which basically
represents how much it's been used.
And that number--
A lot of different calculations
go into that number.
--but it's a very rough
metric that gives you
some idea of how the
community may value that work.
>> And so another sort of even
more fleshed out application
that takes advantage
of this is something
called Stacklife, which is actually
available through the main Harvard
Library portal.
So you go to library.harvard.edu.
You'll see a number of different
ways of searching the library.
And one of them is called Stacklife.
>> And this is an application that
browses the content of the library,
but is completely built
on top of these APIs.
So there's no special stuff
going on behind the scenes.
There's no access to
data that you don't have.
It's using the APIs to provide you
with a completely different browsing
experience.
>> So if I search for Alice
in Wonderland in this case,
I get a result that looks like
this, which is pretty much--
>> It's very similar to any other search
you might do, except in this case
we're ranking the items by
stackscore, which gives you
some idea of how popular these
items were within the community.
And so clearly, Alice in Wonderland
by Walt Disney is highly popular.
But you can also see the top four
here are ones you might not actually--
>> Things that are highly used,
but you may not immediately
connect with Alice in Wonderland.
So our old friend The
Annotated Alice is here.
So I can take a look at it.
And now what I'm looking
at is basically a set of--
I can have The Annotated
Alice right here.
I have information about it.
And I also have a stackscore
of, in this case, 26.
And this tells me sort of roughly
how we got to this stackscore,
like who checked it out, like how
many times it was checked out,
like faculty or undergrads, how
many copies the library has,
and so on and so forth.
>> And you can also, interesting enough
here, browse the stacks virtually.
So the data here, this
is showing you sort
of a virtual representation
of what the shelf might
look like if you were to take
all the library's holdings
and put them together
on one infinite shelf.
And the nice thing is that we can--
>> First of all, the
metadata about these books
often tells you when it was published.
It tells you how many pages it has.
It might tell you the dimensions.
So you can see that's reflected here
in terms of the size of the books.
>> And then we can use the
stack score to highlight
the books that have higher stack scores.
So if it's darker, it means that,
presumably, it is used more frequently.
So in this case, I'm
going to guess that this
is the version of Alice in Wonderland
that is very commonly used and most
accessed, the library
has the most copies of.
So if you're looking
for Alice in Wonderland,
this might be a good place to start.
>> And then here you can also link out
to, say, Amazon to purchase the book,
and so on and so forth.
The point here, again,
is not so much that this
is the best way to browse the library
or the right tool for every occasion.
But it's another way of doing it.
And by making the data
available through an API, which
is made of very simple building blocks,
which allows you to search the content,
you can build something
like this that can
be extraordinarily
valuable to some people.
>> So that's sort of, as much as I want
to say really about what the API is
and what it exposes, there's a whole
bunch of stuff behind the scenes, which
I'm just going to touch on briefly
just because it sort of comes at this
from a completely different angle in
terms of how does something like this
get put into place?
>> So an API is a standard
interface to all of this content.
But to get it there, the
first thing we had to do
was pull together information
of books and images
and the finding aids, the collection
document from various Harvard systems.
Aleph, VIA, and OASIS are
the names of the systems.
And they essentially go into a
pipeline, a processing pipeline.
>> So first of all, we get export
files from all of these systems.
We split them up into individual items.
So we have a file, which is a gigabyte,
which has a million records in it.
So we split it up into individual items.
Then, for each item, we convert it
into MODS, because some of these
are natively MODS, some of them are not.
So we get them all to
be in the same format.
Then there are various
enrichment steps, where
we add more information to the data
than was available in the library.
So we need to add, first of all
we have what libraries hold it.
We go through a step of
calculating the stackscore.
We go through another step of
adding more metadata in terms
of what collections people
might have added this--
>> People are creating
collections of items.
What collections does it belong to?
How have people tagged
this content in the past?
Then you filter out, and you restrict
the records because, as I mentioned,
there's some records that, because of
copyright reasons, we can't display.
And then we load them
into something called
Solr, which is not a misspelling, but
is the name of a piece of software
that does search indexing, which
drives all the search behind the API.
And then it becomes available to
the API, and people can use it.
>> So this is like a fairly
straightforward process.
One of the interesting
things about it is
that we are dealing
with 13 million records
and we are going to be dealing or more.
And we want to be able to handle
these in a relatively speedy fashion.
It takes a long time to
process 13 million records.
>> So how this pipeline is
set up is that you can--
I guess the advantage of the
pipeline, the problem that we're
trying to solve here, is that
all the transformations, all
these steps in this
pipeline are separable.
There's no dependency.
If you're processing
a record of one book,
there's no dependency in
that between another book.
>> So what we can do is basically,
at each step in the pipeline,
we put it into a queue in the cloud.
I happened to be on Amazon Web Services.
So there's a list of,
say, 10,000 items that
need to be normalized and
converted to MODS format.
And we spin up as many servers
as we want, maybe 10 servers.
And each of those servers just
sits there, looks in that queue,
sees that there's one that needs to
be processed, pulls it off the queue,
processes it, and sticks
it on the next queue.
>> And so what that allows us
to do is apply, essentially,
as much hardware as we want to this
problem for a very short period of time
to process the data as quickly as
possible, which is something that only,
now in the world of cloud computing
we can provision servers essentially
instantaneously, is that useful.
So we don't have to have a
giant server sitting around
all the time to do the processing
that might happen just once a week.
>> So that is mostly it.
There's documentation available
for the Library Cloud Item API
at this URL, which will
be available later.
And please go take a look at
it to see if there's anything,
you have any ideas.
Play with it.
Fool around.
And hopefully you can come
up with something great.
Thank you.