>> ANSEL DUFF: All right, hi, everybody.
My name's Ansel.
I am, as you know, a senior in
mechanical engineering in [INAUDIBLE].
Today, we're going to
spend a little bit of time
reviewing how to design
a part from scratch
and how to ensure that it will suit the
needs of whatever its application may
be.
>> So today, we will first design
this little lens support.
I have a couple of
them printed out here.
And I have one actually attached to the
mount that I just sat down right here.
And this just holds up a lens
like so, mounts onto some
rails-- I don't have enough hands
to hold this-- just like that.
So we'll go over how that
was designed, and then
move on to another
part, which is an iPhone
dock, which I've
displayed here, in orange.
We'll go over how to CAD
those, how they were designed,
how to take measurements, and how
to ensure that this won't tip over,
for example, or this
won't buckle under loads.
>> All right, so before
we get started, I just
want to talk about some
overarching design principles
when you're designing
a part from scratch.
Much like when you're
writing code, you want
to be very explicit in
what you tell the computer.
You never want to leave
anything ambiguous.
Luckily for us, in SolidWorks,
when you sketch something,
all the lines are blue when
you initially draw them,
and they become black once they're
constrained in three dimensional space.
So if you have a sketch
with some blue lines on it,
you know that you need to fix some
of those things before you move on.
It's just like a sanity check before
you make a picture out of a sketch.
>> So like I said, you want to
be really explicit in how
the sketches are defined.
The way that it works is you
start out with one point.
SolidWorks gives you an origin
in three dimensional space.
And that point is fixed.
And it will always be there and
will never move, ever, ever, ever.
So you base your whole
sketch around this one point.
And then you relate every line to
either the origin or another line
that's related to the origin.
So I know this sounds a little abstract
right now, but once we get started,
it'll be a little bit clearer.
But just like I said, make
sure that everything is black,
everything is completely
defined, before we move on
and you won't run into problems later.
>> Another thing that I'm really big
on is putting a lot of emphasis
on making sure that you design your part
for scalability such that you can tweak
it later if a measurement is a little
bit off with no negative consequences
or effects.
And the way do we do that is
we add a lot of relations.
So for example, when we define this
part, we have two parallel faces here.
Well, we told SolidWorks
that they are parallel,
and you can draw two parallel
lines, and SolidWorks
will snap your lines to a grid.
But unless you explicitly
tell it that these lines need
to be parallel, maybe later on down
the road when you try to extend the top
or maybe extend the base, if you
hadn't added that relation in,
everything can become a mess.
>> So let's get started here.
And if at any point you have a question,
please feel free to interrupt me.
It goes without saying.
But we'll get started.
So SolidWorks comes with tutorials
that teach you the syntax of the GUI.
I think it would not be an
efficient use of our time
to go over which buttons to click.
So I'll go very slowly today and walk
through every step that I'm taking.
But just know that if you
feel lost or confused,
there are tutorials that explain
exactly what I'm doing here
but on a little bit of a lower level.
And I'm going to put
a lot emphasis today
on adding relations to everything.
I'm going to go over that a lot.
You guys are going to get sick of it.
But it's super important.
And you'll see down the road that
if we want to tweak a dimension,
it's really useful.
So we'll get started here.
We'll select new.
And we're going to design a part.
SolidWorks has three different
types of files you can have.
There are parts,
assemblies, and drawings.
Assemblies are just multiple
parts with relations,
so the parts are related to each
other in three dimensional space.
And then, a drawing is a document
that you might send to a machine shop
or whatever to actually
manufacture your part.
>> So we'll start with a
part here and click OK.
Now, we have a blank canvas.
So we're going to start out with this.
And what we first are going to do,
and this is true for every part,
is we need to create some sort
of stock, some sort of material.
And then, once we have the material,
we can extrude these web features.
I even wrote CS50 on the front of
it, and then a hole in the bottom.
So first, let's start out.
We're going to select Sketch
over here, and then Sketch again.
And SolidWorks prompts us
with three different planes.
You can add planes later on down the
road when you're designing your part.
But we're first going to have
these three orthogonal planes.
And we will select top plane right now.
Oops.
That was not the top plane.
Just go back here and--
>> There's always this tree
that is floating around here.
And this allows you to select
features of your build or planes
or any relations.
And then, the part material.
So we're going to
sketch on the top plane.
So we hit top.
And we are normal to it.
And then, here's our origin point.
So let's just make some
sort of shape here.
We know that there is going
to be a curve on the bottom
and a curve on the top.
So this is actually designed
to fit onto this piece here.
This is actually a lens support that
was given to us by our production team.
And it wasn't tall enough.
>> So the purpose of this part is actually
to just extend this a little bit
by-- we'd chosen two
inches, what we measured.
And it will just bolt on.
There's a hole that already
existed in the bottom of this.
So we know that we want
the width of our piece
to be the same as the
width of the support.
And then, we want the radius on the
bottom to be the same as the radius
here so that it fits nice and snugly.
And then, we'll add a hole on the
bottom that we can bolt it onto it.
>> So we're just going to start out with
the footprint of this feature, which
is just this base.
It's like a rectangle, but with
curves on the top and bottom.
I don't know if I can
make this stand up.
So to do that in SolidWorks, we
could start out with a rectangle.
But that won't be exactly
what we need because we
need a curved face on
the top and bottom.
So I just selected line over here.
And now, when you see the
pencil tool moving around now,
that means that we are ready to draw.
So we're going to start at the origin.
And we're going to draw vertically.
>> You'll notice that as the line becomes
vertical, it'll snap to vertical.
And you see that this little yellow
box right to the bottom right
of the pointer, that means that
SolidWorks is automatically
adding a relation for you.
So that's the theme of today,
what are the relations.
So when we click this,
you'll notice that it's black
because SolidWorks knows
that it's a vertical line
and it began at the origin.
But the endpoint is blue because
we didn't tell SolidWorks
how long the line is.
So we're just going to
make another one of these.
In fact, I'll even draw it
purposefully off vertical
so that we can add the relation in.
>> You'll notice that it
automatically wants
to add another line from the
endpoint of the first line.
So if you just double click like
I did here, we have another line.
If you just double click,
it will cancel that.
So we can hit the green arrow.
I'm just going to delete this.
On most keyboards,
there'll be a delete key.
But on a laptop keyboard, you have to
hit the function key and then delete.
So we select it, and hit function,
delete, and it goes away.
So we need to add the
relation telling SolidWorks
that these lines are, in fact, parallel.
So I select one.
And then I'll hit the Control key,
hold it down, and select the other.
And then this dialogue box
pops up right near our cursor.
So we have a couple
different options here.
>> We can make them both vertical,
make them both horizontal, parallel.
In this case, making them
parallel and making the vertical
will accomplish the same task.
But we can just hit parallel.
And then, we're going to
add one more relation, which
is we're going to again hold down
Control, select both, and tell
SolidWorks that they're the same length.
Cool.
So now, what I'm going to do is
add what's called a center line.
>> So if we hit the line
tool and the little arrow,
this drop down will pop up.
And we have the center line option.
You'll know that something is a
center line because it's dashed.
It's not a solid line.
So let's draw one in.
And we need to tell SolidWorks that
this is going to be horizontal.
Cool.
>> So this is just going to be the
baseline upon which we will make sure
that these, like this
one, isn't too high up.
So it seems to have already
did that automatically.
But just to be safe,
we'll make it explicit.
So if we select this point here, and
then again, holding down Control,
select this line, we have the
option of making them coincident.
So we'll select that.
Do that again one more time.
And now, we know that these
lines are the same length.
They're parallel.
And they start on the same--
this will become a plane,
but it's a line for now.
>> AUDIENCE: So is it the
second one you clicked
on that is made coincident
with the first one, or is it--
>> ANSEL DUFF: So both lines have endpoints
that are coincident with this line.
So since everything is really simple
right now because it's orthogonal.
>> AUDIENCE: Is one always
moved to the other?
ANSEL DUFF: Oh, OK.
Yeah, so it's the order
that you click it.
So if I had clicked the point
and then the line versus the line
and then the point, yeah.
But luckily, the origin
is a fixed point in space.
So now, we need to define
their length, which
we can do by clicking this smart
dimension in the upper left.
And then, select something
that we want to dimension.
So this is probably one of the
most important things in design,
dimension all of your pieces.
This is how you tell the
program how tall it's
going to be, what the radius is for the
top and bottom curved faces, the depth,
and so on and so forth.
And that's all done through
the smart dimension tool.
>> So if we click on the line,
this little arrow pops up.
And this can tell us once we
click, we get a prompt wherein
we can type that we want this
part to be 2 inches tall.
We had measured, and 2 inches seemed
like it would be plenty of space.
So we hit 2.00.
2 is also fine.
Hit Enter.
And then, you'll notice that
both lines are now 2 inches tall.
>> Now question, our first
line is completely black.
It has two black endpoints
and the line itself
is black because it's
completely constrained
in this two dimensional plane.
But this line is blue.
Why is that the case?
Why is that line blue?
We've told SolidWorks that it's
parallel to our original line.
AUDIENCE: How far it is
from the original line.
ANSEL DUFF: Exactly, correct.
So here's where we need to measure.
We don't know how far
this is going to be.
How wide is this supposed to be?
So we can hit Smart Dimension,
then select the first line.
You'll notice that it's blue.
Then, select the second line.
And we get this width prompt.
So we can click it.
And SolidWorks now wants to know
how wide the part is going to be.
But we don't know.
So we have to measure.
So we take our part, and
we use a pair of calipers.
And we're going to just
measure the width here.
>> So calipers are a really precise way
of measuring any dimension, really.
They have two measuring prongs, I guess.
There's one on the bottom
that can measure externally.
So you'll clamp down on something.
And then, there are two prongs on
top that can measure internally,
like the diameter of
a hole, for example.
So calipers are typically good
to about a thousandth of an inch,
meaning that each tick
on the front face here
represents one thousandth of an inch.
Typically, engineers
will speak saying thou.
It's slang, almost.
Saying a part is 80 thou thick.
It's like, this is 80
thousandths of an inch, just
some lingo to cue you guys in on.
>> So since they're so
precise, the first tool,
or the first step when using
calipers, is you open the prongs up.
And then you wipe them to
eliminate any gunk that
will change your measurements.
And then, we close them.
And we ensure that it is zero.
I'm not sure if you
can see all that well,
but once they're closed, the needle
lines up with zero pretty well.
So we don't need to adjust anything.
So now, we open them up.
We're going to clamp down.
And I'll try my best to hold it up here.
>> There are inch indications
on the actual stem
of the caliper, every tenth of an inch.
And then, there are hundred ticks,
thousand, so 1/10 of an inch
all around.
So we clamp down here.
And we see that it's just
past the one inch mark.
And it goes to four ticks past.
So one inch plus 4/1000 is 1.004 inches.
I suspect that whoever designed this
part designed it to be one inch,
and then the anodizing
added two thou on each side,
so 1.004 inches is our measurement.
>> AUDIENCE: How important was
the vertical height measurement
that you originally talked about?
ANSEL DUFF: This is kind of the
specificity of this part itself.
But you'll notice that there's
a bolt holding this in.
Two inches was more
than enough when we were
talking about how tall
this part should be.
It only really needs
to be about an inch.
We just held a tape
measure up and eyed it.
So we added another
inch just for safety.
And if it is too long, this can slide
down and accommodate that extra height.
So two inches was not
measured that accurately.
We just kind of eyed it knowing that it
could be adjusted and accommodated for.
So we'll enter in 1.004, hit Enter.
>> Cool, now both lines are black.
We're good to go.
So now, we need to put in
an arc here and an arc here.
Spoiler alert, this is just kind of
another specificity of this part.
They are the same radius
because it's just an extender.
So if you had made the top radius
and the bottom radius different,
you might be able to
accommodate a larger lens.
But that wasn't our goal here.
So we have no idea how
big this radius was.
But we knew the lens that it
was trying to accommodate.
So much like we had just measured
the width using our calipers,
we will do the same thing, if I
can get them, for our lens here.
>> So I'm just going to open them up
wide here, fit them around the lens,
don't press too much
because it's rubber.
We don't want to deflect it.
And we see this 3.465 is the width.
So that 3.465 is going
to be the diameter
that we are going to make these radii.
We're going to go over here and select
the arc tool in our shape plane.
Hit the drop down, you'll notice there
are a couple different types of arcs.
We're going to use
center point arc, which
is us defining the center
point and then two endpoints.
>> But as you can see,
there's also a tangent
and three point arc option available.
So let's go here and just hit
a center point arbitrarily.
And then, let's draw it here.
And I'm going to purposely
go past what we need.
So everything is blue
here, and that's because we
need to somehow make
this point be completely
between these two and some
specified distance away.
So let's add in another center line.
Just going to draw it vertically.
SolidWorks again snaps to vertical.
If you're ever wondering if in fact
this is vertical, if you select it here,
you'll get all the relations
on a line listed in this box.
>> So we see vertical, too.
That's telling us that the
line is in fact vertical.
I have the option turned off
right now to show relations.
Relations are shown by this
little green box with some symbol.
In this case, it's a vertical line.
They can get kind of
cluttered, especially when
you have a lot of features
happening in your drawing.
So I just to turn them off.
But if ever you need to know
the relations on a line, an arc,
a point, what have you, just select
it, and then there's a list here.
>> So vertical was done by SolidWorks.
We added in the parallel
to the second line.
Equal radius, equal
length was just us telling
SolidWorks these are
both the same length.
And then the distance was
specified by this one inch.
Cool.
So we will add in the center
line, can extend it down.
And then, we need to
tell SolidWorks that it
is equidistant between these two.
So I'm going to add in
another center line here.
>> And you'll notice that it's
coincident on both of these.
But we have no way yet of
saying that this line needs
to hit the midpoint of this line.
So we can add in a point.
We go over here and select Point.
Looks like a little asterisk.
Then, as we move it
along this line, you'll
notice that there is that
yellow box in the middle of it.
And when we hover over
the box, the symbol
goes from those three lines in this
little yellow box to just two lines.
And that's SolidWorks's way of
saying, this is the midpoint.
So we make a line there,
make a dot, rather.
And in our relations
box, it says midpoint.
So we know that's in the middle.
And then, hit the green check.
Undo the point box, because it'll just
continue drawing points every time you
click, which we don't want.
So this point is already selected.
Now, we're going to make this
point and this line coincident.
So hold down Control.
Select this.
Select coincident.
And you're good to go.
Sometimes, I'm just going to undo that.
Sometimes, when you
have these two selected,
that little box doesn't pop up.
You can always just pop
over to this left plane,
or left pane, rather,
and then hit coincident,
and it'll have the same end result.
Cool.
>> So center lines are black if
they're partially defined.
The end points in this are blue
because we haven't defined its length.
But we don't need to.
It's not really relevant.
So now, we're going to put the
center point of our arc on this line.
So we've selected it.
Again, hit Control.
Select the line.
Make it coincident.
Now, we know that this arc is
going to be symmetric to the lines.
And now, we're going to
make the endpoint of our arc
and the endpoint of our line coincident.
So I just was holding down
Control, selected both of those,
and I hit merge in the left pane.
And now, we have a completely
symmetric arc on the bottom.
>> So we need to have another one up top.
I'm going to highlight this
just by clicking on it.
And then hit Command C, and then
move the mouse away, Command V.
And now we have another one.
So again, we need to add all of our
relations just to mirror this up top.
And select it, or select
this center point.
Hit Control, select this line,
make them coincident, cool.
I want to just move through this.
All I'm doing now is I'm just
going to merge all the endpoints.
And then one last time.
Cool, so now we have two arcs.
>> But we need to tell SolidWorks
that they are of the same radius.
So we'll select them both and say equal.
Cool.
And now, we will finally
define their radius.
So I believe we said-- I don't
remember what the number was.
I think it was .
3.465.
Yeah 3.465 was our diameter.
But you'll notice that
we're defining the radius.
So what we're going to do
is say 3.465 divided by 2.
The dimension box can understand
algebraic expressions.
You can use parentheses, multiplication,
division, et cetera, et cetera.
So that's all we're
doing here because we
need to divide the diameter
by 2 to get the radius.
Hit Enter.
We're fully defined, we'll
notice that everything
is black except for this center line.
That is fine, doesn't need to be.
So now we have our footprint.
We have the platform that we
will extrude to make the solid.
Then, once we have the solid, we
can add all the other features.
The hole in the bottom, this webbing to
save a little bit of material, and then
this bridge in the
middle that says CS50.
>> So we're going to exit this sketch,
and we're going to extrude it.
SolidWorks is based on
sketches and features.
Once you've created a sketch and
everything is completely defined,
you can exit the sketch and
make a feature out of it.
In this case, we're
going to extrude, we're
going to create material
from the sketch.
But when we do the hole, you'll see
that we create a sketch for the whole
and then make an extruded
cut from the hole.
So if we go over from the
top left and hit Exit Sketch,
we go to features pane, only
most everything is grayed out.
But we do have the option
to extrude boss base, which
is what we're going to select.
>> Once we hit this, you'll notice
that the solid actually comes out.
SolidWorks has some default,
maybe a tenth of an inch,
but we'll define the height.
So we hit extrude boss base.
Now, you'll notice that it's a solid.
And we need to define the
depth, this d1 over here.
So again, we're going to measure
the height using our part here.
We want the height to be
the same height as the arm
here that the part came on so that
it looks clean and does overhang.
There's no need for it.
>> So again, with our calipers,
we just measure here.
This is pretty similar to what
we did before and wiggle it
around a little bit, make sure
you have nice, firm grasp.
This is made out of aluminum, so
it's not going to deflect at all.
And we see that it is 0.751.
Awesome.
So we'll just type in 0.75.
And now, we have our solid.
So this is what will become
the lens support itself.
We have a couple more
features to add in.
>> So before, we were
sketching on the top plane.
But now, we can sketch on
any plane of the solid.
Or we could create our
own plane using what's
called reference geometry, which
is not necessary right now,
but could be later.
So let's just select this plane.
And then we're going to hit-- you'll
notice that this little box pops up
when you move the mouse around.
If you lose it, it's always
available on the top here.
There's this web of a box
with a little arrow beside it.
You'll notice that there is a plane
with an arrow coming out of it.
If you click this, this will make
the view that you're looking at,
the computer's view, normal
to the plane you've selected.
>> So we hit that.
And we have the plane that
we're going to sketch on.
So if we go over to the sketch
box over here we hit sketch,
SolidWorks is going to say, I don't
know which plane to sketch on.
Which one did you intend?
And it won't even let
you sketch anything.
It won't let you do anything.
That's why there's this error message.
So we hit the x.
We need to select the plane
first and then hit sketch.
Now, we're going to go.
It didn't give us any
errors or warnings.
So all we're going to do in this case
is really just to find some webbing.
And then, I made a little
bridge to say CS50.
We can keep that in there.
So one neat little
feature that we can do
is we can unhide the sketch
that we made for the footprint
and use all those
geometries in this sketch.
So in our feature tree, we
have this boss extrude one.
And then, I hit the little
plus arrow underneath it.
And sketch two pops up.
So we can-- it's always a
good idea to label things,
just like when you're writing code.
You want to appropriately
label your variables
so that it's clear
how you're using them.
It's the same case in
SolidWorks where you
want to label all your features so
that you know exactly what they do.
>> So if you select a feature and
then hold your mouse down over it,
it prompts you to rename something.
So we'll call this base.
And then, same thing here, we'll
just call this sketch base.
So by default, once you've exited
a sketch, it becomes hidden.
But you can change this
just by hitting this.
And then, this little box will
pop up with a pair of glasses.
And you hit show, and now
we have everything back.
You can see that there
are endpoints here.
Cool.
>> So now, what we can do is we will
sketch-- we can just hit line here
or even I'm going to just select
all these entities, again,
by holding down Control.
And I'm going to go up
here to offset entities.
So we want to add some wall thickness.
And that can be done by just
taking the base footprint,
and then offsetting
entities on the inside.
>> So then, we'll specify the depth.
So SolidWorks, by default, goes
for the outside, apparently.
You could see this yellow line
around the base of our feature.
So if we just hit reverse, now
it becomes inside, which is cool.
A tenth of an inch sounds fine.
We hit the green arrow.
And we have our dimension down here.
Now typically, if we're defining this
part to be like a load bearing part,
I guess technically it is
varying the load of the lens.
But the plastic that
we're using to print these
is actually pretty strong, so we're just
going to guess on the wall thickness.
A tenth of an inch is plenty, probably
a third of that is really required,
but we'll just add a little
bit more for rigidity.
>> If we were designing it to be
a part on, say, a race car,
we would run it through a computer
simulation called Finite Element
Analysis, FEA, wherein the computer
meshes up our part into arbitrarily
many little mesh segments.
And then, we subject it to
loads and fixtures like saying,
don't let the base move, but subject
the top curved face to a load of 150
Newtons normal to it.
Or I guess it's a curved face,
it can't be normal to it.
But downward, and then it will
tell you when the part will fail
and which areas of the part
are under the most stress.
It's overkill right now.
But we'll just eye it, a
tenth of an inch is plenty.
>> Cool, so now we have all this.
And we're going to add in another
centerline to bisect this part here.
Just the same procedure as before.
I'm going to start to
go a little bit faster
because this is becoming
a little repetitive.
We'll add a point.
That is the midpoint here.
In fact, this is even unnecessary.
>> We can just draw the
centerline from the midpoint.
So we find it.
That yellow box pops up.
So we hover over it.
Draw it across again.
Now, we have this line
is bisecting this line.
This vertical line here.
>> So again, we can offset entities.
We want to.
We're going to create the bridge on
which we will later extrude cut, CS50.
We want to add some thickness to it.
So we hit offset entities, and by
default, it adds a line on one side.
But if we just hit bidirectional,
there's a little check box down here,
it adds two.
And let's make this
a little bit thicker.
So say 0.15, maybe even a
little bit more than that.
So this is 0.2 inches on each
side, so 0.4 inches in total.
Can move the dimensions out of the way
so that we don't clutter the drawing.
That looks good.
>> Typically, when you're
dimensioning a part,
there are seemingly infinitely many
ways to display all the dimensions
on your sketch.
In the interest of not cluttering it,
it's nice to move your dimensions away.
And there are other rules
that kind of follow,
like you don't want them
to crisscross or overlap,
because it becomes ambiguous.
But this is good for now.
So hit the green arrow.
Now, we want to add
in this webbing, which
we're going to do in the same
way with offset entities.
>> So we hit center line.
And I'm just going to draw two
x's in here on the top and bottom.
Here is one.
do the same thing on the bottom.
And you'll notice that
all of these lines
are black because all of the
points, all their endpoints,
are completely defined.
So that's cool.
We don't need to add any more relations.
And let's select them and
hit offset entities again.
And that ought to do it.
You can only do one at
a time, which is fine.
Offset entities, whoa, that looks crazy.
I accidentally selected
more than one thing.
Offset entities, that's weird.
Don't know why it's doing that.
Hm, didn't expect that.
That's fine.
We will just do it by hand.
>> So we will add in-- I'm just
going to draw in some lines
here that we will add
relations to in a bit.
So we want these lines to
be parallel to this line.
So we just hit make parallel.
Then likewise, on the other side, cool.
And we'll just make the endpoints match.
>> AUDIENCE: All of these
varied thicknesses,
is this just experience and insight?
Or is there math that's
behind the choice
of these thicknesses for
the structural integrity?
>> ANSEL DUFF: Yeah, so right now, I'm
just kind of going off of instinct
and eyeing it, guessing.
We had made a version zero prototype.
It's around here, and clear.
And I had guessed a
tenth of an inch, and I
had the idea to just print
one, a dummy, try it out.
Maybe modify a couple of the dimensions,
and then go for the actual part.
But a tenth of an inch was fine.
If we wanted to be really a bit
more thorough, what we could do
is we could calculate the
axial stress under which it's
placed from the weight of a lens.
>> A great engineering practice and
one that is upheld universally
is to design in a safety factor.
So let's say this lens
weighs three pounds.
I just made that up.
But if we weighted this lens,
and it weighs three pounds,
and you design your part to be
able to sustain three pounds,
but buckle after that, then
that's not really great practice
because there's going to be impulse
when you pick the camera up.
This will experience
greater than three pounds.
So you always want to
design your part for greater
than it will actually ever experience.
So typically, a safety factor of
two is fine for something like this.
But honestly, at a 1/10
of an inch wall thickness,
this probably has a
safety factor of like 15.
So right now, we're just
going off of instinct.
>> But if we were to do it
out of a material that's
a little bit easier to work
with, like aluminum or steel,
we could calculate the
stress and then compare that
to that material's yield
stress or ultimate stress.
AUDIENCE: Does this kind of plastic
such numbers associated with it?
Or is it [INAUDIBLE]?
ANSEL DUFF: No, it does.
So what we're using
out of our 3D printer
is PLA filament, which
is like a bioplastic.
And although I haven't
personally looked these up,
I know there are figures available
for yield stress and yield
sheer associated with this plastic.
We did not design for that because
it's actually hollowed out.
The MakerBot software processes
honeycomb, and it adds it in.
So it's not completely solid.
So those calculations would be faulty.
They would not be accurate, unless
we made this completely solid.
But it would take days
to print in that case.
So just in the interest of time, we
let the hollowing happen and test.
>> So now, we're just
going to tell SolidWorks
that these are the same distance away.
So there are two ways of doing this.
One way is to go to Smart Dimension
and dimension both of these lines
and to make them the same number.
That's not a great practice
because down the road,
if we find that this webbing is
too thin, we would have to go
and change eight dimensions just
for one fundamental property, right?
>> If we said that these webs are
buckling, let's double their thickness,
you don't want to have to go
in and modify eight dimensions.
It's like when you're
writing code, if you're
going to be using the
same number over and over
and over again, you define a constant
at the beginning of the file,
and then use that constant throughout.
And then, when it's time to change it,
you only have to change one number.
It's the same principle here.
So our constant is adding relations.
>> So we'll dimension it one time.
So we'll go Smart
Dimension, we can go 0.05.
And I'm making this half
of our 100 thou thickness
because there'll be two sides to it.
So we define it once, and then we add
center lines to make the relations.
So we go here.
We make two.
And then, we're just going
to make these equal length.
The dimension will be taken care of.
So highlight both, make them
equal, and now this line is black.
So we'll do that again.
Just going to go a little bit faster.
>> You'll notice that when I'm hovering the
mouse over the line, it becomes orange.
And then, I click.
You can be sure that the line is--
these two lines are coincident.
They meet at this end point
because it was highlighted orange
when we selected it.
So make these parallel,
likewise for this piece.
We're going to do the same thing with
our center lines, zoom in a little bit.
Just select these.
Selected a face there,
that's why it turned blue.
>> And I'm going to go back to the
original and make them all equal.
So we dictated the length of this
with this dimension, 0.05 inches.
And because we made these all equals,
SolidWorks just figured the rest out.
I'm trying to think.
>> One option is we could
take all these, in fact,
we probably didn't even need this x.
And we could mirror them.
You could manually redraw them.
But it's a bit redundant because
the features are the same.
So what we will do
is-- actually won't be
able to mirror it because
these are not mirror images.
Whoops.
>> So what I was thinking is this
bulges out, and this bulges in.
So this is concave and this is convex.
If they were both
convex or both concave,
you could highlight all of these,
mirror them about the center line,
and then everything
would be taken care of.
But if we were to do
that, this line would
translate to being a
convex line down here.
But we need it to be concave.
So that's no good.
We'll just draw it in by hand.
Adding in the cross of our center line.
Great.
Go back, select actual
line, can zoom in.
>> In SolidWorks, you can just
zoom by scrolling on your mouse.
And then, the middle click, so if
you have a mouse with a jog wheel,
if you hold down that
jog wheel, that will
allow you to change
your view orientation.
Some mice, like mine here, they
do not come with jog wheels.
It's a touch pad on top effectively.
So I've configured my mouse using
a program called Magic Press, which
is a free Mac preference
program to be able to just hold
two fingers down onto it and
move the part around for view.
So if you're using a Mac and running
a Windows virtual machine like I am,
I've seen a lot of people
with the same Magic Mouse,
I would recommend Magic Press.
It's free.
So you can make these parallel.
Oops.
Not what I want.
>> So sometimes, when you're
working at an obscure angle,
it can be kind of hard
to see the relation.
So we're just going to select this
little box here and then go back
to the normal.
And that'll make everything
a lot easier to look at.
So sometimes, the part
will be really far away.
If you want to zoom in and have
it fit your screen if you just
hit F on your keyboard, that zooms in.
You can see it's kind of far away
because these center lines are
a bit longer than they need to be.
But if we just shorten these down a
bit, like so, and then hit F again,
now zoom in.
So we make these parallel.
Awesome.
Do likewise here.
>> And then, we'll add in those
little support structures,
these center lines to dictate the
depth or the thickness of these lines.
You'll notice that when
I'm drawing, SolidWorks
creates that yellow dashed line.
That dashed line is normal
or orthogonal to the line
that this line that
we're drawing started on.
So if you follow that
dashed yellow line,
you can be sure that it
is in fact orthogonal.
We'll do it again.
>> Just for good measure,
we can double check
once we're done sketching
just by selecting a line,
and all the relations come up
here, perpendicular, awesome.
We'll make these all equal length.
Select them all.
Then, we're going to go back to the
original line that we dimensioned.
Select that, hit equal,
and then we zoom out.
These lines are all black.
Cool.
>> So we are ready to exit our
sketch and cut out these webs.
So we hit Exit Sketch notice that
the sketch is still highlighted here
because we're going to
do something with it.
Now, if I go to Features and I hit
Extrude Cut, which is now an option,
it's going to freak
out because it doesn't
know which sketch we're
going to use as the base.
So leave that.
We can hide this.
We don't have any need for it.
>> So we select the sketch
that we just made.
We can even label it.
We'll call it webbing,
or just web sketch.
Now that it's highlighted,
we can extrude
it, which is-- we don't
want to create material.
We want to cut material away.
So we'll go and we'll
use an extruded cut.
So now, there are a lot of
geometries happening in our sketch.
>> We need to tell SolidWorks which pieces,
which triangles and rectangles we
want to cut.
So if we go down here and we hit
Selected Contours and highlight
this box, it becomes blue.
And then, you can click
on different parts.
I'll just click on
everything we want gone.
And it will cut everything
away that is highlighted.
So there's the option now of
how deep do we want to cut.
We could cut partially.
We don't have to cut
all the way through.
We could do like 0.751 divided by 2.
This will cut halfway through.
You can see in the preview there.
But that's not what we want.
We want to go all the way through.
>> So this little dialogue
box, we just click.
And select Up To Next, and
that'll cut all the way through.
Hit the green arrow.
And our sketch is still
highlighted, but if you click away,
now we have the webbing done.
So you'll notice if you look
kind of closely at this part
that the corners are
rounded off internally.
That's a feature called a fillet.
What a fillet does is it eliminates
what are called stress concentrations.
If you have really sharp points
at any place in your part,
whether it's made of some composite
or steel or aluminum or what have you,
really sharp points can
cause stress concentrations
when they're subjected to loads.
>> So if we were to really
push this part, it
would likely break at one
of these really sharp nodes.
So to combat that, we
use what are called
fillets, which is just really
gentle rounding in there.
So we go to this fillet feature.
We have a dialogue box.
I find it helpful to select
this full preview option.
And all we have to do is just click on
a line, and it creates a fillet for us.
So it defaulted to having the
radius be a tenth of an inch.
That's a little extreme.
So we'll do maybe 20 thou.
That's a little small.
Split the difference, say.
Not split the difference.
Let's do 50 thou.
That looks good.
So now, we're just going to
select all these other fillets.
Kind of just fly through this.
>> So once we complete the part,
I'll go back and show you
how painless it is to
modify a dimension.
Like I said, it's helpful to
print out kind of a dummy version,
test it, see if it's strong enough.
Maybe you want to make the letters
larger or something of the like.
Oops, I selected a face accidentally.
We don't want that.
Select this line, one more time.
That was the wrong one.
If it's hard for you
to deselect that line,
you can go over to the box here that's
listing everything, right click,
and then say delete.
Do not say Clear Selection
because that'll delete every line,
unless that's what you want to do.
Cool, just one more to god.
Oh, missed a couple at the top.
All right.
>> AUDIENCE: There's more up top, the
left triangle at the top and bottom.
>> ANSEL DUFF: Oh, god.
That is code red.
All right, now we have our fillets.
Now, it looks a little weird.
They look a little bit
bigger than they need to be.
So if we want to adjust that,
let's just label this web fillet.
We can right click on this, and this
box pops up, and we hit Edit Feature.
And we just have to change one number.
Let's do maybe say 30 thou.
And they become smaller
and get the green arrow.
So if we wanted to change all those
features, there were a lot of them,
you just had to change one number.
And that's really helpful for us.
>> Something that I've not yet done
is save my part, not a bad idea
during the middle of it.
We'll just hit Save As.
We'll call it lens support 2,
since I've already made one.
And now, we want to just add in
letters, and then we're ready to go.
>> So to do that, we're going to make
ourselves normal to this plane again.
Now that it's selected, we
can go and sketch on it.
And now, we're going to add letters in.
So part is actually upside down.
This probably wasn't a
good face to sketch on.
I'm going to sketch on this one.
So sketch, SolidWorks
has a letters feature.
But we need to orient
the letters in space.
And that's done, again
by making a center line.
In case you haven't noticed,
that's kind of the theme,
to make center lines for
anything you might need it for.
>> So for now, let's just add a
Smart Dimension from this line.
We'll say 0.01 inches.
I'm just eyeing that.
We're going to go back and
change that in a second.
But for now, it just
constrains this line in space.
Cool.
So now, we go to our
little font feature here.
It's that big A. So we just hit that.
That's A for Ansel.
So we type CS50.
Cool.
But we need to type the curve
that it's going to sit on.
So just click on that line, awesome.
Now, it's a little bit small here.
We want to make it a little bit larger.
So by default, it uses
the document font,
which is just defined in
some property list somewhere.
>> So we'll deselect that,
hit the font button,
and make this a little bit bigger.
I like to use this
units option because it
allows you to specify
the height in inches.
So I believe before we had made
this bridge 0.4 of an inch high,
so perhaps making the letters 3/10
of an inch tall, it'll look big.
That's pretty good.
Get the green arrow.
Make this a little bit smaller.
Let's halve it, so we
could go divide by 2.
And then, we'll just drag this dot
over to where I think it looks good.
This is what we call a code orange.
The letters look a little bit too big.
So we're going to select them.
Go back to font, and let's make them
a quarter of an inch tall instead
of 3/10.
Make them a little smaller,
move them into position.
Cool.
That looks pretty good.
We'll add a couple,
say, maybe bigger there.
>> SolidWorks is really interpretive
in this dimension box.
I had mentioned before that you
can use algebraic expressions.
But let's say we wanted
to be in millimeters.
We could say make this 5 millimeters,
and it will understand it.
So it'll automatically
convert it to inches.
So 5 millimeters, SolidWorks
tells us, is 0.19685039 inches.
So we'll go back to inches.
We'll say 0.07 inches.
My program is set up
to default to inches.
Everything we do in the
States is in inches.
But if you want to convert something,
there's no need to go to Google
and convert it because
SolidWorks will do it for you.
>> So this is just about centered.
If we really wanted to
be very, very precise,
we could measure the
width of the letters
and then center it against
the center line of the piece.
But that's kind of overkill here.
We'll just visually center it for now.
That looks almost there.
We'll drag it over a little bit.
Sometimes, when you want to drag a
point by a very small amount, if you
click on it and try to drag it a
little bit, it won't do anything.
So it's nice to move it far away, and
then come back close to where you were.
>> So hit F to bring us back out.
That looks pretty good.
We'll hit the green arrow.
Oh, wait a minute,
somebody said in the back.
The sketch is still blue.
So what are we going to do?
You'll notice that we have put
all the letters on this line.
But we haven't constrained them
in this dimension, left to right.
So the way we do that, this
is the point that we're
moving that dictates all letters,
we will fix this point in space.
And it will not move.
So in our pane left
here-- in fact, we'll
deselect it-- we click on this point.
This point dictates how the
letters are placed left to right,
like I had mentioned.
>> Select this point.
We see all the relations
over here, it's an empty box.
Nobody's home.
We hit fix.
Boom.
Oh my gosh.
What happened?
We have over defined the sketch.
So what this means is you
have multiple relations,
multiple dimensions
referring to the same entity.
So for example, if we had
made two lines parallel,
and then we added a dimension up top
to say that these lines are one inch
apart, then we add another dimension
at the bottom to say these line are two
inches apart, SolidWorks is going
to scream at us and give us the same
warning because you can't-- both
dimensions are referring to the same
entity.
Somehow, we have done that here.
>> So we can let's just rebuild it.
If at any point you want to rebuild
your sketch, or you change a dimension
and it didn't take, if you just hit this
little stoplight at the top here next
to the mouse, hit that,
SolidWorks will process it.
>> So this sketch has a little
yield flag next to it,
which means something's wrong.
So if we right click
and hit what's wrong,
we get a really unhelpful error message.
This sketch is over defined.
Consider deleting some-- so that
didn't tell us anything new.
We'll go back to sketching it.
And what happened?
>> Oh, we can't fix it in
space because it's already
defined to be 70 thou off of this line.
So if we just delete this and refix
this point, it should be fixed in space.
So I know the letters are still
blue, but they are fixed in space.
That I'm sure of.
So we'll just move on.
>> Now, we're going to cut these
letters into the material.
If we wanted to, we could
cut them all the way through.
But that might compromise
our part structurally.
Not really, but it's not really great
practice to add an aesthetic feature
or have an aesthetic feature
be structurally compromising.
So we'll just cut them to be
maybe 10 thou deep or 100 thou,
depending on how it looks.
So we highlight our sketch.
We'll label it because
we're good people.
Computer froze for a second there.
We'll call this letters sketch.
And now, we will do an extruded cut.
And we can change how deep they go.
>> So right now, they are halfway through.
That seems a little much.
Let's do 200 thou.
That looks pretty did.
Hit the green arrow.
And we are cooking, ready to go.
So there are a lot of things that could
be the next step in our manufacture.
We've completely designed a part.
We can build it in varying ways.
But what we first want to do is double
check that all of our measurements
are right.
It's very painless to
change the dimensions
when you're in this build state.
The part is completely
defined, and you just
have to change maybe a number
here or a number there.
But it's not that fun to build
it and then measure it or try
to fit it and realize that
you messed something up.
We're not actually going to manufacture
this part right now because it
takes a very, very long time to print.
But we would go back and
double measure everything.
Measure twice, cut once, and
ensure that everything is correct.
Let's hypothetically say that we
messed one of the measurements up.
>> Let's say that the webs are too thin.
They were buckling and we
want to make them thicker.
It was kind of a pain to add in
all those dimensions before, all
those relations, and make all
those lines of equal length.
But now, if we want to
make the webs thicker,
we can just go-- oops,
forgot to label this guy.
We'll call this web cut.
And this is letters cut.
>> You'll notice that we have a
very neatly organized tree.
In fact, if we're going to make this
part, we want to learn more about it,
we need to define its material.
So in this material box, we'll right
click, and then hit Edit Material.
And SolidWorks gives us a very long
list of things that we can choose from.
Let's say we're going to
make it out of aluminum.
We'll do 6061 P6, that's
a tempering rating.
We'll hit apply, close.
And now it's out of aluminum.
It looks slightly brighter.
Doesn't really do much for us.
>> But it allows us to measure some
really interesting or cool aspects
about this part specifically
being made out of aluminum.
For example, if we go to the
Evaluate tab and hit Mass Properties,
we see that the part
weights 0.09 pounds.
Volume is not going to
change based on material.
But weight is dictated by
which material you use.
It's pretty cool.
If we were to run a stress simulation,
the material that you choose
will drastically alter the results.
So that's pretty cool.
>> If we wanted to make
it look different, we
could pop out this tab here just by
hitting these double arrows and right
click here and say appearance.
And then, we can change to make
it blue, whatever you want.
And then, in a final
render, if we wanted
to make an actual render of this part,
we can choose its surface finish.
So a lot of times,
you'll design your parts.
They have this flat gray or
flat black aesthetic to them.
But that just lightens
the load on SolidWorks
so that you're not using
superfluous graphics power
to render your part while
you're designing it.
But if we did want to
do a render, we would
have to define the surface finish.
So let's just say that it's
polished aluminum for now.
Notice that polished
aluminum pops up over here.
Hit the green arrow.
Cool, that took.
And let's just change this
thickness of these webs.
So all we have to do is go over to our
very neatly organized feature tree.
And we see web cut.
Expand that.
Click on the web sketch.
And then, we're just going
to change one number.
>> So let's change it to instead
of being 50 thou on each side,
so 100 thou total, let's
make it 80 thou total.
Cool.
You see the webs got
a little bit skinnier.
Awesome.
So we just changed all those
features just by one number.
We changed the thickness.
SolidWorks automatically recalculates
the fillets to make them fit.
It changes all the geometries.
And it works because we had
defined them to be all symmetrical
and all defined off of one dimension.
Like I said before, it's
analogous to defining
a constant when you're writing code.
>> AUDIENCE: Does it work if
you use any TrueType font,
or are you limited to
what they [INAUDIBLE]?
>> ANSEL DUFF: It works
off of your system font,
so if we go back to our letters cut,
we had just gone with the default font.
If we hit Edit Sketch, zoom in a little
bit, double click on the letters.
If I can do that.
Take a second to trace them out.
And hit Font again.
So we have a list of fonts here.
And those are system fonts.
If you want a specialty font,
and it's not on this list,
you're going to need to
install it on your system.
Just a little bit of Googling
around on how to do that on Windows.
>> AUDIENCE: Also, does this thing know
what font size or changes are not
going to be [INAUDIBLE]?
ANSEL DUFF: Yeah.
So the question was how do we know
how thick or thin to make the fonts?
How will the machine be able
to handle really thin features?
So of course, it's going to
vary from machine to machine.
But just by reading the
spec sheet of our printer,
we know that it has a
resolution of about 4 thou, four
thousandths of an inch.
So we want to make all the
features be well beyond that.
So if you were to make a font that
was, say, 10 thou tall, that's
like two sheets of paper, you
wouldn't be able to read it obviously.
But just hypothetically,
if we wanted to make
a font that was on the order
of the accuracy of the machine,
it would look horrible.
So in our case, we know that
we're well beyond the accuracy
of the machine in terms of the
ratio of the height of our font,
or even the thickness of
any feature in the font
to how accurate the machine
is capable of being.
>> So we're in the clear here.
But if hypothetically you
were using a machine that
had an accuracy of maybe 250
thou, like a quarter of an inch,
then our font would look
really crappy because it's
on the same order of how
accurate the machine is.
Another thing that we
need to pay attention to,
and this is specific to 3D printing, is
how thick are our layers going to be.
So I'll go over to MakerBot settings in
a little bit and we can play with this
and talk more exhaustively
about it in a second.
But the way that the
3D printer works is it
extrudes filament in a
very fine thread almost.
And if we make the thread or
the filament strand really,
really large, then it's going
to look kind of blotchy and not
that clear when we actually print.
>> So again, just as a
rule of thumb, you want
the size of your fonts
or all the features
to be well beyond the
order of the thread size.
Yeah, so Exit Sketch.
And it takes.
If we were to change the font,
again, we can just hit this.
And it will recalculate
it automatically for us.
So we'll go font here.
Choose Comic Sans.
Great, looks atrocious.
Hit the green arrow.
Exit the sketch.
And you'll notice that
it still looks so bad.
Wow.
I can't even look at that.
I'm just going to undo that.
Great.
It will recalculate all the
curves and make the cut.
>> So cool.
We are good to go.
So now, the next step.
You're going to want to grab
a Snickers at this point
because we've been working for a while.
It's a good idea to take a breather.
So what is the next step in manufacture?
We could 3D print it.
We could mill it.
Those are the two popular options.
If we were to mill it,
we would have to write
what's called G code or CAM,
which is going to take a while,
and we're not going to do.
All that does is it tells a tool,
like an N mill, which is basically
a fancy drill bit, where
to move around this piece
to create all these features.
Some things are impossible
to do with a mill.
>> For example, if we go to our fillet
here, should be in web fillet,
and we suppress that, which is done just
by hitting this little downward arrow,
all the fillets go away.
We have all these really sharp points.
This is a horrible design practice,
and you should never do this.
But hypothetically, if you did want to
design a really sharp corner in here,
you could not create that corner
with an N mill of finite diameter.
You cannot have-- you can
conceptualize it as a fancy drill bit.
You can't have a drill
bit moving around and just
bumping off the bottom of that corner
node and leaving a very hard corner.
That's just impossible.
>> So those are things to be aware of.
And when you create CAM, those
will all become apparent.
But just things to be aware of.
Luckily, the 3D printer
is really cool because it
can create really obscure geometries
and really obscure fixtures.
So we're in the clear here, but it's
nice to think about those things.
So one last thing we want to
add in is a hole on the bottom.
Like I mentioned before, there's
a mounting hole in our piece here.
And that's how we bolt it in.
>> When I made the version zero,
I did not CAD in that hole.
I just went and took a Sharpie
and held it up and marked it
and drilled it by hand.
That was kind of a pain, and not
really excited about doing that again,
so we'll just CAD it in.
So here's a really exciting time because
we need to add in a reference plane
because, shock, you cannot
sketch on a curved face.
Something that you cannot do.
This face is curved.
We had provided it with a radius before.
I'm going to move this
dimension out of the way.
You cannot sketch on it.
>> If we select it and try
to hit sketch, oh my gosh,
cannot sketch on a non-planar face.
Wow, good thing your buddy
Ansel told you about that.
And he also taught you how
to create a reference plane.
So we select this.
We hit Reference Geometry, Plane.
Now, we have a plane that
is tangent to our face.
Or maybe we don't.
That's not good.
I don't know why it's doing that.
>> So we need to-- if we were to just
select this face and create tangency,
the plane could be at
infinitely many angles
while still being tangent to that face.
So we need to constrain it
again using a second plane.
So I had selected the
side of our face here.
And SolidWorks defaulted
to perpendicularity.
But you could select that yourself,
and it would give the same result.
>> So all we've done is
just define this plane
that is tangent to our
bottom face here but then
orthogonal to the side of the part.
So when we create our
hole, our hole is going
to extrude normal to the
plane, which is going
to be parallel to the side of the part.
That's what we want.
If we were to create tangency
on a different plane,
then perhaps the hole would be at
an angle, and nothing would line up.
So this is a nice,
simple example for us.
So we just hit normal to, now we're
normal to the bottom of the part,
and now we can go through the
same procedure of CADing up a hole
and extruding it.
>> So again, we'll just
create a circle here.
A better idea would be-- we're
not technically sketching
right now, which is why
SolidWorks just yelled at us.
It's kind of like your mom, yelling
at you to clean up the room.
So let's sketch here,
add in some center lines.
I don't know why it
doesn't want me to sketch.
Oh, we forgot to select the plane
that we're going to sketch on.
So let's rename our plane bottom plane,
hit Sketch, make a center line here.
Something that's really cool is
even though we're normal to this
and we haven't unlocked
or unhidden any sketches,
SolidWorks will still allow us to
create a sketch that is making relations
to features of the part that
we did not tell it to do.
>> So you'll notice, when I hold
the pencil over the corner
here, that little orange bubble pops up.
We can create a relation
to the corner of the part.
But we didn't tell SolidWorks
that we want it to do that.
So I think that's super cool.
So we'll just make a
center line up top here.
Make another one down the center.
Uh-oh.
I did not do it off the midpoint.
That is offensive.
All right, go down the middle here.
>> It's vertical.
Cool.
It's all black, so we're good to go.
We'll make a circle.
And dimension its diameter.
I'm just going to arbitrarily say
0.10 inches, a tenth of an inch.
Everything's bolted together, so we
don't have anything to measure off of.
But we would, if this were threaded,
you could stick several different screws
in there and then just
find which matched.
But it's not just a clearance hole.
So there are two
different types of holes,
threaded or tapped holes, that will
accept threads, accept a screw.
And those will not be able to move.
That's how you bolt things together.
Or there are clearance
holes, which are larger
than the biggest
diameter of the threads.
>> And that allows threads to
just pass right on through.
So the way our fixture
works here is that we
have a clearance hole in the metal.
And then, another
clearance hole in the part.
And then, just a nut on top.
You could go in and measure with
calipers using the interior prongs here
what the diameter is.
But everything's bolted together,
so we're not going to do that.
We'll just set it at 1/10
of an inch arbitrarily.
Then, you would measure this height.
I'll just set it at 0.250.
>> Again, this is arbitrary.
But you would ideally measure
that and be good to go.
So hit the green arrow.
Exit the sketch.
Sketch is done.
Now, we're going to make it into
a feature by hitting extrude cut.
We want it to only go through the
first layer, so we hit Up To Next.
Hit the green arrow.
Now cool.
So another cool thing, I'm just going
to hide this plane because it's not
doing anything for us right now.
>> So another cool thing is that
we did not tell SolidWorks
how deep we wanted that hole to be.
We just said Up To Next, which means
that there are many, many layers here.
There's one, two, three, four, five
layers that it could have cut through.
But just by saying Up To Next, it knew
to only cut through the first one.
If we were to say Through
All, hit the green arrow,
it sketches through everything.
You can see daylight on
the other side of it.
That's not what we want.
So Up To Next.
There are a lot of options here,
but Up To Next is what we want.
Cool.
So now our part is completely
done, and it is time to machine it.
So like I said, we're going
to step through doing this
with MakerBot 3D printer.
But you can do it with anything.
So we'll go here.
We're going to save our
part as a .stl file.
So we do Save As, lend
support to, and select .stl.
Hit Save.
I'm actually going to save
this in my Downloads folder.
Hit Save.
SolidWorks prompts us.
Do you want this to be an STL?
Hit Yes.
Cool.
And now, we are ready to fire up
to MakerBot desktop application.
>> So let's do that.
All right, ready to go.
So at this point, I always like
to view the plate from the top.
It's nice to be on top.
So we'll just go here.
Add file.
We're going to go to our downloads.
I think we called it lens support 2.
So here we go.
Open it up.
It is on our platform.
>> So this is kind of an impractical
way for us to print the part.
If we zoom in a little
bit here, you'll notice
that the arc is touching the base.
So the 3D printer is going to try
to figure out a way to print this.
But it's going to freak out
unless you add supports to it.
But that's kind of a headache.
>> The easy way to do it
is just to select turn.
The part is selected because
it's highlighted in yellow.
Turn, and then we're going
to want to go-- whoops.
We're just going to
push it back 90 degrees.
Hit Lay Flat.
Lay Flat ensures that its
bottom face is touching
the bottom face of the build plate.
And we're good to go.
So our maker bot is
not right now connected
to the network for some reason.
But that's OK.
We can just hit Export Print File.
It'll take a second to process.
>> And you can put it on
a flash drive and then
plug that flash drive into the printer.
So it's a good idea sometimes to
mess around with the settings.
When you first open this box up,
it'll say-- it has a couple presets.
Do you want low resolution,
high resolution?
But we can actually change these
at a much more granular level.
So I'll just walk through a couple of
these parameters and what they mean.
>> Infill is percent of the volume of
the part is being actually printed.
So if infill were at 100%,
everything would be printed.
It wouldn't do any null hollow
features, no honeycombing.
It would print a completely solid part.
It would take an eternity.
So we will set it as 15% here.
I think the default that
MakerBot comes with is like 10%.
But 15% is fine.
If you print the part and then try
it out and it buckles or breaks
or it seems kind of weak, then
you can just bump that number up
and it'll be a lot stronger.
The plastic filament itself
is actually pretty strong,
so just bump that number up.
It'll make it a bit stronger.
>> Number of shells is
how many shells on top
of the honeycomb, how many layers
on top of the honeycomb it prints.
I set it to five to give
it a nice finish quality.
And then, layer height is the diameter
of the thread that is being extruded.
So right now, 0.2 millimeters,
a fifth of a millimeter
is what it's printing at.
But I think it goes all the way down
to, wow, a hundredth of a millimeter.
That is tiny.
So that will take-- if we set this
to 100% infill with five shells
at 0.01 millimeter layer height, hit
Save Settings, and then Export Print
File, you'll see the expected
time is going to be huge.
We'll just let it process because I'm
curious to see how large it would be.
>> I think this part using 15% infill,
0.2 millimeter layer, and five shells
took about two hours to print.
But you can see it's even
taking a really long time
to prepare and to create the
actual MakerBot file for it.
>> So something that's MakerBot about
specific is that from this desktop
application, it will export
in a .makerbot file format.
That is only file format
that the machine will accept.
If you try to give it an STL, it
will freak out, maybe explode.
So always a good idea to export
in a .makerbot file format.
So that's going to process.
>> In the meantime, let's just hop back to
SolidWorks here and look at our part.
So this was kind of a
nice example of a part
because it allows you to design for
something that already exists, right?
We had to measure all the
supports that already exist.
In reality, there are a
lot more considerations
that you need to take into
account for when designing a part.
For example, I won't do an in depth
demo of this little phone dock,
but there were a couple
more considerations
that we needed to take into account.
>> So you'll notice that
when the phone is sitting,
and I'll try to give
you a side angle there.
When the phone is
sitting in the dock, it
is kind of raked back by a little bit.
I think I set that at 15 degrees.
That's somewhat arbitrary.
But as it's raked back, the
center of gravity of the phone
is going to be displaced
from its base meaning that,
if when designing the part we had just
cut it off and not had this back panel,
but it was only this much,
then when we put the phone in,
it would've just toppled over.
>> That's because the center
of gravity of the whole part
of the phone, the heavy part,
would extend proud of the base.
And it will create a tipping
moment, and it'll fall over.
So a way to combat that in design
is to just make a quick mock up
of your phone, which will
take like two seconds.
We'll just make a new part.
Make the fastest mock up of an iPhone.
So let's make a rectangle
on the top plane.
Here, create, define these.
Just going to measure
quickly with calipers.
The width is 2.308.
And then, the height is 4.880.
And then, the depth, this is the number
that everybody cares about in tech,
0.30.
I have a screen protector on it, 0.303.
>> Cool.
Extrude it.
And then, I'll add some fillets.
It's a little bit trickier
to measure the fill diameter.
You can use a gauge, but I
don't have one on me right now.
We'll just eye it, and that'll be fine.
That looks about right, just visually.
This is like a dummy phone that
we just made in like a minute.
So we'll save this as iPhone dummy.
And now, we can create an
assembly with our dock and measure
how far the middle of our
phone is from the base.
So I had mentioned before that we
create parts, assemblies, and drawings.
Drawings are not really
something that you'll
mess with unless you're designing
parts that will be made out
of house at a machine
shop or what have you.
And it's a little bit more involved
to properly dimension a drawing
and make sure that every
dimension is clear.
And you also have to add tolerances,
and that gets a little bit more
involved, so we'll just
kind of gloss over that.
But let's say we want to make an
assembly with the phone dock that I've
already designed and our dummy phone.
>> So we've already saved this.
Let's go up to File.
Make Assembly From Part.
And then, we're going to
hit Add and iPhone dummy.
Also, nice to just select
this graphics preview.
That'll show you the actual part itself.
And then, insert another component will
browse for the iPhone dock, CS50 dock.
Cool.
So now, it's a nice sanity
check just to double check
that the phone will actually fit
in the dock that we've designed
and how it will look.
So let's make this face coincident
with the bottom of this face.
And these relations are all handled
through what are called mates
in assemblies wherein
you have two parts,
and you need to join them by a
list of defined joining features.
>> So for example, we need to put our
phone which is being currently blown up,
call you later!
In a dock, and we need to say
that the bottom face of our phone
is coincident with the inside
bottom face of the dock.
And then, this will be centered inside.
We've given a little bit of a tolerance
so that it's not a super tight fit.
And that will completely define it.
We'll make these two coincident.
Select mate up here, and it defaults
to coincident, but it's inverted.
So if we just hit this little
button down here, it'll flip it.
We hit the green arrow.
So looking good.
I've actually forgotten what the
tolerance was on the spacing.
Like I said, I gave it a
little bit of extra space
because it doesn't really
want to be a tight fit.
So what we can do is measure
the difference between them
and then split the difference.
>> So we can use the measure
tool in SolidWorks.
We go up here to evaluate, measure.
Little tape measure comes
up and that annoying window
in the middle of your part.
And we're going to select these two
faces, they're highlighted in green.
And their distance is 2.36 inches.
So I think we said 2.36.
We'll remember that.
This was 2.308.
So we'll just split that
difference with space.
Whoa.
So we got a mate.
Select these two faces.
Coincident.
Whoa, gotta add a little
bit of space in there.
So it was, I think, 2.36.
We'll make this in parentheses to be
clearer, minus 2.308 divided by 2.
That's splitting the
difference for space.
Good to go.
But if we eye it, it looks
like the phone is actually
extended in this
direction beyond the dock.
So we just need to flip it.
It made very little difference.
Can't really see all that well.
Hit the green arrow.
And then finally, we'll make this back
face coincident to the back there.
>> Realistically, there's also a
tolerance for, you can see there,
space in the front.
We could split that difference.
But it's just the same
procedure, so it's redundant.
Cool, so let's look at it from the side.
Mate is still selected there.
>> If we were to draw a line
normal to this in the middle,
you'll actually see that the
center of gravity of the phone
is somewhere in this region.
It's in the middle of the base.
We purposefully extended the base well
beyond where the center of gravity
falls such that it will be able
to sustain a tipping moment,
like when you place
your phone in the dock.
You don't have to do it super gently.
You can just put it in.
It doesn't fall over.
>> If the distance between where the
center of gravity falls on the base
and how far we extend the
base back was really small,
it would take a very, very small
tipping moment to actually tip it over.
So that would just be very
impractical because you
would have to very delicately
place your phone inside.
So I just added maybe a
quarter of an inch or half
inch beyond what we needed.
I did not calculate the required
tipping moment to take this over.
I think that might be a little overkill.
>> But physically, that's
how it would be done.
Cool.
So now, we have this assembly saved.
You could make a more detailed
iPhone if you wanted dimensions.
I had made this little
extrusion for the Home button,
and this is iPhone specific.
But if your phone's in
the dock, you can just
turn it on without having to take
it out and look at all the text
messages that you're getting
or SnapChats, my preference.
>> So another assumption, viewers at home
might be thinking, Ansel, you idiot!
You assumed that the phone was
uniformly distributed mass wise,
like that mass inside the boundaries
of the phone is uniformly distributed.
That is not the case.
But I think that's a fine assumption.
So we can save this assembly.
We'll call it iPhone in dock.
We're good to go.
>> So you can create really complicated
or ornate, involved assemblies
from many, many parts.
Just know that each part has a certain
number of fixtures and lines associated
with it.
So if you have an assembly
with a lot of parts
and you want to move it around and
measure and do a lot of things,
it can become laggy depending on
how powerful your computer is.
Just something to be
aware of that will happen.
>> So that is kind of an intro to CAD.
The takeaways, I would say, are
definitely add relations everywhere.
You will kick yourself
in the rump if you don't.
It's very painful to go back later
and change redundant dimensions.
It's useless, right?
You always want to dimension everything
such that you dimension one number,
and then add relations from that number.
That's a huge takeaway.
Just being clean, just like when you're
writing code, being clean and labeling
everything.
Labeling your features-- you'll notice
that when we made this little lens
support, everything is labeled.
If you don't make this in house
and you ship it to somebody,
most places, maybe 95% of
machine shops or whatever,
will take a SolidWorks
part file, you don't even
have to make drawings for it,
you just send them this file.
And they'll be able to get every
measurement they need off of this file.
And it's a lot easier for them to work
with if everything is neatly organized.
You can even add folders.
We can select the bottom feature,
hit Shift, or rather hold down Shift,
and select the top.
And everything in the
middle becomes selected.
And then right click adds a new folder.
We'll call it awesome folder.
And now, everything is in a folder.
Things like that, just making
everything very neat and organized,
another takeaway.
>> And then ultimately,
being very explicit.
So there are relations between
something that you've already defined
and other things that are
related to it, but then there
are also dimension relations.
So it's really important to
be explicit and make sure
that everything in your sketch is
completely black before you move on.
So at this point, I'm going to
open the floor up to questions,
and we can start to talk a
little bit more about that.
And then, once questions are done,
I'll show you the render process pretty
quickly wherein we can generate a
really realistic looking image of this.
When you're looking at this in CAD, it
just looks kind of a dull gray blob.
But when you do a render, it will
be very, very realistic looking.
So questions?
>> AUDIENCE: MakerBot stuff?
>> ANSEL DUFF: Any other questions?
The MakerBot is, no fault of
our own, actually, no, it's
definitely fault of our own.
We have lost a couple sheets,
the tape sheets on the bottom.
So once we get those in,
we'll be able to print again.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ANSEL DUFF: Oh, what's that?
Oh, yeah.
I thought you were talking
about the actual MakerBot.
76%, wow.
It's going so slowly.
I thought you meant can we print yet.
AUDIENCE: You put together
the tutorial online.
Does that include the best resources
for people to remember what to click
and how to do some of the
things you went through today?
ANSEL DUFF: Yes.
So there is-- the MakerBot tutorial,
is that what you're referring to?
>> AUDIENCE: The one you
put on the website.
>> ANSEL DUFF: Yeah, this one.
So this is MakerBot specific.
This is not SolidWorks specific.
I hope that this video will be
available in high resolution
as a reference to the syntax and
the GUI associated with SolidWorks.
But the tutorials, I think, are super
helpful as far as getting started goes.
So when I hit New, or even use a hot
key for that, but if we go to File, New,
we get this prompt box where
we would typically select part.
But if we hit this
tutorials box, then we
are venturing into the
world of the tutorial.
>> So this is how I learned SolidWorks,
was doing a bunch of these tutorials.
In fact, if you take
CS 51, which is kind
of the intro to computer
and machine design class,
they will require, I
think, the first p-set zero
is doing all these tutorials.
They're super helpful.
They're quick.
You follow along in your own time.
They're a good way to
learn the commands.
I know I was starting to go a
little bit quickly towards the end.
>> AUDIENCE: Do they have cheat
sheets or PDFs you've come across?
ANSEL DUFF: Yeah, so there is a page.
I'll put it on the staff site.
There is a page with a bunch
of hot keys for SolidWorks.
SolidWorks is also super configurable.
Like, you can change
just about everything.
If we go back to the main page--
I'm just going to cancel this.
If we go back to the main page, if you
don't like this toolbar being there,
you can drag it and put off to the side.
I'll put it back up top, because
I think it's the cleanest.
You can change just about everything.
If you want everything to be in
millimeters, you can change that.
You'll notice, when we were
dimensioning something,
let's go back here, that
everything's to two decimal places.
That's rubbish.
Let's make it to three.
We'll go to Document
Properties up here, which
is two icons over from the stop light.
Document Properties,
Dimensions, and then we
set this to three decimal places.
Hit OK.
Everything changes to
three decimal places.
You can customize up the wazoo.
>> But the biggest thing, I think the
most useful user aspect of SolidWorks
are hotkeys, just like
many programs out there.
I've been using them a lot,
mainly holding down Control
to add relations, Shift to highlight
multiple things, and F to fit,
like if we zoom out and then hit
F. It fits the part in our view.
But there are many, many,
many, many more hotkeys.
And I will put the page on the
staff site that lists all them,
and they're super useful.
And just little shortcuts
like double clicking
when you're drawing a line to exit.
Any other questions?
>> AUDIENCE: Where do you [INAUDIBLE]?
ANSEL DUFF: That's hidden.
That is hidden.
>> AUDIENCE: Why is the MakerBot
printing that [INAUDIBLE]?
ANSEL DUFF: So that's actually a bug.
I contacted the manufacturer.
There's somebody with the same
name at that organization.
>> AUDIENCE: The random one when you
did the plane tangent to the hole,
is it then possible once
you've drawn on the plane
to make the plane itself
curve to fit on the surface?
What if you drew something
on the plane to eventually go
onto the surface itself.
ANSEL DUFF: Great question.
So let's go back here to
bottom plane, normal to it.
Sometimes after a restless night,
my bottom plane is not there either.
But hit bottom plane.
We're good to go.
The question was, if we draw something
on the plane, can it wrap around?
Or rather, can the plane itself
wrap around to a curved surface?
And the answer to that,
disappointingly, is no.
You cannot wrap a plane to a face that
is not planar, not completely flat.
But if we did, watch, let's
go back and sketch on here.
And we'll write, I don't
know, let's write SolidWorks.
>> If we wanted extrude this here,
even though we sketched it
on a plane that was tangent to the
curved surface, it will still work
and it'll still take
to a curved surface.
If that makes any sense.
You can make holes, any feature
that you want in a sketch,
and then apply that to a curved surface.
But all the sketching has
to be done on a plane.
Also, the nice thing about the feature
tree is that once you create something,
it's easy to pick and choose
what you want in your assembly.
So like this, SolidWorks looks
ridiculous because it's overflowing.
>> So if we wanted to kind of put i
on a shelf and use it later down
the road, we don't want it right now,
if we just hit Suppress, it goes away.
So all I did was I left clicked, and
then this little dialogue box pops up.
You have a ton of options here.
I just hit suppress.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> ANSEL DUFF: If we want it gone,
or rather if we want it back,
we just hit Unsuppress.
It's back.
So that's a really useful feature.
Not so much in parts, but
when you have an assembly,
there are a couple other--
I'll go back to the assembly
and show you some cool
assembly features.
So if we wanted to see how the
phone how the fillets morph
to the fillets of the dock,
we can highlight this.
So we go to dock.
Then we hit Change Transparency.
This makes it semi-transparent.
You'll notice that the fillets that
we made here, there's plenty of space.
>> Additionally, we'll change that back.
You can also view in plane while
moving through the depth of the part.
So this little count,
it's like a half donut.
It's called Section View.
If we hit that, actually,
we want a different plane.
Let's do top plane.
>> So we hit Section View, and
then move this in and out.
Kind of hard to see.
We'll zoom in a little bit.
But this actually takes your field
of view, your plane of vision,
and pushes it through the part.
So what's blue is actual material.
There's a phone, there's a fillet.
It's not that interesting for this part.
But this can be done in
both assemblies and parts.
So if we go back to
our lens support, then
hit the same thing,
little half donut here.
It's kind of cool to see.
>> Sometimes, when you're designing
a complicated internal feature,
this is really useful
to check clearances,
as a sanity check to make sure that
holes are concentric, what have you.
But you can just move it up and down.
I'm just holding it down, left clicking,
and it will show you everything.
This can be done on any plane.
So we'll see if the MakerBot is done.
Oh, 80%.
We'll do the render and we'll come back.
>> So we had defined this
part to be aluminum.
We had also defined its
appearance to be gray.
We'll do polished aluminum.
So as far as SolidWorks is
concerned, it's appearance
is completely taken care
of, completely defined.
So now, we're going
to go and we're going
to make a really realistic render of it.
It's going to look as
it would in real life.
So the package I have enabled here
is, actually, I don't have it enabled.
If there's something, you can pick
and choose which tools are displayed.
>> The package that we have in our
office has everything available,
the academic license has
every feature that SolidWorks
makes incorporate in our package.
But not all of them are showing.
So if you want to add or subtract
from this menu, just right click.
Nope.
You right click, and then
you get this list here.
So we want Render Tools.
Render Tools uses an engine called
Photo View 360, which may or may not
be enabled.
So to double check, we'll
go to Tools, Add-ins,
and then we select Photo View 360.
Hit OK.
Now, we're good to go.
So we go to Render Tools.
You can do a preview render.
But it's not going to
do anything for us.
So we're going all
the way, final render.
And this will take a little
bit of time to process.
But it'll look pretty cool.
>> So there are all these parameters on
the right hand side that we can adjust.
The resolution, lighting,
where the light's coming from,
the diffusivity of the surface.
Those are all adjustable.
But we're just using the defaults.
You can even move it
around a little bit.
You can see it's really shiny.
All the fillets are glistening.
Oops, just lost my power.
Sky is the limit as far as that goes.
It's pretty cool.
>> For some letters, and in
fact a doorknob that we
had designed a little bit earlier,
I had done a render of the door
handle also in false aluminum,
and this is what it looks like.
There are some more advanced
features with renders,
like you can add-- like if you were
designing a battery pack, for example,
you can have a sticker that
says high voltage or decals.
You can import your own
decals and add them.
So it's very product designy.
85%, I'm dying to know how
long this is going to take.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: You are printing
something that's solid,
and then you have something
that's [INAUDIBLE] in the middle.
MakerBot and SolidWorks work together
and printed in a way that [INAUDIBLE]?
>> ANSEL DUFF: Great question.
So the question was, is there a way
for us to print internal features?
Internal features are
something that's suspended.
A good example is like if
you were to print an A,
the center triangle of the A
is an internal feature that's
completely suspended.
Or rather, if you were to print
a hook that's overarching,
when the printer wants to get to the
level where this part of the book
first starts, there's
nothing holding it up.
It can't just print in mid-air.
Those are called internal features
or suspended features, many names
for the same idea.
>> But the answer to your
question is yes and no.
SolidWorks does not do
anything to that extent.
SolidWorks is a CADing
and simulation program.
And we can design really
precise and advanced parts.
And even create CAM and G code for them.
But it doesn't really care
about how we make them.
It only cares about us designing them
very precisely and very efficiently.
>> However, once we've exported our
part as a .obj or .stl-- side note,
if you have the option to choose between
exporting using the file formats .obj
and .stl, always go with STL.
Once we've exported and we put it into
the MakerBot desktop application, which
is what we're looking at right now, we
have the option of creating supports,
printing these little
support structures.
They're little towers
that taper off at the end
and then hold those internal features.
So if we wanted to print
a hook, for example,
when it prints this part
of the hook, it would also
start to print a little tower.
And then, when the tower gets
close to this base of the hook,
it would taper off into a really,
really small plastic feature.
And that will support
this part of the hook.
Then, it would just join the two.
>> And we do have the option
of printing like that.
That option is turned off right now.
We haven't really needed it.
But yes, we can do that.
And that's how it's done.
You print supports.
And then, once everything
is done, just break it away
and you can peel the supports off.
Any other questions,
concerns, comments, remarks?
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah, supports.
Within the shapes?
I'm thinking like going
back to the A example, what
if the A had something
hanging down from the top?
Then the support is
latched onto the A itself.
ANSEL DUFF: I can't say for sure
without actually trying to do it.
But it would be cool.
I would imagine that
they could print supports
that are on the side of the A that
don't interfere with your part.
Some internal features are going
to become kind of a lost cause.
For example, if you wanted to print a
sphere with a smaller sphere located
internally, they're both
independent, not attached at all,
it would probably try to
print supports inside it.
But then, you'd never be able to remove
those supports unless you cut a hole
and peeled them out.
>> So it almost takes a
little bit of foresight
when you're designing the part
and getting the part prepared
for print to ensure that
it will be printable.
So like this feature, when it
first imported, it was vertical.
That would be really challenging
for the printer to print.
So always make sure that
you lay it on its side.
And you'll be set.
88%.
We will sit here until it's done!
>> [APPLAUSE]