>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID CHOUINARD: I'm David
Chouinard, and this is D3.
Welcome.
We're going to learn about D3 today.
D3 is a JavaScript framework
for building a high quality
interactive visualizations for the web.
Things like what we're
seeing in back of me,
we're going to learn to make those
things, kind of the basics of it.
But it's going to be cool.
Let's get started
making pretty pictures.
We've got more demos
of prospects available.
Let's do it.
>> Act I, DOM manipulation-- we're going
to start right away making cool things.
First of all, on the left, we have code.
On the right, we have
the result of our code.
Let's go through it.
>> Let's make a circle.
How does that sound?
svg.append circle--
we just made a circle.
You don't believe me, right?
It's not there.
>> So what we did right here is,
SVG is scalable vector graphics.
This is the way we tell the browser to
make vector graphics in the browser.
What we just did right now
is added a circle to browse.
>> The promise is that the circle
requires a bit of basic attributes
before we can actually see it.
We need to tell it its x position,
its y position, its radius.
We didn't tell it any of that,
so we're not seeing it right now.
But let's tell it stuff.
>> So first of all, you've got
to give our circle a name.
So let's call it circle.
Our circle has a name now.
And let's give it a few attributes.
How about cx would center x, so
the center of the x position.
Let's say, 200 for 200 pixels.
>> Let's give it a y of 200 pixels as well.
And an r, a radius, of about 40 pixels.
Now let's see.
I cannot spell.
>> There you go.
We have a circle at position 200
pixels, 200 pixels, radius of 40 pixels.
Kind of cool, right?
We have a circle.
Yeah.
>> So no need to follow along.
All these examples, all of
the code I'm doing today
will be provided online at the end
in the form of interactive examples
with checkpoints at
every act, and so on.
>> Let's do more stuff.
This black circle is really ugly.
I'm sorry for that error
messages right there.
There we go.
>> Let's give it a color.
How's that?
I like to steel blue.
Well, our circle changed color.
That's great.
Let's make it semi-transparent
too-- semi-transparent.
>> So these are attributes
we're defining on the circle.
The first thing we did is
we put a circle on the page.
And then we're defining
a bunch of attributes.
Some of these are required,
like CX, CY, and Radius.
And others are optional.
>> There are a lot more attributes.
There's a lot of them.
For example, we could have a
stroke as well, a stroke of red.
But let's remove that.
We're back to a circle, a blue circle.
>> So let's make more circles.
How's that?
Let's make another circle.
This is exciting, right?
>> So say I just Copy-Pasted
what we had already.
Let's call it circle2.
And let's do the exact
same thing and give it
attributes, given an x position of 300.
Yay, we have two circles now.
>> And of course, we could
update these values.
I could put it at 400, and now it moves.
And since it's annoying, let's
remove it, so circle2.remove.
It's gone now.
>> So what we're doing and
is just very, very-- this
is very similar to what you
might do in jQuery, for example.
We're just manipulating
the DOM, it's called.
You might have heard that word before.
We're creating stuff, setting
attributes on stuff, removing stuff.
>> Now, here's where it gets interesting.
So later in the code, we could still
refer to the original circle here.
So let's reset its attribute to cx.
Let's say, its x position to 400.
And I'm going to transition
that, so it's obvious.
There we go.
>> So we added a circle.
We set some attributes.
We added another circle, removed it.
And then we're modifying
the original circle.
>> But here's where it gets
a lot more interesting.
Not only can we set attributes
as just values, we can say,
hey, circle, go to position 200.
We can also set them as functions.
>> So instead of giving 400 here,
we can make some calculation
on the fly for what we
want that attribute to be.
So this is how you'd express that.
We say, instead of 400, let me
give you a function instead.
And here, inside this function,
we can make any crazy calculation.
>> We could take the time and
look at some other thing
and dynamically decide for
the circle what value we want.
How about we just give
it a random x position?
So that's that.
>> So what that says is, for
every x, run this function.
And what we're doing is calculating
some things, a random times the width
and returning that.
So every time we run that, we get a
circle that goes to a random place.
It's kind of cool.
I feel like I could look
at this for a little.
We're starting to get to
something interesting here.
Let's make this data driven now.
There's no data here.
Let's change that.
>> Act II, Data Driven Documents--
So let's return to here.
And let's just get rid of circle2,
because we're just adding and removing
it.
So we don't really need it.
We need to be a lot more clever here.
Let's say, we have
some data of some sort.
One moment-- let's say,
we had data of this form.
We had an array, just
a bunch of numbers.
We have seven numbers here,
whatever these represent-- amount
in people's bank account, how
much they weigh, god knows what.
>> These are numbers, and we
want to use our circles
to represent those numbers somehow.
We want to tie our
circles to those numbers.
So what we do.
Let's say, we want a
circle for every number.
We could do the old
thing we were doing--
circle append and circle2 and circle3.
But this gets out of hand, and
there's a lot of repeating logic.
>> So let's get more clever with that.
Instead of using the var circle
svg.append that we were just using,
we're going to use
this little block here.
I don't want to go in-depth
into what all these parts do.
And it's kind of an advanced topic.
And I wish I could.
>> But the key thing to recognize-- and
you'll see is very often in D3 code.
This block of text basic
creates as many circles
as there are data elements
in this array right here.
So this creates as many
circles as there are elements.
It's going to create us seven circles.
And it does a really, really key thing.
So let's run that.
Let's remove our other circle.
Let's just comment this
part out and run this again.
>> There we go.
So our circle here is a
lot darker, because we
have seven circles, one
on top of the other.
We just created seven circles, one
each for each of these data elements.
But there's a key thing that happened
with this snippet right here.
>> It's that data was bound.
So every single one of
those data elements,
10, 45, 105, was bound
to a particular circle.
So these not only created
a bunch of circles
but ties those two things together.
>> And in the future, because we created
those circles with this D3 function,
if I give you a circle, you can
give me the data associated with it.
So we can ask D3.
Hey, D3, I have this circle.
What's the data that the circle has?
And D3 would tell us 10 or 45 or 105.
>> These things are bound.
That's a very, very fundamental concept.
Let's look at that.
>> So the way we'd ask D3-- so
this is irrelevant for this,
but just trust me on it.
This is how we ask D3.
Hey, D3, give me the first
circle that you can find.
Give me the first circle you can find.
And then we could ask D3, what's
the data on that, like this, 10.
>> So we just ask D3, find me
the first circle you can find.
What's its data?
10, that is indeed our
first data element.
We could ask it, hey, D3,
find us our third circle.
105.
Why is this really important?
>> So right here, I mentioned
that we could use functions.
And I mentioned that was
a very powerful thing.
So not only can our functions do things
like do some computation, for example,
return a random number, it can
also do things based on the data.
This is what data driven documents mean.
That's what D3 stands for.
>> So this x postition-- instead
of just saying, all the circles,
get x position 200, we
could give it a function.
And here, we can make some calculation.
and d here stands in place for the data.
So every time we have
a circle, basically,
D3 will create these seven circles.
And then for every
>> circle, it's going to go, hey,
circle1 what's your x position.
Previously, we were
always answering 200.
But now, every time D3 asks
us what's your x position,
it's going to give us-- we have
that circle, so we have the data.
It's going to give us the data and say,
what do you want the exposition to be,
based on that data.
>> Let's just return the actual data.
So if we run this, this gives
us data driven documents.
These circles are based
in relation position--
they're bases as a function of the data.
>> So for the first circle,
D3 puts a circle.
And then D3 asks us, what do
you want the exposition to be.
And we just say, whatever the data is.
Make the exposition 10.
>> Then it asks, what do you want the
exposition to be for the second circle.
And we answer, 45.
And we, of course, can
make some computation here.
I find that those circles
are kind of squished up.
>> So multiply it by 3, multiply data by 3.
Our circle just got expanded out.
Our value was tripled.
>> The circle is really on the edge,
so let's maybe kind of offset it.
Let's say, by 20.
Here you go.
>> This is a data visualization.
It's a very basic one, but this
gives us some insight into our data.
It tells us that, for example, we
have a little cluster of elements.
And we have a big outlier here.
This gives us some information
about the distribution.
>> If we were, for example, to change
the data to 150 here and refresh,
our visualization is changed.
This document is data driven.
>> So of course, all these elements,
all these attributes here,
we can use a function, not
just the numbers, not just
the x and y positions.
So we can use a function for the color.
So we'll do the same.
We'll give it a function.
>> And let's say, we could have
conditionals in our function.
This function can be
hundred of lines long.
It can do very, very complicated things.
>> So let's put an if statement here.
Let's say, if our data is less
than 50, that's some threshold
that we're interested
in for some reason.
Let's make it green.
Otherwise, let's make it red.
How's that?
Nice.
>> So our data visualization is starting
to convey more interesting information
on many channels.
So now we know a bit
about the distribution.
And we know that there's some sort of
cut off at 50 that we're interested in.
We know that there are two data points
below that threshold and most of them
above.
>> So as a final step, this data here,
it's very rare to see this like that.
So let's just move it out to a variable
because that's cleaner, like this.
And then we use that variable here.
It's the exact same thing.
It's just a bit cleaner.
>> Next up, Act III, Scales--
So one problem right
here is, if we change our
data in this 200 value--
if we change it to 400
or something and refresh,
then this value just went offscreen.
So our logic right here
of how we do the times 3
and 20, to spread it out and then
offset it a bit is really clunky.
>> What do those numbers mean?
They're just hard coded there.
And they're very much tied to the data.
We want a data driven document.
We want a very flexible document,
that given data, adapts to it
and represents it.
>> What we basically need is, we
have this range of numbers 10.
45, 105.
And we want to map that out onto
the width, the full width here.
So we have the range of
numbers going from 0 to 100.
And we have this campus I goes
from 20 to 700, in this case.
>> We kind of want to map that on.
We want to scale that up and
then offset it a little bit.
It turns out that D3 has these.
It's called a scale.
So let's use it.
>> The way that works-- I'm going to
type this up and then explain it.
This is a scale.
What it will do is, it will map out
values from 1 to 200 on to 20 to 600.
We can check that.
We can see that here.
>> So if I feed it 1-- one moment.
Give me one second.
I must have mistyped it.
There you go.
I'm sorry about that.
>> So what a scale will do
is, it will take a value
and then convert that,
expand that out, so it
fills the full range you're asking for.
So in this case, if we give it one,
it's going to map that out onto 20.
And if we give it 200, it's
going to map that on to 600.
And somewhere in between,
if we get 100, it's
going to be somewhere
in between 20 and 600.
>> And of course, now this is what
we need to remove those hard coded
things we have right there.
So what we want to do is
take the data that we're
given, that individual data
element, and pass it to scale first.
So scale will scale it up.
>> Well-- Oh, we have a little error here.
We're missing data.
There you go.
And that expands it out.
>> That gives us the same
result we had before,
but instead of having those
hard coded constraints.
And if the size of our
canvas changes, for example,
if we want to have this over
400 pixels and it squishes out,
we can have it over--
we can expand it, or we
can reduce this left margin to
something less or more than 20.
These numbers, these hard coded
numbers now make sense to us.
>> And we could do a lot more
interesting things as well.
So instead of having a linear
scale, we might want to log a scale.
And that will give us a log scale.
>> So now our scale, instead of
just expanding out that range,
it's doing more sophisticated things.
Instead of having this range hard
coded, and instead of having that 600,
we might want to just use the width,
so from 20 to the width minus 40,
2 times the margin on the other side.
And this makes a lot more sense to
somebody who might look at the code.
>> Interestingly, the scales get
very, very sophisticated as well.
They do a lot of interesting things.
So scales don't necessarily have
to operate just with numbers.
Let's make a color scale.
>> So our range could be--
our domain is 1 to 200.
That's the input thing.
But we might want to map from
green to red, for example.
And now, if we pass it 1,
we're going to get green.
If we give it 200, we'll get red.
And if we pass it something in between,
it's going to be some mix of that,
somewhere on the gradient
between green and red.
>> And instead of having
this kind of clunky logic
we have here with the
conditional right there,
we could have something-- a
linear scale between those.
So we'd use the scale we just
created, which we called color.
And we'd give it d, which
is our data element.
And there we go.
We have a color scale.
>> So this is mapping.
So the far left is completely green.
The far right is completely red.
And everything in between
is a function of d.
We have an interesting
visualizations here.
But our data was kind of boring.
Let's see what we could do if
we had more interesting data.
>> Act IV, Working With
Data-- the first thing
we'll want to do to make our
visualization more interesting
is to move the data somewhere else.
It's very clunky to have
the data hard coded here.
And generally, we'll be asking
somebody else for the data.
We'll be maybe asking the government,
the Census Bureau, what's your data
and then plotting that or asking
some third-party entity for some data
and then building a
visualization on that.
>> So the first thing we want to do
is move that to somewhere else.
So I'm going to create a
file here called data.json.
JSON is the data format.
You don't have to know much about that.
And we're going to copy the
little data we have there,
paste it in there verbatim, go
back to our visualization code
here, and use this function right here.
You don't have to know the details.
But what this will do is,
it will find that file,
fetch it, and return it to us.
So what this does is, it goes
and get the data.json file.
And then all the code that's
indented inside-- essentially,
all the code we have there-- will
run only when we get the data back.
And then it's going to run that
code with the data we have.
Great, we have a
visualization that queries
for some code somewhere
else, which is usually
where it queries some data from
somewhere else, which is usually
how visualizations work.
>> But I want to go back to the data.
So the data fundamentally in D3-- D3
consumes data that's a list of things.
D3 expects the data just be a list
of things, an array of things.
It doesn't matter what those things
are, so long as it's an array of them.
>> So here, for example, we could of
course have floating point values.
We could have negatives.
D3 doesn't care, so long
as it's a list of things.
>> As interesting things we
could have, we could also
have a list of strings like that.
So these are the Crimson headlines
I picked up a few days ago.
And maybe you can find some interesting
things about these a headlines.
>> So again, this is a list of things.
D3 doesn't care.
These happen to be a string.
We've changed our data.
>> Let's return to our visualization.
Now, our visualization expects
the input to be numbers.
So we're going to have
to make a few changes.
So for example, first of all, maybe
we want to put these circles along
by the length of the headline, the
number of characters in the headline.
>> So what we'll do is-- every time our
function is called with a string,
we'll find it's length And
then pass that to scale.
The color, I'll return
that to steel blue.
And there we go.
We have a visualization
of Crimson headlines.
>> Our scale is a bit off.
Let's assume that the longest
headline is 100 characters long,
so span that out a bit.
And we have a visualization.
So it seems that most headlines
are pretty close together,
in terms of character line.
But one there really stands out.
>> We could build some tools
to explore that more.
But when I was working on this, I was
curious whether, in this data set,
headlines with a colon
in them would be longer.
I assumes they would.
>> So let's find out.
Let's use the color
channel like we did before,
to encode some about whether
there's a colon or no.
So we'll use a conditional again.
You don't have to know
the details of this,
but this is how we check a
string for a particular character
in JavaScript, again, not relevant.
>> But if we don't find a
colon, we'll return green.
And if we do, we'll return red.
So again, headlines that
have a colon will be red.
This is what this means-- nice.
>> So it seems that my
hypothesis is bumped.
There's only two.
We only have six data points
and only two had colons.
But it seems a bit more
on the lower end, in fact.
Headlines with colons seem
to generally be shorter,
at least in our data set-- interesting.
>> Let's return that to
steel blue and then see
what we can make with even
more interesting data.
So again, I mentioned that
data in D3 is a list of things.
We've seen numbers of many types.
We've seen strings.
But the things can also be objects.
>> They can be complicated things
that include a lot of things.
To say that more clearly,
in most cases, we
want to build every data point as
more complicated than just one value.
If you'd imagine a
database about students,
there might be a student
name, a student ID,
and a lot of things associated
with a particular record,
not just a string or a number.
So let's look at that.
>> This is one such data set.
This is a data set about earthquakes.
So everything here on our list or array
of things contains many things itself.
So every data point has a
magnitude and a coordinate.
And coordinates themselves
contain two things.
>> So every day is now a lot more
complicated and a lot more interesting
and contains much more
interesting information.
Let's see we could build out of that.
Returning back to here, again, using
our histogram circle visualization
we've built, let's see if we can build a
visualization of magnitude distribution
in our data set.
>> So here, it's the same concept.
But now, d contains more things.
d contains many data elements.
So we get d back.
D3 gives us d.
And we respond by finding the magnitude
of d and then passing that to scale.
>> And then we need to change
our scale, of course.
So magnitudes simply don't
go much more than 10.
Actually, there's never been
a 10 magnitude earthquake.
But that's kind of our upper
end, our upper spectrum.
>> Let's refresh.
Nice, we have a visualization.
It's interesting to note-- so
there are two data points that
are almost exactly on top of each
other, in terms of magnitude.
You see this by the opacity we're using.
>> We have geographic data now.
We have latitudes and longitude.
Maybe we could do something a
lot more interesting with that.
Let's find some more
interesting way to visualize
this more complicated
data we have access to.
>> Act V, Mapping-- fundamentally,
we want to put these on a map.
I mean, this is where this is going.
We want to encode information about the
position of these earthquake readings,
as well their magnitude,
because we have that now.
We understand how to consume
more complicated data.
>> The first thing we'll do is
create a map, a background map.
I'm going to go through
this very quickly.
This is tricky code.
It's another one of those
recipes you don't really
have to understand fully for you to use.
But this is code.
This code right here creates a map.
>> We're not going to go in detail.
But superficially, what it does is,
it queries this us.json file, which
is a data file like
the one we had before.
It's more complex, of course.
But in this case, everything,
every data point is this state
and has a list of
latitudes and longitude
that define the polygon,
that form, that state.
>> So what D3 will do is similar
to what we did before.
It will request that and
bind that to an element.
And there's a function that
will map that element out,
based on the latitudes and longitude.
You can read more on that.
And I recommend it.
>> There are links at the
end of this code posted.
And the code is commented.
In there are links for further on this.
I recommend you look it up.
But what we care about is
this projection function.
I want to go through that.
>> First of all, let me show
you that, yes, we have a map.
Maps are cool.
So let's look at this
production function.
>> Projection is very much
like a scale, scales again.
So what production for
this projection function
does is, we could pass it longitude
and latitudes-- in this case,
these values here are the
lat-longs of the building
we're sitting in right
now-- to projection.
And projection will convert
that into x and y pixel values.
>> So what projection is doing
is very similar to our scale.
It's taking our latitudes and
longitude that represents a whole globe
and shrinking and sizing that
down to the square that we want,
that we've given it.
In this case, we're
passing these values.
And it's giving us, well, that
on your screen means 640 pixels.
This whole screen is 700 pixels
wide, so that makes us about here,
and 154 pixels down, which I would
estimate is pretty much here.
>> So taking those lat-longs, which
represent something on the whole globe
and squishing and moving that around
to give us x and y pixel values,
this is the first thing that's
done in this mapping code.
And then the rest of the
code consumes the data
and then maps those lat-longs
onto something on your screen.
>> But we're going to use this projection
functions, because it turns out
we have lat-longs longs as well.
Looking back at our data, we have
latitudes and longitude coordinates
for every observation.
So let's use projection.
>> So looking at our exposition,
we want our exposition--
we have a latitude and a longitude.
But we want pixel values.
And it turns out, we have exactly
what we want-- projection.
Very much like we were
using scale right here,
we're now going to use projection
and pass it coordinates.
So the first thing
we're doing-- so we're
getting d, which is an individual data
element of an individual earthquake
reading.
The first thing we do
is get the coordinates.
All right, we have the coordinates.
>> The second thing we do is
pass that on to projection.
Projection converts those coordinates
into pixel values, x and y.
And then the last thing we
want to do is just get the x,
which this case is the first one.
It's the first of the two things
that are returned by projection.
>> We'll do the same for y.
But instead, we'll return
the second element, the y.
Get ready to refresh.
Ooh, extra character
here-- nice, we have
a data driven document that's
concealing this JSON file of objects,
making a map, and changing the
attribute in relation to the data
to project it on a map.
This is really interesting.
This is cool.
>> Let's take it up a notch.
I mean, we have two pieces of
information with every data point.
I mean, three.
We have the coordinates,
which is an x and y.
And we have the magnitude.
>> We need to encode magnitude somehow.
We have a lot of channels.
We can use color.
We can use radius.
We could use opacity.
We could use many things in code.
Any of these attributes and many
more that are not listed there,
because they're optional, we could
use to encode this data, the stroke
and all these things I've mentioned.
>> Let's do radius.
I think radius is the most intuitive.
So again, we'll replace that hard-coded
40 and make some calculations.
We'll use our favorite scale again.
And we're past d.
But not d because we want the magnitude
of d. d is just the data point.
We'll pass the magnitude to scale.
>> Let's try that again.
Ooh, it doesn't work.
Why does it not work?
>> So remember what scale does.
Let's look at scale again.
Scale maps from 1 to 10 on
to 22 to 600, more or less.
600 is huge.
This is why we're getting this.
>> So we want to change our scale
to something more reasonable.
Let's say, we want 0 to 60.
60 is big, but 10 earthquakes
are incredibly rare.
In fact, they've never happened.
>> So what this will do is, it'll take
our magnitude that goes from 1 to 10
and map it on to expand it out.
And map it on to 0 to 60.
Let's refresh.
>> Nice, we have a visualization.
This is great.
This is actual data.
You'll notice, in my little toy
example, the biggest earthquake
is right on top of us.
But that's it.
We have a date driven visualization
that consumes the data
and gives us really
interesting information.
Yeah, let's add some
interactivity to it.
I mentioned that was
the strong force of D3.
>> So here, for every element, we're
describing a bunch of attributes.
But we can also describe what we want
to happen with interactivity elements.
For example, we could describe
what happens when we mouse over.
And very similar that,
that'll take a function,
very similar to the
attributes we had before,
where we do something to the
element when we hover over it.
>> So first thing we need to
do is select that element,
to find it basically, in the browser.
and then we could set
an attribute to it.
So what I'm doing here is, when we hover
over something, we'll get that element
and then set its opacity back
to 1, to completely opaque.
Let's see what that looks like.
>> It appears we have an
extra semicolon here.
So if we hover over here, it gets full.
But now, of course, it
stays full, because we
have to describe what happens
when remove our cursor.
So let's do exactly that on
mouseout, as opposed to mouseover.
>> And we'll reset it to
what we had before-- 0.5.
And now, every time we
hover, we get a full circle.
It helps us see what we
we're selecting essentially.
>> And now let's make this really great.
Let's connect this to real data.
So let's ask could
USGS about their data.
So the US Geological Survey
has data about earthquakes.
They have a public API that's able
to be consumed in JSON format.
So let's do that.
>> So this is a bit of code that
connects to the USGS API.
And there's a bit of processing on it.
This is not relevant but simplifies it
to a simple data format like the one
we had before.
So I get rid of our call to
our fake data.json on file.
And instead, I'm calling
the USGS essentially.
>> Let's refresh, nice.
This is actual, real-life data
from this week for earthquakes.
This is really interesting.
This is not surprising
for us, but there are
a lot of earthquakes on the
West Coast in California.
But I thought it was very interesting
that there were so many earthquakes
in Alaska, and apparently,
here in the Midwest.
I mean, interesting, and we're good.
That's the conclusion.
>> But fundamentally, this
is what D3 helps us do.
It helps us take data, bind
it to elements in the DOM,
and have those elements change
as a function of the data,
have those attributes, all the
many attributes of the elements,
all be useful for channels
to convey information.
>> D3 is an incredibly powerful
library and amazingly well run.
This is some powerful stuff.
Data visualization is an
incredibly powerful tool
for conveying to people deep
insights that gets to their core
and helps them understand, in
this profound and intuitive way,
how data works and how
data changes our life.