>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAN BRADLEY: Alrighty.
Welcome, everyone, to the
first CS50 seminar of the year.
We today we'll be talking
about how you set up hue light
bulbs to use all the fancy
features that hues actually have.
So we can control hue light
bulbs via the web, and with that,
change the color of the
bulb, turn on the bulb
and turn them off, and do all
sort of other fancy features.
So what we're going to
actually do today is
build a little web app that
controls one of these bulbs,
and turns it on, turns it off,
and is able to change its color.
>> First and foremost I'm going to
assume, if you guys are watching this,
that you have access to this,
which is a Phillips Hue Bridge.
It is the thing that is actually
going to be controlling these bulbs,
and is essentially
just a wireless router
that has some extra features built in.
So the first thing we need
to do to make this work--
and again, I'm assuming
that you have the hardware,
but nothing actually set up.
So to get it working on Harvard WiFi,
you need to grab your Hue Bridge,
plug it into your wall, wherever
that is, so to the ethernet.
Obviously, have it plugged
in so it has power.
And then you need to go
to the FAS Autoreg page,
autoreg.fas.harvard.edu,
sign in, and then register
the new Bridge for the internet.
>> So I got logged out, so
I'll just click log in.
And let's actually register this Bridge.
So to register a Bridge you need the
MAC address, which is the bottom most
line of numbers on the bridge,
so it's at the very bottom,
by the ethernet port.
And it starts with 00:17: such and such.
So I'm just going to quickly
type that in, so we can actually
use this on the Harvard internet,
and we'll go from there.
>> All right, so we've
registered it, so now it
can actually access the internet.
And when it finally actually
manages to access the internet,
this light that's flashing will stop
flashing, and just be solid blue.
But until that happens,
we can just wait.
And the other thing
we're going to need to do
is actually register this
Bridge with Philips Hue.
So Phillips is the company
that makes the Bridge,
so we need to actually go
and register for an account.
So I'm going to do that here, too.
>> All right.
And as we can see, the
third light has now
turned, on so we're all the way there.
So you sign in, now you
just activate the Bridge
by clicking on the button
in the middle, and Hue
realizes that, hey, you've
actually registered this.
So we now have this on Hue, so it
actually realizes that it exists.
Now we can start doing some
more interesting things.
>> We have this.
Now we want to actually create
a website-- or a web app,
rather-- that lets us
control these bulbs.
First-- every time you use Hue bulbs,
they actually need to be turned on.
So there actually has to
be power going to them.
You can then tell them to turn off.
So the light will be off, but there
will still be power going to it.
So this-- if I actually used a
light switch how it's normally used,
it isn't actually all that
useful, because you can't turn it
on if there's no power going to at all.
So we're just going to have this
on, and hopefully not staring you
guys in the face for the next few steps.
>> OK, so to actually
control these bulbs we
need to use what's called
the Phillips Hue API.
So an API is an called an
Application Program Interface.
So it's essentially a
way to access and control
data on a system that
isn't necessarily yours.
So this light bulb uses an API,
so it has its own system that
has all sorts of fancy things in
it-- like, it's a zigbee wireless
system-- we don't actually have to know.
All we need to know is how to interact
with this API, this Application Program
Interface.
And so if we can talk to that, we
can do everything we need to do.
And how we actually are going to
talk to it is by using web requests,
just like we did for
this last problem set.
>> So how we get started is
we again register for this.
We need to do a fair bit of registering
to actually get started using the Hue,
but-- and hopefully
it's actually exists.
I agree.
And can I actually read that?
Good.
Alrighty.
cool.
So e-mail address.
That's now password stuff,
because of course there is.
I need uppercase letters.
Cool All right.
>> So we have gotten in, or we're about to.
I think we're in.
OK, cool so we're in.
>> This, the API documentation
that we're on now,
is going to be your
best friend if you're
trying to do anything
useful with these bulbs.
Basically, it'll tell you how to
get started using these bulbs-- how
to change the lights to
whatever color you want,
how to create groups, which isn't all
that important right now because we're
only going to be talking
about a single bulb.
But if you say have multiple
bulbs, it is very handy.
And all sorts of things.
>> To get started we'll go to their
Getting Started page-- surprise.
And to actually check if we are in
fact getting everything working,
we can see-- you can use this
link, meethue.com/api/nupmp.
I don't know what all the letters
are supposed to stand for.
But we can find a list up here of
all the Bridges on this network.
Luckily, I know which Bridge is ours,
which is the first one, because we
haven't bothered to
change the name of it yet.
So it's just starting as Philips Hue.
But we have all sorts of
interesting things here.
We have its IP address, which we're
going to be accessing pretty soon.
We have its MAC address,
which we used earlier.
And we have its name, but that
doesn't matter to us in the least.
>> So how we actually go about interacting
with these bulbs is we use this IP
address, and we also
go to /debug/clip.html.
So debug/clip.html.
So there we go.
We have this nice,
relatively nice interface,
so we can actually talk
to the Bridge right
here, to figure out, OK, which
lights are connected to this?
Are they on?
That sort of thing.
There's a few steps to
actually getting this started.
So right now, as we
can see, the debugger
looks just like this page that it has.
Again, I can't stress this enough,
this developer.meethue.com,
incredibly useful if you're actually
interacting with these bulbs.
So if we actually want to walk through
what this debugger looks like, it gives
us a URL to interact with, a set of
methods we can use, a message body,
and then we'll get back
some sort of response
from the client, which is the Bridge.
>> So just like we did for this last
problem set, right, where we have,
instead of saying using Telnet,
we're just using this interface,
but we're still using a get
request to a certain absolute path,
with a certain body.
And the body, in this case, is
actually just going to be our query.
>> Let's walk through how we
actually get to using this.
If we say, go here-- so,
1234 is an unauthorized user.
You have to set up, again,
another user for this Bridge.
So that's fun.
We have a lot of users
that we have to set up.
So we're going to call
ourselves New Developer.
But again, if we get
that that doesn't work,
we actually have to go about and post
with the body device type, test user,
and username, New Developer,
to the API of the Bridge.
So let's see if I have
that exactly right.
Yes.
Bridge IP address-- oh yes, of course.
Sorry about that.
So it's actually visible, always handy.
>> So to actually create a new user,
we put in the message body device
type, test user, username New
Developer, and we post this.
Except this doesn't work,
because we haven't pressed
the big button in the middle.
So if we press the button in
the middle and do that again,
we have our new user in.
It's very handy.
>> OK, so now that we
have our New Developer,
we can start getting
information about ourselves.
So we have that there is apparently
three lights hooked up to this Bridge.
This is because all Bridges
come with a starter kit,
and they have three
lights automatically.
And it has all the information about
all these lights-- Light 1, which
again isn't actually this light
bulb, so that's not all that handy.
It is apparently on state off.
Each light-- let's actually just run
through this newdeveloper/lights/get.
If we look at each of these
lights, we can get their name,
if we just look at
the lights as a whole.
Then we can also look at
each light and its state.
So if we get its state-- it states not
available, because it's not plugged in.
But--
>> OK, so if we want to actually
connect to this light to this Bridge,
we need to use a program--
and I need to download it,
because I forgot about this--
called Lamps Dealer, which
Phillips Hue actually
already built for us.
It's very helpful.
So if we download that, opening
in four seconds-- there we go.
OK.
Open up Lamps Dealer.
And we agree.
We find the bridge.
We know which MAC address we have, which
is the thing on the back, so 8809F2E0.
We find that.
>> And to actually make
Lamps Dealer work, you
put the light bulb against the
Bridge, and hit Start Linking.
It'll flash to say that it's
working, and we have the light bulb.
OK, so once we've done that to actually
connect that bulb to our light,
we use post.
So we go api/newdevelopers/lights.
Hit post.
That'll find any new
lights that we have.
Then if we hit get, we now have a
fourth light bulb, which is the bulb
that we actually just added on.
>> So now, if we go for
light/force/state, and get that---
I might actually not be doing the
right thing, when I ask for state.
So let's go Philips Hue API, lights.
Flashlights gets us all
the different lights.
And Get New Lights.
We already did that.
We searched for lights.
So but we don't actually have to
go to state to get the lights.
So it's just light/force/get.
>> OK, so interestingly, this says that
this fourth bulb that we just added
is off.
And that's because we haven't
actually done anything with it yet.
So if you just plug in
a bulb to a light socket
and don't try and
manipulate it using Hue,
it'll just assume that
it's probably off.
We need to actually tell it that
it wants to be either on or off.
So we just give it the body on,
quote, colon, true or false,
if we want to actually
see it do something.
And we put that, and
we have the light off.
If we want it to turn back on,
we put that, light turns back on.
>> So that's fancy, right?
We're controlling a light
bulb all through the internet.
Obviously we can do better.
So if we want to do
something more interesting,
like change the colors that
it is, we can also do that.
Where now it's a sort of shade of green,
if we want it to be red we can do that.
Anyway, very nice, right?
That's the first step, right?
We have this light set up, so we
can actually do things with it.
>> What if we then want to
actually create a website that
can control this light bulb?
So, conveniently, I have written sort
of the-- going to make this bigger,
so we can actually see.
Ah yes, there we go.
>> So I've built a little sample
website that will actually
be able to control this
light bulb with, once we
add all the actual features
that we're going to need.
So here's what it looks like right now.
It's kind of hideous.
And it also doesn't do anything.
There's a couple bad things right
there, ugly and doesn't do anything,
but we can make it better, and
we are going to make a better.
Quick aside-- we're going to
talk about a couple things here,
JavaScript, which is a language we
haven't talked about yet in the class,
and AJAX which is a use of
JavaScript that we haven't talked
about in the class, not
surprisingly, because we
haven't talked about JavaScript.
So we're going to need
both of these things.
So JavaScript is what's known
as a client side language.
So basically it's a language that
runs on the client's machine.
So it's running.
>> So if a website uses JavaScript, it's
your computer running the JavaScript,
unlike PHP, where it's the
server that runs the JavaScript,
and then tells your
computer what to see.
Your computer is saying
what it's going to see,
by running the JavaScript itself.
So it's a client side language, and
it runs completely independently
of the website, basically.
>> We're going to use JavaScript, which is
basically the only thing that we want
to use, because I don't actually
have this site up on the Web.
It's just on my own computer.
We don't want it to
connect to the Web at all.
We're just running it.
>> And we're also going to
use this thing called AJAX.
So AJAX stands for Asynchronous
JavaScript and XML.
And it's basically a way for a part of
your web page to talk to the internet.
So if we say, want when we click on
this button, to talk to our API--
so to talk to our
bridge-- and say, we want
to change the color to
whatever I've typed in here,
we can do that using AJAX.
It's fairly straightforward, and
we'll obviously go into more detail
as we actually write some code for it.
But are we feeling OK about it so far?
Ask me questions if not.
>> Alrighty, so I've created
here this website.
We're including here a
call to jQuery, which
is just a library of a bunch
of handy JavaScript functions.
We'll talk about that in
more detail in the future.
And then inside this
script tag I've created
a sort of wrapper
function, which will just
get called once the website
is finished loading.
And then I've built
some basic descriptors
of functions, change color and toggle.
So what toggle's going to do is
just turn this light on and off,
and change color is going to
change the color of the light bulb.
So far so good?
>> Okey doke.
So I've also included on here, inside
the actual HTML part of the page,
a on click tag, or attribute,
rather, which calls change color.
And this onclick calls toggle.
So if we want to, say, just make
it obvious that these are actually
doing something-- so, ideally, onclick
is getting called if I hit that,
and onclick is getting
called if I hit that.
But to actually make it
explicit we can use the console,
which is a handy thing
for JavaScript, and .log,
so it's just like using
Print-F, basically.
And we'll just give it change color,
and we can do the same thing for toggle.
>> OK, so we reload the page, and
then if we open up the console
and click this-- that was unexpected.
Don't mind me.
OK, let's see.
There we go.
So if I hit Submit, right, it knows
that it's calling change color.
If I hit toggle, it knows
that it's calling toggle.
Right?
So, so far so good.
>> Basically this is
just-- this onclick here
is just a way of saying to the
website that when I click this,
I want you to call the
function change color.
How we feeling?
Good so far?
All right.
>> So if we actually want to talk to
the API, so to talk to these lights,
we need to know the IP address,
which we found earlier,
and how we're actually
going to talk to them.
So if we want to just talk about
this again, or use this again,
so api/NewDeveloper/lights/fore/state--
or-- I guess light slash four.
We'll just call a get request,
and we get all this stuff.
We can see that if we call using the
web a get request, of this address,
we'll get back all this information.
>> So we can do gets that
way very easily, right?
Basically everything we do over the web
these days is using gets as the method.
Using put is much harder, right?
It's confusing, because
that isn't something
that the Web is built to handle anymore.
Luckily, if we use AJAX we can
just tell it what method we want.
We don't have to rely on how
the Web works these days.
>> So if we want to use
AJAX, we simply do $ --
and so this is using the
jQuery library-- .ajax.
And we pass AJAX a body.
So I think we give it method equals put.
Let's see.
URL equals get/state.
And we give it the body
of-- and so the body
that we want to give it is
the same thing we gave here,
of just Hue, followed
by some number, if we
want to change that
color to that number.
So it's just got to be as simple as hue:
>> And we're going to start
with a fixed number,
and we'll talk about how we'll
change that in the future,
And that should be enough.
We'll want to actually check to
see if that works, but we can try.
So.
It did not.
OK, so bear with me for a
second as I open the recent file
that I might have done all
the work on, any second ago.
Scratch examples, JS, I guess
I want OK, get the IP address,
[INAUDIBLE] state's on through Hue.
>> Oh, data not body.
That was it.
Let's-- OK, and-- hm, crap.
So this a little
embarrassing, obviously.
And of course that's still
closed on itself again.
>> So we put that URL, our data of Hue.
Oh, right.
And data.
The whole thing needs to be in a string.
There we go.
So much better.
>> OK, so debugging on the fly,
not the best, but did the job.
So let's quickly talk
about what just happened.
So we're calling this AJAX call.
We're giving it the method put, right?
We're calling it to
this URL, which happens
to be the IP address of my Hue bulb.
It's the same IP address we had up here.
Passing it
api/NewDeveloper/lights/4/state,
inside the debug mode.
And then we give it
the body of Hue 2500.
>> So if we wanted it to go back and
forth, we can put this one to red,
we can put this one to green.
This to red, this to
green, and so on, right?
Obviously that isn't
that impressive yet,
though, because we have
this fixed color, right?
We can only change this to green.
Luckily with JavaScript
you can actually figure out
what is going on on your
page, so we can figure out
the inner values of this text box.
So that's kind of neat.
>> And then the other thing we still
need to do that we haven't done yet
is actually have our on and off switch.
So which do we want to do first,
on/off switch, or actually get colors?
Actually get colors?
Sounds good.
>> All we need to do here
is figure out what
the actual value inside of this box is.
And we can do that using JavaScript.
It's very handy.
So we're going to
quickly use this console.
So I'll make that bigger, too, and just
talk about how we actually get things,
and then we'll go into basically
copying that code over again.
>> So jQuery, again, how you access
things on a page using jQuery.
Again, it's a great
library for JavaScript.
You first use a $, which says
I'm using the jQuery library,
then you pass it a set of parentheses,
which is basically the function body,
and then you give it a string
that represents something.
So I'm going to quickly
do this, and then we'll
talk about what that actually means.
>> So I give it this hash switch,
which is the ID-- oh, sorry.
I don't want to give it switch,
because that's the check box.
But you can give it the
idea of whatever instance,
or the whatever thing
you want to look at.
So instead of hash switch, I
want to give it hash numbers,
and this gives us this text box.
I think just value-- nope.
>> Well, so .txt-- What's that?
Yeah, I think that's
the one I actually want.
Because .txt would give
us the inner text in HTML,
but that isn't-- this
.val is what we want.
So .txt would give us the inner HTML.
But because this isn't inner HTML,
because we typed this in ourself,
we use .val, which is just
the value given to whatever.
And we can figure that out.
>> So if we have this 2,500 that we
can-- or 255,000-- no, 25,000,
rather, because I can
read numbers real well,
we can figure out exactly
what we've put into this box.
And we can use that.
So number equals that.
Hue equals-- and we'll talk about
what I'm doing here in just a second.
>> Basically we get the
number from the page,
using number equals $
of hash number .val,
and then we are inserting it into this
string so the plus sign in JavaScript
just means string concatenation.
So we have this string, followed by
the string, followed by this string.
And even though we think
of 25,000 as a number,
JavaScript can just
interpret it as a string.
>> So if we do that, we give this a
zero, we can change the color to red.
If we give it 2,500 again, or 25,000
again we can change it to green.
And let's see, what's a good
blue, like 49,000, I think?
Purple.
So yeah.
So far we can change--
>> SPEAKER: Just a question.
what scale are the numbers?
>> DAN BRADLEY: So the numbers
are weird in Hue bulbs.
You might have noticed that this
is sort of a not great green.
It's not a very bright
green that we have here.
That is actually as good
as Hues get, because it's
a number between 0 and
65,000-- or 65,556.
So whatever that is, I
think 16 to the fourth?
It's-- no, 16 to the eighth.
So it's eight hexadecimals
in a row, basically.
But it unfortunately doesn't-- you can't
just use hex notation as well as you
could in other systems.
So you actually have to
convert that to actual numbers.
>> They're kind of odd If
you want a good sense
of what they look like, look it up.
Oops, I just did something.
There we go.
But yeah, it's between
0 and 65,000, roughly.
And you can get fairly decent
sense of what colors want to be.
So 46,000, I think is
actually the good blue.
Nope, that's also.
>> So other things I guess we
should talk about on Hue bulbs
is there's a bunch of different settings
you can have for each of these bulbs.
So we can have-- the Hue, obviously.
You can also include things
like the saturation, so
SAT, which is just some
number between 0 and 255.
>> So if we want high saturation, I guess
that is as high as the saturation goes.
I actually do-- that is the
size and saturation goes.
Or, so if we say set it
to a lower saturation,
it'll be a less bright color.
Not that it's all that bright, as is.
Or is that just not working?
It's hard for me to tell from here.
So the saturation went down,
because I set the saturation to 100.
Since I don't know, I kind of like
colors, I'll leave it at 26,000,
or 255.
I don't know where 26,000 came from.
And we can have it nice and dark.
>> So how are we feeling?
Able to change colors on some bulbs
that we just took out of a box.
Pretty good.
>> The other thing we want to do is
actually turn this thing on and off.
So if we know how to do
each of those things,
it's easy enough to turn it off, because
we just use exactly this AJAX call,
and instead of doing Hue we do on.
And instead of any of this
stuff, we just do false,
and we can just-- unexpected token.
What's that?
>> SPEAKER: For the false,
can you do colors?
>> DAN BRADLEY: No.
Let's see, unexpected token period.
Where is the period?
Not what I meant to click.
All right.
Dollar sign.
There we go.
Much better.
>> So if we just want to turn
it off, we can turn it off.
But now we can't turn it back
on, so that's unfortunate.
So if we switch it to true,
obviously we can turn it on,
but it'll just stay on when we click.
We need some way of first
checking whether it's on or off,
and then either setting it to on if
it's not on, or off if it's not off.
>> So if we go back to our debug, we
can get information about each bulb.
Or if we go to light/4, rather, we can
get each information about the bulb.
We have that on equals true.
We have that brightness equals 254.
We have its hue, we have all the stuff.
So if we actually want to get the
information we want-- for instance,
this is the thing we actually
care about, this on equals true.
>> We can make an AJAX call to see what
color it is-- or not what color,
whether it's on or not.
And then once we have that
information, make another AJAX call
to either turn it off, or turn it on.
>> So let's talk about how we do this.
So if we go up here-- again,
our URL was the IP address,
so 10.245.12.1.75/api/n
ewdevelopers/lights/floor.
And we use the method get.
So, if we actually want to just do that,
just getting the information alone,
we are already there.
Right?
We can get the information
just with that.
>> But we want to do something
with that information,
and this is something that
AJAX is kind of interesting on,
Because it's asynchronous.
If I just made this call
and then immediately checked
what that was supposed to
return, it would fail, right?
Because AJAX is asynchronous, that means
it just sends off a call somewhere else
in space, and it's going to
return when it's ready to return.
But it's not-- you shouldn't
wait around for it, basically.
So you can actually, in this AJAX call,
make a call for when it's successful.
>> So when it finishes you
can tell it what to do.
So on success you give it a function.
Function get.
And I guess it takes data.
>> If we have this function that
we're going to call on data,
or when it successfully returns--
and it'll return some data,
which is this response
that I just showed you.
It's this whole thing.
We want to look at the data , the
success or the state field of the data,
and then the on field
of that state field.
Does that makes sense so far?
>> OK, so because we are
dealing with JavaScript,
this is actually pretty easy.
So let's just do this,
so we're going to-- this
is just doing, again, that
same print that we did earlier.
We'll just console.log
of data .state.un,
and we'll see what we get back.
So this isn't get it end
up changing anything.
It'll just print true
for us, if it works.
>> Let's inspect elements so
we get our console out.
And that did nothing.
Did I hit refresh?
I might not have.
No, that didn't do the thing
I was hoping it would do.
And I apologize for the
confusion for all this.
Let's see, is it quotes?
>> So there's-- I've been dealing with a
fairly wide set of languages lately,
and all of them deal with
objects slightly differently.
So it's possible that
JavaScript treats it
as associative arrays, and no such luck.
OK.
So, going back to my
previously written code,
because obviously I'm going to
need to fall back on that again.
>> Function text.
Oh, we don't return to no string.
OK, the one time that is in
the string is when it gets me.
And this should be dot state dot on.
OK.
Figures.
And there we go.
>> The success field on
AJAX, apparently-- and I
forgot this, obviously-- doesn't take a
string like the rest of the fields do.
It just has whether or not, or basically
you actually pass in the function
that you want it to call on return.
So does this make sense why this works?
>> So we're calling AJAX, so we're
calling off to the internet
with the method get, so we're saying
we're going to use the get method,
just like we did for problem set six.
We're calling to this URL,
which is the lights/--
the 10.245.12.175/api/ne
wdevelopers/lights/4.
And we're calling when
it succeeds, and returns
whatever body console dot log of data.
And so we log the data dot state dot on.
So the on field of the state field
of data, which, looking back here,
is the state field of data, and
the on field of the state field,
which is true.
>> If we have this get, right,
we know whether or not
these this bulb is on or not.
Then we can figure out if we're going
to turn it on or turn it off, right?
Because if it's false, we turn it on.
If it's true, we turn it off.
So let's make another line here,
so we can make it a little bit more
obvious what we're doing.
If data dot state dot on-- so in that
case we know that our light bulb is on.
We want to turn it off.
Let's talk about how are
we going to turn it off?
>> SPEAKER 2: Change the state?
>> DAN BRADLEY: Change the state.
Change the state using AJAX,
just like we did before.
Maybe I'll move that over one.
And instead of having all this extra
stuff, we'll just turn it off, so.
On equals false, and
we'll tab this over, also.
OK.
>> So if it's on, we call
AJAX and turn it off.
If it's off, what is the guess of
what we were going to want to do?
>> SPEAKER 3: Find if it's true.
>> DAN BRADLEY: Yep.
So if on is false.
So we want to set on to true.
So, else.
On, true.
And that should do us.
All right, let's try it out.
What are the bets on
it working first try?
Not good, not good?
All right, let's try it.
>> So turned off, turned on.
It doesn't actually have the check box
right for on versus off, but you know,
You can't win everything.
That's pretty close to everything we
wanted or we needed to talk about.
Since we can turn it on, we can turn
it off, we can change the color.
>> SPEAKER: Dan, I'm sorry.
Question online.
Is it possible you're
missing an HTML tag?
Your HTML--
>> DAN BRADLEY: Uh, yes.
I'm missing one at the
bottom and the top.
Who sent me, or who sent that?
>> SPEAKER: They can trust the viewer.
>> DAN BRADLEY: I see.
Yeah, I totally was missing that.
Of course, it doesn't make any real
difference to whether it works or not.
SPEAKER: Well, for validity's sake.
DAN BRADLEY: But for
validity's sake you need
to have the HTML tag around everything.
But Yeah.
So.
We have this.
Everything's working fine.
Little tips and tricks, if you want.
So you might have noticed that this goes
about or moves kind of slowly, right,
so if we go to 0, submit,
it turns kind of slowly.
If you want that to be faster,
you use the transition time field.
So transmission time of-- if you
just give at 0, so 0 milliseconds.
Oh yes, I do have an extra s in there.
Thank you.
So we can make it turn instantly.
>> I don't think it matters
quite so much for the colors,
because transitioning kind of slowly
and colors' kind of looks nice .
But when with the on and off this
really slow turn on turn off time
is not all that is impressive.
So if you switch, if you use
transition time of 0 there,
that's a little nicer in
general, according to me.
>> So that's interesting.
In any case, there's still a couple
of bugs in how this actually works.
So notice that this turned
on, but didn't turn on bright.
For some reason if you use a shorter
transition time, then the set,
the automatic one or the default.
It Doesn't turn on bright,
unless you tell it to.
I don't know why.
It's something to do with the bulbs,
or the way the Hue bulbs work.
But to fix that you just change the
brightness to 255, when you turn it on.
>> So I closed that accidentally.
Oh, well.
Luckily we're done.
So there you go, see?
Nice and bright.
Alrighty.
So how are we feeling?
Feel like we could set up
if a Hue bulb application?
Cool.
All righty.
Thanks, guys.