>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> STEPHEN TURBAN: So I'm Stephen Turban.
Over on the side here, maybe we
can get some people to dive in.
We have Gabriel and Zack.
So for a brief roadmap on what
this is going to look like,
I'm going to be doing some extremely
high-level look at what MVC is.
Gabe?
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: I'm going to
talk about Ruby and a little bit
how Rails works and how it can
help you build web applications.
>> ZACK CHAUVIN: And I'm going to
show you a specific example of how
to use Rails to build
a super awesome app.
STEPHEN TURBAN: Awesome.
Sweet.
All right.
So let's talk about MVC.
So let's go to the next slide, which
I will do by pressing this button.
And let's go to the next-- development,
I like to think about going to CVS,
because CVS is a store and
also has a V in the center.
>> And so let's imagine to a store.
And let's make this store
sell only one thing.
So we're going to have this
store only sell these red cups.
And imagine you walk in, and you go
to the front of the store, and person.
And his name is Vince.
>> And Vince waves hello at you, says hi.
And you notice one thing about Vince.
So whenever we think about Vince, we
have to think about two key adjectives.
Vince is beautiful, but he's stupid.
OK.
So you know, no fault of his own,
unfortunately, he's beautiful.
He is our view.
So our first cast member is there.
Keep that in mind.
>> Now, you ask Vince, you go, hey Vince.
I'm a customer.
He says hi.
I really want one of your red cups.
And what does Vince say?
Does anyone have any
idea what Vince says?
I'm going to cold call.
What do you think Vince says?
>> AUDIENCE: He says, I can show you
where it is, but I can't give you one.
>> STEPHEN TURBAN: He says, I can show you
Even worse.
Anyone else have another
idea what Vince might say?
>> AUDIENCE: He has to go check
if they have any red cups.
STEPHEN TURBAN: Vince doesn't
even know he has to check.
Anything else?
So you said, has to
check if he has red cups.
Go ahead.
AUDIENCE: What's a red cup?
STEPHEN TURBAN: What's a red cup?
What's a red cup?
Vince is confused.
So Vince is going to talk to
our next cast member, Carl.
And when we think about Carl, we
gotta think about two big adjectives--
he's controlling, but he's incapable.
>> So Vince goes-- he
goes, what is a red cup?
I don't know what a red cup is.
He turns around, and he asks Carl.
He says, Carl, someone
asked for a red cup.
Can you do that?
And what does Carl say?
Let's figure it out.
Does anybody have any
idea what Carl says?
And I'll just repeat it back to you.
I saw a hand movement.
>> AUDIENCE: He tells someone
else to get the red cups.
>> STEPHEN TURBAN: He tells
someone else to get the red cup.
Exactly.
And do we have an idea
who that person might be?
It's a hint.
It's going to start with an M. Mob?
>> AUDIENCE: Model.
>> STEPHEN TURBAN: The model, yes.
His name is not Model, unfortunately,
because that's a silly name.
We have Mitt.
And when we think about Mitt--
no, this is not a picture of Zack.
We have to think of two
key adjectives with Mitt.
He's capable, but he's submissive.
So Mitt knows what he has to do,
but he really can't do anything.
Or he really can't decide on his own.
>> So we have Carl.
Carl shouts at Mitt.
And he says, hey Mitt, we need red cups.
And Mitt goes to his red cup depository.
He grabs a cup, and he gives it back.
Does anybody have any
idea what happens then?
Gives the cup.
So far Mitt has gone to his red
cup repository, taken it out,
checked it off, said,
I took one red cup.
And he's giving it to Carl.
Do you have an idea?
What do you think Carl does?
>> AUDIENCE: Carl gives it to Vince.
>> STEPHEN TURBAN: Carl gives it to Vince.
Vince.
>> AUDIENCE: And Vince
shows it to [INAUDIBLE].
STEPHEN TURBAN: Exactly.
So that's exactly it.
So Vince takes the cup,
doesn't even know what it is,
but he shows it to the user.
So let's try to recreate
this really briefly.
And we're gonna need
three silent volunteers,
as you guys are not going
to be able to speak.
So could I grab three?
OK.
And who would you like to be?
>> AUDIENCE: I'll be Vince.
>> STEPHEN TURBAN: Vince, OK.
Beautiful but stupid.
Great.
Anyone else?
We're looking for a
capable but submissive.
Anybody else want to be capable?
>> AUDIENCE: I could be Carl.
STEPHEN TURBAN: Sweet.
We've got Carl.
>> AUDIENCE: Mitt.
>> STEPHEN TURBAN: Mitt, OK.
And we're going to need
a-- I'll be the customer.
So come on up, come on up.
And is everyone in view?
So I'm going to ask Vince to
stand in the front, just smiling,
just smiling as bright as possible.
And we're going to ask Carl,
right, why don't you, like,
stand right behind her?
And Mitt, why don't you
just go off in the back,
and then I'll give you a group
of cups to hang out with.
>> So I'm a customer.
I come.
And I make [INAUDIBLE] I
say, hi, I'd like a cup.
Perfect.
So Vince has no idea.
So what does Vince do next?
Vince-- OK, so I'm going
to be narrating now.
>> Vince shouts at Carl, cup!
What does Carl do?
Carl yells at Mitt.
Mitt grabs a cup.
Mitt gives it to Carl.
Carl returns it to Vince.
And Vince shows it to the user.
>> And that is a high, high,
high, so high look at MVC.
We divide it by having a view, what
the user sees, a controller, someone
who does everything in the background
but really can't update anything
or can't do anything of any significance
except calling the view and the model.
And then we have Mitt, the model,
who updates whatever data we have.
So thank you so much for our beautiful,
controlling, and capable volunteers.
And I think that was it.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> I think Gabe is going to talk now
on a hopefully less high level.
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: OK, guys.
Now let's talk a little bit more about
code and about Ruby on Rails itself,
and about how it relates
to all of this MVC story.
Basically, Ruby on Rails is a framework.
More about that in a second.
>> But just to give you a
sense of who's using it,
like, all of these big companies--
so GitHub, Groupon, Twitter--
they're all using Ruby on
Rails as their main framework
to implement their website.
So I'm sure a lot of people
have used these websites here.
And it's all Ruby on Rails to implement
the model, the view, and the controller
on all of these websites and many more.
OK?
>> So as I said, Ruby on
Rails is a framework.
And you can kind of think of a framework
in the sense of like building a house.
So if you're going to build
a house-- and you can always
start from scratch, right?
You can try to come up
with a way to saw the wood,
and to bring the wood to the place, and
to get the stones in the right shape,
and then all of that.
But that's going to take
probably lots of years
until you get all the material,
and you get everything together,
and you actually start
to build your house.
>> So it turns out if you start out with
a framework with something that's
already kind of in place
for any type of house
that you want to build-- something
that's very generic but that you can
then model towards your own
goals-- then you can leverage
this power of the frameworks to build
them something much, much faster.
OK.
So this is the same idea in a
framework for a web application
or for any type of
application, for that matter.
>> You actually start out
with half an application
already there in place for you.
And by that, I mean you get lots of
files that already have functions,
like libraries, like functionality,
and commands that you can run in order
to make your life much
simpler and easier.
OK.
>> So in this case, we're going
to talk about Ruby on Rails.
There are lots of different
frameworks out there.
There's Django for Python.
There's Zend framework
or Laravel for PHP.
There are lots of different ones.
Ruby on Rails is a pretty nice new one.
A lot of people use that in startups
and this kind of environment.
And some of these very big
companies that I showed here before
are also using Ruby on Rails.
>> So just to give you a
sense of what Ruby is
like, since you guys are more used
to, like, C and a little bit of PHP
now, so Ruby is going to be the
equivalent of your PHP in this sense.
This is not Ruby.
This is C. OK?
But this is like the
DJBHash function that I
know many people used
for PSET misspellings.
>> And in Ruby, pretty
much like in PHP, you
could implement this with
only a few lines of code.
Instead of having to worry
about the hash function,
having to worry about the buckets,
and all of that, you can just say,
dictionary= Hash.net.
And then you use kind of like
the same idea that PHP had.
And so it's to true.
And then if you want to
check, so check function
would be if dictionary "foo"
equals equals true, return true.
And that's all, OK?
>> So you notice a few differences.
There are no semi-colons
here, as there were in C.
But the general idea is very similar.
OK?
>> Also, in Ruby, there are gems, which
are kind of the Ruby libraries.
And Rails handles them in
a very nice way for you.
So if you want to put
in some library that
does emails, or that
does text messaging,
or that does integration with
Facebook, or any kind of thing
like that for your app,
it's very, very easy.
Odds are you can find something
like that on the internet.
And they just do
something like put which
gem you want to use in the gem file.
And then Rails installs everything.
You don't have to worry about any
of that, so that's really cool.
Also, there's plenty,
plenty of help online.
So you can find lots of things.
If you have an error,
you can just Google it,
and it's going to be
very easy to get help.
>> And it's a lot of fun--
exactly-- because you
don't have to worry about the low-level
details, implementation of hash tables
and having to come up with all of
the HTTP headers, and lots of things,
and even some more higher level things.
You don't have to worry
about that in Rails.
It does it very, very nicely for you.
And we're going to show that
more concretely very soon.
OK.
>> So a little bit about Ruby again.
So it's just like C, as I said.
Instead of printf, we say
"puts," which is "put string."
It puts a string to the console.
And in this case, we're
just printing "Hello World."
We don't need the parentheses,
but it's pretty much similar.
>> And then if you want
to do something here,
like print a bunch of "smalls" and
a bunch of "bigs" in a While loop,
it's kind of like in C, right?
You don't have the params,
but it's pretty much the same.
The indentation here
counts, so x equals 1.
And then While x is smaller than
50-- this is an If, this is an Else.
It's pretty much like what you saw.
>> And then x+= 1 is just incrementing,
kind of like doing the ++ that you can
do in C. But it's pretty
much what you saw in C.
It shouldn't be too complicated.
But it is more powerful.
So there are a few commands here
that are definitely a bit newer.
>> So for example, "puts."
You can use this hashtag notation
here to just print something--
pretty much like what you would do if
the %D or %C or somewhat like that.
And you can actually put an
If right after the statement.
So I only want to do this--
If x is greater than 3.
So why would I have to
make an entire If block?
I don't know.
I can just print this only
if x equals greater than 3.
So this is a one line way
of doing this in Ruby.
>> A list in Ruby is
something very versatile.
So you don't really need
to have just one type.
You can have a string, and then
some numbers, and whatever.
And if you want to append
something to a list,
you can just use this
notation right here.
>> And if you want to iterate.
Pretty much the 4each in PHP, here, you
have a list and you do "List.each do."
And this "elem," this is
like the name of each element
that I'm going to have in my list.
And then I can just "puts elem."
And "puts" pretty much handles
putting it for you, printing it.
It doesn't matter if
it's a string or an int.
It's going to work that out for you.
Right?
Cool.
>> And just like PHP, Ruby and HTML
also integrate very, very nicely.
And here, there's some
HTML with Ruby in it.
So we have a body tag like in HTML.
And if we want to check
that a user is, for example,
logged in, we can just say, beginning of
Ruby, if user.logged_in?, end of Ruby.
Print this entire thing, which
has some Ruby in it, which is just
kind of like that syntax for
PHP that prints out a variable.
Let's print the user.name.
>> So welcome, Stephen,
inside of an HTML div.
And at the end, we have an "end" and
Ruby code, which means this is my
If block.
OK?
So it's just like a seamless
integration between Ruby and HTML.
There are also lots of resources.
But before we move on, does anybody
have any questions about Ruby, anything?
OK.
>> There are lots of resources online
to tryruby.org, Code Academy,
ruby-lang.org, where you can try it
out on your browser before you actually
say, oh, OK, I'm going to use
Ruby for my final project.
And so definitely give those a try.
All of these slides are
going to be available online,
so you can just download them.
And yes?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
what you just showed
was HTML and the code embedded into
it to this notion of Model View
Controller?
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: Yes.
We will do that in a second
when we show our example, OK?
Thanks for the question.
So the question was basically if we
can show this integration of Ruby
in HTML within the Model
View Controller framework.
>> So the idea of the Model
View Controller framework
is it's basically a philosophy,
just like Stephen showed here.
And it's not something
that you have to do,
but it's something that makes
your life so much simpler.
And Ruby on Rails is built
around this philosophy of code.
So we're going to show
an example very soon.
>> So Rails is love.
A lot of people are using it, as I said.
And it's really fun.
You guys should
definitely give it a try.
MVC makes everything simpler.
So the Model View Controller,
the separating things
and putting one person, per se,
or one part of your application
to do each of the different jobs
that you application has to do.
And less time spent
on low-level problems.
And very popular right now.
We have Rails 4.0,
which is a new version.
And it comes with a lot of cool stuff.
Another question.
>> AUDIENCE: Another question.
Ruby on Rails versus
Ruby on Rails Grails.
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: OK.
The question was, Ruby
on Rails versus Ruby--
AUDIENCE: Grails.
Ruby?
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: Yeah.
So Ruby is the language.
>> AUDIENCE: No.
I'm asking you to compare a language
and a framework, Ruby on Rails,
with another popular language
framework-- Grails-- with Ruby
on Rails.
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: OK.
Sorry.
The question was, compare
Ruby and Ruby on Rails
to another framework and another--
>> AUDIENCE: Ruby.
It's OK.
If you don't know about it, that's fine.
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: Like,
what I understand is that--
>> AUDIENCE: There's another
framework called Grails.
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: Oh, Grails.
I never heard of it.
Sorry.
I never heard of Groovy on Rails.
>> AUDIENCE: It's much better
integrated with Java.
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: I see.
>> AUDIENCE: I'm just curious
about some people I know like--
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: No, I never
heard of that one, unfortunately.
Grails.
>> AUDIENCE: And some people
obviously like Ruby on Rails.
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: I've
used Ruby on Rails a lot.
I've used some Django
with Python, as I said.
I've used some Laravel.
But I hadn't used Groovy on Rails.
Sorry.
And it's very popular
now with Rails 4.0.
Like, some of the stuff that Rails
does for you, for example, is you
have lots of CSS files and
lots of JavaScript files.
And you can treat them as
separate and everything.
>> But then it automatically-- when
you send your code to production,
it automatically compiles
them all into one single file
that's minified without any
spaces, so that it takes up
less space in your application, so
that you can really scale things a lot.
That's why such big companies
like Twitter and GitHub
are using Rails, because it does all
that for you, which is really cool.
>> One thing that is very,
very, very daunting
for people, including me,
who are trying to work
with a framework at the beginning, is
that when you start out an application,
you're going to see a bunch of files.
Like, when you create
Rails New, My Application,
you're going to see all of these
folders-- app, bin, config, db, lib,
log, public.
Like, lots and lots of stuff.
>> And the first time I
saw that, I was like,
OK, I have no idea what's going on.
I just want to create a
website with "Hello, world,"
and this is giving me, like,
100 billion different pages.
I don't know what's going on.
So please do not be too daunted by that.
>> The idea is that it actually has half
of a house there for you already.
It has an entire
framework for you already.
That's why there are so many files.
But the nice thing is that it
separates all of them very nicely.
Odds are you don't have to worry
about most of these folders.
>> The most important one, I
would say, is the app folder,
where your app actually lives.
So the config, you're going to
have to configurate some stuff,
like your database and things like
which kind of database you're using.
But other than that, like most of
your work is going to be done in app.
So in app, you have assets, controllers,
helpers, mailers, models, views.
So here, you start seeing that
controllers, models, and views come
into play.
>> Mailers are just if you
want to send emails.
Helpers if you want to
create some functions
that you use a lot in the view.
So you put them in helpers.
And assets is basically all of
your images, all of your CSS,
all of your JavaScript,
and like those kinds
of things that get sent to the client.
And everything that's in the assets,
that I said before, gets minified.
It's compiled.
And you don't really have to worry about
that when it goes to production code.
Cool.
>> Now Zack's going to come in, and he's
going to do an example of Twitter50.
>> AUDIENCE: Woo-hoo!
>> ZACK CHAUVIN: Awesome.
So I had the chance to work
with Ruby on Rails this summer.
It's an amazing framework.
I'm very partial to it.
And I'll just show you a little bit of
an example of what it could look like.
Jump over to Chrome.
So this is an example of a very simple
Ruby on Rails application-- something
like this is something
that Ruby really excels
that-- just where your
models are very well-defined.
>> In this example, you'll see
two different models, which
are that we have users
and we have tweets.
So this is Twitter50,
Harvard's own Twitter.
As you can see, I'm logged in as @zack.
And I'm able to make new tweets.
So I think-- "This is an"-- sorry?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
ZACK CHAUVIN: Oh, OK.
Need to stop the server.
Excellent.
So here we are.
As you can see, we have our
Twitter application right here.
And it's super easy to start the server.
We'll just do "rails server."
Great.
OK.
Thanks for that.
So now we're running.
>> And we'll say, "This
is an awesome seminar."
And let's see what happens.
So we'll tweet about it.
Down at the bottom, you can see
now there's more than three tweets.
So we have a little bit
of pagination going on.
And we have that tweet.
And I can also search through my
tweets-- search for this and the two
ones that have the word
"this" in them show up.
We can also delete tweets by
clicking on the little Delete button.
And obviously, I can only delete
the post that belonged to me.
>> Already, we almost have the
functionality of Twitter.
Like, when you think about it, Twitter
really doesn't do all that much.
It has users, it has tweets.
There's some more complex functionality.
But when you really get down to it,
it's quite a simple Ruby on Rails app.
And something like this, with a
good understanding of Ruby on Rails,
you could probably
make in an hour or two.
>> And that really comes
back to the Ruby mantra,
which is convention over configuration.
So back in the day, people, anytime
they wanted to make this website,
would have to start from scratch.
OK, I want to make a website.
Let's make this file and
this file and this file.
>> With Ruby on Rails,
there's none of that.
You say, I want a new app.
And just like Gabe showed us, it
creates the whole file structure for us.
And we just change the
little parts that we need to.
We just customize what
is unique about our app.
Cool.
So going back to our presentation
preview-- interesting.
Where do I present?
AUDIENCE: Full screen.
Top right.
>> ZACK CHAUVIN: Excellent.
Cool.
OK.
So first of all, the model.
Stephen did an awesome
job of outlining MVC.
And now we're going to relate
that back to Ruby on Rails.
So the model you can kind
of think of as the database.
You've been seeing this in CS50
Finance, where the model stores
the information about
how many stocks you have,
or all the transactions that you made.
This is an example of
a line of how you would
go about making a new model in Rails.
So I want a user.
It's going to have an
email, which is a string,
and a password, which
is also the string.
So it's like those-- I want each row
in my table of users to look like that.
>> A really awesome part
about Rails is that it
makes it unnecessary to
write any SQL pretty much.
How many of you guys loved
writing SQL in PSET 7?
Exactly.
SQL is not very user-friendly.
And Rails abstracts all that away
with these really easy commands.
So for example, if we have a
user, a user has many tweets.
And each one of those
tweets belongs to a user.
>> So if you look here, this
is our model for our tweet.
And all we have to say is
this single line-- I'm a tweet
and I belong to a user.
And with that single line and a
little bit of database configuration,
Rails sets up this relationship.
Anytime, I can just say, zack.tweets,
like, give me all of Zack tweets.
No SQL.
Super easy.
Again, that's convention over
configuration coming into play.
>> You can see a little bit
of an example of Ruby here.
Like Gave said, writing Ruby is
sort of like writing English.
It's a very high-level language,
and it makes it really easy
for us to say things like, I want to
make sure that this tweet has a body.
Its presence is true.
And I want to make sure that this
tweet, just like normal Twitter,
has a max length of 140.
It's super-intuitive, a
really great language.
>> Next up we have the view.
So this involves HTML and CSS.
And here's an example of a view.
So Ruby on Rails kind of seamlessly
integrates both Ruby and HTML
in order to generate
what we want on the page.
So this is an example of our layout.
So you can see some tags that you
guys are used to, like HTML, body,
all that good stuff.
>> And right in here, though, we
incorporate some Ruby by saying,
if there's a message to display,
then display the message in a div.
So I won't get too much into that.
But this is generally a
page that gets rendered on--
and no matter what page you're
on, this one gets rendered.
So this is what gets included always.
Cool.
>> Another example of a view-- this is
the one where it chose all the tweets.
And some of this stuff
might look pretty familiar.
So for example, right here, we're
looping through each of the tweets,
and we're printing them out.
So here is where we're
printing out the body.
And if the tweet's user-- here's a
real example of no SQL is involved.
I'm just asking, is this
tweet's user the current user?
Then show a link to delete it.
It's super simple.
>> The controller.
So this is, again, the interface
between the model and the view.
It's the one that does the hard work
of interacting-- being the middleman.
It loads information for the
view, which we'll see in a sec.
And in order to interact
with the model, it
calls model methods, which are what
you guys are familiar as functions.
>> So for example, this is
our tweet's controller.
It might look a little
daunting right now.
But it is actually super intuitive
once you start diving in.
So for example, in our index, that's
where we want to show all the tweets.
And so this line basically
just asks for all the tweets.
And then we initialize both
the new tweet-- so like
if they want to create a
new tweet on that page.
>> And it asks what the current user is.
And this is very akin to the
render that you saw in PSET 7,
where it's just kind of telling
the view-- it's kind of, like,
passing the variables that you're
going to need in the view to the view.
And there's a whole bunch
of different methods
that this tweet's controller can handle.
>> But really, Rails does
a great job of kind
of dividing them into the different
actions that your controller might do.
Are there any questions about
any of the MVC parts of Rails?
Kind of just a breeze by.
So you guys can check
it out on your own.
Awesome.
We'll keep going.
>> So installing Rails.
Installing Rails might be, like,
one of the more daunting parts
of the whole Rails
process, unfortunately.
But obviously, all of
us are around to help.
And once it's on there,
a lot of great resources,
as Gabe mentioned, for getting started.
Here are the links that
you'll need in order
to download Rails to get it
installed on your machine.
Obviously, it's available
for both Windows and Mac
and for the CS50 appliance.
Questions about anything we've said?
>> AUDIENCE: I would be
interested in, actually--
so I know that downloading
software is the biggest barrier.
If there's enough interest to have a
downloading mini session or something.
ZACK CHAUVIN: Mm-hm.
Yeah.
That might be really helpful.
If anyone's really gung-ho about
using this for their project
or in the future, then we'd definitely
be happy to talk to you about that.
Mm-hm.
>> AUDIENCE: A related question
to what I asked before.
For those of you who have done
other frameworks that are still
trying to do the same
thing, make it easier
to build a website or a
functionality, I think any sense
of why we would be on Rails versus
Zend or some of the other frameworks
and languages.
>> ZACK CHAUVIN: I'll just
say my $0.02 about that.
I love Ruby on Rails.
I've had the chance to work
in both PHP and Ruby on Rails.
I much prefer Ruby on
Rails because of Ruby.
Definitely, that's a big part of it.
Like, when you're
choosing your framework,
you also choose your language.
>> Ruby is super accessible-- I think
a much better language than PHP.
But that's kind of personal preference.
As well, another consideration is
the community behind the framework
that you're working with.
>> Right now Ruby on Rails is really hot.
There's tons of support behind it.
You post something on Stack
Overflow about a problem you're
having in Ruby on Rails,
and it's answered.
Again, it's open source, which means
that it's constantly being changed.
There's tons of people
that are really dedicated
in order to making this a
really awesome framework.
So that's why I would
choose Ruby on Rails.
GABRIEL GUIMARAES: Yeah.
I would say that the idea
behind most frameworks you're
going to find out there is
very, very similar, right?
So the Model View Controller,
the fact that our controller's
going to look like something
like this-- each of the functions
is like one of your pages,
and it redirects you,
and it initializes the variables.
That's going to be the same thing for
every framework that you see out there.
And there's going to be the model.
And you can do stuff like, "belongs to."
So instead of doing the SQL version,
you just, like, do, user.tweets,
and you get everything.
Everybody has that.
Except in Ruby, you do user.tweets,
and then some frameworks in PHP,
you do user.getalltweets
WHERE my PHP is not a problem.
Like, it's a big line.
It's the same thing,
but it's a big line.
>> So that's one of the main reasons
of my preferences over Ruby.
It's just I do exactly the
same thing in other frameworks,
it just takes me twice
as long lines of code.
OK?
>> Any other questions?
>> ZACK CHAUVIN: Something
I'll mention quickly-- Gabe
talked a little bit about gems.
And that's a really great-- I mean, this
is kind of common to all frameworks,
that there's kind of a gem concept,
which is like in my little example,
I have login.
Like, you can sign in, sign out.
Like, that's actually
kind of a complex process.
It was handled a little
bit for you in PSET 7.
But I still don't fully know how
to implement sign-in, sign-out.
And that's because
Ruby on Rails has tons
of gems that do stuff like that for you.
>> Again, convention over configuration.
Everyone's going to be doing
this sign-in, sign-out step.
So why not just make a package, called
Devise in this case, which is a gem.
You just include it.
And then there is some help
online with how to use it.
And you don't have to worry
about anything like that.
>> Attaching pictures to these
things-- a gem for that.
Like, anytime you're trying to do
anything new, there's a gem for that.
And you kind of just
piece together these gems
and build a really complex
application very quickly.
Cool.
Any other questions?
>> STEPHEN TURBAN: Woo-hoo.
I don't think [INAUDIBLE].
>> GABRIEL GUIMARAES: OK.
Thanks so much, guys.
>> STEPHEN TURBAN: Buh-bye.
ZACK CHAUVIN: Buh-bye.
>> STEPHEN TURBAN: Woo-hoo.
[APPLAUSE]
>> Yay.