>> TOMAS REIMERS: Cool.
So hi, everyone.
My name's Tomas.
I'm a TF and this is
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Armi.
Nice to see you guys.
TOMAS REIMERS: Cool.
So we're going to be talking
about Leap Motion today.
So Leap Motion is a
really cool product that
lets you interact with a
computer in a different way.
So the whole idea behind
leap motion is that you
can use your hands to
interact with the computer.
So right here I have something set up.
I'll talk about it in a bit.
But the basic version is you can
see that I have my hands in front
of my computer and when I move them,
you get the analog on the computer
and you can analyze this.
You can make gestures.
You can use your hands to
interact with the computer
in new and interesting way.
>> Well, I actually first
want to pass off to Armi
to show you some cool demos of what
some people have done with this.
And then we'll talk about how
you actually code with this.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah.
Hello.
So as we saw, little
data here, but let's see
what some people have done with this.
So let me just open up this example.
And then, so, for example, you can see
my hand analog there, but now this time
some people using Unity have
decided to put a little more skin
and stuff around the hand.
So I can, let's go with this one,
sure, have my hands interacting.
And you can probably imagine a
couple of other cool useful things
that you can do with this.
So this is at least one example.
And then let's jump out of this.
>> And then another cool one
is, let's go with this one.
Plasmo ball.
Again, we wouldn't necessarily
expect this level of complexity
from a final project for CS50.
This is just to show you
some of the, give you guys
a little inspiration for what
you guys can do with Leap Motion.
So for example here's a cool
physics example, which there we go.
Has both of my hands so now you
have this little plasma ball.
And the ball is reacting to the physics
of me moving my hand around the ball.
Now this is all though using Unity,
using kind of tools and frameworks
that we haven't taught
you guys in class,
but as you can see some pretty
cool run throughs with that.
>> But one thing that you guys can do
starting off right now with Leap Motion
is work in JavaScript.
Leap Motion has a JavaScript API that
you guys can use and we highly, highly
recommend that you guys build
your projects using that.
So with that, let me
pass it back off to Tomas
to talk about Leap
Motion and JavaScript.
TOMAS REIMERS: Cool.
Or do you want to show
them the Visualizer first?
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Oh yes.
Yes.
Let's talk more about that Visualizer.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So on a most basic
level, when you first get to Leap Motion
you're going to have this box.
Here, want me to take control?
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah, go for it.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So When you
first get to Leap Motion
you're going to have this box.
It has a device which
looks something like this.
You plug it into your computer,
install the necessary drivers,
and then it will basically be set up.
So the easiest way to sort
of deal with Leap Motion
is open up this program it installs
called the Leap Motion Visualizer.
And the Visualizer is literally
what I'm showing here.
It allows you to see the
skeletal outline of your hands.
And what the Leap Motion
is interpreting them as.
So the Leap Motion uses the camera
to sort of look at your hands
and then it tries to guess what the
basic skeletal composition that you
see on the screen is.
And that's what it shows you.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Every
single little point
and thing that you see there is
data that's available to you guys
as well to use.
So you see that it's
capturing that Tomas
has five fingers, each of
those different fingers
are also available for you as data
points to use in whatever application
that you might want.
If you want to see if
somebody's doing a thumbs up
you can see if their fingers
are curled and whether they're
thumb finger is pointing
upwards, or where
their wrist or palm is
and that type of stuff.
TOMAS REIMERS: Cool.
So you can see some gestures it
understands better than others.
Remember, that it is looking at your
hand from at a camera from the bottom,
so when you have your hands like
this it understands them fully,
but once you start to try and do a
thumbs up, sometimes it reads it,
sometimes it can guess, but honestly
the camera just can't see the thumb.
So it's not really
sure what's happening.
Just some limitations to keep in mind
when you're developing with this.
>> Anyway, so going back to this.
The Visualizer actually
has a lot of useful tools.
So the Leap Motion is
programmed in such a way
that they don't expect you to
interact with that image data.
They don't really
expect you to understand
what's happening behind the scenes.
What they do is expose
a bunch of APIs for you
such that you can
interact with this data
directly without understanding
what's going on under the hood.
>> So if we hit H here in the Visualizer
you'll see a lot of options.
The important one here though
is if you hit O and then hit H,
you'll see that it
lets you draw gestures.
So a gesture, you'll see
it draws an arrow across.
A gesture is one of the ways which Leap
Motion sort of lets you get at the data
without having to process it.
So rather than me needing to figure
out, oh, the hand was moving,
even if I have point access, the
API will sort of just tell me,
hey, they made this gesture.
So you can make basic arrow gestures.
You can make circle gestures.
You can make tapping gestures.
And you can make key press gestures.
Yeah.
And that kind of stuff.
So now that we've sort of
seen what Leap Motion can do,
you can see it can read a
whole bunch of gestures.
I think I'm going to
pass it back to Armi
and he's going to talk about how
you get at these with JavaScript,
how you even begin a project with this.
And then we'll talk about some
cool places you can go with that.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah.
Sounds good.
So yeah, the very first thing we
will want you to do of course,
is after you get the Leap Motion is to
go to leapmotion.com, set up, install
the drivers and stuff.
After doing that you can go
make sure that it's connected.
If you see in your little tray the
Leap Motion icon and it's green,
then you know you're all set.
And of course check out exactly what
Tomas just showed you with the gestures
and doing the screen taps, and
key taps, and that type of stuff.
>> After that though we,
once again, like I said,
we have access to all of these
things in JavaScript as well.
The ideal set up that
we would recommend you
guys is to go into your
vhost directory, local host,
public in your CS50 appliance.
And when you go there what you'll
see is a index dot HTML file.
Now that index dot
HTML file or index dot
PHP file, whichever is
fine, what you can then do
is go to your main operating system.
And if you go to the IP address
that's listed in the bottom right
corner of your appliance right here,
as you can see, then what happens
is you go to the page that's
referenced by that index dot HTML file.
So all the code that you might put in
there gets sent and is usable here.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So it's also
important just for reference
that if you guys actually know
how to set up a server yourself,
or you want to put this on the worldwide
web, you're welcome to do whatever.
Remember that these are
just JavaScript files
and all the Leap processing
is done on the client.
So it doesn't really matter
where your server lives
so long as the computer
you're viewing the website on
has Leap Motion installed.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Absolutely.
Like Tomas said, yeah,
whatever works for you guys.
This is just one of our recommendations.
Now to start using Leap
Motion what you would do
is you would import the
JavaScript file from Leap Motion.
And then from there what
you can do is, right now
I just have this paragraph
tag set up with an ID of text.
Things that we would recommend
are setting controller options
for Leap Motion with the
enable gestures to be true.
So by default those
gestures that we showed you
guys, the circle, and the
key tap, and the swipes,
those aren't shown to
you guys by default.
But we highly recommend using those
so you're not reinventing the wheel.
Enable those to true, passing those
controller options to leap dot loop
and you're all set to go.
Because then you just have
defined a anonymous function
that will take in a
frame from Leap Motion
and that frame has all the
information that you're going to need.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So just to
recap, you have one object.
You have this function
called leap dot loop.
And you call it with two arguments.
You call it with one,
the controller options.
And there are a lot of
options you can put in there.
The one we're going to
emphasize is enable gestures.
And if you set it equal to true then
you can get access at this gestures
that we showed you in the Visualizer.
>> And then the second argument is a
function, it's kind of like a call back
which will be called every
time every frame of Leap,
so every time leap registers that
your hand move, it has a new frame.
And it calls this function with one
argument, which is the frame object.
And that frame object describes
the frame as Leap sees it.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Exactly.
So this contains all the useful
bits and pieces of information
that we were talking about earlier.
Checking frame dot gestures
is a array of gestures
that the leap motion caught your
hands doing in the last frame.
So for example, what we're
doing here is we're checking,
hey, Leap, in that last frame did
you catch any gestures that I did?
And if so what we decide to do
is iterate through those gestures
and try and get some useful
information from them.
Each gesture has a unique
ID associated with it.
They have types.
You can look at which fingers
were involved in the gestures
by checking out this pointable stuff.
So if when you go through the
Leap Motion JavaScript API stuff,
when they mention pointables,
they're talking about these fingers.
And then hands are, of course,
the entire hand object.
>> What else?
You can check how long
the motion went on
for and, yeah, all those useful things.
So what I'm doing right now
here is I logged the frame,
and then I update my HTML to display
all of these bits of information
from the frame.
So let's check that out.
>> So here it is.
Here's the index dot HTML file.
And as you just saw when I just moved
my hand Leap caught a circle motion.
So you can see me doing a circle over
here, updates with circle information.
Doing swipes, catches swipes.
Let's try a screen tab.
There we go.
Screen tap and a key tap.
So key taps also, by the
way, are when you hit down.
So you can imagine
maybe playing a piano.
>> And then screen taps are
when you hit the screen.
So you can imagine maybe you actually
have a touch screen in front of you
and you're hitting the touch
screen in front of you.
And then we can grab one
of these objects in here.
So remember I said that I was
passing the frame into console log.
And so we can check out all the
bits and pieces of information
that are available in
that frame as well to use.
>> Like I said earlier,
pointables are the fingers.
At that moment we didn't have our
hands in front of the Leap Motion
so it registered zero,
but this is how you
would start to find out maybe
how many fingers are the screen.
And that type of information.
TOMAS REIMERS: And remembering
this is just an object.
So everything can be accessed
sort of like a struct
in C. You have the object
name dot the property name.
And then within that you have
arrays and you have other objects,
but remember it's just an object.
There's nothing special
because we're using Leap.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah.
Cool.
Should we check out a couple
of JavaScript examples?
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So
quickly remember that we
said that Leap can actually
run on any website.
LeapJS is just served to a client.
And so along as the client has
Leap Motion attached it will work.
So Leap Motion has a
website where people
can share their examples
of things they've made.
So we're just going to go
through a couple of them
to see what's possible before
diving into more specifics about how
it's possible.
So
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Let's see.
TOMAS REIMERS: Now it should be working.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: So now
before we saw an example
using Unity that rendered our hands
with pretty impressive graphic skins,
but now you can see you can do the
same thing inside a web browser.
This is all inside Chrome
just using JavaScript.
And then the other nice
thing is if you want
to know how they did this,
the examples on JavaScript
also include code options that
you can check out and then see
how this person was grabbing
hands and codes and such.
>> So that's all you can find
at developer.leapmotion.com.
You can go and check out JavaScript
examples that they have there.
So yeah.
Here are these, oops sorry.
Let's try that again.
Oh.
I have two right hands.
So yeah.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So and again,
remember sometimes Leap messes up.
Just give it a second.
It's not perfect, but it's pretty good.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: One
other recommendation also
is to not do it in direct sunlight.
So the way Leap Motion
works is, actually
if I show the camera this
as well, infrared light.
So it sends those out and then
reads them when they come back.
So if you're trying to
do it direct sunlight,
for example, it's probably
not going to work,
or it's going to require
some calibration to do so.
>> Also another recommendation is to
clear the space behind the Leap
and in front of Leap.
Think of it as working
inside of a dome that's
surrounding this Leap Motion object.
If there's stuff right
behind it as well,
that's also going to interfere
with how the Leap Motion's trying
to recognize your hand
and that type of stuff.
>> So, for example, I think in this
case it's my laptop actually
that's kind of making the Leap Motion.
Yeah, there we go.
So if I clear out my laptop from
behind it the hand show up pretty well.
So yeah.
There's that.
So what else did we show them.
TOMAS REIMERS: I think
now would be the time
to sort of dive into and let's just
make a demo totally from scratch.
It's going to be really simple.
Basically what we're going
to try to do is make it
so that when you swipe your hand, the
background's going to start out as red,
and when you swipe your hand, the
background's going to turn green.
OK?
Really simple.
And it's basically just
going to go through a lot
of the concepts behind
Leap so that we can
get into this ideology of how Leap works
and how we can build stuff with that.
And then from there we'll
probably just show you
the API Docs and where you
can read more about this.
And then we'll call it day.
So do you want to code or
do you want me to code?
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah.
Well, I guess we can work
together on this and try
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So we'll
do some pair coding.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: There we go.
That's exactly what I
wanted to check out.
Cool.
So for example in here, let's see.
While we are iterating
through the gestures already,
TOMAS REIMERS: Want to make
just a completely new file?
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Completely new file?
Yeah, sure.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: Yeah.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: So let's do that.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So we're going
to make a completely file.
We'll call it hand dot HTML.
That's cool with me.
So remember you do an HTML tag,
then within that you have a head.
That head has a title within it.
So tab the other way.
There you go.
Title, we'll call it Leap Example.
Yep.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Oops.
Title.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: Yep.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: There we are.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: And
then let's make a body.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Wait, let's
also make sure to import.
TOMAS REIMERS: Oh, of course.
My bad.
So always make sure you have the Leap
script so that's a script given to you
by Leap Motion which basically
allows the web browser to connect
to the device on the user's computer.
And then in this we also
need a body and let's just
make the body say hi so
that we can show students
how to connect to this new
web page that they made.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Sure.
So let's just put another--
>> TOMAS REIMERS: Hi, hello world.
So a very basic example.
Really just a demo.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: And then in here we
can go to, we called it hand dot HTML,
right?
And oh!
So I wonder what's wrong
with this right now.
Let's add read permissions
to hand dot HTML.
TOMAS REIMERS: Do you want
to do it in the big terminal
so that we can just show it on the--
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah, that makes sense.
All right.
So I just added the
permissions, but if we
were to check out the
permissions before we
would have seen that actually hand
dot HTML didn't have read permissions
and therefore we couldn't render it.
But now if we do so, we see our
little hello world right there.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So let's actually,
as he was writing, hello world,
I thought about a way
we could change this.
Let's make it say hello world, and
then when you wave, it says goodbye.
Right?
So hello, goodbye.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Sure.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: That sounds pretty good.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: That
sounds good to me, too.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So if we're
going to do that let's just
think through the web page a little bit.
We're going to need some script
which basically registers
that you waved and to a Leap,
a wave and a swipe, same thing.
So we're going to need a script that
basically registers for that swipe.
And another thing we're
going to need is we're
going to need some
actual content to change.
>> So as you remember, jQuery
allows you to change content.
So one thing we might want to include
in this is the jQuery library.
And then to be able to select what
we're actually going to change content,
that's going to need an ID
or a class, or something
that we can use to select it.
So we'll just give it a
quick ID of change text.
And then do you want to grab jQuery?
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: So what's the first
thing on our to do list then now?
TOMAS REIMERS: Let's grab jQuery?
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Let's
grab jQuery, OK, cool.
In that case, I'm going
to have to actually--
where would be the
best place to do that?
>> TOMAS REIMERS: jQuery, so if you
Google jQuery, hit jQuery, the first
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Very first one.
TOMAS REIMERS: Or download.
It's fine.
Hit download v1 and v2 on the left.
So we're describing jQuery from
online like you've probably done.
Scroll down.
Up, up.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Oh, right here now?
TOMAS REIMERS: Or that.
Yep.
So jQuery has a hosted version
which means that you don't actually
need to download it,
but you're more than
welcome to download it
and host it yourself.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Cool.
So now we have jQuery.
Now what's next on our to do list.
TOMAS REIMERS: Awesome.
So next what we need
do is we actually need
to give p hello world an ID
so we can change it, right?
So let's give an idea of,
I don't know, change text?
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Let's just
do it this way, I guess.
TOMAS REIMERS: changeText, cool.
And now let's just refresh the page.
Make sure everything works.
So back in the browser.
Cool.
Always a good reminder that
when you're building a website,
probably refresh every time you make
any somewhat significant change just
because sometimes you
accidentally drop a tag,
or you accidentally delete something,
and then you break something small,
but then when you make a bigger change
you're like, why did this big change
seemingly break the unrelated thing.
So it's always good to sort of
go and do those sanity checks.
>> Anyway so now let's do
one last sanity check,
which is let's try to change
text without Leap Motion,
without anything, just
on the page load it'll
change hello world to
goodbye using jQuery.
So if you remember jQuery exposes
this dollar sign function,
which we can pass CSS selector to,
namely hashtag change text, which
selects the element with
an ID of change text.
And then we're going
to call the method HTML
on the object it returns with the
argument of a string goodbye, which
will change the items
HTML to say goodbye.
Awesome.
That seems pretty cool.
And now when we refresh
the page we're going to see
it instantly changes to goodbye, right?
Because it doesn't wait for anything.
Sort of as soon as that script
runs it changes it to goodbye.
Cool.
>> So now let's wrap that in a function.
Right.
So we're going to want
to make a function.
We'll call it goodbye.
So function goodbye is
going to take no arguments
and it's not really
going to return anything.
And it's just going to
do that in JavaScript.
Excellent.
So our function goodbye now
changes the text to goodbye, right?
So this gives us a way
to basically change
that text to goodbye whenever
we called that function.
Right?
So this is pretty cool.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Well, we
can also just make sure
that now since we're not calling the
function, if we refresh the page,
notice it's not going
to change the text.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: Excellent.
So now we're going to start
to get into that Leap stuff
that we were talking about.
So Armi, do you want to
take it from here or?
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah.
Sure.
I'm probably going to need
to double check things,
but for example remember
we said we wanted
to make sure in Options
we set enable gestures
TOMAS REIMERS: Good catch.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: To be true.
And then we were recommending
that you guys would
run leap dot loop, which
as we said earlier,
has two options, a JSON object that
is the options for how you want
to configure the Leap Motion to
work, and then a function that's
going to catch a frame as a callback
function like Tomas was saying.
And then edit what you want
to do with that function.
>> So we pass in the
option and now we define
a function that will take in a frame.
And now we have to define
what that function does.
It's also for the sake of the
future, do that to make sure.
TOMAS REIMERS: Excellent.
So now we have this
leap dot loop function
call which basically says watch Leap
with these options and every time
something changes, call this
function frame with all of the data
that you are aware of in frame.
Sounds pretty good.
So now quick sanity check,
which I always recommend,
is in that just put
console dot log frame.
And then in Chrome open it
up and look at your console
and play around with Leap to see the
frames being logged because that will
get you an idea of what
data you have access to.
And as always if you get confused,
look up the API reference.
And we'll include the link
for that at the end of this.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: So we
refresh the page and then
we go and open up the console again.
And now we notice that we're
having frames passed in,
these little objects we saw earlier.
So yeah.
These are our frames
showing up in the console.
Cool.
>> So now that we've grabbed the
frames, as you might remember earlier
from the example that we had,
if we check frame dot gestures
we get the list of gestures that
the frame most recently caught.
We can check the length of that array
to see if Leap caught any gestures.
So if that array is
greater than zero then we
know that we have some stuff to do.
>> So let's wrap that up in an if condition
and now in here what we know is we
have seen a gesture, let's act on it.
So now that we're in here we
have a gesture to check out.
TOMAS REIMERS: Well, the first
thing is it's not just one gesture,
it could be as many gestures.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Very true.
TOMAS REIMERS: So per
classic C style here
we'll probably want to use a for loop.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Here we are then.
We decided to iterate
through the gestures.
And let's see.
i plus, plus.
And now if we maybe made
just a var gesture equals
frame dot gestures
bracket i, now we have
gesture itself, which is just one
single instance of a gesture object
for us to work with
inside of this for loop.
All right.
TOMAS REIMERS: Let's sanity
check here again and just console
dot log gesture to see what we get.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM:
Console dot log gesture.
Okie dokie.
And refresh one more time.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: And let's
try making a gesture.
You'll see that a bunch
of, when he swipes,
you get a bunch of gestures in the
console and if he tries to do a circle,
it's just--
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Circles
are just really nice.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: Now there's a weird thing
here, which is he's doing one circle,
but this is logging 80 gestures, right?
That's a lot of gestures.
So the first sort of thing to
realize, and this can be confusing,
is that a gesture
isn't just logged once.
>> On every frame, right,
so if I'm doing a circle
Leap will detect this
is a change, from this
is a change, from this is a change.
And it will log each one of those.
But in each one of those,
it's going to say, oh,
there's a gesture currently in progress.
So let me just say, hey, there's a
gesture and it's currently in progress.
So what we don't want to
do is say, oh, on every one
of those gestures you
want to change text.
What we want to do is when that gesture
stops, and we can check for that,
then we want to change text.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Mhmm.
So like Tomas is
explaining these gestures
might appear through multiple
frames, but for example,
when we were having
that circle, we can see
that the ID for that one
single circle that we
might have been trying to complete
was the same ID throughout.
And in fact, you can also
check out the status.
updated.
>> And then this is probably the
last circle that, oh, well, OK.
So sometimes it shows you a
status of stopping a gesture
and it also shows you a status
of starting a new gesture when
it recognizes for sure that
you've started a new gesture.
For example in this case.
TOMAS REIMERS: Cool.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: So yeah.
And then, let's see.
You can also notice
though we were making
a circle and gesture
has a field called type
that tells us what kind
of gesture that is.
So that might be useful for us
you try and do what we're doing.
TOMAS REIMERS: So
transitioning back to JS,
the first thing that occurs to me
also, just reading through this code
is there's a small optimization,
which is we actually
don't need this if condition, right?
Because if frame dot gestures dot
length is zero, that for loop's
not going to run anyway.
So we may as well just go
ahead and get rid of that.
Again, while you're writing code
it's important to go back and sort
of refactor as you realize that you
could have done something better,
or that there is another way to do that.
So now we're just going to clean this
up quickly and also clean up your code.
That's a big deal.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Good
style is very appreciated.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: You can
always tell when someone
has code where there used to be an if
condition and then they removed it,
but they didn't uncomment it.
It's very obvious and
it kind of looks ugly.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: So what's
next on our to do list?
TOMAS REIMERS: So now as we were saying,
I guess the first thing we want to do
is make sure that that gesture's
actually a swipe, right?
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So if we're saying that
our goodbye is kind of like a swipe,
we'll go with it's a swipe, the
first thing we need to say is, hey,
is the gesture type a swipe, right?
Not a circle or a top,
but is it a swipe?
So the way we can do that
is we can say gesture
dot type equal equal swipe as a string.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: [INAUDIBLE] gesture
dot type equals equals swipe.
There we are.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: And
then the last question
we want to see is gesture dot
state equal equal stop, right?
So that's when the
gesture's been stopped.
I actually think for swipe, I
know this off the top of my head,
but you're welcome to
look it up, when you
swipe every time it registers it
until you stop is a start gesture.
And then the last one's
just a stop gesture.
So there will only be one stop
gesture, which is great for us.
So what we can do is say if gesture dot
type equal equal swipe and gesture dot
status equal equal
stop, then let's sanity
check here console dot log gesture.
>> So we'll go back here.
We'll refresh the page.
And now the only time something should
be console dot logged is when we swipe.
And we try to swipe and we see nothing.
Right?
So this is actually a big issue.
We're not seeing what we expected to.
And debugging can be a big part of this.
So the first thing we're going
to say is, OK, let's console dot
log it if gesture dot
type equal equal swipe.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah, let's do that.
TOMAS REIMERS: So we're
going to go back to this.
We'll refresh.
We'll swipe.
And we're going to see a bunch of them.
OK.
So clearly the problem was
with our gesture dot status.
So if we open up one of these we'll
look in the objects and we'll see,
well, it's a stop, but, oh,
it's called state, not status.
So if we head back to
our code we can say
if gesture dot type equal equal swipe
and gesture dot state equal equal stop,
then we'll console dot log it.
And so refresh.
We swipe.
And we'll see that on
every swipe, we're only
getting one, which is the
end, which is great, right?
That's what we want.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yep.
And we can also notice that the IDs for
each of these gestures are separate.
So as Tomas was saying because we're
catching this one stop state that
exists at the end of a swipe, we're
getting individual separate gestures
from Leap Motion.
Great.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: Let's go ahead and
just do the final thing, which is,
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Goodbye.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: Awesome.
And now let's check out our website.
One
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Second.
We did, yeah, we did call it Goodbye.
Great.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: No, Goodbye
is a real function.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah.
Let's do that.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: And when we
wave goodbye, it says goodbye.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: We have victory.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: So pretty exciting stuff.
Hopefully you can build something
else, but you get the idea of, right?
You can detect gestures.
You can call functions.
And from that that really gives you
some very fundamental building blocks
to say, oh, maybe when they swipe up,
because you can also detect things
like direction.
I want them to do something.
Or when they swipe right, I
want them to do something.
And we can start to get
creative with how exactly
we're going to improve our website
using these swipe gestures or circle
gestures, or tap gestures,
either key taps or screen taps.
And then other than that you're
more than welcome to play
with the actual data,
but if you want to do
that we would suggest you go to the docs
because they're actually really good.
So headed to the docs now.
Or do you want to talk about that?
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah.
Let's do that.
Also one other tidbit of advice,
do try and think of this in 3D.
So actually let's pull up those gestures
one more time console dot log gesture
and we do that.
Come back in and now let's try a
couple of these, couple of those.
>> If we go in and check out
these gestures as well
as you can see that
they're dimensionality
is in three directions, actually.
So don't just limit
yourself to a 2D screen
even though you might
be on a 2D website.
You can try and think how a user
might interact with the website in 3D.
TOMAS REIMERS: In a 3D space.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Exactly.
And yeah.
So you get directions, velocities,
all these cool bits of information.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: And if you're not
familiar with that, it goes x, y,
and then z is this last dimension.
Just something which you probably are
familiar with if you've dealt with 3D
coordinate planes before.
If you haven't, it's the same as a 2D
one except there's a third dimension.
We call it z.
And everything, sort of like
direction, which is where it's going,
position-- I think it might even
expose acceleration, I'm not sure.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah, I believe.
It definitely has speed.
I'm actually not 100%
sure about acceleration.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: It may be an option
you can pass on to something.
So position and speed are exposed
in these sort of three coordinates.
So x, y, z or delta x, delta y, delta z.
So now headed to the documentation
it's developer.leapmotion.com
and then you can click Documentation.
Again, Leap Motion has all these
wonderful APIs, one for JavaScript,
one for C Sharp and Unity, one for
C++, one for Java, one for Python,
and one for Objective C. I personally
would push you towards JavaScript
or if you want to learn a
new language, try Python.
Both of those languages I've worked with
before and they're really easy to learn
and you already know JavaScript, which
makes it a really good contender.
>> One word of caution
when you enter the docs.
Make sure you're on Docs v2.0.
Because if you're on
version one, it won't work.
Also for the example gallery.
We spent a good 30 minutes
trying the debug our Leap
before we realized that
V1 doesn't work with V2.
So just make sure you're on version two.
And then I'll let him
show your the docs.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah.
So here's the API overview and then
some bits and pieces of the information
that we've already told you.
Nice little floating
hands above a Leap Motion.
And a reminder to think
about space in 3D.
One of the first objects to think about
with Leap Motion are hands, of course.
We saw those recognized
by the Visualizer.
And then you might have
seen that it recognized
part of the wrist and the
arm associated with it.
TOMAS REIMERS: If you want
to pull up the Visualizer.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah,
let's do that again.
TOMAS REIMERS: You can see, always
just a good reminder to sort of see,
the Visualizer tries to show
all the data that Leap sees.
So you'll see that we have
these sort of four points
by the wrist and then the actual wrist.
And you also have this ball at the palm.
All of these are points
recognize recognized by the leap.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Exactly.
And so with that hand object
each frame has a hand array
as well where you can also get
the left and the right hands.
You can get which
direction the hands are
facing with the normal
direction of the palm,
or as they call it the palm normal.
What else do we have?
We also, oops.
Let's try and scroll down this way.
The arms, the fingers are
represented by the finger
class, which is a pointable object.
So like we were saying, we saw that
array of pointables for each hand.
Those are the little
fingers to think about.
So this is a good overview to go
through to try and understand.
TOMAS REIMERS: [INAUDIBLE]
hand anatomy up there.
ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah, exactly.
So yeah.
There's a lot of raw data that the
Leap Motion takes in interprets well
for you, so it's a great
idea to go through here
and try and figure out how Leap has
already figured things out for you
and so what information you
have available from there.
And then from there I would recommend
going into this left section over here,
which goes, well actually no, those are
actually just more API stuff about--
>> TOMAS REIMERS: The API reference at the
bottom is usually a good place to go.
You guys probably saw this when
we did the Google Maps PSET.
But the reference really
just goes through all
of the functions and parameters
available in the object to you.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah.
For example, this is what
I was looking for before.
When we have a hand we
can go and figure out
how Leap recommends
to us to find a hand.
Like I said earlier,
we have a hands array.
Find out if we have hands and
then try and grab a single hand
to interact with in that way.
So that's what we
recommend for you guys.
The gestures and stuff as well.
This API documentation is going to
be a fantastic tool for you guys.
Do you have any other recommendations?
>> TOMAS REIMERS: I don't.
I think that's good for now.
>> ARMAGHAN BEHLUM: Yeah,
I think so as well.
Feel free to email us and get
in touch about Leap Motion
if you're having maybe any issues
or need any recommendations.
And we can try and figure stuff
out with you guys as well.
Thank you.
>> TOMAS REIMERS: Great.