[MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DOUG LLOYD: So one more
sort of notion that
sort of falls under the umbrella of
JavaScript is something called AJAX.
Up until this point, our
interaction with JavaScript
has been limited to push a
button and something happens.
And specifically, the
something that happens
is our websites look and feel changes.
Right?
Like in particular, in the
document object model video,
I changed the background color.
But when I did that, I didn't have
to do any special extra requests.
I didn't have to request that
the server send me a new page.
I just changed what I already had.
I didn't have to reload my page,
and things definitely changed,
so that's great.
But there's definitely some
manual user interaction involved.
AJAX is a cool technique that allows
us to update a page's content,
and not just the look and
feel, without reloading.
>> And by specifically when I
say updating a page's content,
I'm not saying we rewrite
the page using JavaScript.
I'm saying we actually request
more information from the server
without our page having to reload.
>> Now that sort of a bit of
a more advanced technique
that we're going to talk
about in this video.
We're going to have some interaction.
But when we do, I'm going to be
making requests to the web server.
In this case, just what's
running my Apache web server.
I'm going to be making additional
requests while I'm visiting a web page,
but my page won't refresh.
>> It's just going to
asynchronously update my page.
And that's, in fact,
which AJAX stands for,
is Asynchronous JavaScript and XML.
XML is another kind of markup
language, and you can sort of
think of it just like HTML.
It's not quite the same thing, but
it's basically just a markup language.
So it's an asynchronous
JavaScript and a markup language.
>> So in order to use this
AJAX technique-- AJAX
is not a separate programming language.
It's just sort of a
set of techniques-- we
need to create a special
JavaScript object, which
is called an XMLHttpRequest.
Now, it's very easy to do this.
We just say var, whatever
we want to call this object,
equals new XMLHttpRequest.
And now we have now obtained
an AJAX sort of object,
or an XMLHttpRequest
object, which will allow
us to asynchronously update our page.
>> After we have gotten this new
object, this XMLHttpRequest,
we have to do something to its
onreadystatechange behavior.
Onreadystatechange
behavior is really just
when you make a request
to a web page, the page
goes through a number of steps.
First, a request hasn't been sent.
Then, the request has been
sent, but not acted upon.
Then the request has been acted upon.
Then the request is
being sent back to you.
>> Then, the request is
fully loaded in your page.
Those are different states.
And so we need to set our
new XMLHttpRequest object
to change when the ready state changes.
And typically, we do this by
defining an anonymous function, which
we're familiar with from
JavaScript now, that
is called when the ready state changes.
It's really not much more than that.
We're just going to be defining an
anonymous function, sort of like what
we were doing in
JavaScript, where we would
have an anonymous function
respond to an on click,
or when we were doing a map of
the various objects in an array.
>> Something happened when
something was clicked.
In this case, it's just something is
happening when the state of our page
changes.
There are two other properties
that are sort of-- they're not
the only properties that are
inherent to XMLHttpRequest,
but they're pretty important ones.
There's something called readyState,
which as you can probably guess,
is related to onreadystatechange.
It actually tells you
what the readyState is.
0, 1, 2, 3, and 4 are
the possibilities there,
and they sort of roughly
correspond to what
I was just talking about a second ago.
>> And then status, which
hopefully if everything went OK,
is 200, which is short
for, of course, OK,
which we're familiar with from Http.
So we're hoping that our ready state
is four, and our status is 200.
And if our ready state
is four, and the response
is ready to be put on the
page, and the status is 200,
we were able to do
everything successfully,
now we can asynchronously
update our page
without having to reload
the entire content of it.
>> After we've defined what happens
to the onreadystatechange behavior,
and we've checked that readyState
is 4 and status is 200,
then all we need to do is
open up an asynchronous
request, which is just making
an Http generally GET request.
Just doing it programmatically,
instead of through our web browser.
And then we send that request.
So what does this maybe
look like in context?
So here's a function that
deals with AJAX requests.
OK?
And I've arbitrarily said
it accepts an argument.
And this a sort of a
general skeleton here.
At the very beginning, we get
ourselves a new XMLHttpRequest object.
Then, I need to set the
onreadystatechange behavior.
And so I'm going to say
when the readyState changes,
I want you to call this function.
>> Which is going to ask the
question, if the readyState
is 4, if the readyState has changed
to be 4, and the status was 200,
so we had a successful request, I
want to do something to the page.
And we'll take a look
at an example of what
that something might be in a second.
So then, now I have defined
my anonymous function,
my response function whenever
the readyState changes.
>> So then I just need to open up a
request, using the Open method.
And then, I send that request.
And let's take a look at
a more concrete example
of what AJAX can do on our web pages.
So I have here a very simple
page called home.html.
And I've got an information goes
here and some sort of drop-down menu.
>> And we'll revisit this in one second.
But I think we should now take a
look at the actual source code.
And so, I'm going to open up home.html.
And we'll see what's going on.
So up at the very top here, I have
some JavaScript stuff that's going on.
>> And here, I apparently have
a div whose ID is infodiv,
and some information
is going to go there.
And then I have this form.
And inside of this
form, I have something
called a Select, which
is just a drop-down menu
with a bunch of different options.
And apparently when that changes, when
the option that has been selected has
changed, I'm going to call
some function cs50Info,
and then I'm going to
pass in this.value,
where this refers to
which option was selected,
and value is one of these here, option
value= equals empty, "blumberg,"
"bowden ," "chan," and "malan."
>> So what might actually
happen here when I do this?
Well, let's take a
look at blumberg.html.
Looks like it's just a
snippet of some Html.
And in fact, what I'm hoping
is going to happen here
is I'm going to be able to plug
this Html directly into my web page
without having to reload
the page, such that when
I choose Hannah from the drop-down
menu, information about Hannah,
in particular, this information
here in blumberg.html,
is what shows up on the page.
And I don't have to refresh.
And if I chose somebody else,
their information would show up.
How do I do this?
Again, this requires
us to use some AJAX.
And so, we'll open up ajax.js.
And here is that function, cs50Info.
If name is nothing, I return.
I'm not going to do anything if
the empty option has been chosen.
Otherwise, I'm going to
create a new XMLHttpRequest.
And then I'm going to say, when the
readyState changes, call this function.
>> And if the readyState is
4 and the status is 200,
here's a little bit
of jQuery on line 13.
But all I'm doing is saying,
change the contents of infodiv
to be whatever I got back as a
response from my HttpRequest.
>> What is my HttpRequest?
Well, that's right
here on line 18 and 19.
Line 18, I'm basically preparing
a GET request for name + .html.
And again, name here is
the argument that was
passed in as a parameter to cs50Info.
>> So basically, I am passing in somebody's
name, which was that set of options
that we saw in the
drop-down menu in the form.
I'm getting that name.
And I'm saying I would like you to
please obtain for me that file.html,
and then send that request.
>> And so that onreadystatechange is going
to be listening and waiting and waiting
and waiting, until the readyState
is 4, and the status is 200.
So it's ready to be served,
and the request was successful.
And then if it is, it's going to
change the contents of infodiv
to be the response text that I got back.
>> So let's see how this
might actually work.
So we'll head over to my browser
window, and we'll look here.
So let's take a look at
what's going on here in AJAX.
So we'll choose somebody
from the drop-down menu.
So in this case, let's
just choose Hannah.
And notice that Hannah's
information has changed,
but I didn't have any-- my
page didn't entirely reload.
The stuff stayed.
Most of the stuff stayed.
AJAX Test didn't change.
The button itself, this
drop-down menu didn't change.
But information there did change.
And depending on how
quickly my computer moves,
you actually might see that the content
disappears and then reappears really
quickly.
That's the content being
deleted from infodiv,
and then replaced with a
new asynchronous request.
>> So if I switch it to be say,
Rob-- and again, take a look,
and maybe we'll see it actually
disappear and reappear quickly.
You see that?
How it just popped away,
and then it refilled?
That's the AJAX request
sort of taking place.
And so depending on the
person I choose, I'm
making a different asynchronous
request to a different file
that I have on my server.
And the contents of my
infodiv are updating,
based on which of these I've chosen.
So that's really all there is to AJAX.
It allows us to make these asynchronous
requests, updates to a page.
Without having to
refresh the entire page,
we're going to get new
content from it by making
a new fresh request to the server.
And so, our pages can become
quite a bit more dynamic.
>> And as we get more
and more advanced, you
might get things like
say, your email inbox,
where you don't have to do anything.
You don't have to click a
drop-down menu or click anything,
and all of a sudden, your newest
email shows up at the top.
That's also just an Ajax request.
Ajax is requesting your
server, the email server,
to send over all the information
about your latest emails,
and changing what you see on the
screen to be your newest set of emails.
And if you have a new one in
there, then the content of that div
will change to reflect
the updated content.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.