>> DOUG LLOYD: So in CS50 we learn about
a variety of sorting and searching
algorithms.
And sometimes it can be
a little tricky to keep
track of what algorithm does what.
We really only skim the surface, too.
There are many other searching
and sorting algorithms.
So in this video, let's
just take a few minutes
to try and distill each algorithm
down to its core elements
so you can remember the most
important information about them,
and be able to articulate the
differences, if necessary.
>> The first is selection sort.
The basic idea behind selection sort
is find the smallest unsorted element
in an array, and swap it with the
first unsorted element of that array.
We said that the worst case
runtime of that was n squared.
And if you want to recall why, take
a look at the selection sort video.
The best case runtime is also n squared.
>> Bubble sort, the idea behind that
one, is to swap adjacent pairs.
So that's the keyword that helps
you remember the difference here.
Selection sort, is so
far find the smallest,
bubble sort is swap adjacent pairs.
We swap adjacent pairs of
elements if they are out of order.
Which effectively bubbles
larger elements to the right,
and at the same time, it also begins
to move smaller elements to the left.
>> The worst case runtime of
bubble sort is n squared.
The best case runtime
of bubble sort is n.
Because in that situation
we don't actually--
we might not need to
make any swaps at all.
We only have to make one
pass across all elements.
>> In insertion sort, the
basic idea here is shifting.
That's the keyword for insertion sort.
We're going to step once through
the array from left to right.
And as we do, we're
going to shift elements
we've already seen to make room for
smaller ones that need to fit somewhere
back in that sorted portion.
>> So we build the sorted array one
element at a time, left to right.
And we shift things to make room.
The worst case runtime of
insertion sort is n squared.
The best case runtime is n.
>> Merge sort, the keyword
here is split and merge.
We split the full array-- whether
it's six elements, eight elements,
10,000 elements-- we split it
down by half, by half, by half,
until we have an array of n one-element
arrays-- a set of n one-element arrays.
So we started with one a
thousand-elementary array,
and we get to the point where we
have 1,000 one-element arrays.
>> Then we begin to merge those sub arrays
back together in the correct order.
So we take two one-element arrays,
and create a two-element array.
We take two two-element arrays,
and create a four-element array.
And so on and so on, until we've
again rebuilt one n-element array.
>> The worst case runtime of
merge sort is n times log n.
We have n elements, but
this recombining process
takes log n steps to get
back to a full array.
The best case runtime is also n log
n because this process doesn't really
care whether the array was sorted or not
to start with, the process is the same.
There's no way to short circuit things.
So n log n in the worst case,
n log n in the best case.
>> We also talked about two
searching algorithms.
So linear search is about iterating.
We proceed across the array
once, from left to right,
trying to find the number
that we're looking for.
>> The worst case runtime is big O of n.
It might take us to iterating
across every single element
to find the element we're looking
for, either in the last position,
or not at all.
But we can't confirm that until
we've looked at everything.
In the best case, we find immediately.
The best case runtime of
linear search is omega of one.
>> Lastly, there was binary search,
which requires a sorted array.
Remember that's a very
important consideration
when working with binary search.
It's a prerequisite to using it.
The array that you're looking
through must be sorted.
Otherwise, the keyword
is divide and conquer.
Split the array into half, and
eliminate half of the elements
every time, as you proceed through.
>> Because of this divide and conquer
and splitting things in half approach,
the worst case runtime
of binary search is
log n, which is substantially
better than linear searches n.
The best case runtime is still one.
You might find it immediately the
first time we make a division.
But again, remember, that although
binary search is substantially
better than linear search, by
virtue of being log n vs n,
you might have to go through the
work of sorting your array first,
which might make it less
effective, depending
on the size of the array being sorted.
>> I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.