>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DOUG LLOYD: All right.
Working with single
variables is pretty fun.
But what if we want to work
with a lot of variables,
but we don't want to have a bunch of
different names flying around our code?
In this case, arrays are
going to come in really handy.
Arrays are a really fundamental data
structure for any programming language
that you will use.
And they're really, really useful,
particularly, as we'll see, in CS 50.
>> We use arrays to hold
values of the same data type
at contiguous memory locations.
That is to say, it's a
way that we can group
a bunch of integers together in
memory or a bunch of characters
or floats in memory really
close together and work
with them without having to give each
one its own unique name, which can
get cumbersome after a little while.
>> Now, one way to analogize arrays
is to think about your local post
office for a second.
So step away from programming
and just close your eyes
and visualize in your mind
your local post office.
Usually, in most post
offices, there's a large bank
a post office boxes on the wall.
>> An array is a giant block
of contiguous memory,
the same way that a mail
bank in your post office
is a large space on the
wall of the post office.
Arrays have been partitioned into small,
identically sized blocks of space,
each of which is called an element, in
the same way that the wall of the post
office has been partitioned into small,
identically sized blocks of space,
which we call a PO box.
Each element of the array can
store a certain amount of data,
just as each post office box is able
to hold a certain amount of mail.
>> What can be stored in each element of
the array is variables of the same data
type, such as int or char, just
like in your post office box,
you can only fit things
of a similar type,
such as letters or small packages.
Lastly, we can access each element of
the array directly by index number,
just as we can access our post office
box by knowing its mailbox number.
Hopefully, that analogy
helps you get your head
around the idea of arrays by
analogizing to something else
that you are probably
already familiar with.
>> In C, the elements of an array are
indexed starting from 0, not from 1.
And this is really important.
And in fact, this is why we, in CS 50,
and why computer scientists frequently
will count from 0, is
because of C's array
indexing, which always starts at 0.
So if an array consists of n elements,
the first element of that array
is located at index 0, and
the last element of the array
is located at index n minus 1.
Again, if there's n elements in our
array, the last index is n minus 1.
>> So if our array has 50 elements, the
first element is located at index 0,
and the last element
is located at index 49.
Unfortunately, or fortunately,
depending on your perspective,
C is very lenient here.
It will not prevent you from
going out of bounds of your array.
You could access the minus
3 element of your array
or the 59th element of your array,
if your array only has 50 elements.
It won't stop your program from
compiling, but at run time,
you might encounter a
dreaded segmentation fault
if you start to access memory
that is outside the bounds of what
you asked your program to give you.
So do be careful.
>> What does an array
declaration look like?
How do we code an array into existence
like we code any other variable?
There are three parts to an array
declaration-- a type, a name,
and a size.
This is very similar to a
variable declaration, which
is just a type and a name,
the size element being
the special case for an array,
because we are getting a bunch of them
at the same time.
>> So the type is what kind of variable you
want each element of the array to be.
Do want it to an array of integers?
Then, your data type should be int.
Do you want it to be an
array of doubles or floats?
Data type should be double or float.
The name is what you
want to call your array.
What do you want to name this giant
bank of integers or floats or chars
or doubles, or whatever have you?
What do you want to call it?
Pretty self explanatory.
>> Lastly, size, which goes
inside of square brackets,
is how many elements you would
like your array to contain.
How many integers do you want?
How many floats do you want?
>> So for example, int student grades 40.
This declares an array called Student
grades, which consists of 40 integers.
Pretty self explanatory, I hope.
Here's another example.
Double menu prices 8.
This creates an array called
Menu prices, which consists
of room in memory for eight doubles.
>> If you think of every element
of an array of type data-type,
so for example, a single element of
an array of type int, the same way you
would think of any other
variable of type int,
all the familiar operations that we
discussed previously in the Operations
video will make sense.
So here, we could declare an array
of Booleans called Truthtable,
which consists of room for 10 Booleans.
>> And then, just like we could just assign
a value to any other variable of type
Boolean, we could say something
like Truthtable square bracket
2, which is how we indicate,
which element of the truth table?
The third element of the
truth table, because remember,
we're counting from 0.
So that's how we indicate the
third element of the truth table.
Truthtable 2 equals false,
just like we could declare--
or we could assign, rather, any
Boolean type variable to be false.
>> We can also use it in conditions.
if(truthtable 7 ==
true), which is to say,
if the eighth element
of Truthtable is true,
maybe we want to print a message
to the user, printf("TRUE!n");.
That causes us to say Truthtable
10 equals true, right?
Well, I can, but it's pretty
dangerous, because remember,
we have an array of 10 Booleans.
So the highest index that the
compiler has given us is 9.
>> This program will compile, but
if something else in memory
exists where we would
expect Truthtable 10 to go,
we could suffer a segmentation fault. We
might get away with it, but in general,
pretty dangerous.
So what I'm doing here is legal C,
but not necessarily the best move.
Now, when you declare and
initialize an array simultaneously,
there's actually a pretty
special syntax that you
can use to fill up the array
with its starting values.
It can get cumbersome to
declare an array of size 100,
and then have to say, element 0
equals this; element 1 equals this;
element 2 equals that.
What's the point, right?
>> If it's a small array, you
could do something like this.
Bool truthtable 3 equals open
curly brace and then comma
separate the list of elements
that you want to put in the array.
Then close curly brace semicolon.
This creates an array of
size three called Truthtable,
with elements false, true, and true.
And in fact, the instantiation
syntax I have here is
exactly the same as doing the
individual element syntax below.
These two ways of coding would
produce the exact same array.
>> Similarly, we could iterate
over all of the elements
of an array using a loop, which, in
fact, is a very strongly recommended
at-home exercise.
How do you create an array
of 100 integers, where
every element of the array is its index?
So for example, we have a array of 100
integers, and in the first element,
we want to put 0.
In the second element, we want to put 1.
In the third element, we want
to put 2; and so on and so on.
That's a really good
at-home exercise to do that.
>> Here, it doesn't look
like too much has changed.
But notice that in between the
square brackets, this time,
I've actually omitted the number.
If you're using this very
special instantiation
syntax to create an
array, you actually don't
need to indicate the size
of the array beforehand.
The compiler is smart enough
to know that you actually
want an array of size 3,
because you put three elements
to the right of the equal sign.
If you had put four, it would have
given you a truth table of size four;
and so on and so on.
>> Arrays are not restricted to a single
dimension, which is pretty cool.
You can actually have as many
side specifiers as you wish.
So for example, if you want to create
a board for the game Battleship, which,
if you ever played, is a game that is
played with pegs on the 10 by 10 grid,
you could create an array like this.
You could say Bool
battleship square bracket 10
closed square bracket square
bracket 10 closed square bracket.
>> And then, you can choose to
interpret this in your mind as a 10
by 10 grid of cells.
Now, in fact, in memory,
it really does just
remain a 100 element,
single dimensional array.
And this, in fact, goes for if you
have three dimensions or four or five.
It really just does multiply
all of the indices--
or all of the size
specifiers-- together,
and you just get a one-dimensional
array of that size.
>> But in terms of organization and
visualization and human perception,
it can be a lot easier
to work with a grid
if you're working on a game
like Tic-tac-toe or Battleship,
or something like that.
It's a great abstraction,
instead of having
to think about a Tic-tac-toe
board as a line of nine
squares or a Battleship board
as a line of 100 squares.
A 10 by 10 grid or a three
by three grid is probably
a lot more easy to perceive.
>> Now, something really
important about arrays.
We can treat each individual
element of the array as a variable.
We saw that earlier
when we were assigning
the value True to certain Booleans
or testing them in conditionals.
But we can't treat entire
arrays themselves as variables.
We cannot, for example, assign one array
to another array using the assignment
operator.
It's not legal C.
>> If we want to, for example-- what
we would be doing in that example
would be to copy one array into another.
If we want to do that, we actually
need to use a loop to copy over
each individual element one at a time.
I know it's a little time consuming.
>> So for example, if we had these couple
of lines of code, would this work?
Well, no, it wouldn't, right?
Because we're trying
to assign food to bar.
That's not going to work,
because it's an array,
and we just described
that that's not legal C.
>> Instead, if we want to
copy the contents of food
into bar, which is what
we're trying to do here,
we would need a syntax like this.
We have a for loop that goes
from J is equal to 0 up to 5,
and we increment J on every iteration of
the loop and assign elements like that.
This would result in bar also
being one, two, three, four, five,
but we have to do it this very
slow element-by-element way,
instead of by just
copying the entire array.
In other programming
languages, more modern ones,
you can, in fact, do just
that simple equals syntax.
But C, unfortunately, we're
not allowed to do that.
>> Now, there's one other
thing I want to mention
about arrays that can be a little
bit tricky the first time you
work with them.
We discussed in a video
about variable scope,
that most variables in C, when you call
them in functions, are passed by value.
Do you remember what it means
to pass something by value?
It means we're making a copy of the
variable that's being passed in.
The callee function, the function
that's receiving the variable,
doesn't get the variable itself.
It gets its own local
copy of it to work with.
>> Arrays, of course, do
not follow this rule.
Rather, what we call this
is passing by reference.
The callee actually
does receive the array.
It does not receive its
own local copy of it.
And if you think about
it, this makes sense.
If arrays are really large, it
takes so much time and effort
to make a copy of an array of
100 or 1,000 or 10,000 elements,
that it's not worth it for a
function to receive a copy of it,
do some work with it, and then
just be done with the copy;
it doesn't need to have
it hanging around anymore.
>> Because arrays are some
bulky and cumbersome,
we just pass them by reference.
We just trust that function
to, don't break anything.
So it does actually get the array.
It doesn't get its own local copy of it.
>> So what does this mean,
then, when the callee
manipulates elements of the array?
What happens?
For now, we'll gloss
over why exactly this
happens, why arrays
are passed by reference
and everything else is passed by value.
But I promise you, we will
return and give you the answer
to this in a later video.
>> Here's one more exercise for you
before we wrap up things on arrays.
The bunch of code here, that's
not particularly good style,
just I'll make that caveat.
There's no comments in here,
which is pretty bad form.
But it's only because I wanted to be
able to fit everything on the screen.
>> At the top, you can see that I have
two function declarations for set array
and set int.
Set array apparently takes an array
of four integers as its input.
And set int apparently takes
a single integer as its input.
But both of them don't have an output.
The output, the return
type, of each one is void.
In Main, we have a
couple of lines of code.
We declare an integer variable
called A and assign it the value 10.
We declare an array of four integers
called B and assign the elements 0, 1,
2, and 3, respectively.
Then, we have a call to set
int and a call to set array.
The definitions of set array and set
int are down below, at the bottom.
>> And so, again, I ask you the question.
What gets printed out
here at the end of Main?
There's a printout col. I'm
printing out two integers.
I'm printing out the contents of A and
the contents of B square bracket 0.
Pause the video here and take a minute.
Can you figure out what this
function will print at the end?
Hopefully, if you recall the
distinction between passing by value
and passing by reference, this
problem wasn't too tricky for you.
And the answer you would
have found is this.
If you're not really sure as to
why that's the case, take a second,
go back, review what I was just
discussing about passing arrays
by reference, versus passing
other variables by value,
and hopefully, it'll make
a little bit more sense.
>> I'm Doug Lloyd, and this is CS50.