>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DOUG LLOYD: All right.
So binary search is an
algorithm we can use
to find an element inside of an array.
Unlike linear search, it requires a
special condition be met beforehand,
but it's so much more efficient if
that condition is, in fact, met.
>> So what's the idea here?
it's divide and conquer.
We want to reduce the size of
the search area by half each time
in order to find a target number.
This is where that condition
comes into play, though.
We can only leverage the power of
eliminating half of the elements
without even looking at
them if the array is sorted.
>> If it's a complete mix up,
we can't just out of hand
discard half of the elements, because
we don't know what we're discarding.
But if the array is sorted,
we can do that, because we
know that everything to the
left of where we currently are
must be lower than the
value we're currently at.
And everything to the
right of where we are
must be greater than the value
we're currently looking at.
>> So what's the pseudocode
steps for binary search?
We repeat this process until the
array or, as we proceed through,
sub arrays, smaller pieces of
the original array, is of size 0.
Calculate the midpoint
of the current sub array.
>> If the value you're looking for is
in that element of the array, stop.
You found it.
That's great.
Otherwise, if the target is
less than what's at the middle,
so if the value we're looking
for is lower than what we see,
repeat this process again, but
change the end point, instead
of being the original
complete full array,
to be just to the left
of where we just looked.
>> We knew that the middle was too high,
or the target was less than the middle,
and so it must exist, if it
exists at all in the array,
somewhere to the left of the midpoint.
And so we'll set the array
location just to the left
of the midpoint as the new end point.
Conversely, if the target is
greater than what's at the middle,
we do the exact same
process, but instead we
change the start point to be
just to the right of the midpoint
we just calculated.
And then, we begin the process again.
>> Let's visualize this, OK?
So there's a lot going and on here,
but here's an array of the 15 elements.
And we're going to be keeping track
of a lot more stuff this time.
So in linear search, we were
just caring about a target.
But this time we want to
care about where are we
starting to look, where
are we stopping looking,
and what's the midpoint
of the current array.
So here we go with binary search.
We're pretty much good to go, right?
I'm just going to put down
below here a set of indices.
This is basically just what element
of the array we're talking about.
With linear search, we
care, inasmuch as we
need to know how many
elements we're iterating over,
but we don't actually care what
element we're currently looking at.
In binary search, we do.
And so those are just
there as a little guide.
>> So we can start, right?
Well, not quite.
Remember what I said
about binary search?
We can't do it on an
unsorted array or else,
we are not guaranteeing that the
certain elements or values aren't
being accidentally
discarded when we just
decide to ignore half of the array.
>> So step one with binary search
is you must have a sorted array.
And you can use any of the sorting
algorithms we've talked about
to get you to that position.
So now, we're in a position where
we can perform binary search.
>> So let's repeat the process
step by step and keep
track of what's happening as we go.
So the first we need to do is calculate
the midpoint of the current array.
Well, we'll say we're, first of
all, looking for the value 19.
We're trying to find the number 19.
The first element of this
array is located at index zero,
and the last element of this
array is located at index 14.
And so we'll call those start and end.
>> So we calculate the midpoint by
adding 0 plus 14 divided by 2;
pretty straightforward midpoint.
And we can say that
the midpoint is now 7.
So is 15 what we're looking for?
No, it's not.
We're looking for 19.
But we know that 19 is greater
than what we found at the middle.
>> So what we can do is
change the start point
to be just to the right of the
midpoint, and repeat the process again.
And when we do that, we now say the
new start point is array location 8.
What we've effectively done is
ignored everything to the left of 15.
We've eliminated half
of the problem, and now,
instead of having to search
over 15 elements in our array,
we only have to search over 7.
So 8 is the new start point.
14 is still the end point.
>> And now, we go over this again.
We calculate the new midpoint.
8 plus 14 is 22, divided by 2 is 11.
Is this what we're looking for?
No, it's not.
We're looking for a value that's
less than what we just found.
So we're going to repeat
the process again.
We're going to change the end point to
be just to the left of the midpoint.
So the new end point becomes 10.
And now, that's the only part of
the array we have to sort through.
So we have now eliminated
12 of the 15 elements.
We know that if 19
exists in the array, it
must exist somewhere between element
number 8 and element number 10.
>> So we calculate the new midpoint again.
8 plus 10 is 18, divided by 2 is 9.
And in this case, look, the
target is at the middle.
We found exactly what we're looking for.
We can stop.
We successfully completed
a binary search.
All right.
So we know this algorithm
works if the target is
somewhere inside of the array.
Does this algorithm work if
the target is not in the array?
Well, let's start it
again, and this time,
let's look for the element
16, which visually we can see
does not exist anywhere in the array.
>> The start point is again 0.
The end point is again 14.
Those are the indices of the first and
last elements of the complete array.
And we'll go through the process we just
went through again, trying to find 16,
even though visually, we can already
tell that it's not going to be there.
We just want to make sure this algorithm
will, in fact, still work in some way
and not just leave us
stuck in an infinite loop.
>> So what's the step first?
Calculate the midpoint
of the current array.
What's the midpoint
of the current array?
Well, it's 7, right?
14 plus 0 divided by 2 is 7.
Is 15 what we're looking for?
No.
It's pretty close, but we're looking
for a value slightly bigger than that.
>> So we know that it's going to
be nowhere to the left of 15.
The target is greater than
what's in the midpoint.
And so we set the new start point to
be just to the right of the middle.
The midpoint is currently 7, so
let's say the new start point is 8.
And what we've effectively
done again is ignored
the entire left half of the array.
>> Now, we repeat the
process one more time.
Calculate the new midpoint.
8 plus 14 is 22, divided by 2 is 11.
Is 23 what we're looking for?
Unfortunately, no.
We're looking for a value
that is less than 23.
And so in this case, we're going
to change the end point to be just
to the left of the current midpoint.
The current midpoint is 11, and
so we'll set the new end point
for the next time we go
through this process to 10.
>> Again, we go through the process again.
Calculate the midpoint.
8 plus 10 divided by 2 is 9.
Is 19 what we're looking for?
Unfortunately, no.
We're still looking for
a number less than that.
So we'll change the end point this time
to be just to the left of the midpoint.
The midpoint is currently 9,
so the end point will be 8.
And now, we're just looking
at a single element array.
>> What's the midpoint of this array?
Well, it starts at 8, it
ends at 8, the midpoint is 8.
Is that what we're looking for?
Are we looking for 17?
No, we're looking for 16.
So if it exists in the array,
it must exist somewhere
to the left of where we currently are.
So what are we going to do?
Well, we'll set the end point to be just
to the left of the current midpoint.
So we'll change the end point to 7.
Do you see what just
happened here, though?
Look up here now.
>> Start is now greater than end.
Effectively, the two ends
of our array have crossed,
and the start point is
now after the end point.
Well, that doesn't
make any sense, right?
So now, what we can say is we
have a sub array of size 0.
And once we're gotten to
this point, we can now
guarantee that element 16
does not exist in the array,
because the start point
and end point have crossed.
And so it's not there.
Now, notice that this is slightly
different than the start point and end
point being the same.
If we had been looking
for 17, it would have
been in the array, and the start point
and end point of that last iteration
before those points crossed,
we would have found 17 there.
It's only when they cross that we can
guarantee that the element does not
exist in the array.
>> So let's take a lot fewer
steps than linear search.
In the worst case scenario, we had
to split up a list of n elements
repeatedly in half to find the target,
either because the target element
will be somewhere in the last
division, or it doesn't exist at all.
So in the worst case, we have to
split up the array-- do you know?
Log of n times; we
have to cut the problem
in half a certain number of times.
That number of times is log n.
>> What's the best case scenario?
Well, the first time we
calculate the midpoint,
we find what we're looking for.
In all the previous
examples on binary search
we've just gone over, if we had
been looking for the element 15,
we would have found that immediately.
That was at the very beginning.
That was the midpoint of
the first attempt at a split
of a division in binary search.
>> And so in the worst
case, binary search runs
in log n, which is substantially better
than linear search, in the worst case.
In the best case, binary
search runs in omega of 1.
So binary search is a lot
better than linear search,
but you have to deal with the process of
sorting your array first before you can
leverage the power of binary search.
>> I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS 50.