DOUG LLOYD: If you've seen
the video on recursion,
the whole process might have
seemed a little bit magical.
How does it work?
How do the functions know that they
need to wait and wait for another value
to return from a different function
call in order to get the result we want?
>> Well, the reason this works is because
of something known as the call stack.
When you call a function, the
system sets aside space in memory
for that function to do its work.
And we call these chunks of memory that
are being set aside for each function
call a stack frame or a function frame.
And as you might expect,
these stack frames
live on the stack part of memory.
>> More than one function stack frame
can exist in memory at a given time.
If main calls a function move,
and move calls direction,
all three functions have open frames.
But they don't all have active frames.
These frames are arranged in a stack.
And the frame from the
most recently called
function is always on top of the stack.
And that is always the active frame.
There's only really ever one
function that's active at a time.
It's the one on top of the stack.
>> When a function calls another
function, it sort of presses pause.
It sort of is on hold, waiting.
And another stack frame is pushed
onto the stack on top of it.
And that becomes the active frame.
And the frame immediately
below it needs to wait
until it is again the active frame
before it can resume its work.
When a function is
complete and it's done,
its frame is popped off the stack.
That's the terminology.
And the frame immediately
below it, as I just said,
becomes the new active frame.
>> And if it calls another function,
it's going to pause again.
That new function's stack frame will
be pushed onto the top of the stack.
It'll do its work.
It might pop back off.
And the other function
below it can resume again.
>> So let's go through this again, looking
at the idea of the factorial function
that we defined in the
recursion video to see
exactly how the magic behind this
recursive process is taking place.
So this is our entire file, right?
We defined two
functions-- main and fact.
And as we might expect,
any C program is going
to start at the first line of main.
>> So we create a new stack frame for main.
And it's going to begin running.
Main calls printf.
And printf is going to
print out factorial of 5.
Well, it doesn't know
what factorial of 5 is,
and so this call is already
depending on another function call.
So main is going to pause right there.
I'm gonna leave its
arrow right there, color
it the same color as the
stack frame on the right,
to indicate that main is going to freeze
here while factorial of 5 is called.
>> So factorial of 5 is called.
And it's going to start at the very
beginning of the factorial function.
It asks the question am I equal to 1?
Is 5 equal to 1?
Well, no.
So it's going to go down to
the else part, return n times
factorial of n minus 1.
Well, OK.
>> So now, factorial of 5 is
depending on another call
to factorial, passing
in 4 as the parameter.
And so the factorial of
5 frame, that red frame,
is going to freeze right there
at that line I've indicated
and wait for factorial of 4 to finish
what it needs to do so that then it
can become the active frame again.
>> So factorial of 4 starts at
the beginning of factorial.
Is 4 equal to 1?
No, so it's going to do the same thing.
It's going to go down the else branch.
It's going to get to that line of code.
OK, I'm going to return four times.
Oh, factorial of 3-- so factorial of
4 depends on factorial of 3 finishing.
>> And so it needs to call factorial of 3.
And that's gonna go through
the same process again.
It starts through, gets here.
Factorial of 3 depends
on factorial of 1.
So factorial of 2 starts, gets here.
It depends on factorial of 1.
Factorial of 1 starts.
>> OK.
So now, we're getting
somewhere interesting, right?
So now, 1 is equal to 1.
And so we return 1.
At this point, we are returning.
The function's done.
It's behavior is-- there's
nothing else for it to do,
and so the stack frame for
factorial of 1 pops off.
It's finished.
It returned 1.
And now, factorial of 2, which
was the frame immediately below it
in the stack, becomes the active frame.
>> And it can pick up
exactly where it left off.
It's been waiting for a factorial
of 1 to finish its work.
It has now finished.
And so here we are.
>> Factorial of 1 returned a value of 1.
So factorial of 2 can
say return 2 times 1.
Its work is now done.
It's returned 2 to factorial
of 3, which was waiting for it.
Factorial of 3 is now the top frame,
the active frame in the stack.
And so it says, OK, well, I'm going
to return 3 times 2, which is 6.
And I'm going to give that
value back to factorial
of 4, which has been waiting for me.
I'm done.
Factorial of 3 pops off the stack, and
factorial of 4 is now the active frame.
>> 4 says, OK, I'm going to return 4 times
the factorial of 3, which was six.
That was of value that
factorial of 3 returned.
And so 4 times 6 is 24.
And I'm going to pass
that back to factorial
of 5, which has been waiting for me.
Factorial of 5 is now the active frame.
It's going to return 5 times
factorial of 4-- 5 times 24, or 120--
and give that value
back to main, which has
been waiting very patiently for a
long time at the bottom of the stack.
>> It's where it started.
It made this call.
Several frames took over at the top.
It is now back on top of the stack.
It's the active frame.
So main got the value 120
back from factorial of 5.
It's been waiting to
print out that value.
And then it's done.
There's no more lines of code in main.
So main's frame pops off
the stack, and we're done.
>> And that's how recursion works.
That's how stack frames work.
Those function calls
that happened previously
are just on pause, waiting
for the subsequent calls
to finish so they can become the active
frame and finish what they need to do.
>> I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.