All right.
So now let's talk about something
really useful in programming--
conditional statements.
So conditional expressions
allow your programs
to make decisions and take different
forks in the road, something
I alluded to little earlier,
depending on the values of variables,
or based on what the user inputs at
the programmer, at the command line,
or if you have a prompt
or something like that.
C has a couple of different ways to
express conditional expressions, which
we also sometimes will call a
conditional branch in your programs.
And some of these are going to look
pretty familiar to you from scratch,
so we'll even pull them
up side by side, just
you can make that analogy in your head.
>> So, if-- if is a pretty
simple conditional.
If you recall from
scratch on the right here
you could fill in that is hexagon
with a blue expression if mouse down
or if x is less than 10,
or something like that.
And then, if x was less than 10,
or if the mouse was in fact, down,
all of the code inside of the
puzzle piece would execute.
All the things that fit
inside that C shape.
>> Similarly, do we have
if on the left there.
If Boolean expression,
which I'm just using
as a substitute for one of the Boolean
expressions we previously discussed,
open curly brace, close curly brace.
So think of open curly
brace and closed curly brace
as sort of analogous to the sandwich
effect of the if block on the right
from scratch.
>> If the Boolean expression
in the if statement is true,
then all the lines of code
between the curly braces
will execute in order
from top to bottom.
If the Boolean expression
is false, we'll
skip over everything in between
the curly braces, because we only
want to go down that fork in the road
if the Boolean expression is true.
>> We can take this one step
further with if else.
So this Scratch block is
pretty similar to the one
we saw just a second ago, except
it takes two different paths based
on what happens.
So if the mouse was down,
or if x was less than 10,
we'll do everything that's in between
that first fork, that first C. ,
>> Otherwise, if the mouse is
up, or x is not less than 10,
we will do everything in the second set.
And that's analogous to what you see
here for C. If Boolean expression,
do the stuff between the
first set of curly braces.
Else, do the stuff between the
second set of curly braces.
So if the Boolean
expression is true, we'll
do whatever's between the first set.
If the Boolean expression is
false, that would trigger the else,
and we would do whatever's in
the second set of curly braces.
Again, top to bottom, all
lines in between the braces.
>> In C, it's possible to create
an if-else if-else chain.
In fact you can have if-else if-else
if-else, if, and so on and so on and so
on.
In Scratch, this required
nesting the blocks.
You add an if-else, and you had to
put another one inside of the else,
and so on, and it got kind
of nested and complicated.
But C, we don't have to do that.
We can actually just have
it be a chain like this.
Again, as you might expect, all of
these branches are mutually exclusive.
You can only ever go
down one of the branch.
If this is true.
Otherwise, if this is true.
Otherwise, do this.
So all four of the branches in this
example are mutually exclusive.
It's an if-else if-else chain.
>> It is possible though,
and sometimes very useful,
to create a chain of not
mutually exclusive branches.
In this example, only the third and
fourth branches are mutually exclusive.
It could be that you could
satisfy the first condition,
and you could satisfy
the second condition,
and you could satisfy the
third condition-- in which case
you would go down the first branch,
then you go down a second branch,
then you would go down the third branch.
Or perhaps you satisfy the first
condition, and the second condition,
but you don't satisfy
the third condition.
In this case you go down the first
branch and the second branch,
and then the fourth branch,
>> The reason for this is that the else
will only bind to the nearest if.
So even though there's
an else here, that
doesn't necessarily create a mutually
exclusive chain of everything.
It's only the expression
there with Boolean
expression 3-- that's the
mutually exclusive with the else.
So it is possible, and
sometimes quite useful,
as I said, to create a chain of
not mutually exclusive branches.
Let's take a look at a different
kind of conditional, which
you have not seen before in Scratch.
There's something called
the switch statement.
The switch statement is
kind of neat because it's
a conditional statement that allows
you to specify distinct cases,
instead of relying on Boolean
expressions to make decisions for you.
So for example, let's say
that I have this program,
and I'm asking the user
to provide input to me.
So I say, int x = Get Int(),
and if you're not familiar yet,
get int is a function that is
also included in the CS50 library,
so if you #include CS50.H you'll have
access to Get Int() and all of its
cousins-- GetFloat,
GetString, and so on.
Basically one Get function for every
data type that we've already discussed.
>> So Int x equals GetInt.
Basically what's happening
is I'm at the terminal.
I'm asking the user to type in a number.
>> And here I'm switching
what I'm doing, depending
on what the user typed at the prompt.
So if they typed one, I print out one.
And then I break.
If they type two, I print out two.
It's important to
break between each case
because otherwise you will fall through.
So if I didn't have any
breaks there, and the user
typed one, what would happen is it
would print one, two, three, sorry.
That's kind of strange behavior, right?
You might think so.
But there are actually some cases where
this could be a pretty useful thing.
So here's another example of a switch
statement where I omit the breaks.
But I do it on purpose.
>> So what happens here?
Think for a second.
You may even want to pause the video.
>> What happens here if
the user types four?
So I've asked the user for input.
And they provide the value 4.
What gets printed when I do that?
On the previous slide, there were
breaks between all the cases.
And so it would just
print four and then stop.
But in this case, it won't.
What will happen is you
will fall through each case.
>> So in this case I've organized my cases
in such a way that if the user types 4,
I will print four, three,
two, one, blast off.
And if they typed 5, I would start
at five and do the same thing.
If they typed 1, I would
just do one, blast off.
>> So in this case, I'm using
a switch kind of cleverly so
that I do intend to fall
through all the cases.
But generally you're probably gonna
want to break between all of them,
unless you have a situation
like this one where you're
kind of leveraging the fact that you'll
fall through the cases without a break.
So that's the second of the major
types of conditional statements.
The last of which is ?: So I
have two snippets of C code here.
One on the left and one on the right.
The one on the left should
probably be pretty familiar to you.
>> I have Int x.
And I probably should
have asked the user
for-- this should probably be Int x
equals GetInt, or something like that.
And then I'm making a decision.
If some Boolean expression is
true, assign x the value 5.
Otherwise, assign x the value 6.
>> That on the left should probably be
pretty familiar from our discussion
of If Else just a moment ago.
Would you be surprised to know
that the line on the right
does the exact same thing?
>> So this is called ?: or sometimes
called the ternary operator.
And it's pretty cool.
It's usually used as a cute trick.
>> But what it allows you to do is to
simulate an If Else with really small,
really trivially short
conditional branches.
You generally wouldn't use ?: if you
had six lines of code between each set
of curly braces.
But if you're just
making a quick decision,
if you're going to do one thing
or the other and it's very simple,
this might be an example of how to
do it with ?: the ternary operator.
So Int x equals expression ?
The thing after the question
mark is what x's value
will be if expression is true.
>> The thing after the
colon is what x's value
would be if the expression was false.
So I'm asking myself,
is the expression true?
If it is, assign x the value 5.
If it's not, assign x the value 6.
Again, like I said.
This is usually just a cute trick.
And sometimes if you become
really comfortable with it,
you'll do this because it looks
kind of cool in your programs.
Generally I'm presenting it to
you now so you're familiar with it
if you see it.
But certainly know you don't have
to write it in any of your code.
But it is something to be familiar with,
because you'll definitely encounter
snippets of code here and
there where this ?: syntax,
AKA the ternary operator, is used.
>> So quick summary on
what conditionals are,
and what the options are available
to you in C. You have If and if-else,
and if else if, et cetera.
You can use Boolean expressions
for those to make decisions.
>> With switch statements you use
discrete cases to make decisions.
You would specifically say, if it's
one, or if it's two, or if it's three,
I'll do this thing, or
this thing, or this thing.
And ?: can to be used to replace
very simple if-else branches,
or if-else chains to make
your code look a little fancy.
>> I'm Doug Lloyd.
And this is CS50.