>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DOUG LLOYD: So let's take one more
video to talk about one more language.
This time we'll talk about CSS.
So CSS, which is short for
Cascading Style Sheets,
is another language we use
when constructing websites.
Think about it like this.
If HTML is what we use to organize the
content we want to put on our page,
CSS is the tool that we generally use
to customize how our websites look,
and how the user experience really
is, interacting with our website.
>> Similar to HTML, CSS is
not a programming language.
It doesn't have logic.
It doesn't have variables.
It doesn't have any sort of that
flow related things that C does.
It's a styling language.
And its syntax is pretty
simple, and just describes
how the elements of our
page have certain HTML
elements should be modified.
To that end, if you haven't
yet watched our video on HTML,
or are unfamiliar with
HTML generally, you
may want to take a look at that
first, because this discussion of CSS
is going to depend on
some knowledge of HTML.
>> So here's a really
simple CSS stylesheet.
Even if you've never
programmed with CSS before,
I'm pretty sure you can figure out
exactly what this stylesheet does.
What does it do?
Well, applied to the body of our web
page, everything between body tags
on our HTML, and it sets the
background color of that page to blue.
Well, it's a very simple stylesheet.
It's actually very human
friendly language, CSS.
So even if you've never used it before,
you probably could guess what that did.
In fact, if we loaded a page, where
this stylesheet was embedded somehow,
the background color of our page would
be blue, and not the standard white.
>> So how do we build stylesheets?
Well first, we have to
identify a selector.
In the last example,
that selector was body.
Then we have an open
curly brace, and we're
going to begin defining the
stylesheet for that selector.
In between the curly braces, we
just have a list of key value pairs.
The previous value pair was
background color blue semicolon,
but we could do more and more of these.
You could have multiple things applying
to that tag, that selector body.
Each one of them is separated by a
semicolon, and we call each one of them
a declaration, a CSS declaration.
When we're done with all the styling we
want to apply to that particular tag,
we just have a closing curly
brace to end the stylesheet,
and we're done defining the stylesheet
for that particular selector.
>> What are some common CSS properties?
Well, maybe you want to put
a border around something.
So you can say, border,
that would be your key,
and then your values would be,
what style, color, and width
you want it to be.
So the style could be a solid
line, a dotted line, a dashed line,
a ridge line, which would be wavy line.
Maybe you want to have it
be blue or black or green.
Maybe you want it to be
1 or 2 or 10 pixels wide.
You can specify all of those things.
Maybe you want to set the background
color of your page in a particular way.
We already saw that, setting the
background of the body to be blue.
>> Then you can use a key word,
so CSS has certain colors
that are built into it, blue, green,
black, a very simple colors we know.
But you can also specify any
hex color that you'd like.
Recall that colors can be identified
by a set of three hex numbers
from 0 to 255, rg and b, the
red, green, and blue component.
And so we can specify
any color we want by,
instead of using blue or green or black,
using pound and then six digits of hex,
and that would give us
the six digit color.
So that's the background color.
>> We also have the foreground
color, which is usually
going to be the text of your page.
And you could similarly do that
with key word and or six digit hex.
So you can specify any color you
want for the text of your page
against a particular
background color, up above.
You can also change and deal
with font, and the way text
is rendered on the page.
>> So you can change your font size.
You can use key words, such as extra,
extra small, or xx small, or medium,
large, and so on.
You can use fixed points, 10
point, 12 point, and so on.
You can use percentages, 80%, 20%,
where 100% is the default font
size, which is usually going to
be something like 11 or 12 points.
Or you can even base it off
of the most recent font size.
If you just wrote something and you know
what you want is for it to be smaller,
but you don't know exactly what size you
want it to be, well, you can just say,
font size smaller.
And it will base off of the,
just up above, it's font size.
And you can get smaller or larger.
So there's a lot of different
ways to specify font size.
>> You can also specify what
font family you want.
If you have a particular
name, there's a way in CSS--
we're not going to talk about it
here-- to define a very specific font
and embed it into your page.
You can also use generic names.
There's a lot of web safe fonts
that are pre-defined in CSS.
And if you are a user of Microsoft
Office in the last 20 years,
you're probably familiar with
a lot of these web safe fonts
already, Times New Roman, Arial,
Courier New, Georgia, Tahoma, Verdana,
and so on.
Those are all considered web safe fonts.
And actually, part of the
reason they came to be
was to be used to make web-- every page
had access to this default set of fonts
with various serifs, and all this
font stuff we won't get into,
but these are usually
accessible in your CSS,
even if you don't
otherwise define the fonts.
Lastly, you can align your text,
instead of it being, by default, aligned
to the left, you could
align it to the right,
or you could align it centered, or
justified so that it hit both margins.
So those are all options you can use
to change what your text looks like,
and how it's displayed on your page.
>> Your selectors don't
have to be tags only.
We previously saw a body tag
selector, and tag selector
does look just like that.
You name a tag, and then you
define a stylesheet for that tag.
But you can also do something
called an ID selector.
An ID selector looks pretty similar.
But notice, that now I'm not using
an HTML tag, I'm using, in this case,
#unique, or hash unique.
If you recall from our
video on HTML, we talked
about how tags can have attributes.
>> And one attribute that applies
to pretty much all HTML tags,
but we didn't talk about it,
is something called an ID tag.
So this particular CSS would
apply only to HTML tag that has
a very specific ID, that you've named.
So if you have somewhere
in your code, somewhere
in your HTML file, a tag and you
specify as an attribute to that tag,
ID equals unique, this
particular stylesheet
here will only apply in between
that tag with the ID of unique.
>> You can also do something
called a class selector.
So in addition to having
ID attributes, you can also
add a class attribute to HTML tags.
And when you use a class attribute,
it can be applied to multiple tags.
So if you have several things that
are similar, maybe you want to say,
open tag blah, blah, blah,
blah, class equals students.
And then this particular
stylesheet would apply
to every tag whose class is students.
In this case, we'd set the
background color to yellow,
and we'd set opacity, which
is a tag we didn't talk about,
but just deals with how transparent
something is, to 70%, in this case.
>> There's two options for
writing stylesheets.
You can write them
directly into your HTML
by placing the stylesheets
in between style tags.
And those style tags go inside of
the head tags of your web page.
The perhaps more preferred way to do
it is to write a separate .css file,
and then link it into your
document using link tags.
Link tags, again, are
different from hyperlinks,
if you recall from our video an HTML.
And link tags are how we
pull in separate files.
It sort of like the equivalent of
the #include for web programming.
>> So let's take a look at table.HTML.
If you recall from our
HTML video, I showed
an example of a very
simple multiplication
table that looked pretty
ugly, and maybe there's
a way to make it better with
CSS, to make it actually look
more like a multiplication
table, or something
that isn't just stuck together
with no actual division
between the rows and the columns.
So let's head over to
CS50 IDE, and take a look
at how CSS can, sort of, tweak
what we started with before,
and make it something a lot better.
>> So we're in CS50 IDE
now, and if unfamiliar,
we'll pull up in this
table that HTML page.
Table.HTML basically
just defines the contents
of a multiple-- it was supposed to be
a four by four multiplication table.
It's pretty straightforward.
And we would think that it would
look pretty well organized.
But in fact, when we preview this page,
we see that it's kind of ugly, right?
Clearly we have rows and columns here.
There some sort of separation.
But it's not a meaningful separation.
We're not actually getting
too much information here.
And there's no separation between
the rows and columns in terms
of horizontal or vertical rules.
We could probably make this
look a little bit better.
So let's try.
So I'm going to close this tab up here.
And I'm going to close my table.HTML,
and I have another version here
called table2.HTML.
We'll open that up.
The body of the page is
pretty much the same,
but I've changed a
little bit at the top.
And I'll scroll up here.
Notice that this time, I'm
using embedded style tags.
I've opened a style tag, and I'm now
defining a CSS stylesheet just inside
of it.
I have a stylesheet that says, table.
That's my tag selector.
I'm not using dot or hash,
which I would be doing if I
was using an ID or a class selector.
I have a tag selector here-- table.
This style is going to
apply to every table tag.
Apparently I want to put a one
pixel wide, solid blue border,
inside my table.
That sounds like it would probably
help the situation, right?
We're going to have
things look a lot better.
So this is fine.
Stylistically, I've just
embedded my stylesheet in here.
It's certainly an
acceptable way to do it.
Let's see what this looks like.
So I'll go back down here, and
I'll will preview my table2.HTML.
Well, that's not quite what I wanted,
but it is exactly what we asked for.
We said that this style is
going to apply to our table.
Our table now has a one pixel
wide, solid blue border around it.
We're not actually getting
at the table cells.
We're just getting at the table.
So CSS worked.
It has applied a
stylesheet to our table.
But didn't quite do
what we wanted it to do.
How do we get to do
what we want it to do?
>> Well, let's take a look at one more
version of this in table3.HTML.
So I'm just going to close these tabs.
I'm going to go back over here to my
file tree, and open up table3.HTML.
Again, it's going to look pretty
similar here at the beginning.
But notice, this time, instead of using
a stylesheet embedded right in there,
I'm going to link in a
stylesheet using the link tag.
So I'm apparently linking in a
stylesheet called tables.CSS,
and this well equals
stylesheet just means-- well,
what is this file relative to what
I'm doing-- is a stylesheet that I'm
using for my page.
So if I really want to see what
I'm doing with the CSS here,
I need to go open that
table.CSS file as well.
So we'll go back over here
again to our file tree.
There's table.CSS.
We'll pop it open.
Now we're seeing a little of the CSS.
Apparently, I have a couple
of things going on here.
I apparently want to put a five
pixel wide, solid red border,
around my table.
We already know that that's going
to just go on the perimeter.
We saw that in table2.HTML.
With each row, I
apparently want to specify
that the row height is 50 pixels high.
So for every row, remember
that's what the tr tag does,
I'm making it 50 pixels high.
>> Lastly, I have this comment.
And this is how we make comments in CSS.
It's very similar to seize block
comments syntax slash star.
All the text you want.
There's no slash slash though in CSS.
For short inline comments, we have
to use this particular format here.
It looks like I'm doing a
lot of things in my td tags.
Remember td tags, or table
data, which really are just
the columns inside of
our rows, and apparently
for each piece of data
in my table, I want
to set the background color to
be black, the color to be white,
color is foreground color.
So this is going to be
the text of my page.
I want big font, 22
point font, and I want
it to be of the font family, Georgia.
So I'm not going to
have the default font.
I'm going to specify Georgia, which
is one of those web safe fonts
that we've seen before.
I want my text to be aligned
centrally, in the middle of the box,
I don't want it to be left
aligned or right aligned.
And I want my column width
to be 50 pixels wide as well.
Let's take a look at
what this looks like,
and see if this is maybe an improvement.
So I'm going to go to table3.HTML, which
recall, includes table.CSS as a link,
and we'll preview it.
That's a lot better, right?
This is actually starting to look a
lot more like a multiplication table.
I have that red border
around my table but now
I also have specified that
each row is 50 pixels wide,
or it's 50 pixels tall-- excuse
me-- each column is 50 pixels wide.
The data in each column, and only
the data, has a black background.
So that's why those
white lines are there.
Because the space in
between all of those cells,
it's not a border in
and of itself, it's just
I'm only filling in the
cells, which actually
makes the borders of the table, which
apparently did exist all along, it
was just thin white lines.
Now they're visible.
Now they pop off on the screen.
And so this is a very simple
stylesheet that I've applied,
and now my table looks a lot more like
a four by four multiplication table,
instead of a just jumbled mess, where
everything is clearly rows and columns,
but not super well organized.
We're really just scratching the surface
of what you can do with CSS here.
Fortunately the CSS documentation
is pretty straightforward.
You'll use several of its
attributes, fairly frequently.
The ones we talked about
earlier in this video.
There are several that you
probably won't use all.
And that's fine, too.
But just know, that there's a
lot of documentation out there.
So even if we didn't cover everything,
you're certainly not left on your own.
But CSS is really fun
to experiment with.
And I would strongly encourage you
to play around with your web pages,
and see how you can make them
look and feel to improve the user
experience of visiting your page.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.