DOUG LLOYD: All right.
So now let's tackle a
really big topic, functions.
So far in the course, all the
programs that we've been writing
have been written inside of main.
They're pretty simple programs.
You don't need to have all these
branches and things going on.
We can just fit it all
inside of main and it
doesn't get terribly overwhelming.
But as the course goes on and
as you begin to develop programs
independently, they're probably going
to start to get a lot more than 10
or 15 lines.
You might get hundreds or thousands
or tens of thousands of lines of code.
And it's really not
that crazy a thought.
As such, it's probably not a good idea
to keep everything inside of main.
It can get a little difficult to find
what you're looking for if you do that.
>> Fortunately, though C, and pretty much
every other programming language that
might work with, allows
us to write functions.
And I'm just going to
take a quick aside here
to mention that functions is
one area of computer science.
And you'll see many more of them at
various points throughout the course
and if you continue on.
Where there's a lot of
synonyms for the same word.
So we call the functions.
But you might also hear them
referred to as procedures,
or methods, particularly, if you've ever
done any object oriented programming
before-- and don't worry
if you haven't, not
a big deal-- but in
audit oriented languages
are frequently called methods.
Sometimes they're called subroutines.
But they really all refer
to the same basic idea.
>> Let's see what that idea is.
What is a function?
Well a function is really
nothing more than a black box.
A black box that has a set of zero
or more inputs and a single output.
So for example, this
might be a function.
This is a function called func.
And it takes three inputs a, b, and c.
And inside that black box, we
don't know exactly what it does,
but it processes the inputs
in some way and then it
gives a single output, in this case, z.
Now to make it a little
less abstract, we
could say that maybe we
have a function called
add that takes three inputs a, b, and
c and processes the output in some way
inside the black box to
produce a single output.
So in this case, if
add takes 3, 6, and 7.
Somewhere inside the
add function, we would
expect them to be added together
to produce the output, which
is 3 plus 6 plus 7 or 16.
>> Similarly, you have a function called
mult that takes two inputs, a and b,
processes them in some way such
that the output of the function
is the product of the two inputs.
The two inputs multiplied together.
4 and 5 being passed into mult,
something happens, the output we expect
is 20.
Why do we call it a black box?
Well if we aren't writing the
functions ourselves, which
we've done quite a bit so far cs50.
We've seen print f, for example, which
is a function that we didn't write
ourselves, but we do use all the time.
If we aren't writing
the functions ourselves,
we don't really need to know how it's
actually implemented under the hood.
>> So for example the black box I
just showed you for multiplication,
mult a, b could be
defined-- and this is just
some pseudocode-- could be
defined as output a times b.
That make sense, right.
If we have a function called
mult that takes two inputs.
We would expect that the output would
be the two inputs multiplied together,
a times b.
But mult could also be
implemented like this,
we have a counter variable to
get set inside of mult to 0.
And then we repeat this process
b times add a to counter.
For example, if we multiply 3a by
5b, we could say set counter to 0,
repeat five times, add 3 to counter.
So we start at 0 and then we do
this five times 3, 6, 9, 12, 15.
It's the same result. We
still get 3 times 5 just
the implementation is different.
>> That's what we mean
when we say a black box.
It just means we don't really care
how it's implemented under the hood
as long as the output is what we expect.
In fact, that's part of the contract
of using functions, particularly
functions that others write.
The behavior is always going
to be typical, unpredictable
based on the name of the function.
And that's why it's really
important when you write functions
or when other people write
functions that you might use,
that those functions have
clear, relatively obvious names,
and are well documented.
Which is certainly the case
for function like print f.
>> So why do we use functions?
Well as I said earlier, if we write
all of our code inside of main things
can get really cumbersome
and really complicated.
Functions allow us the ability
to organize things and break up
a very complicated problem into
a lot more manageable sub parts.
Functions also allow us to
simplify the coding process.
It's a lot easier to debug a 10
line function versus a 100 line
function or a 1,000 line function.
If we only have to debug
small pieces at a time,
or write small pieces at the time,
it makes that programming experience
a lot better.
Trust me on that one.
>> Lastly, if we write functions we
can reuse those various parts.
Functions can be recycled.
They can be used in
one program or another.
You've already written
the function, all you
need to do is tell that program
where to find that function.
We've been recycling and using
print f for over 40 years.
But it was only written one time.
Pretty useful, right.
All right.
So functions are great.
We know that.
Now let's start writing them.
Let's start getting
them into our programs.
In order to do that, the first
thing we do is declare the function.
When you declare a function
what you're basically doing
is telling the compiler,
hey, just so you know,
I am going to be writing
a function later on
and here's what it's going to look like.
The reason for this is
because compilers can
do some weird things if
they see a set of symbols
that they're not familiar with.
So we just give the compiler a
heads up, I'm creating a function
and it's going to do this.
Function declarations generally if
you're organizing your code in a way
that others will be able to
understand and make use of,
you generally want to put all
of your function declarations
at the very top of your code, right
before you start writing main even.
And conveniently, there's
a very standard form
that every function declaration follows.
They all pretty much look like this.
There are three parts to a function
declaration, return type, name,
and argument list.
>> Now the return type is what kind of
variable the function will output.
So for example, if we think back a
minute ago to the multiplying two
numbers function, what do we expect if
we multiply an integer by an integer
the output will be
probably an integer, right.
Multiplied two integers
together, you get an integer.
So the return type of that
function would be int.
Name is what you want
to call your function.
This is probably the least important
part of the function declaration,
in terms of functionality.
But is actually probably one
of the most important parts
of the function declaration in terms
of knowing what the function actually
does.
If you name your function f or g or
h or mystery or something like that,
you're probably going to get
a little tripped up trying
to remember what those functions do.
So it's important to give your
function's meaningful names.
>> Lastly, argument list is
the comma separated list
of all the inputs to your function,
each of which has a type and a name.
So not only do you have to
specify what type of variable
the function will output,
you also want to specify
what type and types of variables the
function will be accepting as inputs.
So let's do an example here.
Let's just take a look
at a more concrete one.
So here's an example of a function
declaration for a function that
would add two integers together.
The sum of two integers is going to
be an integer as well, as we just
discussed.
And so the return type,
here in green, would be int.
That just tells us that add two ints
is going to, at the end of the day,
output, or spit it back
out to us, an integer.
Given what this function does we
want to give it a meaningful name.
Add two ints seems
appropriate, considering
we're taking two integers as inputs
and hopefully adding them together.
It might be a bit of a cumbersome
name and frankly this function
is probably not necessary
since we have the addition
operator, if you recall from our
discussion of operators, previously.
But let's just say for sake of
argument that this function is useful
and so we'll call it add two ints.
Lastly, this function takes two inputs.
Each of which is an integer.
So we have this comma
separated list of inputs.
Now we generally want to
give a name to each of them
so that they can be used
within the function.
The names aren't terribly important.
>> In this case, we don't necessarily
have any meaning attached to them.
So we can just call them a and b.
That's totally fine.
If however, you find
yourself in a situation
where the names of the variables
might actually be important,
you might want to call them
something other than a and b
to give them something more
symbolically meaningful.
But in this case, we don't really
know anything else about the function.
We just want to add two integers.
So we'll just call
those integers a and b.
That's one example.
>> Why don't you take a second
to think about this one,
how would you write a function
declaration for a function that
multiplies two floating point numbers?
Do you remember what a
floating point number is?
What would this function
declaration look like?
I actually recommend you pause the video
here and take how much time you need.
Think about what this
function declaration would be?
What would the return type be?
What would a meaningful name be?
What would the inputs be?
So why don't you pause the video here
and write-up a function declaration
for a function that would multiply
two floating point numbers together.
Hopefully you paused the video.
>> So let's take a look at an example
of one possible declaration.
Float mult two reals float x, float y.
The product of two
floating point numbers,
which recall are how we
represent real numbers
or numbers with decimal values in c,
is going to be a floating point number.
When you multiply a
decimal by a decimal,
you're probably going to get a decimal.
You want to give it a relevant name.
Multiply two reals seems fine.
But you could really call it
mult two floats, or mult floats.
Anything like that, as long as it
gave some actual meaning to what
this black box was going to do.
And again, in this case, we don't
seem to have any meaning attached
to the names of the
variables we're passing in,
so we just call them x and y.
Now if you call them something
else, that's totally fine.
In fact, if you did
this declaration instead
using doubles instead
of floats, if you recall
that doubles are a different
way to more precisely
specify real numbers or
floating point variables.
That's totally fine too.
Either one of those would be fine.
In fact, there are several
different combinations
of ways to declare this function.
But these are two pretty good ones.
We've declared a function, that's great.
We've told the compiler what it
is, what we're going to be doing.
Now let's actually write that function.
Let's give it a definition,
so that inside the black box
predictable behavior is happening.
In fact, we are multiplying two real
numbers together, or adding numbers
together, or doing whatever it is
that we asked our function to do.
>> So in fact, let's try and define
multiply two reals which we just
talked about a second ago.
Now the beginning of
a function definition
looks almost exactly the same
as a function declaration.
I have both of them here.
At the top is the function declaration,
type, name, comma separated argument
list, semicolon.
The semicolon indicates that
that is a function declaration.
The beginning of the function
definition looks almost exactly
the same, type, name, comma separated
argument list, no semicolon,
open curly brace.
The open curly brace, just as
we've been doing with main,
means that we are now
beginning to define
what happens inside the black box that
we've decided to call mult two reals.
Here is one way to implement it.
We could say, we could declare a new
variable of type float called product
and assign that variable
to the value x times y.
And then return product.
What does return mean here.
Well return is the way
we indicate that's how
we're passing the output back out.
So return something, is the same as,
this is the output of the black box.
So that's how you do it.
Here's another way to implement it.
We could just return x times y.
x is a float.
y is a float.
So x times y is also a float.
We don't even need to
create another variable.
So that's a different way to
implement the exact same black box.
>> Now take a moment,
pause the video again,
and try and define add two ints,
which is the other function that we
talked about a moment ago.
Again here, I've put the function
declaration, and so the semicolon,
and an open curly brace
and a closed curly
brace to indicate where we will fill
in the contents of add two ints,
so that we define the particular
behavior inside the black box.
So pause the video.
And take as much time as
you need to try and define
an implementation of add two ints, such
that when the function outputs a value,
it does, in fact, return
the sum of the two inputs.
So just like the previous example,
there are several different ways
that you could implement add two ints.
Here's one.
In here in orange I've
just had some comments--
I've just added some
comments to indicate
what's happening on each line of code.
So I declare a variable
called sum of type int.
I say sum equals a plus b.
That's where we're actually doing
the work adding a and b together.
And I return sum.
And that makes sense because
sum is a variable of type int.
And what's the data type that this
function tells me it's going to output?
Int.
So I'm returning sum, which
is an integer variable.
And that makes sense given what we've
declared and defined our function
to do.
>> Now you can also define
the function this way,
int sum equals a plus b-- skip that
first step-- and then, return sum.
Now you could have also
implemented it this way,
which I highly do not recommend.
This is bad style for one
thing and really bad design,
but it does, in fact, work.
If you take this code, which is int
add bad adder dot c, and use it.
It actually does add
two integers together.
It's a very poor implementation
of this particular behavior.
But it does work.
It's just here to illustrate
the point that we don't really
care what happens inside
the black box, as long
as it has the output that we expect.
This is a poorly designed black box.
But at the end the day, it does
still output the sum of a plus b.
All right.
So we've declared functions.
And we've defined function.
So that's really good.
Now let's start to use the functions
that we've declared and we've defined.
To call a function-- it's actually
pretty easy-- all you need to do
is pass it appropriate arguments,
arguments of the data type
that it expects, and
then assign the return
value of that function
and this-- excuse me--
assign the return value of that function
to something of the correct type.
>> So let's have a look at
this in practice in a file
called adder 1 dot c, which
I have in my cs50 IDE.
So here is adder 1 dot c.
At the beginning you see I have
my includes, pound include,
standard IO, and cs50 dot h.
And then I have my function declaration.
This is where I'm
telling the compiler I'm
going to be writing a
function called add two ints.
It's going to output an
integer type variable.
That's what this part is right here.
And then I have two inputs to it a
and b, each of which is an integer.
Inside of main, I ask the user for
input by saying, give me an integer.
And they are prompted to forget
int, which is a function that
is included in the cs50 library.
And that gets stored in
x, an integer variable.
>> Then we prompt them for another integer.
We get another integer
and store that in y.
And then, here on line 28, is
where we make our function call.
We are saying, int z equals
add 2 ints x comma y.
Do you see why this makes sense?
x is an integer type variable and
y is an integer type variable.
So that's good.
That make sense with what our function
declaration on line 17 looks like.
The comma separated input list
expects two integers, a and b.
In that case, we can call
them whatever we want.
It just expects two integers.
And x is an integer and y is an integer.
That works.
>> And we know that function is going
to output an integers as well.
And so we are storing the
output of the function,
add two ints, in an integer type
variable, which we're calling z.
And then we can say, the sum of
percent i and percent i is percent i.
x, y and z respectively
filling in those percent i's.
What is the definition of
add two ints look like?
It's pretty simple.
It's one of the ones we
just saw a second ago,
int sum equals a plus b return sum.
Does this work?
Let's save the file.
And then down here on my terminal
I'm going to make adder 1,
and I clear my screen.
I'm going to zoom in because I know
it's a little difficult to see.
>> So we compile this program as adder 1.
So we can do dot slash adder 1.
Give me an integer, 10.
Give me another integer, 20.
The sum of 10 and 20 is 30.
So we made a successful function call.
You can run the function again, negative
10, 17 sum of negative 10 and 17 is 7.
This function works.
It has the behavior
that we expect it to.
And so we've made a successful
function, definition, declaration,
and a successful function call.
Couple miscellaneous
points about functions
before we conclude this section.
Recall from our
discussion of data types,
previously, that functions
can sometimes take no inputs.
If that's the case, we
declare the function
as having a void argument list.
Do you recall what the
most common function
we've seen so far that takes
a void argument list is?
It's main.
Recall also that function sometimes
don't actually have an output.
In that case, we declare the function
as having a void return type.
Let's conclude this section by
tackling a practice problem.
>> So here's the problem laid out.
I want you to write a function
called valid triangle.
What this function should do
is take three real numbers
that represent the lengths of the three
sides of a triangle as its parameters,
or its arguments, or its
inputs-- another set of synonyms
that you might encounter.
This function should
either output true or false
depending on whether those three lengths
are capable of making a triangle.
Do you remember the data type that
we used to indicate true or false?
Now how do you implement this?
Well know there are a couple
of rules regarding triangles
that are actually useful to know.
A triangle can only have
sides with positive length.
That makes sense.
You're probably saying, duh.
The other thing to note
though, is that the sum
of the lengths of any
two sides of the triangle
has to be greater than the
length of the third side.
That's actually true.
You can't have a triangle of sides 1,
2 and 4, for example, because 1 plus 2
is not greater than 4.
So those are the rules that
determine whether or not the three
inputs can conceivably form a triangle.
So take a couple of minutes
and declare and then define
this function called valid
triangle, such that it actually
has the behavior specified here.
>> It will output true if those three sides
are capable of comprising a triangle,
and false otherwise
Ready to see how you did?
Here's one implementation
of valid triangle.
It's not the only one.
Yours might vary slightly.
But this one does, in fact, have
the behavior that we expect.
We declare our function at the
very top, bool valid triangle
float x float y float z.
So again, this function
takes three real numbers
as its arguments, floating
point value variables,
and outputs a true or false
value, which is a Boolean, recall.
So that's why the return type is bool.
Then we define the function.
First thing we do is check to make sure
that all of the sides are positive.
If x is less than or equal
to 0, or if y is equal to 0,
or if z is less than or equal to 0,
that can't possibly be a triangle.
They don't have positive sides.
And so we can return
false in that situation.
Next, we check to make sure
that every pair of inputs
is greater than the third one.
>> So if x plus y is less
than or equal to z,
or if x plus z is less
than or equal to y,
or if y plus z is less than or equal to
x, that also can't be a valid triangle.
So we return false again.
Assuming we passed both of the checks
though, then we can return true.
Because those three sides
are capable of returning--
of creating a valid triangle.
And that's it.
You've now declared and defined.
And you may be able to now
use and call this function.
Great job.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is cs50.