>> DOUG LLOYD: All right GDB.
What is it exactly?
So GDB, which stands
for the GNU Debugger,
is a really awesome tool that we can
use to help us debug our programs,
or find out where things are
going wrong in our programs.
GDB is amazingly powerful, but
the output and interaction with it
can be a little bit cryptic.
It's usually a command line tool, and
it can throw a lot of messages at you.
And it can kind of hard to
parse exactly what's going on.
Fortunately, we've taken steps
to fix this problem for you
as you work through CS50.
If you aren't using the graphical
debugger, which my colleague Dan
Armandarse has spoken quite
a bit about in a video that
should be over here
right now, you might need
to use these command line
tools to work with GDB.
If you're working in the CS50
IDE, you don't need to do this.
But if you're not
working in the CS50 IDE,
perhaps using a version
of CS50 Appliance,
or another Linux operating
system with GDB installed on it,
you may need to use
these command line tools.
>> And since you might
have to do that, it's
useful just to understand how
GDB works from the command line.
But again, if you're
using the CS50 IDE, you
can use the graphical debugger
that is built into the IDE.
So to get things going with
GDB, to start the debugging
process of a particular
program, all you need do
is type GDB followed
by the program name.
So for example, if your program is
hello, you would type GDB hello.
>> When you do that, you're going
to pull up the GDB environment.
Your prompt will change, and
instead of being what it usually
is when you type things
at the command line-- ls,
cd-- all of your typical
Linux commands, your prompt
will change to, probably, something
like parentheses GDB parentheses.
That's your new GDB prompt, because
you're inside the GDB environment.
Once inside of that environment,
there's two major commands
that you'll probably use
in the following order.
>> The first is b, which
is short for break.
And after you type b, you typically
type the name of a function,
or if you happen to know
around what line number
your program is starting
to behave a little weird,
you can type a line
number there as well.
What b, or break, does
is it allows your program
to run up until a certain point,
namely, the name of the function
that you specify or the line
number that you specify.
>> And at that point, it
will freeze execution.
This is a really good thing, because
once execution has been frozen,
you can begin to very slowly
step through your program.
Typically, if you've been running
your programs, they're pretty short.
Usually, you type dot slash whatever
the name of your program is, hit Enter,
and before you can blink, your
program is already finished.
It's not really a lot of time to try
and figure out what's going wrong.
So it really to be able to slow things
down by setting a break point with b,
and then stepping in.
>> Then once you've set your break
point, you can run the program.
And if you have any
command line arguments,
you specify them here, not when
you type GDB your program name.
You specify all the command line
arguments by taking r, or run,
and then whatever command line arguments
you need inside of your program.
There are a number of other really
important and useful commands
inside of the GDP environment.
So let me just quickly
go over some of them.
>> The first is n, which is short for next,
and you can type next instead of n,
both would work.
And it's just the shorthand.
And as you've probably already gotten
used to, being able to type things
shorter is generally better.
And what it will do is it'll
step forward one block of code.
So it'll move forward
until a function call.
And then instead of
diving into that function
and going through all of that functions
code, it will just have the function.
>> The function will be called.
It will do whatever its work is.
It will return a value to
the function that called it.
And then you'll move on to the
next line of that calling function.
If you want to step
inside of the function,
instead of just having
it execute, especially
if you think that the problem
might lie inside of that function,
you could, of course, set a break
point inside of that function.
Or if you're already running, you can
use s to step forward one line of code.
>> So this will step in
and dive into functions,
instead of just have the execute
and continuing on in the function
that you're in for debugging.
If you ever want to know
the value of a variable,
you can type p, or Print,
and then the variable name.
And that will print out to you,
inside of the GDB environment,
the name of the variable, that you--
excuse me-- the value of the variable
that you've named.
If you want to know the values of every
local variable accessible from where
you currently are in your
program, you can type info locals.
It's a lot faster than
typing p and then whatever,
listing out all of the
variables that you know exist.
You can type info locals, and it
will print out everything for you.
Next up is bt, which is
short for Back Trace.
Now, generally,
particularly early in CS50,
you won't really have occasion
to use bt, or Back Trace,
because you're not having functions
that call other functions.
>> You might have main call a
function, but that's probably it.
You don't have that other function
calling another function, which
calls another function, and so on.
But as your programs get more
complex, and particularly
when you begin working
with recursion, back trace
can be a really useful way to let you
kind of get some context for where
I am in my program.
So say you've written your code, and
you know that main calls a function
f, which calls a function
g, which calls a function h.
So we have several layers
of nesting going on here.
>> If you're inside of
your GDB environment,
and you know your inside
of h, but you forget
about what got you to where you
are-- you can type bt, or back trace,
and it will print out h, g, f main,
alongside some other information, which
gives you a clue that, OK main
called f, f called g, g called h,
and that's where I
currently am in my program.
So it can be really useful,
especially as the cryptic-ness of GDB
becomes a little overwhelming, to
find out exactly where things are.
Finally, when your program is done,
or when you're done debugging it
and you want to step away
from the GDB environment,
it helps to know how to get out of it.
You can type q, or Quit, to get out.
Now, before today's video
I prepared a buggy program
called buggy1, which I compiled
from a file known as buggy1.c.
As you might expect, this
program is in fact buggy.
Something goes wrong
when I try and run it.
Now, unfortunately, I inadvertently
deleted my buggy1.c file,
so in order for me to figure out
what's going wrong with this program,
I'm going to have to use
GDB kind of blindly, trying
to navigate through this program to
figure out exactly what's going wrong.
But using just the tools
we've already learned about,
we can pretty much figure
out exactly what it is.
So let's head over to
CS50 IDE and have a look.
OK, so we're here in my
CS50 IDE environment,
and I'll zoom in a little bit
so you can see a little more.
In my terminal window, if I list
the contents of my current director
with ls, we'll see that I
have a couple of source files
here, including the
previously discussed buggy1.
What exactly goes on when
I try and run buggy1.
Well let's find out.
I type dot slash,
buggy, and I hit Enter.
>> Segmentation faults.
That's not good.
If you recall, a
segmentation fault typically
occurs when we access memory
that we're not allowed to touch.
We've somehow reached
outside of the bounds
of what the program, the
compiler, has given us.
And so already that's a
clue to keep in the toolbox
as we begin the debugging process.
Something has gone a little wrong here.
>> All right, so let's start
up the GDB environment
and see if we can figure out
what exactly the problem is.
I'm going to clear my screen,
and I'm going to type GDB
again, to enter the GDB environment,
and the name of the program
that I want to debug, buggy1.
We get a little message, reading
symbols from buggy1, done.
All that means is it pulled
together all of the code,
and now it's been loaded into
GDB, and it's ready to go.
>> Now, what do I want to do?
Do you recall what the
first step typically is
after I'm inside of this environment?
Hopefully, you said set
a break point, because
in fact that is what I want to do.
Now, I don't have the
source code for this
in front of me, which is probably
not the typical use case, by the way.
You probably will.
So that's good.
But assuming you don't, what's
the one function that you know
exists in every single C program?
No matter how big or how complicated
it is, this function definitely exists.
Main, right?
>> So failing all else, we can
set a break point at main.
And again, I could just type
break main, instead of b.
And if you're curious, if you
ever type out a long command
and then realize that you
typed the wrong thing,
and you want to get rid
of all as I just did,
you can take Control U, which will
delete everything and bring you back
to the beginning of the cursor lines.
A lot faster than just hold down the
delete, or hitting it a bunch times
over.
>> So we'll set a break point at main.
And as you can see, it says we've
set a break point at file buggy1.c,
and apparently the first line
of code of main is line seven.
Again, we don't have
the source file here,
but I'll assume that it's
telling me the truth.
And then, I'm just trying
and run the program, r.
Starting program.
All right, so this message
is a little cryptic.
But basically what's
happening here is it's just
telling me I've hit my break
point, break point number 1.
>> And then, that line of code,
no such file or directory.
The only reason that
I'm seeing that message
is because I inadvertently
deleted my buggy.c file.
If my buggy1.c file existed
in the current directory,
that line right there would actually
tell me what the line of code
literally reads.
Unfortunately, I deleted it.
We're going to have to kind of navigate
through this a little more blindly.
>> OK, so let's see, what
do I want to do here?
Well, I would like to know what local
variables maybe are available to me.
I've started my program.
Let's see what might be
already initialized for us.
I type Info locals, no locals.
All right, so that doesn't
give me a ton of information.
I could try and print out a variable,
but I don't know any variable names.
I could try a back trace,
but I'm inside of main,
so I know I haven't made
another function call right now.
>> So looks like my only options are
to use n or so and start to dive in.
I'm going to use n.
So I type n.
Oh my gosh, what is going on here.
Program received signals,
SIGSEGV segmentation fault,
and then a whole bunch of stuff.
I'm already overwhelmed.
Well, there's actually a
lot to be learned here.
So what does this tell us?
What it tells us is, this program is
about to, but hasn't yet, seg fault.
And in particular, I'm going
to zoom in even further here,
it's about to seg fault about
something called strcmp.
>> Now, we may not have discussed
this function extensively.
But it is-- because we're not going
to talk about every function that
exists in the C standard library--
but they're all available to you,
particularly if you take a
look at reference.cs50.net.
And strcmp is a really powerful
function that exists inside
of the string.h header
file, which is a header
file that is dedicated to functions
that work with and manipulate strings.
>> And in particular, what strcmp does is
it compares the values of two strings.
So I'm about to segmentation fault
on a call to strcmp it seems.
I hit n, and in fact I get the message,
program terminated with signal SIGSEGV
segmentation fault. So now
I actually have seg faulted,
and my program has pretty
much effectively given up.
This is the end of the program.
It broke down, it crashed.
So wasn't a lot, but I
actually did learn quite a bit
from this little experience.
What have I learned?
Well, my program crashes
pretty much immediately.
My program crashes on
a call to strcmp, but I
don't have any local variables in my
program at the time that it crashes.
So what string, or strings,
could I possibly be comparing.
If I don't have any local
variables, you might
surmise that I have-- there maybe is a
global variable, which could be true.
>> But generally, it seems
like I'm comparing
to something that doesn't exist.
So let's investigate
that a little further.
So I'm going to clear my screen.
I'm going to quit out of the
GDB environment for a second.
And I'm thinking, OK, so there's
no local variables in my program.
I wonder if maybe I'm supposed to pass
in a string as a command line argument.
So let's just test this out.
I haven't done this before.
>> Let's see if maybe if I run this program
with a command line argument it works.
Huh, no segmentation fault there.
It just told me that I figured it out.
So maybe that's the fix here.
And indeed, if I go back and look at
the actual source code for buggy1.c,
it seems as though what I'm doing is
I'm making a call to strcmp without
checking whether in fact argv[1] exists.
This is actually the
source code for buggy1.c.
So what I really need to
do here to fix my program,
assuming I have the
file in front of me, is
to just add a check to make
sure that argc is equal to 2.
So this example, again, like I said,
is a little bit contrived, right?
You're generally not going to
accidentally delete your source code
and then have to try
and debug the program.
But hopefully, it gave
you an illustration
of the kinds of things that
you could be thinking about
as you're debugging your program.
>> What's the state of affairs here?
What variables do I
have accessible to me?
Where exactly is my program
crashing, on what line,
on what call to what function?
What kind of clues does that give me?
And that's exactly the
kind of mindset that you
should be getting into when you're
thinking about debugging your programs.
>> I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.