[MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DOUG LLOYD: By now you
know a lot about arrays,
and you know a lot about linked lists.
And we've discuss the
pros and cons, we've
discussed that linked lists
can get bigger and smaller,
but they take up more size.
Arrays are much more straightforward to
use, but they're restrictive in as much
as we have to set the size of
the array at the very beginning
and then we're stuck with it.
>> But that's, we've pretty much
exhausted all of our topics
about linked lists and arrays.
Or have we?
Maybe we can do something
even more creative.
And that sort of lends
the idea of a hash table.
>> So in a hash table we're going to try
combine an array with a linked list.
We're going to take the advantages
of the array, like random access,
being able to just go to array
element 4 or array element 8
without having to iterate across.
That's pretty fast, right?
>> But we also want to have our data
structure be able to grow and shrink.
We don't need, we don't
want to be restricted.
And we want to be able
to add and remove things
very easily, which if you recall,
is very complex with an array.
And we can call this
new thing a hash table.
>> And if implemented correctly,
we're sort of taking
the advantages of both data
structures you've already seen,
arrays and linked lists.
Insertion can start to
tend toward theta of 1.
Theta we haven't really discussed,
but theta is just the average case,
what's actually going to happen.
You're not always going to
have the worst case scenario,
and you're not always going to have
the best case scenario, so what's
the average scenario?
>> Well an average insertion
into a hash table
can start to get close to constant time.
And deletion can get
close to constant time.
And lookup can get
That's-- we don't have a data
structure yet that can do that,
and so this already sounds
like a pretty great thing.
We've really mitigated the
disadvantages of each on its own.
>> To get this performance
upgrade though, we
need to rethink how we add
data into the structure.
Specifically we want the
data itself to tell us
where it should go in the structure.
And if we then need to see if it's in
the structure, if we need to find it,
we want to look at the data
again and be able to effectively,
using the data, randomly access it.
Just by looking at the
data we should have
an idea of where exactly we're
going to find it in the hash table.
>> Now the downside of a hash
table is that they're really
pretty bad at ordering or sorting data.
And in fact, if you start
to use them to order or sort
data you lose all of the
advantages you previously
had in terms of insertion and deletion.
The time becomes closer to
theta of n, and we've basically
regressed into a linked list.
And so we only want to use hash
tables if we don't care about
whether data is sorted.
For the context in which
you'll use them in CS50
you probably don't care
that the data is sorted.
>> So a hash table is a combination
of two distinct pieces
with which we're familiar.
The first is a function, which
we usually call a hash function.
And that hash function is going to
return some non-negative integer, which
we usually call a hashcode, OK?
The second piece is an array, which is
capable of storing data of the type we
want to place into the data structure.
We'll hold off on the
linked list element for now
and just start with the basics of a
hash table to get your head around it,
and then we'll maybe blow
your mind a little bit when we
combine arrays and link lists together.
>> The basic idea though
is we take some data.
We run that data through
the hash function.
And so the data is processed
and it spits out a number, OK?
And then with that number
we just store the data
we want to store in the
array at that location.
So for example we have maybe
this hash table of strings.
It's got 10 elements in it, so
we can fit 10 strings in it.
>> Let's say we want to hash John.
So John as the data we want to insert
into this hash table somewhere.
Where do we put it?
Well typically with an
array so far we probably
would put it in array location 0.
But now we have this new hash function.
>> And let's say that we run John
through this hash function
and it's spits out 4.
Well that's where we're
going to want to put John.
We want to put John in array location
4, because if we hash John again--
let's say later we
want to search and see
if John exists in this hash
table-- all we need to do
is run it through the same hash
function, get the number 4 out,
and be able to find John
immediately in our data structure.
That's pretty good.
>> Let's say we now do this
again, we want to hash Paul.
We want to add Paul
into this hash table.
Let's say that this time we run
Paul through the hash function,
the hashcode that is generated is 6.
Well now we can put Paul
in the array location 6.
And if we need to look up whether
Paul is in this hash table,
all we need to do is run Paul
through the hash function again
and we're going to get 6 out again.
>> And then we just look
at array location 6.
Is Paul there?
If so, he's in the hash table.
Is Paul not there?
He's not in the hash table.
It's pretty straightforward.
>> Now how do you define a hash function?
Well there's really no limit to the
number of possible hash functions.
In fact there's a number of really,
really good ones on the internet.
There's a number of really,
really bad ones on the internet.
It's also pretty easy
to write a bad one.
>> So what makes up a good
hash function, right?
Well a good hash function should
use only the data being hashed,
and all of the data being hashed.
So we don't want to use anything--
we don't incorporate anything
else other than the data.
And we want to use all of the data.
We don't want to just use a piece
of it, we want to use all of it.
A hash function should
also be deterministic.
What does that mean?
Well it means that every time we
pass the exact same piece of data
into the hash function we always
get the same hashcode out.
If I pass John into the
hash function I get out 4.
I should be able to do that 10,000
times and I'll always get 4.
So no random numbers effectively
can be involved in our hash tables--
in our hash functions.
>> A hash function should also
uniformly distribute data.
If every time you run data through the
hash function you get the hashcode 0,
that's probably not so great, right?
You probably want to big
a range of hash codes.
Also things can be spread
out throughout the table.
And also it would be great if really
similar data, like John and Jonathan,
maybe were spread out to weigh
different locations in the hash table.
That would be a nice advantage.
>> Here's an example of a hash function.
I wrote this one up earlier.
It's not a particularly
good hash function
for reasons that don't really
bear going into right now.
But do you see what's going on here?
It seems like we're declaring a variable
called sum and setting it equal to 0.
And then apparently I'm doing something
so long as strstr[j] is not equal
to backslash 0.
What am I doing there?
>> This is basically just another
way of implementing [? strl ?]
and detecting when you've
reached the end of the string.
So I don't have to actually
calculate the length of the string,
I'm just using when I hit the
backslash 0 character I know
I've reached the end of the string.
And then I'm going to keep
iterating through that string,
adding strstr[j] to sum, and then at the
end of the day going to return sum mod
HASH_MAX.
>> Basically all this hash
function is doing is adding up
all of the ASCII values of
my string, and then it's
returning some hashcode
modded by HASH_MAX.
It's probably the size
of my array, right?
I don't want to be getting hash
codes if my array is of size 10,
I don't want to be getting
out hash codes 11, 12,
13, I can't put things into
those locations of the array,
that would be illegal.
I'd suffer a segmentation fault.
>> Now here is another quick aside.
Generally you're probably not going to
want to write your own hash functions.
It is actually a bit of
an art, not a science.
And there's a lot that goes into them.
The internet, like I said, is full
of really good hash functions,
and you should use the internet to
find hash functions because it's really
just kind of an unnecessary
waste of time to create your own.
>> You can write simple ones
for testing purposes.
But when you actually are going to
start hashing data and storing it
into a hash table you're
probably going to want
to use some function that was generated
for you, that exists on the internet.
If you do just be sure
to cite your sources.
There's no reason to
plagiarize anything here.
>> The computer science community is
definitely growing, and really values
open source, and it's really important
to cite your sources so that people
can get attribution for
the work that they're
doing to the benefit of the community.
So always be sure--
and not just for hash
functions, but generally when you
use code from an outside source,
always cite your source.
Give credit to the person who did
some of the work so you don't have to.
>> OK so let's revisit this
hash table for a second.
This is where we left
off after we inserted
John and Paul into this hash table.
Do you see a problem here?
You might see two.
But in particular, do you
see this possible problem?
>> What if I hash Ringo, and it
turns out that after processing
that data through the hash function
Ringo also generated the hashcode 6.
I've already got data at
hashcode-- array location 6.
So it's probably going to be a bit
of a problem for me now, right?
>> We call this a collision.
And the collision occurs when two
pieces of data run through the same hash
function yield the same hashcode.
Presumably we still want to get both
pieces of data into the hash table,
otherwise we wouldn't be running Ringo
arbitrarily through the hash function.
We presumably want to get
Ringo into that array.
>> How do we do it though, if he
and Paul both yield hashcode 6?
We don't want to overwrite Paul,
we want Paul to be there too.
So we need to find a way to get
elements into the hash table that
still preserves our quick
insertion and quick look up.
And one way to deal with it is to
do something called linear probing.
>> Using this method if we have a
collision, well, what do we do?
Well we can't put him in array location
6, or whatever hashcode was generated,
let's put him at hashcode plus 1.
And if that's full let's
put him in hashcode plus 2.
The benefit of this being if he's
not exactly where we think he is,
and we have to start searching,
maybe we don't have to go too far.
Maybe we don't have to search
all n elements of the hash table.
Maybe we have to search
a couple of them.
>> And so we're still tending towards
that average case being close to 1 vs
close to n, so maybe that'll work.
So let's see how this
might work out in reality.
And let's see if maybe we can detect
the problem that might occur here.
>> Let's say we hash Bart.
So now we're going to run a new set
of strings through the hash function,
and we run Bart through the hash
function, we get hashcode 6.
We take a look, we see 6 is
empty, so we can put Bart there.
>> Now we hash Lisa and that
also generates hashcode 6.
Well now that we're using this
linear probing method we start at 6,
we see that 6 is full.
We can't put Lisa in 6.
So where do we go?
Let's go to 7.
7's empty, so that works.
So let's put Lisa there.
>> Now we hash Homer and we get 7.
OK well we know that 7's full
now, so we can't put Homer there.
So let's go to 8.
Is 8 available?
Yeah, and 8's close to 7, so if
we have to start searching we're
not going to have to go too far.
And so let's put Homer at 8.
>> Now we hash Maggie and
returns 3, thank goodness
we're able to just put Maggie there.
We don't have to do any
sort of probing for that.
Now we hash Marge, and
Marge also returns 6.
>> Well 6 is full, 7 is full, 8 is full,
9, all right thank God, 9 is empty.
I can put Marge at 9.
Already we can see that we're starting
to have this problem where now we're
starting to stretch things kind
of far away from their hash codes.
And that theta of 1, that average
case of being constant time,
is starting to get a little more--
starting to tend a little more
towards theta of n.
We're starting to lose that
advantage of hash tables.
>> This problem that we just saw
is something called clustering.
And what's really bad about
clustering is that once you now
have two elements that are side by
side it makes it even more likely,
you have double the
chance, that you're going
to have another collision
with that cluster,
and the cluster will grow by one.
And you'll keep growing and growing
your likelihood of having a collision.
And eventually it's just as bad
as not sorting the data at all.
>> The other problem though is we
still, and so far up to this point,
we've just been sort of
understanding what a hash table is,
we still only have room for 10 strings.
If we want to continue to hash
the citizens of Springfield,
we can only get 10 of them in there.
And if we try and add an 11th or 12th,
we don't have a place to put them.
We could just be spinning around in
circles trying to find an empty spot,
and we maybe get stuck
in an infinite loop.
>> So this sort of lends to the idea
of something called chaining.
And this is where we're going to bring
linked lists back into the picture.
What if instead of storing just
the data itself in the array,
every element of the array could
hold multiple pieces of data?
Well that doesn't make sense, right?
We know that an array can only
hold-- each element of an array
can only hold one piece
of data of that data type.
>> But what if that data type
is a linked list, right?
So what if every
element of the array was
a pointer to the head of a linked list?
And then we could build
those linked lists
and grow them arbitrarily,
because linked lists allow
us to grow and shrink a lot more
flexibly than an array does.
So what if we now use,
we leverage this, right?
We start to grow these chains
out of these array locations.
>> Now we can fit an infinite
amount of data, or not infinite,
an arbitrary amount of
data, into our hash table
without ever running into
the problem of collision.
We've also eliminated
clustering by doing this.
And well we know that when we insert
into a linked list, if you recall
from our video on linked lists, singly
linked lists and doubly linked lists,
it's a constant time operation.
We're just adding to the front.
>> And for look up, well we do know
that look up in a linked list
can be a problem, right?
We have to search through
it from beginning to end.
There's no random
access in a linked list.
But if instead of having one linked
list where a lookup would be O of n,
we now have 10 linked lists,
or 1,000 linked lists,
now it's O of n divided by 10,
or O of n divided by 1,000.
>> And while we were talking
theoretically about complexity
we disregard constants, in the real
world these things actually matter,
right?
We actually will notice
that this happens
to run 10 times faster,
or 1,000 times faster,
because we're distributing one long
chain across 1,000 smaller chains.
And so each time we have to search
through one of those chains we can
ignore the 999 chains we don't care
about , and just search that one.
>> Which is on average to
be 1,000 times shorter.
And so we still are sort of
tending towards this average case
of being constant time, but
only because we are leveraging
dividing by some huge constant factor.
Let's see how this might
actually look though.
So this was the hash table we had
before we declared a hash table that
was capable of storing 10 strings.
We're not going to do that anymore.
We already know the
limitations of that method.
Now our hash table's going to be
an array of 10 nodes, pointers
to heads of linked lists.
>> And right now it's null.
Each one of those 10 pointers is null.
There's nothing in our
hash table right now.
>> Now let's start to put some
things into this hash table.
And let's see how this method is
going to benefit us a little bit.
Let's now hash Joey.
We'll will run the string Joey through
a hash function and we return 6.
Well what do we do now?
>> Well now working with linked lists,
we're not working with arrays.
And when we're working
with linked lists we
know we need to start dynamically
allocating space and building chains.
That's sort of how-- those are the core
elements of building a linked list.
So let's dynamically
allocate space for Joey,
and then let's add him to the chain.
>> So now look what we've done.
When we hash Joey we got the hashcode 6.
Now the pointer at array location 6
points to the head of a linked list,
and right now it's the only
element of a linked list.
And the node in that
linked list is Joey.
>> So if we need to look up Joey
later, we just hash Joey again,
we get 6 again because our
hash function is deterministic.
And then we start at the head
of the linked list pointed
to by array location
6, and we can iterate
across that trying to find Joey.
And if we build our
hash table effectively,
and our hash function effectively
to distribute data well,
on average each of those linked
lists at every array location
will be 1/10 the size of if we
just had it as a single huge
linked list with everything in it.
>> If we distribute that huge linked
list across 10 linked lists
each list will be 1/10 the size.
And thus 10 times quicker
to search through.
So let's do this again.
Let's now hash Ross.
>> And let's say Ross, when we do that
the hash code we get back is 2.
Well now we dynamically allocate a
new node, we put Ross in that node,
and we say now array location
2, instead of pointing to null,
points to the head of a linked
list whose only node is Ross.
And we can do this one more time, we
can hash Rachel and get hashcode 4.
malloc a new node, put Rachel in
the node, and say a array location
4 now points to the head
of a linked list whose
only element happens to be Rachel.
>> OK but what happens if
we have a collision?
Let's see how we handle collisions
using the separate chaining method.
Let's hash Phoebe.
We get the hashcode 6.
In our previous example we were just
storing the strings in the array.
This was a problem.
>> We don't want to clobber
Joey, and we've already
seen that we can get some clustering
problems if we try and step
through and probe.
But what if we just kind of
treat this the same way, right?
It's just like adding an element
to the head of a linked list.
Let's just malloc space for Phoebe.
>> We'll say Phoebe's next pointer points
to the old head of the linked list,
and then 6 just points to the
new head of the linked list.
And now look, we've changed Phoebe in.
We can now store two
elements with hashcode 6,
and we don't have any problems.
>> That's pretty much all
there is to chaining.
And chaining is definitely
the method that's
going to be most effective for you if
you are storing data in a hash table.
But this combination of
arrays and linked lists
together to form a hash table really
dramatically improves your ability
to store large amounts of data, and
very quickly and efficiently search
through that data.
>> There's still one more
data structure out there
that might even be a bit
better in terms of guaranteeing
that our insertion, deletion, and
look up times are even faster.
And we'll see that in a video on tries.
I'm Doug Lloyd, this is CS50.