>> SPEAKER: Let's talk about another
protocol-- the Hypertext Transfer
Protocol, or HTTP.
So we've talked about IP
and TCP in previous videos.
And those are protocols
that dictate how information
moves from machine to machine and
from program to program or service
to service via the internet, via
this network of routers and machines.
>> But that's usually not
the entire picture, right?
Usually when we send
information, the program
itself-- when data is
received, say, for example,
in email via TCP port 25 or a
web page request via port 80,
there's usually a system of rules there
to process what I've just received.
And HTTP is an example
of just such a protocol.
>> HTTP is the only
application layer protocol
that we're going to talk about.
But it is another set
of rules dictating how
information is to be transmitted
and processed via the internet.
In particular, HTTP
specifies exactly how
one must make a request for
a web page and exactly how
a server, a machine
that hosts web pages,
delivers that information
back to clients.
>> So this protocol doesn't
actually have anything
to do with how information
moves from point A
to point B. It's really
the system of rules
for-- it's basically the rules of
engagement for working with a web page,
similar to when somebody
waves their hand at you,
you're supposed to wave back.
That's sort of a
conventional human protocol.
HTTP protocol just says, if
you want to request a web
page, make sure your format looks
like this-- sort of like formatting
a business letter, for example.
And the response will similarly
come according to this protocol.
There are other
application layer protocols
that we're not going to
talk about in videos.
But these include things like
the File Transfer Protocol,
Simple Mail Transfer Protocol for
sending emails, the Data Distribution
Service, Remote Desktop
Protocol, RDP, which
is used if you want to remotely access
your computer from another computer,
XMPP, which is frequently
known as Jabber or chat,
so this is the protocol
for using chat services.
And there are many, many, many others.
>> So every time you're using
a service, the service
is expecting information
to be received-- a request
to be received-- in a
very particular format
and is required to
return information back
in a very particular format as well.
>> So let's go back to our illustration
of us wanting to talk to the internet.
So we're happy, and we want
to go to cats.com, right?
So if we're just talking to cats.com,
we might say something like hey,
can I see your home page?
And cats.com will probably
respond, yeah, sure.
Here you go.
So that's a human sort
of ask-and-answer.
>> What does that look like in HTTP?
Well, it actually kind of translates
pretty cleanly to something like this.
We might say GET/HTTP/1.1
from host cats.com.
So basically what I'm doing here is
asking for the web page www.cats.com/.
We usually omit the slash
nowadays, but that would just
mean cats.com's homepage.
>> Oh, and by the way, I'm going
to be using HTTP version
1.1 to communicate with you.
That's sort of analogous to
saying, like, by the way,
I'm going to be speaking
in French, or by the way,
I'm going to be speaking in English.
That's just the format of the protocol.
It's also 1.0, which is
not commonly used anymore.
So I'm speaking HTTP 1.1, and
I would like www.cats.com/.
Please get that for me.
>> And then there's other information,
too-- the dot, dot, dot there,
which is information about
who you are so cats.com
would know where to send it.
But these are the two
sort of critical parts
at the very beginning
of an HTTP request--
just like when you start a
letter you say, dear, blank.
This is very similar in spirit to that.
>> And if cats.com is going to
say, oh, sure, here you go.
They might respond like
this-- I'm also responding.
I also speak HTTP 1.1.
Your request is approved, 200 OK.
What you're about to
receive is HTML and then
dot, dot, dot some extra information.
And at the very bottom of the
request is actually the HTML,
the markup language, the
content of cats.com's homepage.
>> So HTTP/1.1-- I acknowledge your
request was accepted via HTTP 1.1.
Your request was approved.
I can give you what you want, 200 OK.
You're about to receive HTML.
And then here's the
HTML that you requested.
>> But sometimes our requests don't
always go quite according to plan.
Can I see your cats.html page?
Well, what if they say, we
don't have a cats.html page,
which seems kind of unrealistic
because they're cats.com.
You'd think they would have cats.html.
But OK.
So this is sort of the
conventional human interaction
we've now had with cats.com.
How does that translate?
>> This might be something familiar to you.
Our request looked exactly the same,
except instead of getting slash
we're now getting cats.html.
So now what basically this entire
request is saying is please give me
www.cats.com/cats.html.
So the host and the middle
part of that top line
there indicate precisely
what page I am asking for.
But cats.com in this case isn't going
to be able to respond positively.
They don't know we're talking about.
And so this is something you might have
seen before-- HTTP 1.1 404 Not Found.
I couldn't find what
you were asking for.
By the way, I'm going to give you
back some HTML, and usually that HTML
is the content of some 404 page.
And in the case of
cats.com, it's probably
some cute cats in a basket with
a sad 404 face next to them,
because you're going to be
sad when you don't get page
that you were looking for.
>> That's kind of the basics of what a
protocol, the HTTP protocol requests
look like.
They're really similar to how we
would make a similar interaction
in just human conventions
asking for something
and getting it back or writing a
letter and expecting a response
letter in a particular format.
That's pretty much what
HTTP is just canonicalizing
for all devices that wish to access
web pages, hypertext transfers.
>> So a line of the form, this the
method request target HTTP version,
is called an HTTP request line.
It's usually the first thing that is
transmitted as part of an HTTP request
or if you're asking for HTTP.
It's sort of like, as I said, saying
dear, blank at the top your letter.
They know that you're
writing them a letter.
So this is very similar
to saying, I know
that they're making an HTTP request
and this is the particular format
they're asking for.
>> HTTP version is probably
always going to be HTTP/1/1.
1.0 also exists but isn't
really used anymore.
For purposes of CS50,
GET is probably always
what you're going to be
using when you're actually
making direct HTTP requests.
But POST is another option that we're
not going to talk about right now.
And then request-target is
what page on the host's server
you would like to get.
As I said, that host name
is a separate line, usually
the second line of the overall request.
And so taken together, the host
name and the request target
specify a specific
resource being sought.
In our 404 example a second ago, I
was asking again for www.cats.com,
cats.com being the host.
And in my request line,
I said /cats.html.
That was my request target.
So overall I was asking for the
contents or the resource located
at www.cats.com/cats.html.
>> And then based on whether
the resource exists
and whether the server can deliver
the resource pursuant to the client's
request, you might get
various status codes back.
Some of these status codes you've seen
because they're part of the response.
Some of them, 200 OK, are
probably pretty silent.
You've probably never seen
a page respond 200 OK.
You just get the page.
It's not like a 404 error,
which is usually pretty clear.
You usually see that it says 404.
>> So let's talk about what some
of those status codes might be.
Again, when the server
responds to us, they're
going to respond HTTP version status.
Usually HTTP/1.1.
What are these status codes going to be?
Well, we might get a success.
So in the success category, we
might get code 200 with the text OK.
What does this mean?
Well, everything is good.
You made a valid request.
Here's a valid response.
I was able to deliver
exactly what you wanted.
>> Sometimes you might get other things
that you won't notice right away
but are somewhat failures.
They're called redirections.
There's two common ones here.
301 Moved Permanently--
what this basically means
is the page is now at a new location.
It will live there forever.
And most browsers will
automatically redirect you.
So you'll never really see
a 301, either, unless you're
using a really out-of-date
browser, possibly,
because the 301 response is part of
the dot, dot, dot of the 301 response.
It also tells you where the new page is.
And so most browsers will
just redirect you there,
assuming that you want to go there.
>> Sometimes you'll also get 302 Found.
And this one you actually
might still see occasionally.
Sometimes pages move temporarily.
So it's not going to be built into
the request telling the browser
to permanently change any time
it sees the request that you
make to change it to something else.
So you might see 302
Found, which basically
says this page lives somewhere else.
But it's not going to
live there forever.
It will eventually probably go
back to where you think it is.
>> Then you'll get things
like client errors.
So these are ones you've
probably seen, now.
You probably haven't seen
the 200s or the 300s,
but you're probably
familiar with the 400s.
And that's what we'll talk
about in a second, 500s as well.
>> You might see 401 Unauthorized.
Usually this means you're
trying to access a page,
but you haven't logged in.
So you try and go to some
profile or something on Facebook
or you try and access
some-- you're at work.
You're trying to access something
on your work's internet,
but you're not logged in.
You can't see the page.
You might get a 401 unauthorized,
which means we probably
will be able to satisfy this request,
but first you need to log in to do so.
>> Conversely, you might get 403
Forbidden, which is it doesn't really
matter if you're logged in or not.
This request isn't allowed.
The resource exists on the server.
But you are not allowed to access it.
This is usually internal files that
live on the server for various reasons
but are not intended to be
accessed from the outside world,
and so they are forbidden.
They live there.
I'm not saying I can't find it.
But I'm saying I cannot give it to you.
And it doesn't matter if
you're logged in or not.
And then of course, the
very common 404 Not Found.
The file doesn't exist on the server.
I would like to satisfy
your request, but I can't.
>> You also sometimes see server
errors, the most common generally
being 500 Internal Server Error, which
doesn't actually tell you anything
at all about what has gone wrong.
But it's not actually you making
a mistake in your request.
It's actually the server failing
to deliver on the request somehow.
So 500 is the general response.
>> You'll also see something
like Service Unavailable,
which I believe is code 503.
And Gateway Timeout-- if
you ever had a page just
sit there loading and
loading and loading
and you never know if it's going to
load and then eventually it just says--
just gives up.
That's a 504 Gateway Timeout.
The server wanted to
execute your request,
but something went wrong
on the server side--
not on your side-- to
cause that to be a problem.
Now, we could end the story here,
but what I'm actually going to do now
is I'm going to open up
my browser and show you
how you might be able to see
some of these status codes
even if you don't generally see them.
And we're going to do that by taking
a look at some developer tools.
>> All right So here I am
now in my browser window.
And I want to learn a little bit
more about these HTTP requests.
How do I know-- certainly we know if a
page goes-- when something goes wrong,
we get a 404.
We've all seen that.
We don't need to illustrate that.
But what are some other ones?
And how would we see
these requests in action?
>> So first thing I'm going to
do is open up Developer Tools.
So Developer Tools are built
into most modern browsers
and allow us to see things
that we don't otherwise
see-- some extra information sort of
being transmitted underneath our web
requests.
I'm using Google Chrome here.
And to open Developer Tools
in Chrome, you just hit F-12,
and it's going to open
it up on the side.
Once I type the request, I'll zoom in
so we can see what's going on here.
But what I'm going to do in my browser
bar is-- and I'll zoom in over here--
I will make a request to www.google.com.
We've all probably made
this request before.
I'm going to hit Enter.
>> Now, over here in my Developer
Tools, I've chosen the Network tab.
And you notice a lot of things here.
Look at these-- 200 OK, 200 OK, some
of these status codes coming up.
I don't know why I'm getting 302 Found.
I didn't realize I'd see that one.
But basically notice that pretty
much, in terms of my Google request--
I made a very simple
request for Google's page.
And in the process of
delivering my request,
Google has apparently made a lot
of other requests on my behalf.
>> But I've made a get request for Google's
page and I'm getting a lot of 200 OKs.
I'm not seeing 200 OK on
my screen, but I'm getting
a lot of requests that have been made.
One more that I'm pretty
sure is going to work
is-- for those of you who
are really old-school,
you may know that Facebook was
not always at Facebook.com.
In its early days it was
at wwww.thefacebook.com.
They apparently could not get access
to Facebook.com for quite awhile.
>> And so what I'm expecting
here is to get information.
And we'll see if this pans out.
What I'm expecting here
is to get information
that Facebook has moved permanently
from thefacebook.com to Facebook.com.
So I'm expecting somewhere
near the top of my requests
over in my Developer Tools
to get a 301 notification
that Facebook has moved permanently.
Again, I won't see 301
on my browser screen.
And because it's a 301,
it's a permanent move.
My browser, being that
it's a modern browser,
is probably going to redirect
me to Facebook.com anyway.
But let's see what happens.
>> And now I'm going to
go to thefacebook.com.
And yep, there it is right at the top.
It went away, but it was there.
Let me scroll up here.
Right here at the top.
I made a request to thefacebook.com,
and I'm getting a response
that this page has moved permanently.
And then 307 here is
an internal redirect.
And so this is what has actually
moved me to the much more
familiar www.facebook.com.
>> So these response codes do still
happen, even if we don't see them.
I'm not going to
illustrate 401, 403, 404,
because you've probably seen
those at various points.
And 500, I would just be
kind of-- we'd get lucky
if got a 500 because we don't know what
servers are currently down anywhere.
But these codes do
exist, and there is a way
to access them even if we don't
see them firsthand on our systems.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.