BRIAN SCASSELLATI: One of the really
great things about computer science
is that, with even only
a few weeks of study,
you're able to understand some of the
software and the intelligent structures
that are all around us
in the modern world.
In this short video series, we're
going to be talking about some
of these different tools
that are out there.
We'll talk about things like how Netflix
is able to suggest movies for you
that you might like, how Facebook
is able to tag photos of you
with your name, how Siri is
able to answer your questions,
or how at Google an autonomous
car is able to drive on the roads.
>> You'll find that each of
these different systems
runs on basic concepts that
map back to the concepts
that we've talked about in class.
So I hope you'll join
me, watch these videos,
and see that the things that
you studied here actually
give you a great amount of leverage on
the structures in the world around you.
I think you'll be surprised
by just how much you know.