DOUG LLOYD: If you watched
our internet primer video,
I left a bit of a cliffhanger
by talking about the internet
and how it's a system of protocols.
Well, let's talk about the
first of those protocols that
actually comprises the internet.
And interestingly enough, it's
called the Internet Protocol,
which we usually refer to as IP.
>> So the internet, as I said, is an
interconnected network, an internet,
which is really just several networks
woven together and agreeing somehow
to communicate with one another.
What is this somehow I'm talking about?
Well, this is the Internet Protocol.
This dictates how information is
transmitted from point A to point B.
And this is sort of a condition of
joining the network of the internet
is agreeing to follow this
protocol when information needs
to be moved from point A to point B.
>> So at the very end of that
internet primer video,
I showed this image of
what the internet was.
And on a small scale, this is
actually probably pretty accurate.
This might be how three networks
actually talk to each other.
But it's a bit misleading.
And the reason it's a bit
misleading is because-- if I
just number the networks for
the sake of convenience here
and we get rid of everything else
and just focus on the networks--
it's a bit misleading because it
implies that all three network have
a connection to one another.
>> One is connected to two.
Two is connected to three.
And three is connected to one.
And when I talk about
a connection here, I'm
talking about a physical,
wired connection.
We do have wireless.
But it's really impractical for
data to be transmitted wirelessly
over a large scale.
And so at some point, we really do rely
on wired technology-- telephone wires,
fiber optic wires, various technologies
that are physically connecting
point A to point B.
>> And on a small scale like
this-- this might be accurate,
but as the image gets a
little bigger, let's now
imagine we have six different networks.
If that's true, now we have
something like this for every network
to be connected to every other network.
And if you look, every network
has five arrows connected to it.
So everything is connected
to every other network.
>> We only have six networks here,
and already look at how much wiring
we have to employ, right?
And the internet consists of
a lot more than six networks.
We can't afford to wire each
network to each other network,
especially considering some of
these networks span oceans, right?
If we're trying to connect to
a network in Asia or in Europe,
we're going to have to
span an entire ocean.
We're going to need to
use wires at some point,
but we want to minimize the
number of wires we actually use.
We don't want to send a
million wires across the ocean,
because they cost millions of
dollars apiece to lie down.
And so rapidly, we wouldn't be able
to afford the internet anymore.
So we have to have another
way for every network
to talk to every other
network or else we
have pieces of the internet
that are disconnected
from other pieces of the internet.
And that's not what we want.
But we don't want to have
them all wired together.
>> And this is where routers
come back into play.
We can use routers in the following way.
What if instead of every
network being physically
connected to every other network, we
had these intermediary pieces, where
the networks were connected
to these intermediaries, which
are connected to a few networks.
So instead of having one connect to
two, three, four, five, six, maybe one
connects to a router,
which maybe connects
to one or two of those
networks, but also
maybe connects to other
routers, which also
will connect to those other networks.
>> And the router's job is--
it contains information
called a routing table
that dictates where do
I go if I see a particular IP address?
If I see an IP address starting
with four, I'm going to go this way.
If I seen IP address starting with
a 12, I'm going to go that way.
We don't need to be connected
physically to network number four
or network number 12 in this example.
We just know generally
where we want to go.
And if you think about it, this is sort
of similar to the concept of recursion
that we talked about when
we were talking about it
in C. I'm not going to connect you
to exactly where you want to go.
I'm just going to move you one step
closer to where you want to go.
And I'll let somebody else deal with
solving the rest of the problem.
I'll just solve this little piece of
the problem and defer the rest of it
to somebody else.
So routing information is actually
kind of similar to recursion.
If that's a concept that you understand
well, maybe that analogy would help.
>> So let's take a look at
this networking example
again and assume that, again,
we're going to use those same six
networks, one through six.
So let's just say that every
IP address on network one
starts with one dot something.
And we'll say that there's
some other thing that
deals with how all the systems
are connected to network one.
We just care about connecting all of
those networks together in an internet.
So every device that is
connected to network one
has an IP address that starts with
one dot and then three other numbers.
>> This is a generalization of
the way things actually work.
It's quite a bit more precise than this.
But this should give you a
general idea of what the Internet
Protocol is actually doing.
So this was the diagram we had before.
This was the system that
was not sustainable.
Even six, this might be OK.
But if we get to 10 or 20 or 50, we're
going to be lying a lot of wires.
And 50 is still also not
even the tip of the iceberg
as to the number of networks we have.
So this model is unsustainable.
We can't stick with this.
>> So let's instead adopt
this model where we get rid
of all the wires between the
networks and we add routers.
So these yellow boxes represent routers.
And their job is to move
information generally
closer to where it's supposed to go.
And maybe these are the connections
that these networks have.
And maybe these are the tables
that are built into the routers.
>> So if we just start by looking
at network one, for example,
basically what it says is if
I ever see an address that
doesn't start with a one-- that's what
the exclamation point one or the bang
one there, not one-- I'm going
to pass it off to a router.
And from there, the router
can make a decision.
The router says if I see a one, I'm
going to move to network number one.
That's the green arrow heading to
the left out of that top left box.
>> If I see a two-- that's
the arrow sort of heading
to the top right towards
the purple network--
if I see an IP address
starting with a two,
I'm going to go towards the two network.
If I see a three, a four, a five, or a
six-- that's that red arrow coming out
of the top left router-- I'm not
connected to three, four, five, or six.
But I know somebody who is or
who's a little bit closer to there.
So I'm just going to say,
every time I see an IP address
starting with three, four,
five, or six, I'm just
going to send it to that router.
So I'll move it a little closer to
where it's supposed to go and let
that router deal with the problem.
>> And as you can see-- if you
wanted to pause here and trace--
you can get to every other point in
the network from wherever you are.
All six networks can still
connect to every other network
but they're not physically
connected anymore.
They're now these intermediate steps.
Now, of course there's a
trade off of speed, right?
If one was directly
connected to six, we wouldn't
have to go through two
routers along the way.
So we may be able to get the
connection a little bit faster.
But maybe that trade-off
is worth it, right?
If it's going to be so expensive
in terms of actual cost, dollars
and cents, to physically wire
all these networks together,
maybe a little bit of a
slowdown in speed is OK.
We can tolerate that.
>> So again, in that example we were just
talking about, none of the networks
directly connect to each other all.
There could have been--
maybe in that example
we could have made it so that
maybe network one and two were
directly connected.
And that would be OK.
Some networks are physically
connected to other networks.
But they're not all
connected to each other.
They rely on the routers--
in this particular example--
to distribute the communication
from point A to point B.
On a small scale-- like what
we're talking about here--
this configuration actually might
be more inefficient than just
having direct connections.
But on a large scale, we can
scale the system a lot better.
It's really going to reduce our
cost of network infrastructure
to have intermediary routers whose job
it is to move traffic from the sender
to the receiver, from point A to point
B, as opposed to wiring everybody
together.
>> So let's take a look at
an example of information
traveling using this Internet Protocol.
Let's say that I am physically
located at IP 1.208.12.37
so I exist somewhere on the one network.
And I want to send a message to you.
And you're on the five
network at 5.188.109.14.
Your IP address specifically doesn't
matter, but in this particular example
we're talking about this generalization
of what the internet protocol is all
about.
You're on the five network,
and I'm on the one network.
As you can see, we're not
connected to each other at all.
>> So I start out.
And I want to send you a message.
And so somehow I communicate
that message to the router.
The router is the one that
actually has the IP address.
And it's looking at where
it's supposed to go.
We're going to five dot something.
So now I'm going to start
using my-- or the router,
rather, is going to start using its
router table to pass information along.
It sees that five is not one, so it
says I'm going to pass it to this guy.
Then this guy has to make a decision.
Where am I going to go?
Well, it's not a one, so I'm not
going to move to the one network.
And it's not a two.
I'm not going to move
to the two network.
It starts with a five.
I'm not connected to
five, this router says.
And so I'm just going to pass it off
to-- I'm going to go down this path.
This is where threes and
fours and fives and sixes go.
And I'll let that guy deal with it.
I'll get it a little closer
to where it's supposed to go.
I know it's supposed to go
in that general direction.
But maybe that guy can deal with it.
OK.
So that guy looks.
He says, OK, this IP
address starts with a five.
Well, I'm connected to three and to
six, so I can't get the message directly
where it needs to go.
But that other router over there, I
know if I send it fours and fives,
it can handle those.
>> So it passes it along down the path.
And then this router says, well, I'm
connected to networks four and five.
So, yes, I can help you.
I'll take your IP address
that starts with a five.
I'll give it to the five network.
The five network will do some work on
its end and give the message to you.
And now we've successfully
transmitted a message from me
to you using the Internet Protocol.
>> Again, very generalized for purposes
of illustration as to what's happening.
But that's pretty much how
the Internet Protocol works.
The routers know
generally where to send it
and will send it one step along the
way, getting it closer and closer
to its destination until one
router is physically connected
to the network or the
address or whatever
in question and gives it there.
>> Now, in general, except for really,
really small, small messages,
it's not going to send it
as one big chunk of data.
If I'm sending you an
email-- a very long email,
say-- it's not going to
take that entire email,
bundle it up in a ball
or a package or whatever,
and send that entire
thing down the network.
>> First of all, sending information
along the network is expensive.
It does add up.
And the larger the
chunk, the more costly
it is to move every step of the way.
And if there's somehow
a slowdown and then
there's this giant-- sort of like
if you're driving on the highway
and there's this giant truck
kind of blocking the way
and you can't get around it on either
lane because it's kind of spread out.
It slows everybody else down behind it.
But small cars, if they
were all small cars,
they might be able to move around,
if that analogy sort of helps
a little bit.
>> So one big block in the system can
really slow everybody else down.
And so what IP is going to do
is split this data into packets.
It's going to take this big email
or FTP transfer or a file transfer,
or maybe I'm making a
request to a web browser
because I want a picture of cat.
And it's going to take that
request or that email or that file
and break it up into many pieces and
send all of the pieces separately.
So in fact, I'm filling the highway
with a lot of small cars, which can all
move instead of a big truck that
might, if something goes wrong,
throttle the traffic for everybody else.
>> Another side effect
of this is if there's
some sort of catastrophic
failure and something goes wrong
and the packet gets dropped.
Something is failed and the
message can't be communicated.
The router maybe had
too much stuff going in.
It couldn't juggle everything.
And so it just literally dropped it.
That's sort of the analogy, right?
>> It's got a lot of things going on.
It's passing information
from point A to point
B. We're not the only two
people on the internet,
so it has to process a lot of traffic.
And if it doesn't have enough hands and
it can't figure out what it's doing,
it might just drop something.
So it can do something else.
It's got too much going on.
>> If we had our message as one huge
block and that was what got dropped,
now we have to send the message again.
And we are now possibly
causing traffic again.
And we run the risk of that
huge block being dropped again.
But if the data's been broken up into
packets and we drop one of those,
it's a lot less costly to send that
packet one more time as opposed
to the entire thing one more time.
So IP is responsible for getting
information from point A to point B
and also breaking the
information into small pieces
so that the network isn't overly taxed.
>> IP is also known as a
connectionless protocol.
There's not necessarily a defined path
from the sender to the receiver or vice
versa.
Now, in this example we've talked
about, there actually is only one way
to get to every network.
So in this particular
illustration, there actually
is a defined path from
point A to point B.
But we can change that by just making
one modification to the two routers
on the left by adding this
condition to the router tables.
>> Now notice that from
the top left router,
there are actually two ways to deal
with a four or a five IP address.
It can go down to the lower left
router, or can go to the right,
to the right router.
It has multiple options.
And this is actually
kind of a good thing
because it makes our
network more responsive.
>> If for example-- it's
sort of like a GPS.
If you've ever been
driving on the highway
and suddenly your GPS warns
you that traffic is ahead,
you want to avoid it if you can.
And so you can recalculate your route.
And a router network, in
addition to having information
about where packets should
go or where data should go,
there's also sort of this general pulse
on the state of its local network.
What's going to happen if I send
it down this path versus this path?
>> And so in light of heavy traffic
situations on the network, maybe
things will get routed a more
inefficient way or a more generally
inefficient way, because
if we go the regular way,
there's going to be a lot of traffic.
The highway is completely jammed.
So maybe what we'll do is
instead take side roads, which
ordinarily would take a
lot more time, but no one's
really using those side roads.
And so we can route
our packets that way.
>> So not every packet
of a big chunk of data
might take the same path from
the beginning to the end.
And our network becomes
a lot more responsive
if our router tables allow for there
to be multiple options for where to go.
We're not depending on that one
truck moving out of the way.
We can get off the highway at the
next exit and take a different path.
And so the Internet Protocol sort
of does a little bit of that, too.
>> So that's the basics of
the Internet Protocol.
But there's one more
issue to deal with, which
is what happens if we do drop a packet?
How do we know we're going
to send that packet again?
Right?
Well, Internet Protocol
doesn't guarantee delivery.
We're going to be depending
on another protocol
to deal with that called
Transmission Control Protocol, TCP.
And we're going to talk
about Transmission Control
Protocol in the next video.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.