>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DOUG LLOYD: So by now we're old
pros at web programming, right?
And we've covered several
languages in individual videos.
And now let's do one more, JavaScript.
>> First the good news, JavaScript
is a modern programming
language much like PHP whose
syntax is derived from C,
so that's a good place to start.
It's about as old as PHP, as well,
having been around about 20 years.
It was invented around
the same time as PHP.
And JavaScript is actually pretty
fundamental to the user experience
of the web.
In fact, there are
three languages that I
would say sort of make up the
user experience of interacting
with the website, html,
css, and JavaScript.
And so now let's talk a
little bit about JavaScript.
>> The bad news, though, with JavaScript is
that it sets a lot of rules for itself,
and then it breaks them.
And JavaScript can actually be
kind of challenging to learn,
because it's unlike C and
PHP, which are very structured
and have very rigid rules
for how things can work.
JavaScript has kind
of gotten so flexible
that maybe things aren't going to
work the way we expect them to,
and maybe we really can't learn
our first programming language
as a JavaScript.
So maybe because it doesn't
set itself any rules,
and it doesn't really
enforce good coding habits.
But now we've hopefully developed
some good coding habits,
and so we can start to foray
into JavaScript a little bit.
>> To write JavaScript, similar to opening
up a C file with a dot C extension
or a PHP file with a dot PHP extension,
all we need to do is open up a file
with the dot js file extension.
We don't need to have any special
delimiters like we did in PHP.
That sort of angle
bracket question mark PHP
that we're used to from that, the way
we tell our browser that what we have is
JavaScript is by including
it in an html tag,
and we'll see a little bit about
how to do that in just a moment.
>> The other thing that makes
JavaScript different,
though, is that it runs client side.
So recall with PHP that
we could never really see
the PHP that underlined a website.
If we ever viewed the
page source, we would only
see the html that was
generated by that PHP.
But JavaScript runs client side.
Your JavaScript runs on your computer.
And that's why you can do
things like add blockers.
Right?
Ad blocking is usually done by
killing all of the JavaScript
that is running on a particular website.
And because it would have to
run on your machine client side,
you can just stop the
JavaScript for running entirely.
That also means that when you use
a website that includes JavaScript,
you have to send the JavaScript source
code as part of your http response
to the client when they request it.
And so you might not
want to use JavaScript
to do really sensitive things
like passing information
about users' passwords back and
forth, because they're actually
going to receive all of the source code,
not just the html that is generated,
such as would be the case with say PHP.
>> So how do we include JavaScript
in our html to start with?
Well, similar to CSS, actually,
is sort of how we do it here.
With CSS we have style tags.
And inside of those style tags,
we can define a CSS style sheet.
Similarly with JavaScript
can we open up script tags,
another html tag we didn't
talk about in our html video,
and write JavaScript in
between those script tags.
Also though, like CSS, we
could link in outside CSS files
and pull them into our program that way.
With CSS we can also,
excuse me, with JavaScript
we can also specify the source
attribute of the script tag
to link in JavaScript
separately, so you don't
have to write it in
between script tags, we
can link it in using
that script tag as well.
And just as with the case with CSS where
we recommended that it was probably
in your best interest to write
your CSS in a separate file in case
you need to change it,
similarly do we recommend
that you write your
JavaScript in separate files
and use the script tags source
attribute to tie your JavaScript
into your html, your web page.
>> So JavaScript variables, we'll
start talking about the syntax here.
And we'll go through
this kind of quickly,
because we've done this in PHP, so
this should all be pretty familiar.
So variables in JavaScript are
very similar to PHP variables.
There's no type specifier, and
when you introduce a variable,
you prefix it with the var keyword.
In PHP we would do something
like this, dollar sign x.
That's how we indicated
a variable, but no, we
don't mention the type
of the variable at all.
We would say something like
dollar sign x equals 44 in PHP.
If we were doing the
same thing in JavaScript,
we would say var x equals 44.
So var is sort of our way
of introducing a variable.
That's perhaps a bit more intuitive
than just dollar sign variable.
>> Again, since there's no
data types, we could do this
with any data type, strings,
anything else would all be var.
Conditionals, all of our
old friends from C and PHP
are still available, so we have if,
else if, else, switch and question
mark colon.
Switch remaining as flexible as it
was in PHP, but all of these you're
familiar with by now.
And similarly with loops are
the old favorites of while,
do while, and for still available to us.
So already we know a lot of the
basic JavaScript sort of fundamentals
just by virtue of having quite a bit
of knowledge now about C and PHP.
>> What about functions in JavaScript?
Well, similar to PHP every function is
introduced with the function keyword.
You say function, and then you
begin to define your function.
What's a little different
about JavaScript,
though is the ability to have
what's called an anonymous function.
So you can define functions
that don't have a name.
This is something we
really haven't seen before.
We'll really use the concept
of an anonymous function
a little later in this
video, because it'll
make a little more sense in context
when we see it in a particular situation
that I've crafted here.
But let's just take a look
at what a simple JavaScript
function might look like.
>> So I've gone ahead and
opened up my CS50 IDE
and I've already run Apache
to begin my server running.
And I have this file
open called Home.html.
And I'll zoom in a little bit here.
And basically, you can see the
Home.html is just a bunch of buttons.
And I'm claiming at the top here
that this is the JavaScript section
materials.
So there's a bunch of buttons here,
but what do these buttons actually do?
>> Well, we'll head over to my IED,
and I have Home.html open here.
At the very beginning,
here's where I'm linking
in all of my JavaScript source files.
Right?
So I have anonymous.js, clock.js,
I'm using the source attribute
of the script tag to link in file.
So I haven't written any
JavaScript directly into this file,
but I've pulled in all the
JavaScript I've written separately.
And if we scroll down here, this
should all look somewhat familiar
with a little bit of new syntax.
We have here header tag for
functions and then a button.
I have an input that's a type button,
and apparently when I click it,
I'm going to call some
function alert date.
And this is how we can sort of mix up
a little bit of JavaScript and html.
They actually play pretty nicely
together, and so apparently when
I click on this button, I'm going
to call some function alert date.
And similarly have I defined behaviors
for all of the other buttons that
are on that home.html page,
which we'll keep returning
to during the course of this video.
But let's go back up
here and take a look
at clock.js, which is the
JavaScript file that I
wrote that has this first function
we're going to take a look at.
As you can see, I begin my JavaScript
function with the keyword function,
and I've given this one a
name, it's called alert date.
Inside of there, I apparently create a
new local variable called current date.
And I'm going to assign
an equal to a new date.
And we could get into a lot of
detail as to what a date is,
and really JavaScript is so
big that we can't possibly
cover everything in one video.
But suffice it to say, this is going
to return to me a data item that
encapsulates the current date and time.
I'm storing that in a variable that I'm
apparently going to alert current date.
>> Well, what does alert
current date look like?
Let's take a look at the file itself
back over in the browser window.
So again, this is the button that I
have tied to, this named function.
And I click it there and
look what it did, it alerted.
It popped up this sort of box telling
me that the current time is, apparently
it's November 4 at
10:43:43 in the morning.
And if I click it again, now
it's a few seconds later, right?
So that's all this function does.
When I click this button, it
pops up an alert message to me.
So there's really not
too much to functions
that's different from PHP,
just a little bit of new syntax
that comes with working with JavaScript.
>> Arrays in JavaScript are
pretty straightforward.
To declare an array, you use
the square brackets syntax
that we're familiar with from PHP.
And similar to PHP, we
also can mix data types.
So this array, both
of these arrays would
be perfectly legitimate JavaScript.
One that's all integers, and one that
is mixed up different data types.
>> What's something very different
in JavaScript, though?
That's the notion of an object.
So perhaps you've heard of
object oriented programming.
We don't do a lot of it in CS50,
but we will do a little bit of it
here in the context of JavaScript.
Now JavaScript has the ability to
behave as an object oriented programming
language, but it is not itself
exclusively an object oriented
programming language.
And this again comes
back to why I said, it
can be very challenging to learn
JavaScript as your first programming
language, because it doesn't
really fit a particular paradigm.
>> C on the other hand is a
functional programming language.
If we want to, functions are
sort of the big boss man, right?
They dictate what
happens everything else.
We want to change variables,
we call functions.
We do things to functions.
Objects instead, in an
object oriented language,
objects sort of become the star and
functions become sort of secondary.
But what is an object, what
is this notion of an object?
Well, if it helps, think
about it at first sort
of like a C structure or a struct
that we've learned about before.
In C, a structure contains
a number of fields,
and maybe we now might start to
call these fields properties.
But the properties never really
stand on their own, right?
If I define a structure for a car
like this with the following two
fields or properties, one an
integer for the year of the car
and another a 10 character
string for the model of the car,
I can say something like this,
I can declare a new variable
of type struct car herbie.
And then I can say something
like herbie.year equals 1,963,
and herbie.model equals Beetle.
That's OK.
I'm using the fields in the
context of the structure,
but I could never just
say something like this.
Right?
I can't use the field name
independent of the structure.
It's sort of a fundamental thing.
>> So fields being
fundamental to C structures
are very similar to properties being
fundamental to JavaScript objects.
But what makes them
particularly interesting
is that objects can also have what
are called methods, which are really
just a fancy word for functions that
are inherent to the object as well.
So it's a function that can only be
called in the context of an object.
Only an object that has defined
this function inside of its,
if you think about a
struct, the function
is defined inside those defining
curly braces of the structure.
So it only means something
to the structure.
And that's sort of what we're doing
here with objects and methods.
It's basically like we're
defining a function that
only makes sense on a
particular object, and so we
call that a method of the object.
And we can never call that
function independent of the object,
just like we can't say year or model
independent of the struct in C.
>> So functional programming
paradigms look something like this.
Function and then when you pass
in the object as a parameter.
In an object oriented programming
languages, this sort of gets
flipped, and we would think about
it like this, object.function.
So it sort of that dot
operator again implying
that it's some sort of property
or attribute of the object itself.
But this is what an object
oriented programming language
might do to make a function
call on a method, again, which
is just a special word for a function
that is inherent to an object.
This is what that
syntax might look like.
And so we'll start to see some of
this in the context of JavaScript.
>> You can also think about an object
sort of like an associative array,
which we're familiar with from PHP.
Remember an associative array allows
us to have key value pairs, instead
of having indexes 0, one, two, three,
and so on like we're used to from C
arrays.
Associative arrays can map
words, such as in the PHP video,
we were talking about
toppings of pizzas.
And so we had an array
called pizzas, and we
had cheese was a key and $8.99 was the
value, and then pepperoni was a key,
$9.99 was a value, and so on.
And so we can also think about an
object sort of similar to an associative
array.
And so this syntax here
would create a new object
called herbie with two
properties inside of it.
Year, which is assigned the value 1963,
and model, which is assigned the string
Beetle.
>> And notice here that I'm using
single quotes in JavaScript.
You can use single or double quotes
when you're talking about strings.
It's just conventionally
the case that most times
when you're writing JavaScript,
you just use single quotes.
But I could use double quotes here, and
that would be perfectly fine as well.
>> So remember how in
PHP we had this notion
of a for each loop that would allow us
to iterate over all of the key value
pairs of an associative
array, because we
didn't have this ability to iterate
through 0, one, two, three, four,
and so on?
JavaScript has something very similar,
but it's not called a for each loop,
it's called a for in loops.
So if I said to me like
this, for var key in object,
that's sort of similar to saying
for each something as something.
But all I'm doing here is iterating
through all of the keys of my object.
And inside of the curly
braces there, I would
use object square brackets key to refer
to the value at that key location.
>> Alternatively, there's
even another approach.
If I just only care about the
values, I can say for key of object,
and just use key inside.
So for var key in object, I have
to use object square brackets
key inside the loop.
For var key of object, I can
just use key inside the loop,
because I'm just specifically
talking about the values there.
>> So let's maybe take a
look at the difference
just to quickly show you
the difference between four
in and for of with a very specific
array, which we have here, week array.
So I have to find a new array
that I filled with seven strings,
Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday,
Thursday, Friday, Saturday, Sunday.
And I want to now iterate
through this array,
printing out certain information.
If I use a for in loop
to print out information,
what do you think I'm going to get?
Well, let's take a look.
And before we jump over
to my browser window,
just know that
console.log is sort of one
way of doing a print F in JavaScript.
But what is the console?
Well, that's what we're going
to go take a look at right now.
>> OK, so we're back here
in my browser window,
and I'm going to open
up my developer tools.
Again, I'm just hitting F12
to open up developer tools.
And notice that here at the
top I've chosen console.
So this is the notion
of a developer console,
and it will allow us to
print information out,
sort of like the terminal, but
as you'll see a little later,
we can also type information in
to interact with our web page.
I'm going to zoom in a little bit here,
and I'm gonna now click on for in test.
And four in test-- I'm not gonna
show you the code for it right now,
but you'll get it if you
download the source code that
is associated with this video--
is just that for in loop
that we saw just a
second ago on the slide.
>> So I'm gonna click that
button, and over here,
here's what has printed out in the
console, 0,one, two, three, four, five,
six.
I didn't print out the information
inside those array locations,
because I used a for in loop.
And inside the body of the loop, I
just printed out key not object key.
But if I now clear my console, and I
switch to for of test, and four of test
I say I use for of loop
instead and print out key,
if I click that, now I'm getting the
actual elements inside of my object
or my array in this case.
My array of week days.
I printed out Monday,
Tuesday, Wednesday.
So that's the difference between
a for in loop, which prints out
just the keys if you just use key
inside of the body of the loop,
and a for of loop, which prints
out the values if you use just
key inside the body of the loop.
>> All right, how do we now start to
concatenate strings and maybe mix up
some variables with interpolation
like we were able to do in PHP?
Well, we're pretty familiar
with this from PHP.
This is how we would do it using the
dot operator to concatenate strings.
In JavaScript, though,
we actually use something
called the plus operator, which
is maybe even a little bit more
intuitive, right?
We're adding a bunch
of strings together.
So let's head back
over and see what this
will print if we're trying to print out
all of the information in week array.
All right, so under here
under string concatenation,
I have two options, string building
V1 and then string building V2.
And we'll see why we
need V2 in a second.
But I'm gonna click on
string building V1, which
is the code we were
just taking a look at,
the console.log with all of the pluses.
Let's see if this prints
out what we expect.
>> Monday is day number 01 of the week,
Tuesday is day number 11 of the week.
Well, what I was trying
to do there was get
it to print out Monday is day number
one, Tuesday is day number two.
But it seems like I'm
always printing out one.
Well, why is that?
Well, it turns out, take another look
at this little snippet of code here.
Notice that we're using the plus
operator in two different contexts.
>> And so here's where maybe things
that we've kind of been saying,
oh, it's so great.
We don't deal with data types anymore.
But here's where the fact
that we lose data types
can actually be a bit
of a problem for us.
Now that the plus operator is used to
concatenate strings and add numbers
together, JavaScript has
to make its best guess
as to what I want it to do for me.
And in this case, it guessed wrong.
It just concatenated day, which would be
0, one, two, three, four, five, or six,
and then it just concatenated
that and then concatenated one.
It didn't actually add them together.
And so these languages,
PHP and JavaScript,
that abstracts away
this notion of types,
you don't have to deal with it anymore.
They do still have types under the hood.
And we can, in situations
like this, leverage that fact
by saying something
like maybe this, which
is telling JavaScript, by the
way, treat this as an integer,
don't treat it as a string, even
though we're mixing together strings
and integers here.
>> It's just one of those things
that it seems so great in context
that we don't have to
deal with types anymore,
but sometimes you'll
run into a situation
exactly like this where the fact that
you don't have control over types
can backfire on you
if you're not careful.
And so if we pop back over to IDE, I'm
going to clear out my console again,
and I'm going to click string
building version two, which
is where I use that parse int function.
Now it's printing out
information that I'm expecting.
Monday's day number one, Tuesday
is day number two, and so on.
>> So let's talk about functions again.
I promised we would talk about anonymous
functions, and now the context for that
has finally arrived.
So before we do so, let's talk again
about arrays for just a second.
So arrays are a special
case of an object.
In fact, everything in
JavaScript is actually an object.
So functions are a
special case of an object,
integers are a special
case of an object,
but arrays specifically
have a number of methods.
Remember because they're objects,
they can have properties and methods.
They have a number of methods that
can be applied to those objects.
There's a method called
size, array.size,
which will return to
you as you might expect
the number of elements in your array.
array.pop, sort of like
our notion of popping off
of a stack, if you recall
from our stacks video,
removes the last element from the array.
array.push adds a new element
to the end of an array.
array.shift is sort of
like DQ, it splices out
the very first element of an array.
>> But there's also another special
method of an array called map.
And this is sort of an
interesting concept.
So what is the idea of a map?
You'll actually see this
in several other languages,
and we're not talking about a
sort of cartographers map here,
we're talking about a mapping function.
In the context we're
talking about here, a map
is a special operation we
can perform on an array
to apply a particular function
to every element of that array.
and so we would say in
this case, maybe array.map,
and inside of it, we're passing
into map is a function that we want
to be applied to every single element.
So it's sort of analogous to using
a loop to iterate over every element
and apply a particular
function to every element,
just JavaScript has this built in
notion of a mapping that can be applied.
And this is a great context to
talk about an anonymous function.
>> So let's say we have
this array of integers.
It's called nums, and it's got five
things in it, one, two, three, four,
five.
Now I want to map some
function on to this array.
I want to have a function apply
to every element of the array.
Well, let's say that what I want to
do is just double all of the elements.
What I could do is just use a loop
for var I equals 0, I is less than
or equal to 4, I plus, plus, and
then double every single number.
But I can also do something like this.
I can say nums was formerly
one, two, three, four, five,
now, though, I would like you to
apply a mapping onto this array
where I would like you
to double every number.
And that's exactly
what's happening here.
But notice what I'm passing
in as the argument to map.
This is an anonymous function.
And notice I haven't given
this function a name,
I've only given it a parameter list.
And so this is an example
of an anonymous function.
>> We generally would never call this
function outside of the context of map.
We're defining it as a parameter
to map, and so we don't really
need to have a name for it if the
only thing that cares about is map
and it's defined right
there inside of map.
And so this is an anonymous function.
We have not been able
to do this previously.
Map some function that
accepts one parameter, num,
and what that function does
is returns num times 2.
And so after this
mapping has been applied,
this is now what nums looks
like, two, four, six, eight, 10.
And we'll pop over to my
browser window and just
take a look at this
really quickly as well.
>> So I have another button here
in my home page called double.
And when I click double, and it tells
me before it was one, two, three, four,
five after two, four, six, eight, 10.
And if I go back and click double
again, two, four, six, eight, 10.
And then after, four,
eight, 12, 16, and then 20.
And what am I doing in this function?
Well, if we just pop over to IDE, and
I pull up my anonymous function, here
on line seven through 13, I'm
doing a little bit fancy work here,
but I'm just printing out
what's currently in the array.
Then on line 16, 17,
and 18, there's my map.
This is where I'm applying this doubling
function to every single element.
And then a little further down,
I'm just doing the same thing
I was doing before, except now I'm
printing out the contents of the array
afterwards.
But all I've done here is
just use an anonymous function
to map across an entire array.
>> So one more big topic to talk about in
JavaScript is the notion of an event.
An event is something that just happens
when a user interacts with your web
page, so maybe they click something,
or maybe the page is finished loading,
or maybe they've moved
their mouse over something,
or they've typed something
in an input field.
All of these things are events
that are occurring on our web page.
And JavaScript has the
capability to support something
called an event handler, which
is a callback function that
responds to an html event.
And what's a callback function?
Well, it's generally just another
name for an anonymous function.
It's a function that
responds to an event.
And this is where we come to the
idea of binding certain functions
to a particular html attribute.
Most html elements have
support for an attribute
that we didn't talk about in the html
video for something like on click
or on hover or on load,
all of these events
that you can then write functions
that deal with those events
when those events
occur on your web page.
>> And so maybe your html
looks something like this.
And I have two buttons here,
button one and button two,
and here I have currently
defined nothing,
but this is where the attribute on
click is apparently part of my html tag.
So apparently when I define what's
going on inside of that attribute,
it's going to be some JavaScript
function that responds to the event
presumably of clicking on
button one or button two.
>> What's kind of cool about this is we
can write a generic event handler.
And this event Handler will
create an event object.
And the event object will tell us
which of the two buttons was clicked.
Now how does that work?
Well, it might look something like this.
So we will first define our buttons
to have a response to the callback
function that will be called
when the button is clicked,
we'll call event alert name.
And notice in both cases we're
passing in this event parameter.
So we call this function
or when this function
is triggered by the event happening,
it's going to create this event object
and pass it as a
parameter to alert name.
And that event object is
going to contain information
about which button was clicked.
And how does it do that?
Well, it might look something like this.
So now in my separate
JavaScript file, I might
have to find this
function alert name, which
again accepts that event parameter.
And then here is where I'm detecting
which button was triggered,
var trigger equals event
dot source element.
What was the source that created
this event object that was passed in?
Was it button one or was it button two?
>> And then here all I'm doing is
printing out trigger.innerhtml.
Well, in this case, in this
context, trigger.innerhtml
is just what is written on the button.
It just so happens if we jump
back for a second, that would
be what's in between those button tags.
It will be button one or button two.
And let's take a look at
how this event handler would
look if we had it running in practice.
>> So first of all, you've
opened up events.js,
which is the JavaScript file where
I have defined this function.
And as you can see, it's
pretty much exactly what
we just saw on the slide a second ago.
And I will go over to the
home page we've been using.
And I have here button
one and button two.
And I'll click on button one.
You clicked on button one, if you
can see right here in the alert.
OK.
Click on button two, you
clicked on a button two.
>> So both buttons have the
same function call, right?
They both were alert name
event, but this event object
that gets created when we click on
it tells us which button was clicked.
We didn't have to write two separate
functions or deal with having
to pass any additional information.
We're just relying on
what JavaScript will
do for us, which is to create that
sort of event object on our behalf.
There's a lot more to JavaScript than
what we've covered in this video,
but having these
fundamental should get you
quite a long ways to
learning everything you'll
need to know about this
interesting language.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.