DOUG LLOYD: Sometimes
when we're programming
we do things so commonly, so
frequently, and so many people
do the same idea-- or the same
thing, that it has a name.
MVC is exactly one such thing.
It's called a programming paradigm.
It's sort of like a best practices
that have been distilled down
by people trying to do something.
In this case, implement
a system of pages
that a user interacts with
on a more complex website.
And it's done so commonly that
it's recommended as a standard
that other people might like to follow,
and there's a very specific set of ways
that one could follow this paradigm.
>> So, MVC is a paradigm, and the reason
we use it is to abstract away details
from the user.
Some things the user
doesn't really need to see.
They just want to have
a good user experience,
and we don't need to have them
access every single file that
exists on our web server, perhaps.
There might be some files that are just
used to bolster the user experience,
and so we can abstract those away.
We can sort of hide them so
the user can't work with them,
but our pages-- our pages--
know how to deal with them
and call them or perhaps require,
wants them, or something like that.
>> The primary motivation
for MVC is data security,
because MVC usually comes up in the
context of working with databases.
And in particular we
want to prevent users
from directly impacting databases.
We only want to do it indirectly,
through our filtration.
Or making sure that everything's OK by
us doing a little bit of error checking
or safety proofing before we
send it to the database, where
things could go wrong, perhaps
really wrong, if we're not careful.
>> So MVC stands for Model View Controller.
What do each of these mean?
Basically, model is your database.
It's where all the
important data for your site
lives-- usernames, logins, passwords.
And you can update it, refer to it,
pretty much everything like that.
You'd query a database, you'd ask
information from the database.
That's the model-- all of the
data where your site lives.
>> The view is kind of like
the user experience.
It's the pages they see after
they have requested information.
So maybe they submit
their login information--
which they would do in a controller,
which we'll talk about in a second.
They maybe submit their
login information,
and the database is queried.
Information is requested and
pulled from the database.
And then once the user's logged
in, they see their home page.
That's a view, OK?
>> And then the controller is what's
called the business logic of your site.
And business logic is
one of those terms that
is sort of wishy-washy-- like,
what does business logic mean?
Basically your business
logic is your PHP.
Your user doesn't need
to directly see your PHP,
but your PHP is probably what's going
to be making requests to the database.
>> So the user will input
information in a view,
which will integrate a controller.
Like, they'll type into a form.
How that form processes
information is the controller.
That's the PHP that's actually
making the request to the model.
And then the model gives
information to the view,
which gives it to the user,
perhaps best visualized as follows.
>> So here we are.
Here's us on the left, and our Model
View Controller paradigm arrangement.
How does it work?
>> The user-- us-- makes a
request to the controller.
We submit information
such as by an HTTP form.
Based on that, the controller's
job is to make sure
that what the user has given is not
something that would damage the model.
And so the controller's going to
make sure that everything's OK.
It's going to look very carefully.
If there's any errors, it'll stop things
so the user can't get to the model.
>> But assuming everything's
OK and it's a valid query,
the controller will query the model--
it'll ask it to provide information.
The model will provide that
information to a page that's a view,
it'll transmit it that
way, and then the view
will populate the information
requested from the model.
>> So, for example, if we're talking
about logging into your Facebook page,
for example.
The view would be the data
that came out of the model that
refers to your friends and the news
feed or stuff like that, right?
But you wouldn't see somebody else's.
>> You'd be getting-- so
you submit a query,
you login to the model-- excuse
me, you login to the page.
The controller uses
your login information
to make a request to the model to make
sure that you are who you say you are.
The model's like, OK, yes,
you are who you say you are,
so let me give you your news feed.
I'll give you the raw data for
your news feed to the view,
and then the view makes it
pretty, processes it in a way
that we're used to, displaying
that information to the user.
>> Notice the connection that's
not existing on this diagram.
There's no direct connection
between you and the model.
There's always this buffer of
the controller on the input side,
and there's a buffer of the
view on the output side.
>> Maybe you're a good
person, and so maybe you
wouldn't do any damage to the
model, but maybe you're not.
Or maybe there's somebody who's
a malicious user who would maybe
want to damage your database, maybe
delete everything from your database,
which could be very expensive.
Obviously, having user data is--
there's value to having user data.
And so if we didn't put this buffer
zone between the user and the database--
the user and the model-- things
might not be going so well for us.
>> And so it's important to
have this paradigm where
the user can interact with the database,
sure, but they have to go through us
to do it.
And that's basically the idea with MVC.
It's trying to implement data security.
It's trying to protect the model
from inadvertently or intentionally
malicious users.
>> So what happens when
we apply this paradigm?
Well, we're separating the data
required from our website--
the model-- from the logic
that implements our website's
functionality-- the controller-- and
from the simple aesthetics and page
templates that comprise our
user experience-- the view.
What does this mean?
Well, it means you can make
views visible to the user.
You can hide the model away.
And controllers-- the user
can't maybe directly manipulate.
They don't need to access your PHP code.
They just need to see a form
where they can type stuff in.
So maybe the form is
a view, the controller
is the PHP that the form submits to, the
controller makes a query to the model,
the model gives more information
to a different view that
displays information to you.
>> Your programs can access
all of your business logic,
but your users cannot directly
access your business logic.
And one particularly, perhaps,
visible illustration of this
is you've ever received
a 403 Forbidden error.
Have you ever gone to a web
page and seen 403 Forbidden?
It's sort of like 404 Not Found.
>> 403 Forbidden means you tried to access
a page that you don't have access to.
Perhaps that site is
using MVC separation
to hide away its business logic that
needs to exist on the server in order
for the page to work, but doesn't
want you to directly access it.
So you might get a 403 Forbidden error.
>> And it wouldn't even matter
if you were logged in.
No user can touch this dot PHP file.
They can only touch
this one, and this one--
the one that they can touch-- perhaps
can interact with the locked-down file
more indirectly than the user.
>> So, we sometimes see this permissions
error, this 403 Forbidden.
How do we change permissions so
that things can or cannot be seen?
When we do this typically is to use a
Linux command called chmod-- C-H-mod.
>> To do this, the format is pretty
simple-- chmod, permissions,
and whatever file you want
to apply that change to.
So, maybe you'd see something
like this-- chmod 600 helpers.php.
Or maybe you'd see this-- chmod
a plus x that includes directory.
Was does this mean though?
So, there's two different ways
that permissions are usually
applied using chmod.
The first is called the
octal numbers method.
This usually applies permissions
to three different categories
of users at the same time.
So chmod 711 file would allow you
the right to read, write, and execute
your file, would allow
others-- specifically
your group and the world--
to only execute the file.
That's what this translates to.
The first number there
is what you can do,
the second number is
what your group can do,
and the third is what the world can do.
Anybody who's visiting your
page, that's the world.
>> What are these numbers
actually translate to though?
So these basically translate like this.
If the permission is
zero, nothing can happen.
If it's one, you can execute the
file-- if that's your permission.
If it's two, you can write the file
but you can't do anything else.
If it's three, you
can write and execute.
And so on, as you can see.
And seven means you can do everything.
>> So why are these called octal numbers?
Well, if you think about it,
here's like noes and yeses,
and if we think about them
as red and green boxes,
maybe that makes it a little clearer.
But if we think about those red boxes
as zeros and the green boxes as ones,
these are actually just sets
of binary numbers, right?
000 translates to decimal 0; 001,
decimal 1; 010 is decimal 2, and so on.
And so we call these octal
numbers because there
are eight different possibilities.
There are eight
different digits if we're
talking about three
bits of information--
the read bit, the write
bit, and the execute bit.
So now you can speak binary,
decimal, hex, and octal.
So you know how to communicate with
computers in four different number
systems, so that's pretty cool.
>> So, besides the octal
permission scheme, there's
also the symbolic permission
scheme, which is slightly different
and usually is used best to apply or
remove a permission across the board.
So chmod a plus x file
might add the right
to execute to all three
categories of users--
yourself, your group, and the world.
That plus is the adding part.
The right to execute, that's the x.
And the fact that it applies to all
three groups of users would be the a.
>> So this-- a plus x-- is probably going
to be exactly the same as chmod 711
file, because if you go back and
look at the octal number scheme,
ones and sevens give us the
right to execute a file.
So this is probably the same.
>> And you can use this
reference guide for what
the various things in the
symbolic chmod-ing structure are.
The green items here would be
where all the green colored example
was a second ago.
The blue would be the blue.
The orange would be the orange.
So you can apply things to your
group, to others, to the user,
or to everybody.
You can give them read,
write, and execute access,
and you can add or remove
or assign exactly a set
of permissions using this model.
>> How do we check what a
file permission scheme is?
Before we change it, it's
probably good to actually know
what the file permissions are.
One way to do this is to run ls
but just tweak it a little bit.
So if I type ls dash l--
that's a lowercase l-- maybe
I'll see something like this.
It looks a little bit cryptic, but
the part that we really care about
is the stuff on the left over there.
That actually specifies
a file permission scheme.
And you can probably tell because it's
got r's, w's, and x's interspersed.
>> Those first three--
ignoring the first one
for a second, which
we'll double back to.
Those first three after
the first-- so the second,
third, and fourth characters
of that 10 character string
are the permissions that you have.
So apparently I can read,
write, and execute PHP.
I can read, write, and
execute PHP WebDev,
and I can read and write test.php.
>> My group can do this.
So apparently with the PHP
and PHP WebDev directories,
my group can write to
them but nothing else.
And the world can't do anything.
So these files are not
publicly accessible
and if I tried to
access them and I wasn't
running Apache to make them accessible,
then I would get a 403 error.
It's a failure.
I tried to access a file but I
don't have permissions to do it.
And what is that first character?
Well, you can probably extrapolate
here that the d's refer to directories
and the dash refers to
so-called "regular files."
And maybe you've seen this when you've
tried to remove a file using rm.
You've seen the cryptic message
"remove regular file"-- in this case,
it'd be test.php.
Regular file is just something
that's not a directory.
There are a couple of others
here, but generally you're
going to see d's for directories
and nothing for the first element.
But that's really all there is to it.
You can check file
permissions using ls dash l,
you can change them using chmod.
And, of course, use these--
changing the permissions
to enforce this MVC paradigm to
protect the data on your website
and not allow users
to access everything,
but only the stuff that they need
to access in order for your page
to work the way you want it to work.
>> I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.