>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DOUG LLOYD: You probably think that
code is just used to accomplish a task.
You write it out.
It does something.
That's pretty much it.
>> You compile it.
You run the program.
You're good to go.
>> But believe it or not, if
you code for a long time,
you actually might come to see
code as something that's beautiful.
It solves a problem in
a very interesting way,
or there's just something really
neat about the way it looks.
You might be laughing
at me, but it's true.
And recursion is one way
to sort of get this idea
of beautiful, elegant-looking code.
It solves problems in ways that
are interesting, easy to visualize,
and surprisingly short.
>> The way recursion works
is, a recursive function
is defined as a function that calls
itself as part of its execution.
That might seem a little strange,
and we'll see a little bit
about how this works in a moment.
But again, these
recursive procedures are
going to be so elegant
because they're going
to solve this problem without
having all these other functions
or these long loops.
You'll see that these recursive
procedures are going to look so short.
And they really are going to make
your code look a lot more beautiful.
>> I'll give you an example
of this to see how
a recursive procedure might be defined.
So if you're familiar with this
from math class many years ago,
there's something called the
factorial function, which is usually
denoted as an exclamation point, which
is defined over all positive integers.
And the way that n
factorial is calculated
is you multiply all of
the numbers less than
or equal to n together--
all the integers less than
or equal to n together.
>> So 5 factorial is 5 times
4 times 3 times 2 times 1.
And 4 factorial is 4 times
3 times 2 times 1 and so on.
You get the idea.
>> As programmers, we don't
use n, exclamation point.
So we'll define the factorial
function as fact of n.
And we'll use factorial to create
a recursive solution to a problem.
And I think you might find
that it's a lot more visually
appealing than the iterative
version of this, which
we'll also take a look at in a moment.
>> So here are a couple of
facts-- pun intended--
about factorial-- the
factorial function.
The factorial of 1, as I said, is 1.
The factorial of 2 is 2 times 1.
The factorial of 3 is 3
times 2 times 1, and so on.
We talked about 4 and 5 already.
>> But looking at this, isn't this true?
Isn't factorial of 2 just
2 times the factorial of 1?
I mean, the factorial of 1 is 1.
So why can't we just say that,
since factorial of 2 is 2 times 1,
it's really just 2 times
the factorial of 1?
>> And then extending that idea,
isn't the factorial of 3
just 3 times the factorial of 2?
And the factorial of 4 is 4 times
the factorial of 3, and so on?
In fact, the factorial
of any number can just
be expressed if we kind
of carry this out forever.
We can kind of generalize
the factorial problem
as it's n times the
factorial of n minus 1.
It's n times the product of
all the numbers less than me.
>> This idea, this
generalization of the problem,
allows us to recursively
define the factorial function.
When you define a function
recursively, there's
two things that need to be a part of it.
You need to have something called a
base case, which, when you trigger it,
will stop the recursive process.
>> Otherwise, a function that calls
itself-- as you might imagine--
could go on forever.
Function calls the function
calls the function calls
the function calls the function.
If you don't have a way
to stop it, your program
will be effectively stuck
at an infinite loop.
It will crash eventually,
because it'll run out of memory.
But that's beside the point.
>> We need to have some other way to stop
things besides our program crashing,
because a program that crashes is
probably not beautiful or elegant.
And so we call this the base case.
This is a simple solution
to a problem which stops
the recursive process from occurring.
So that's one part of
a recursive function.
>> The second part is the recursive case.
And this is where the recursion
will actually take place.
This is where the
function will call itself.
>> It won't call itself in exactly
the same way it was called.
It'll be a slight variation
that makes the problem it's
trying to solve a teeny bit smaller.
But it generally passes the buck
of solving the bulk of the solution
to a different call down the line.
>> Which of these looks
like the base case here?
Which one of these looks like the
simplest solution to a problem?
We have a bunch of factorials,
and we could continue
going on-- 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, and so on.
>> But one of these looks like a
good case to be the base case.
It's a very simple solution.
We don't have to do anything special.
>> The factorial of 1 is just 1.
We don't have to do any
multiplication at all.
It seems like if we're going
to try and solve this problem,
and we need to stop the
recursion somewhere,
we probably want to stop
it when we get to 1.
We don't want to stop before that.
>> So if we're defining
our factorial function,
here's a skeleton for
how we might do that.
We need to plug in those two things--
the base case and the recursive case.
What's the base case?
If n is equal to 1, return 1-- that's
a really simple problem to solve.
>> The factorial of 1 is 1.
It's not 1 times anything.
It's just 1.
It's a very easy fact.
And so that can be our base case.
If we get passed 1 into this
function, we'll just return 1.
>> What's the recursive
case probably look like?
For every other number
besides 1, what's the pattern?
Well, if we're taking
the factorial of n,
it's n times the factorial of n minus 1.
>> If we're taking the factorial of 3,
it's 3 times the factorial of 3 minus 1,
or 2.
And so if we're not
looking at 1, otherwise
return n times the
factorial of n minus 1.
It's pretty straightforward.
>> And for the sake of having slightly
cleaner and more elegant code,
know that if we have single-line loops
or single-line conditional branches,
we can get rid of all of the
curly braces around them.
So we can consolidate this to this.
This has exactly the same
functionality as this.
>> I'm just taking away the curly
braces, because there's only one line
inside of those conditional branches.
So these behave identically.
If n is equal to 1, return 1.
Otherwise return n times
the factorial of n minus 1.
So we're making the problem smaller.
If n starts out as 5, we're going to
return 5 times the factorial of 4.
And we'll see in a minute when we talk
about the call stack-- in another video
where we talk about the
call stack-- we'll learn
about why exactly this process works.
>> But while factorial of 5 says
return 5 times factorial of 4, and 4
is going to say, OK, well, return
4 times the factorial of 3.
And as you can see, we're
sort of approaching 1.
We're getting closer and
closer to that base case.
>> And once we hit the base case,
all of the previous functions
have the answer they were looking for.
Factorial of 2 was saying return
2 times the factorial of 1.
Well, factorial of 1 returns 1.
So the call for factorial
of 2 can return 2 times 1,
and give that back to factorial of
3, which is waiting for that result.
>> And then it can calculate
its result, 3 times 2 is 6,
and give it back to factorial of 4.
And again, we have a
video on the call stack
where this is illustrated a little
more than what I'm saying right now.
But this is it.
This alone is the solution to
calculating the factorial of a number.
>> It's only four lines of code.
That's pretty cool, right?
It's kind of sexy.
>> So in general, but not
always, a recursive function
can replace a loop in a
non-recursive function.
So here, side by side, is the iterative
version of the factorial function.
Both of these calculate
exactly the same thing.
>> They both calculate the factorial of n.
The version on the left
uses recursion to do it.
The version on the right
uses iteration to do it.
>> And notice, we have to declare
a variable an integer product.
And then we loop.
So long as n is greater than 0, we
keep multiplying that product by n
and decrementing n until
we calculate the product.
So these two functions, again,
do exactly the same thing.
But they don't do it in
exactly the same way.
>> Now, it is possible to
have more than one base
case or more than one
recursive case, depending
on what your function is trying to do.
You aren't necessarily just limited to
a single base case or a single recursive
case.
So an example of something
with multiple base cases
might be this-- the
Fibonacci number sequence.
>> You may recall from
elementary school days
that the Fibonacci sequence is defined
like this-- the first element is 0.
The second element is 1.
Both of those are just by definition.
>> Then every other element is defined
as the sum of n minus 1 and n minus 2.
So the third element
would be 0 plus 1 is 1.
And then the fourth element
would be the second element, 1,
plus the third element, 1.
And that would be 2.
And so on and so on.
>> So in this case, we have two base cases.
If n is equal to 1, return 0.
If n is equal to 2, return 1.
Otherwise, return Fibonacci of n
minus 1 plus Fibonacci of n minus 2.
>> So that's multiple base cases.
What about multiple recursive cases?
Well, there's something
called the Collatz conjecture.
I'm not going to say,
you know what that is,
because it's actually our final
problem for this particular video.
And it's our exercise
to work on together.
>> So here's what the
Collatz conjecture is--
it applies to every positive integer.
And it speculates that it's
always possible to get back
to 1 if you follow these steps.
If n is 1, stop.
We've got back to 1 if n is 1.
>> Otherwise, go through this
process again on n divided by 2.
And see if you can get back to 1.
Otherwise, if n is odd, go through
this process again on 3n plus 1,
or 3 times n plus 1.
So here we have a single base case.
If n is equal to 1, stop.
We're not doing any more recursion.
>> But we have two recursive cases.
If n is even, we do one recursive
case, calling n divided by 2.
If n is odd, we do a different
recursive case on 3 times n plus 1.
>> And so the goal for this video is
to take a second, pause the video,
and try and write this
recursive function Collatz
where you pass in a value n, and
it calculates how many steps it
takes to get to 1 if you start from n
and you follow those steps up above.
If n is 1, it takes 0 steps.
Otherwise, it's going to
take one step plus however
many steps it takes on either n
divided by 2 if n is even, or 3n plus 1
if n is odd.
>> Now, I've put up on the screen here
a couple of test things for you,
a couple of tests cases for you, to see
what these various Collatz numbers are,
and also an illustration
of the steps that
need to be gone through so you can
sort of see this process in action.
So if n is equal to
1, Collatz of n is 0.
You don't have to do
anything to get back to 1.
You're already there.
>> If n is 2, it takes
one step to get to 1.
You start with 2.
Well, 2 is not equal to 1.
So it's going to be one step
plus however many steps it
takes on n divided by 2.
>> 2 divided by 2 is 1.
So it takes one step plus however
many steps it takes for 1.
1 takes zero steps.
>> For 3, as you can see, there's
quite a few steps involved.
You go from 3.
And then you go to
10, 5, 16, 8, 4, 2, 1.
It takes seven steps to get back to 1.
And as you can see, there's a
couple other test cases here
to test out your program.
So again, pause the video.
And I'll go jump back now to
what the actual process is here,
what this conjecture is.
>> See if you can figure out
how to define Collatz of n
so that it calculates how many
steps it takes to get to 1.
So hopefully, you have paused the video
and you aren't just waiting for me
to give you the answer here.
But if you are, well,
here's the answer anyway.
>> So here's a possible definition
of the Collatz function.
Our base case-- if n is
equal to 1, we return 0.
It doesn't take any
steps to get back to 1.
>> Otherwise, we have two recursive cases--
one for even numbers and one for odd.
The way I test for even numbers
is to check if n mod 2 equals 0.
This is basically, again,
asking the question,
if you recall what mod is-- if I
divide n by 2 is there no remainder?
That would be an even number.
>> And so if n mod 2 equals 0 is
testing is this an even number.
If so, I want to return 1,
because this is definitely
taking one step plus Collatz of
whatever number is half of me.
Otherwise, I want to return 1
plus Collatz of 3 times n plus 1.
That was the other
recursive step that we
could take to calculate the
Collatz-- the number of steps
it takes to get back
to 1 given a number.
So hopefully, this example
gave you a little bit
of a taste of recursive procedures.
Hopefully, you think code is a
little more beautiful if implemented
in an elegant, recursive way.
But even if not, recursion is a
really powerful tool nonetheless.
And so it's definitely something
to get your head around,
because you'll be able to create
pretty cool programs using recursion
that might otherwise be complex to write
if you're using loops and iteration.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.