>> SAM LEVATICH: Welcome to
section for this week.
I am not Andi.
Andi has fallen sick this day, and I
have been sort of called in last minute
to take over.
It's flu season, so make sure that you
are staying clean, washing your hands,
and eating healthy so that
you, too, are not bedridden.
>> But without further
ado, let's get started.
Today, we're going to talk
about PHP a little bit-- how
PHP relates to HTML, how it
relates to CSS, and some of the web
stuff you did on the last assignment.
We're going to talk a
little bit about SQL
and how you can work with databases,
which is a pretty key component of P
set 8-- P set 7.
P set 7.
>> And then we're going to talk a little
bit about how view controllers work
and why that's a philosophy behind some
modern web pages and different design.
Pretty much a lot of types of apps
and applications you might ship
are using this model,
view controller framework,
that you will be using
in P set 7, so I'll
talk a little bit
about why that's become
popular, why it's important and nice.
And then I'll finally move on to
some tips about tackling P set 7.
And if we have time
left over at the end,
we can actually do some
work on that together.
>> So, PHP.
In fact, you may have noticed this--
you didn't really have to dive into it--
but P set 6 had some PHP
code that was going on.
And because PHP is a C-like
language, PHP, unlike HTML and CSS,
is a programming language,
whereas HTML and CSS are static.
They're markup languages dealing
with style and visual layout.
PHP is the real deal.
>> PHP has loops, it has conditions--
all that stuff that's fun about C.
It has a few things that are a little
bit better than C, which we'll see,
but I think the easiest way to talk
about the PHP is just to dive in.
So I'm going to go right
into the IDE at this point.
The first thing we're going
to do is actually look
a little bit at some of the
PHP code that was in P set 6.
So the way that we do that--
before, the way that we were running
the server for the appliance
was that we would have to type--
either use your implementation
or the staff's implementation
of server.c by going into directory
and running server.c with either no
arguments-- so just call it on the
local host, which is what you probably
did most of the time--
and then feeding it
a directory-- with
which to use as its root
where the website would
be run, basically.
>> This week for P set 7, as
great as our code for server.c
is, there are people who have already
written these fine things over at CS50
that have a little bit
more functionality,
a server program that's capable
of dealing with a little more
of the intricacies that we'll
see in both P set 7 and P set 8.
And the way that you start up the
server is by just typing, "apache50."
>> And before you do anything,
you want to make sure
that Apache 50 is not
already running as it is
on my machine, which I did to test it.
And you do that by calling apache50.
Stop, and you'll see that it's stopping
the web server, if you can look there
at the bottom of the terminal window.
And then just to start, we're
going to call, "apache50 start."
And then we're going
to feed it a directory.
>> Now, because we want to look
at some of the P set 6 code
that we had implemented, I actually
copied a little bit of the P
set 6 code into my own folder,
which you can see on the left there.
It's called "SECTION8"
in all capital letters
because I'm just so excited
to be live-streamed today.
>> So if we run this, it should
all work pretty effectively.
It says, OK, our site is now
available at the address of the IDE,
basically, which is what you were using
exactly as it was in P set 7-- P set 6.
All my indexes are one index today.
So we can go to that
address, if you'll remember,
by just clicking this little
button in the upper right.
>> And you'll recall this code, which
happened when you went into hello.php.
And what the code is designed to
do is when you typed in a name
here-- if you say Sam
because that's my name--
and I click Say Hello, when
we went to the next page,
that name was supposed to be displayed.
It would say, "Hello, Sam"
or "Hello," whatever name you
put into it even though we went
to an entirely new web page.
>> And this is the sort of thing
that PHP can do for you.
PHP is able to pass data
between two web pages.
This is a totally different page.
You'll see the title is "hello" here.
Actually, they have
the same title, but I
promise they are different web
pages if we look at the source.
And you can pass the data that's
entered in this text field,
you submit it to the next
page that's being called up,
and then that data is able to
be there in its present form.
>> Now we haven't yet implemented
this ourselves, which
is what we're going to do right now to
sort get a flavor for how PHP works,
but the key idea is that PHP-- you can
sort of think of it like a function.
Something that PHP can let you
do is it can take parameters
that you input into an HTML page
through the use of PHP and forms,
and it can pass those as parameters
to the next page that it loads up.
>> In this case, we're loading up this
page with the "Say hello" button.
But for now, I actually
deleted some of that code
in the hello.php that was being run
that was actually displaying the "hello,
world" or "hello, Sam" or
"hello," whatever was just input.
So for right now, we're
going to do that, basically.
We're going to recreate that and
also add some more functionality,
do a little bit more with it, see
what PHP is really capable of.
>> So first, let's talk about
this file, hello.php.
So if we zoom in a
little bit-- and now I'm
sort of trying to scroll all
the way around-- there we go.
You'll see it's called
hello.php, but the syntax of it
looks like an HTML file.
This is because the
actual PHP in this file
is all stuck between these
question mark-caret blocks.
Everything right here
is considered PHP code.
>> And you'll notice that
when I did a comment,
you'll see the familiar
two forward slashes.
And if you'll recall, in
HTML, if I type a comment,
it looks something closer to
this, which is a comment in HTML.
So really everything between
these two angle brackets
is now PHP code, which
is reflected in the fact
that this little comment symbol
is turned into a comment.
>> So every time you write PHP code, even
if there's no HTML code outside of it,
it's always going to be
enclosed in these angle brackets
with question marks.
You can sort of think about it-- how all
of the code that ran in your C programs
was enclosed in an int main, void,
curly brace, end curly brace statement.
And you'll see curly braces in
PHP, too, but this is sort of
like the main method of PHP.
>> So now, how do we do anything in PHP?
Now, PHP is a programming
language that's very C-like,
but it operates on the web.
So one thing that
you'll immediately-- one
of the first things you really did with
C was you printed stuff out, right?
So in C we did that
with a printf function.
We gave it a string,
probably with a new line,
and then we terminated
it with a semicolon.
>> So the way that we're going to do that
in PHP-- because it's not quite printf.
It's a little bit of different syntax.
The way that we print things out
in PHP is we say, "echo hello"
or "echo" any word.
And that has the effect of doing
printf with a string, "hello."
And it adds the new line to it.
>> So let's right now make sure--
I'll zoom out again a little bit--
let's make sure that
that code is working
because there might very
well be a bug in this code
that we will have to tackle.
So the server is already running.
So if we scroll back down to the bottom,
yup, the server is still running.
So if we just tap on this
little bit right here--
welcome-- we should get-- great.
>> We still are having the
familiar "Say hello" dialogue,
but when I type in "hi," we'll see
that the text "hello" was indeed
printed out, which is exactly as
we expected because echo in PHP
is just like a printf statement.
So back to the code, how in P set 6 did
the distribution code you are provided
make it so that PHP would
output the thing that you
typed in on the previous screen?
>> And to sort of examine
why that happens, we're
going to go into index.html, which
is the original file, the file that
shows up on this screen
with the "Say hello" button.
You notice that there's
all the classic things
we've come to expect from HTML such
as these things, these tags enclosed
in angle brackets, like PHP
but without the question marks,
which indicates a special thing to HTML.
We have title, which is "hello."
And you'll notice that as we saw,
the title is "hello" in both cases.
Let's change this one
to "say" just so we
can distinguish ourselves where we are.
>> But we've got a body.
And then the interesting bit, the
bit that shows up in the HTML,
is this form element.
And so we've got a form.
And this is the key.
This is how we're working with PHP.
The action parameter of
form says that hello.php
is what we're going to send
the values in this form to.
This is where we're passing
the parameters, so to speak.
>> You'll notice another thing here
is that the method is "get."
There are two primary
methods by which will
be using PHP to pass data
between websites-- web pages,
rather-- in this assignment.
And those methods are "get" and "post."
There are some subtle
differences between get and post
that we will get into-- we
will "get" into, if you will.
>> But for all intents and
purposes, get and post
are both just ways that
you pass parameters
with slightly different executions.
For now, we're going to use get because
get was what was used originally
in the PHP file of P set 6.
And actually, if we go in and look
before we've edited anything else,
I'm going to say hi
to-- what's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Elliot.
SAM LEVATICH: Oh, gosh.
I don't know how to spell that.
Could you spell that for me?
AUDIENCE: E-L-L-I-O-T.
>> SAM LEVATICH: I-O-T?
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah.
>> SAM LEVATICH: Perfect.
OK.
I guess I did know how to spell that.
Sorry about that.
But if we say "Say hello," it's not
it's not going to show up on the screen
yet because we modified
the code a little bit.
But if we do "Say hello"--
OK, so "hello" is here.
But if we take a closer
look at the URL itself,
we'll see that it ends
with hello.php?name=Elliot.
>> So, this is a way of
communicating to the next web page
the parameters that we've passed.
We said name=Elliot.
And that's ultimately how P set 6
accessed the variable that we passed in
through the form.
And this is something that
is peculiar to a get request.
A get request makes the parameters
known in the URL of the website.
>> And you'll recall, too,
in P set 6 that you
had to write a function
that dealt with the fact
that this query string
could exist after a file.
There could be a question mark followed
by basically any number of characters.
And that's exactly what's going on here.
And the reason you had to parse that
in your implementation of server.c in P
set 6 is so that you could tell
the PHP code that name=Elliot.
You needed to be able to
parse that out of the URL
so that the PHP file in question
knew what it was dealing with.
>> So hopefully this gives
the motivation to server.c
now that we're moving on
outside of C into PHP.
So let's actually focus on accessing the
things passed through a get request now
at this point.
I'm going to save this.
We didn't change anything.
It looks like we've got a input field.
>> We're setting some properties,
as we can do an HTML.
These are simple things.
We don't need these.
But we've got autocomplete off,
which basically says-- you know,
when you type things
into the web, sometimes
it tries to fill that in for you.
So it's a nice thing.
We want to turn it off for this purpose.
That was a CS50 decision.
So we can delete that if we wanted.
>> Autofocus just sticks the cursor
in the form right at the beginning.
Again, not too important.
>> But name="name"-- it's a little
tricky because it's name and name.
But we could've changed
this to something else.
And in fact, that's
what we'll do right now.
We'll say "person," which
is sort of like name
if a person is defined by their name.
>> So let's close this,
reopen up our website
since our server is still running
Apache 50, and we'll say, hello, here's
Elliot again.
Why not?
Hello.
And if we go up here, we'll see
then instead of name=Elliot,
it says person=Elliot.
And that's a direct result of the fact
that we just changed name="person."
>> So in an input element of
an HTML form, the name field
is the identifier for the
parameter that's being passed.
It's like if you're creating a function
"add" that took in two integers
and you said int a and int b.
That would be name a, and if
you wanted another form, which
we can do just by copying and
pasting, then we would have name b.
>> So now we'll have two parameters
that are being passed through
get to the next website--
the next web page, hello.php.
And we can actually see
that again if we want.
This is the easiest way to deal with
the web code in the IDE, basically.
You start up the server, get it
running, and then every time you
make some changes, just close
that file just to be safe.
Pressing the back button
is a little tricky
because it might load an earlier
version, not the most updated one.
>> And then you just click your
button again, pop right up-- oh,
and now there are two forms.
And so if we type one thing into each
one-- "jason hirshhorn," for instance--
we say hello.
We look up at our parameters.
It looks like we've got, as
expected, a=jason and b=hirshhorn,
which represents the two parameters
that we passed to this function.
>> So now let's actually get to
implementing that functionality that we
had in P set 6.
So right now we're just echoing hello.
And that's not very useful.
We want to echo some variable
that was passed to us.
And we know the name of this variable.
We have a and we have b.
So we could choose to echo either one.
>> But how do we access it?
Well, there are certain
global variables in PHP.
And I'm going to write
them in comments here.
The two most important ones are get
and post for our purposes right now.
These are the arrays or,
technically, the dictionaries
where our variables that we're
passing to the next web page live.
And we shall soon see how to use them.
>> Another brief note about PHP code
and some specifics of it-- in C,
to declare a variable
or to use variables,
you first had to declare them.
And what you had to do when you
declared them was say int a or char b.
You had to declare the types of these
variables before you created them.
PHP-- you don't need to do any of that.
PHP does not ask for
the type of variable.
And the way that you
create a variable-- rather
than saying int, char, string--
which is really char *, as we know--
rather than doing all of
that, because everything
is of the same type,
typeless, we can just
use one character, which
is the dollar sign.
And you'll see it's already popping
up, little autocomplete things.
And it's saying that _GET and _POST
are two options that I have available
to me.
Some of these other things are
other global variables in PHP
that you'll be using over
the course of P set 7.
For now we're going to
focus on get and post.
But this is a helpful
thing that the IDE does
where once you've typed
in that dollar sign,
it'll start filling in global variables
or variables you've already defined.
>> So if you wanted to define
a variable called "string,"
you could just set it equal to "hi."
And it's basically as simple as that.
And then we could do
something like "echo $string."
The IDE should be throwing some
errors if I'm doing anything wrong,
so hopefully I'm doing everything right.
But bugs always do arise.
>> Another tricky thing about
PHP is that it's not compiled.
So with C programs, you would do
the daily routine of-- basically,
you would make edits to
your code, you'd save it,
and then you would
make it, where make was
the step that called the compiler,
clang, to make your code, this text
file, into an executable.
PHP is C-like, but it's executed
on the fly by your web browser.
So there's no way to know.
>> Make would throw those
helpful errors, right?
It would be like, you
didn't declare this variable
before you tried to use it.
You did all this bad stuff-- segfault,
segfault, all that sort of fun times
that came with make.
PHP is a double-edged sword
because you won't get those errors,
but that also means that you won't know
really what's wrong with your program
if you just run it and it's not working.
But the debugger should point out
some hopefully helpful little things
syntactically that you can fix.
>> So now if we go over to--
say, let's close that.
Reopen.
And we're back to here.
So we've got a variable
and a variable b.
And these won't ultimately matter.
We'll call them h and g
for no particular reason.
>> And we say hello.
Now it looks like our string
"hi" is indeed printing.
We created a variable called
"string," set it equal to "hi."
Notice that we didn't have to do
malloc or make a character array.
>> In PHP, because variables
are typeless, a string
is the same as a char for
all intents and purposes.
This could be "hi."
This could be just the character k.
This can be a number 1.
And it doesn't care.
PHP doesn't care about
the type of your variable.
Or, it does care.
It cares when you try
and do things with it,
but it does not care in
the declaration step.
>> And just like you can in C, you can
declare strings on the stack like this
though saying "stack" is a little
bit of a potential misnomer when
we're talking about PHP.
But we don't have to worry about that.
So we got our string
"hi," and we echo string.
So now we've discussed variables.
So now we need to talk about get and
post and perform the final thing that's
needed to really get this back up
to the functionality of the P set 6.
So right now we're
echoing the string, but we
do have these variables get and post.
And because we're using
the method get, it
seems natural that our variable that
we're interested in, both a and b,
will be located in the array
or dictionary, technically get.
>> So if we set up get like this
with your groups-- I pressed enter
and it didn't like it--
but here we have get.
And so get already exists.
So we can already start to access
some of the elements of get.
If we do get, this syntax for
arrays in PHP is very C-like.
We have our two square brackets.
>> So if we say get in a normal
array, we could access
the zeroth index, the first index.
PHP is zero index.
We could say zero, one,
two-- stuff like this.
And I've been saying that get
is technically a dictionary.
So what PHP is doing under the hood,
which is a little bit nicer than C,
is it already is giving you some
dictionary functionality, which
is really hash tables,
or tries to, supposedly.
Or, technically it
could be a try as well.
But PHP is implementing a hash table,
which forms an effective dictionary.
>> And so we know the name
of our variable, right?
It's being passed in
the query string by PHP.
We have a=h and b=g where and b
are the names of the variables.
So the way that we can access the
value that corresponds to the key
in our dictionary is
just by saying _GET_GET["a"].
>> So now we have _GET["a"].
And if we just replace inside
our echo, if we echo _GET_GET["a"]--
and we'll see if the debugger
throws any errors about this--
we'll save that and close this out.
Open it up.
So we're just doing a right
now, so b shouldn't matter.
"her" and "him"--
"hum." "her" and "hum."
Sounds good.
>> And it printed out
"her," which is crazy.
But that's exactly what
was happening in P set 6.
Basically, what P set 6
was doing-- echo hello,
name-- where it had a
variable name and it just
asks you to type in that bit of text.
There was also some
additional code where
it included if statements,
which we can do right now.
>> We can say if exists, which
is a functionality within PHP,
_GET with the underscore, "name"--
which is basically saying,
"if name has been filled in" because
we could have just clicked the button
to submit the form without
typing anything into that field.
And we wrap that in our
friendly curly braces.
We can have an else statement.
And that's all within the PHP angle
bracket, question mark, angle bracket,
if you will.
>> And now we'll see if this works.
I keep waiting for it to debug
and crap out on me, basically,
but it hasn't yet.
Maybe it will now
because I talked about.
Yup.
It did, in fact.
So, nothing is showing up.
That's because of something wrong
that I wrote in the PHP code.
And I mentioned the debugging
is tricky because in PHP, we
didn't compile it beforehand
and the compiler wasn't like,
here's where your errors are.
>> But what we can do
is-- do people remember
how to look at the different network
requests that PHP-- or that websites
send?
[? Malin ?] did this in
lecture once or twice.
You remember where we go to find
the different debts and 200 OKs,
all these codes that are being sent
through HTTP from web page to web page?
Does anyone remember
where we go to do that?
>> AUDIENCE: Page Source.
SAM LEVATICH: Page source.
Exactly.
If you go to Page Source-- perfect.
So Page Source pulls up the inspector.
>> And I'm using Safari.
A lot of you will probably
be using Chrome or Firefox.
But as long as you're
in any modern browser--
and feel free to follow
along if you want.
You can type up this code or
just look inside the P set 6
directory for some similar stuff.
hello.php is what we're
currently working on emulating.
>> So there are a variety of tabs.
We can look at all the resources.
We can see the source code.
So looks like it didn't
get past body in the end.
It found an error in PHP and it
stopped loading the whole web page.
We don't even have an end
tag for HTML or anything.
>> And if we look at the network, we can
see that we're being sent a request.
This is the domain.
This is the address.
It's a document.
We're using the get method.
>> And it's red.
Or, it was red when I
wasn't selecting it.
How do I unselect it?
Well, it was red.
Let me refresh.
There it is.
Now it's red.
>> So it's red, which means
it failed, which is bad.
So let's examine why it did fail.
So all that the Page Source can
basically tell you is your thing
didn't work, which we can already see.
So ideally there would
be a more useful tool.
And there are some browser extensions
that allow you to debug PHP,
but we're not going to
be writing a ton of PHP,
so it's probably just best
to look through your code
carefully and just make sure that
it's not doing anything else.
>> So let's see if the format of this
if statement is where the problem is.
I want to load that back up here.
Hello, hi.
So there's a problem there.
>> So for correct syntax
of PHP, PHP is going
to be C-like in that you'll see loops.
You'll see if statements.
You'll see all these friends
that you've become familiar
with over the course
of this CS50 semester.
But the best way to figure out how to
do something in PHP is to Google it
or to look at some examples of PHP code
because you know the functionality.
>> You know what you can
do with the program.
You can loop.
You can loop as many times as you want.
You can loop in all
sorts of different ways.
You can create functions.
You can create functions that
call other functions, functions
that call themselves.
And you have names for these concepts.
You've got recursion, loops,
if, other control flows.
And so Google is your best friend.
Even say, "PHP if
statement" and there'll
be tons of posts with
answers to other people
who've had similar questions to you,
who are just starting out with PHP
and are curious about a syntax thing.
>> Because we have the luxury of being
able to look at the code in P set 6,
we actually pull it up and see that
OK, here's something interesting.
So this is what it actually
looked like in P set 6.
So if we go through this,
we can see that we've
got several of these little
PHP-like question mark bits.
>> And there aren't curly braces.
There are colons.
And there are curly
braces in PHP, but this
is a format and a way of doing
PHP that works well with HTML
because as you'll see, we're closing
off these PHP bits-- the elses
and the ifs and all of that-- and then
we're interspersing HTML inside them
while still following the
control flow set out by PHP.
>> So I'm just going to
quick walk through this
because it's a lot of the same
concepts that we were doing before.
We've got if not empty,
parentheses, _GET_GET["name"].
This is all the same stuff.
We're using the _GET dictionary that
PHP sends upon request of forms,
because it is the parameters of
action, and the method is get.
And then that ends that.
The colon is a signifier to just do this
if the if statement evaluates to true.
It's like a curly brace.
And in fact, it is a curly brace
in other languages like Python,
which you may encounter if you just
do that for your final project.
>> And then this line, hello.
Then we've got this weird thing.
We've got more brackets.
There's no HTTP there-- or PHP, sorry.
But there's an equal sign.
And then we have a function,
htmlspecialchars(_GEThtmlspecialchars(_GET["name"]).
This is sort of like a more
advanced version of echo.
Like we had echo as a way
to print things out in PHP.
This is a function that's
defined in PHP that
will deal with some more nasty
characters and byte values
that you could pass it.
It's always safest to use this.
But echo will do the job
just fine if we're not
dealing with anything too nasty.
>> And so this has the same
effect of basically,
this stuff in between the question
marks is evaluated by PHP.
htmlspecialchars returns a nice HTML
printed value of _GET_GET["name"], i.e.
whatever we typed in the form.
And then it'll say hello,
comma space, and then that.
That whole thing between
the angle brackets
will be replaced by whatever
htmlspecialchars puts out.
So that's basically similar
to what we're doing.
And we have an else statement that's
hello world, which makes sense.
So now let's go back to our
code and see exactly-- oh.
I said exists, which is not
a thing that we wanted to do.
We wanted to say not empty.
>> And so this should work a little
bit better, not empty _GET_GET["name"].
And that curly brace
matches that curly brace.
We've got our curly braces here.
echo hello _GET["name"].
Let's see if this works a little better.
We're still running our server.
Hello Jason.
And it worked this time.
And so that's a proof
that you can indeed
use the curly braces that you
know and love in PHP code in HTML.
The PHP code provided to
you in pset 6-- pset 6--
provides another way of
doing that same thing.
>> So now we have the power.
We have the functionality to implement
the PHP code that we saw in pset 6
by ourselves, basically.
Before I move on, what are some of the
questions that you have at this point?
Yes [INAUDIBLE].
>> AUDIENCE: So in the version in pset6,
when you run it, there's a space.
And I can see where the space is
after the comma. [INAUDIBLE] start
the open bracket.
How do you incorporate the space in
the way you wrote your own codes?
>> SPEAKER: That is a good question.
And so let's figure that out.
So that's a really good question
and one that I didn't consider.
But let's do it together.
>> So first of all, what
I'm doing with echo
is when we just echo
hello, it outputs hello.
If we echo now this get on a separate
line, let's examine what happens.
So we click this.
We keep saying, hi Jason.
So again, we don't have this space.
>> And that's because, in
PHP, when we have echo,
no matter how many
spaces-- nope, not the V--
no matter how many spaces we put in
here-- if we now load that up again,
hi Jason.
Yeah, see, all of those
spaces got eaten up.
And that's something that
the echo function does.
>> So to take care of
that space, and this is
one of the reasons
why you don't use echo
and you use htmlspecialchars instead.
I'm curious what would
happen if we did this
where we enclosed a space in a string.
I'm honestly not sure what
will happen when I do this.
>> So that's one way.
That's one way to take care of it.
If you wrap the space in
a string, then the space
will be output nicely by echo.
The safest thing to do is
to do htmlspecialchars.
That's always the safe bet.
But now we have a way to do
it with echo if necessary.
And in a similar way, we can
echo new lines, all the sort
of stuff you're familiar doing in PHP.
>> Anyone else, what are any more
questions that other people have
at this point about PHP?
If people showed up a little late,
I'm happy to stay after a little bit
and talk about some of the beginning.
And it's also all livestreamed,
and archived, which is crazy.
>> Anyway, so now let's do some
more advanced stuff with PHP.
And one of the earliest things you
were introduced to in C was for loops.
And PHP has a more powerful for
loop called the foreach loop.
And it looks like this-- for each blank
as blank, curly brackets, do the thing.
So this is basically a shorthand.
>> See, the for loop as a
syntactical construction
was devised in C and in assembly
language and things like.
Devised in C, precisely, as a shorthand
for a lot of the types of loops
that people would see.
Like when you wrote a loop, there
was often an initialization step
executed right at the beginning, a
condition where the loop would stop--
and that's the feature
that's just in a while loop,
or that a while has exactly
just that feature-- and then
an incrementation step at the end.
And so you'd often find yourself
writing code like the following.
I'm going to erase some of this.
>> But if we're iterating through
characters in an array,
for instance, like we've
got an array of characters.
Sorry to bring back C. I know,
you thought you were done.
But it's only for the purpose
of learning PHP, I promise.
So if you got a char str
of length 8, and let's
say it says Hellooo
with a trailing null.
Great, so that's our string.
>> And then we had a for loop.
We have int i equals 0.
And we want to exit when str
of i equals not equal to null,
because we exit when it equals null.
And then we do i++ at each
point in the for loop.
Doing something with str of i.
>> So the basic formula was,
we had this array that we
wanted to treat as separate elements.
But what we had to do is we had to
basically create a separate integer
variable that was counting up every
time we went through the loop.
And then we would have to then call
strstr[i] when what we really wanted to do
is just go character
by character, right?
We don't want to increment an
integer and then use that integer
to access each character individually.
We really want character by character.
>> And so for each intelligently
calculates that for us.
If we have an array, which
we can declare in PHP
as just-- if we have a variable
called, let's call it array.
The miracles of no typing, it's
just like any other variable.
It's just an array.
And we have a little [INAUDIBLE] like 1,
2, 3, just a sort of initialized array.
It's OK, it doesn't like my foreach.
>> But if we do foreach-- actually
I typed that a little wrong.
There are two ways to do a foreach loop.
There's the in syntax and the as syntax.
And we're going to do
in syntax first, not as.
That's my mistake.
>> So foreach num in array, echo num.
And PHP is yelling at
me for some reason.
It's finding an unexpected
in in something,
which is a little bit of a bother.
But we'll figure out
why that is in a moment.
So not like that.
Let's try using the as.
It prefers the as syntax is seems.
So let's do foreach array as num.
>> So a little explanation
of what just happened
is the as syntax is saying-- well first,
let's look at what this prints out.
So we open up our IDE.
We go here.
We say, Hello Jason.
And it did 123, which were the contents
of the array that we created up top.
>> So diving into this foreach loop,
we have a variable called array
which is an array of three numbers.
And then we are doing foreach
array as num, echo num.
And that's more
intuitive than a for lop.
We're saying, treating each of
the things in the array as num,
I want you to give me num.
And that's exactly what it's doing.
>> PHP is calculating that
when you say foreach array,
and you're dealing with an array, what
you're going to want to iterate over
is the characters in that array,
is the ints in that array,
is the elements in that array.
And it's letting you store
those variables as num,
and then just output num
right away rather than saying,
I have a variable called i, and
then I want to output strstr[i].
>> And so that allows us to do cool things.
Like basically we don't have to create
these variables like i's and do all
this incrementation stuff at the end.
PHP takes care of all of that for you.
>> So now let's talk about foreach as
it applies to our _GET dictionary.
So we'll comment this out quickly.
So we have our _GET array.
We have this variable.
And it's got some stuff in it.
>> Right now, we only have one variable
being passed to it, which is name.
But if we press Enter, now
we can have two variables.
We can have name and age, for instance,
if we want to get the age and also
the name of a person, funnily enough.
>> So now _GET is going to be a
dictionary with two elements,
with two key value pairs.
And the first key-- I'm going to
write this one up on the board too.
We have our dictionary is _GET.
Sorry, it's is a little hard to see.
But inside our dictionary we have
name, which is going to be something
that we're given.
And we'll have age, which is also
going to be something that we're given.
And this is the entirety
of our dictionary.
>> So it's got two elements in it.
And so because foreach
loops are smart, we
might think, and correctly
might think that foreach
can iterate through this
dictionary, printing out
the values given by name and age.
>> So let's in fact do just that.
Let's construct a foreach loop.
And we're going to do for _GET as.
And we're going to do the following.
So let's see what happens if we type
just word, and then say echo word.
We're also going to echo a new line
just to make it a little clearer,
what's going on.
>> So let's see.
It's not giving me any errors.
And we'll close this.
On our website, you're going to be doing
a lot of that over the course of pset7.
So we say my name is Sam.
My age is 45.
It's not.
But it prints out, as expected, Sam 45.
>> And so you'll notice that
what foreach loop did-- here,
let's go back to that so it's up
on the board-- we get _GET as word.
And there were four things in _GET.
But it only printed out two things.
foreach, being its intelligence self,
assumed that what we really wanted
was the values, not the keys.
>> But there is a way that we could print
out the keys as well, if we wanted to.
If we wanted to also know what
these variables were called,
there's a way that we
can access this as well.
And the way to sort of do that,
so we can say, lets really
split it into key value pairs.
So let's see what happens now.
>> So we have key.
We have value.
We have another new
line for readability.
And let's see what happens
when we do this now.
I don't know how old Jason is.
Jason's 15.
So we have name Jason, age 15.
So we were able to access the key
and value pairs of this dictionary
just by saying as key points to value.
And that's a foreach syntactic
sugar bit that allows
you to access things in the dictionary.
>> So hopefully this sort of emphasizes
the power of the foreach loop.
You can pretty much throw
anything that seems iterable,
like anything that has multiple
elements like an array,
like a dictionary-- those are two
primary things you'll be working with
both in life and in pset 7.
So you can throw that stuff
at it, and it will figure out
what you want to do with it.
It'll say, OK, I'm going to get
these things from the data that
was passed to me.
And that's something that you're
going to be using a lot of in pset 7.
>> I'm going to quick scroll
down just to see where I'm at.
Do people have questions at this point?
Questions at all?
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: So with the key and value,
you could name it anything else
and it would still work?
SPEAKER: Oops.
Wow, I totally deleted the whole line.
Great work.
So a, a.
Key and value is just a convention.
It's helpful.
You would get some design
points, maybe some style points
for doing that because it
really conveys the intention.
But we say a and yarp.
>> AUDIENCE: You don't have to
change anything in the HTML file
in order to reflect that?
SPEAKER: Not at all.
AUDIENCE: And it just knows that
because of the equals greater than--
SPEAKER: Yes.
AUDIENCE: --that indicator that that's--
That is a foreach syntax, but yes.
>> AUDIENCE: There are not types.
So what if you wanted
age to only be a number?
Is there a way to do that?
>> SPEAKER: There are ways to check if
variables conform to certain types.
So PHP asks a little more from
you because there are no types in.
Some ways it asks less.
In some ways it asks more.
Because if you have just
something in a variable,
you have no idea what type it is.
But if you are smart about the variables
that you assign types to and make sure
that functions only return-- you
want functions to only return
one type of value so
that you can basically
expect that the variable you get back
from a function will be of the type
that you think it will be, basically.
>> But there are some methods
by which you can check.
I don't remember them
off the top of my head.
I'm waiting for it to turn blue.
isint?
isstr?
There are methods
built into PHP that can
check the type of variables for you.
But if you assign variables
smartly, you should not
have to do that too much in pset 7.
But those methods do exist.
And that's something that
is in the language itself.
And I don't remember the precise syntax.
We could even look it up.
But time is of the essence.
have Does anyone else
have any more questions?
Yes.
>> AUDIENCE: I have just one more.
So you mentioned the GET method, but
you didn't mention the POST method.
Are we coming back to that?
>> SPEAKER: Yes, we will
be coming back to that.
That's exactly what I was looking
at my phone, which now fell asleep,
but I'll find it.
Just making sure we hit
all of the PHP notes.
Yep, there's no debugging version.
Yes, we have a few more things that
we want to do now at this point.
>> So talking about POST,
which you mentioned,
the only difference
between GET and POST is
that remember when we looked
at this URL and we saw, oh,
name equals a and age equals yarp
are right in the URL there for us.
POST is a little more secretive
with its passing of information.
>> So if you didn't want a user
to know, for instance, you
didn't want the username
and password of the person
currently logged in to be displayed in
the URL, which is a reasonable thing
to not want in the URL,
because someone can see it.
If they link someone to a page, you
don't want their URL plastered there,
because that would allow people to login
just with the pasting of a URL instead
of actually filling out a form.
POST is a little bit more secretive.
>> And the only things that
we'll have to change
are this method, change
from get to post.
And then inside the HTTP, instead
of accessing the array _GET,
we're going to access the array _POST.
>> And we'll notice that, if
we open this back up again,
Jason slowly declines in age.
name Jason, age 14.
The same stuff pops up.
But we go to the URL and
those variables aren't there.
>> And the way that POST
passes-- so remember
how to look at the source of a page.
We go to the network.
We refresh.
And this is another thing that
POST will give you warnings about.
You might have seen a box, a text
box like this in your browser.
Are you sure you want
to send a form again?
POST is what 's sending these forms.
>> Because basically if you sent your
credit card information to someone,
that's not going to show up in the URL.
That's going to be a POST request.
So when you refresh the page,
it's resending that post request.
So now we do want to send the
form again because it's not going
to create any duplicate purchases.
>> And we'll notice that down here,
the method we're using is POST.
And it did indeed transfer bytes.
It transferred 401 of them.
Program's pretty tiny.
But there's nowhere that we can see
the values that are being passed.
The web pages themselves can see,
but we as users are not able to see,
unless you're a hacker.
If you're a good hacker, you can look.
>> If you know the basic
format of the HTML,
the values will make
themselves known in the pages.
You'll be able to see.
The values will be there, they're
just a little less obvious for you
to access, basically.
>> Do we have any more
questions about GET, POST
before-- what we're going to do next
is actually look at some of the code
that you're giving in pset 7, talk about
how it uses some of these concepts,
and talk about the
things that you are going
to have to do a little bit in pset 7.
Any more questions before that?
More questions you guys have?
Great.
>> All right, let's look
a little bit at pset 7,
no doubt what you are
all most excited about.
I mean, this is something that
David goes through a little bit.
But we'll have three directories at the
top, as well as a configuration file.
That's for databases, which we'll
talk about in about five minutes.
Includes, you never need
to look in this directory
if you don't want to but it's nice to
know there are all sorts of helpers.
Helpers is like helpful functions.
And then we have config,
which sets some stuff up.
>> There are some functions that CS50 has
written that are in helper and config.
And some of the PHP that
already exits in files
will do a lot of the more sort
of obtuse leg work for you.
Like if we go into public
login.php, which is what
shows up right when you go into pset 7.
We'll see that there's
this require statement.
And that sort of like a
sharp include, hashtag
include if you're of a newer generation.
But this basically
says that I need access
to all the functions in config.php.
And you could have a require
for all sorts of other things.
>> config actually requires helpers.
So whenever you require
config, you're also
including or requiring helpers as well.
So that gives you access to all the
cool functions that we're going to use,
things like render.
I'm actually going to ease
this down a little bit.
So the function then we're
going to walk through
just before we move on to SQL a little
bit is the login.php function, just
because it uses some of the topics
that we just talked about in PHP.
>> You see the first thing is if $_SERVER.
This is another global variable that
you're going to be dealing with.
It's like _GET and _POST, but what
server contains is this can let you
know if the request method
was a GET or a POST.
Like previously what we were doing
is just in our code that we wrote,
we were just changing it to be GET and
POST depending on what the HTML has.
But there are pages that can be
accessed with both types of requests.
And you might want to do
different things depending
on the type of request,
just like login does.
>> So you can check that request
method through accessing keys,
through using a key and getting the
value of something in the dictionary
_SERVER.
So that's another global
variable like _GET and _POST.
>> If it's GET, we want to
render the login form.
Render is a function that basically
just puts up the appropriate HTML
and passes it some parameters.
This title is a parameter that's
used in displaying, oddly enough,
the title of the page in
question, the thing up here,
say or hello in our previous example.
Now we have a different thing.
Else if it's POST, we
do some other stuff.
We're using that empty method.
It's not exist, it's empty.
And we saw before, PHP
has a fair amount of built
in methods that David will-- if there
are methods that are useful to you,
they will be alerted to you
in the walk through that David
gives at the beginning overview,
and also Zamyla's helpful bits.
She's back everyone.
We can all rejoice.
apologize is an aptly named function
that just basically prints out
some error messages,
because CS50 is very polite.
>> And now this, this is a
tricky bit because this
is where we're querying the database.
Now we haven't talked about databases.
And we're going to in the next
five minutes or so, maximum.
But this is a function
that CS50 has written
to get a table basically from a database
that we're working with in pset 7.
I'm really bad with my
zero indexing today.
But yes, it is 7.
>> So query it's going to return an
array, basically is the key bit.
And because these things don't have
typing, so rows is an array of arrays.
Because when we're thinking about
a table, what we're going to do
is, as you learned in psets
like the game of 15, anyway
where you had to use a
double array, we basically
have array of other
arrays makes a table.
And you've got rows and columns.
And then you can access them like
[0] [1], you get the [0] [1].
Basic stuff like that.
>> So what we're doing
here in this function,
we're asking the database
if the user that's
trying to login, that will be
sent through the POST method.
We'll see we're getting
the username from _POST.
They'll have sent, the user
or you, will send a value
through a form through POST because
it's username and password stuff.
We're checking the username
to see, is this in the table?
Because if a user is logging
in, then their username
should be stored in the table of
users that exist for this site.
So basically if the
user is in the database,
query is going to return
that row, which is an array.
>> But the tricky part is that if even if
the double array is only of one row,
even if it's a one row array--
like you've got basically--
if you've got a size one array
that's holding another array,
you're really dealing with one column.
But it's still treated
like a double array.
>> And this is where it can sometimes get
tricky, because we've got rows here.
Our variable is rows.
And then we're creating
a new variable called row
and setting it equal to
the first row of rows.
And you'll notice that comment
says it's the first and only row.
>> So this is the tricky
part where now functions
can return arrays very easily.
There's not mallocs.
You won't see mallocs.
So you won't see seg faults.
But functions will still be passing
around arrays and data in groups.
And you have to be wary of what
exactly your functions will return.
And even if it's one
column like this, query
is still going to return a double array.
So to access that column-- or you
can think of all of this as inverted
since we're talking about rows.
But to access that one row,
you can't just say rows.
Even though it is one row, you have to
do rowsrows[0] to sort of eliminate this
outer bit of the array and
have just your one row.
>> Do some other things.
There's a function
called password_verify
that verifies the
password that was POSTed.
And then we see another global
variable here, _SESSION.
Basically session id
is how you keep track
of if someone is logged in or not.
So right now with login.php,
we're logging a user in.
So what we want to do is we want to
say the session id is equal to the row
id, which just makes sense because
each row will have a different id
number as part of the table.
We'll get into SQL in a
second, so if any of this
seems a little bit like blah,
then all will be cleared up.
But we're going to set the id equal to
the proper thing, logging the user in.
Apologize if anything goes wrong.
And that is logins purpose in
life as Professor Malan would say.
>> So that was login.php.
And a lot of the PHP code you write
in pset 7, they'll be a little bit.
Don't forget to chmod to
the proper permissions.
There will be a little bit about
that in the beginning of the spec.
>> But the PHP that you're
writing is going to be
doing stuff that's similar to this.
You're going to be
accessing some things that
are given to you in the
global variables of PHP that
are dealing with the current
logged in user, whether there
have been requests sent to this
page, different things like that.
And it will also be potentially
iterating through rows of this thing.
>> In a different function, query
does return this double array.
And if there are more
than one rows in it,
if there are-- yes, if there
are more than one rows in it,
then it will be a table.
And you might want to iterate
through the rows of this array using
the foreach loop that we described.
>> So if you do foreach on a double
array, what will the word-- here,
I'll actually write it.
I'll write it quick here.
>> If we have a foreach of rows
as row, what's the type of row?
Does anyone know?
You got it?
So rows is a double array.
So what is foreach going to infer
that we want from this double array
if we're iterating over it?
We can basically assume that
it's going to be either elements,
or rows, or columns, basically.
And so rows and columns we
can treat as the same thing.
>> Basically what the foreach loop is going
to do is it's going to return rows.
row is going to be of type row,
whereas rows is a double array.
So if you give foreach
a double array, it's
not going to iterate
more than one level deep.
Which is basically to say if there
are eight cells in this table-- 1,2,
3 4, 5, 6, 7, 8-- the
foreach loop is not
going to go through each of these cells.
What the foreach loop will do
was it will go through this row,
give you this whole row.
And then it'll go through that row.
>> So it only iterates one level deep.
If you add a nested
foreach loop, then you
can treat each row returned from
rows, you do foreach row as element,
let's say.
And then you could echo the element.
So that's a brief
little refresher on how
you might be using foreach
loops in the context of query.
>> Are there any questions on PHP?
Anything at all before we
move on to talking about SQL
and the fun of database?
Feeling good?
Feeling good.
All right.
>> Let's move on back to the
PowerPoint, which you probably miss.
SQL, yay.
People who are in my section typically
will know that subheadings of acronyms
are always just the first words
I think of that match that
algorithm-- that acronym.
It's not an algorithm.
>> So SQL is a database.
It's a language that
works with databases.
And all databases are is
tables, at least in the way
that SQL represents them.
>> Another way to think about databases is
databases are a set of keys and values
basically.
You can think about a database as
a dictionary and also as a table.
Basically it's a way to associate
different data with other data,
often through rows and columns.
And that's the way
that's SQL works best.
>> So this is one example of a table.
I've got a few examples of
people in my section, which
I didn't have time to change.
But we've got things like ID,
name, superpower, and hometown.
I don't know where anyone's
from in my section,
so I'm just going to assume
everyone's from New York
City because I have a high statistical
likelihood of being correct.
>> SQL will automatically take
care of the ID column for you.
If you insert a new row
into a SQL database,
it will increment that
ID number and just
basically stick like five names,
superpower, hometown, whoever
onto the end of that table.
So ID is a column you'll
never have to worry about.
But, like in the case
of login.php, when we
were getting the session ID
from a table and just using ID,
ID is a way to uniquely identify
an element of a database.
>> So if we had two Sams, both of
which taught CS50, and both of who
were from Milwaukee, those would
still have distinct ID numbers
and thus be distinct in
the context of the table.
So this is what SQL is dealing
with, working with in the back end.
>> Now these are the four commands
that you'll need to work with SQL.
And I threw them all up on one slide.
But we're going to go through
them all individually.
>> The first command is UPDATE,
which does what you might expect.
Say you have some data in
the table that's out of date.
Like if you're keeping
track of people's names
and ages, if someone's
age increases, then
you're going to want to go in and
update just that person's age.
For an example that works
with our first table--
don't worry about writing all of
these commands at the same time.
But if you've got update down,
that'll be good for this part,
because we're going to
go back to the table.
>> So if we go back to the table,
let's say something that happened
was there was an earthquake or
a fault line that split directly
through New York City.
And we wanted to update everyone
who lived in New York City.
They all had to move to Pennsylvania.
That's not a hometown.
They all had to move to New Haven.
There we go.
So everyone in New York
moves to New Haven.
>> And so that's something that's
editing three rows in this table.
But in SQL, you can do
that in just one statement.
So we go back to UPDATE.
Let me quick erase this board again.
When we're talking about
updating, there are
a few parts of the syntax that are key.
Well, all of the syntax is key.
But the stuff in green is optional.
The white are required,
like predefined names.
And the light blue are things
that vary depending on the table.
So that's what's going on with
the color scheme here, up there.
>> So if we want to update just those rows
of the people who live in New York,
so what we would do if we said UPDATE?
So table is where we put
the name of our table.
Let's just say the name
of our table is table one.
So we want to UPDATE table one.
And we want to set--
what do we want to set?
Well we want to say, so column-- PHP
treats rows as unique identifiers.
And then columns are
the different fields
of those elements of the database.
>> So the first element of the database
has a name of Sam, superpower of CS50,
and a hometown of Milwaukee.
So if we said set, let's look at
the parameters again that set takes.
We have column equals value.
So we want to say some
column-- which remember
is a field-- we want to see a
field equal to something new.
>> So if we just said update
table 1, set name equal Elliot.
Get some people from the
new section in on this.
But if we just did update table 1
set name equal Elliot, what would
the table look like after that?
People have any idea?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Everything in that
row would become Elliot.
SPEAKER: Everything in which row?
AUDIENCE: In the first row.
SPEAKER: In the first row?
Why the first row?
I don't mean to pick on you.
>> AUDIENCE: Maybe everything
in the whole table?
SPEAKER: Everything in
the whole table, yes.
And that's exactly right because-- I
was just helping you out a little bit
there-- because we omitted
the optional WHERE clause.
If you don't have the WHERE
clause, what this command will do
is it'll work with every
single row in the table.
Everyone's name will
become Elliott, basically,
which Elliot is very happy about.
Or Yanni, one of the two.
But everyone's name will change.
>> So the way we use the WHERE clause--
and this applies to all of the WHEREs
that are in each of
these different things.
So you'll notice that SET
has column equal value.
And so does WHERE.
But these are different
types of statements.
So the column equals value
in SET is in assignment.
Like we're saying we want
to set name equal to Elliot.
But in the WHERE clauses,
these are equality statements.
So let's say we only wanted to
change the person's name to Elliot
if their name was Ryan, let's say.
>> So when we say
>> WHERE name equals Ryan, that
would successfully only change
the name-- it would only
change the name field in rows
where the name field is equal to Ryan.
So if we had multiple people
named Ryan, all of their names
would change to Elliot.
>> This is similar to the example
of if a fault line splits
New York City and everyone has to
move to New Haven, the way we can
do that in one statement is UPDATE
table1 SET hometown = New Haven
where hometown equals New York City.
This is the power of
the UPDATE statement.
We can select any number of
rows through true statements
about the fields in those rows.
We can't say UPDATE table1 set
name = Elliot WHERE row = 1,
except that we can if we say ID = 1.
>> So we're going to be
working with equality
of fields, equality of columns.
But using the ID field is a way to
select individual rows specifically,
because the ID field is a unique
identifier in a SQL database.
So like updating row one, ID equals 1.
Updating row two, just
change that ID number.
But the power of the
WHERE statement is that we
can update things based on what their
current values of certain things are.
Yes Elliot?
>> AUDIENCE: And what if you want to--
again, this is another question.
But my first question was,
where is this happening?
Where am I updating this?
Is this in a PHP code?
>> SPEAKER: Where you update, yes.
We're going to talk
about where all of this
happens sort of once we go
through all the commands.
But what you need to
know for now is basically
that your SQL database
exists as something
to be accessed by the query
function, which CS50 defines.
So if you use the query function,
you can access this table.
>> So you will be sending these
commands to your table in PHP files
through the query function.
You can also play around
with your table directly.
And that's the best way to
test these sorts of commands.
And we'll go through exactly how
to do that in just a little bit.
>> So that's UPDATE command.
And the rest of the commands
are going to be sort of similar,
working on similar things.
The INSERT INTO is probably
the most different from UPDATE.
I'm going to leave that up there for
just a little bit and work over here.
So INSERT INTO, you'll see
that table is still the same.
You want to INSERT INTO.
The capitalization, SQL
is case insensitive.
So you don't have to
capitalize these things.
By convention, the words
in white are capitalized.
But I also color coded them.
The only reason that you capitalize
those when you're typing them
is just to emphasize
that those are constants.
And so you can either look at
the capitalization or the fact
that I've colored them differently.
>> So we've got INSERT INTO,
let's do table1 again.
This is all on one line.
I'm just separating it by
the different statements.
So don't worry about the fact that
table1 made it onto the second line.
>> So we want to INSERT
INTO table1 some values.
And you'll notice the optional
bit, which I'll get to in a second.
So we've got VALUES.
>> So let's say we want to add Andi
to our table, because we miss Andi.
Andi is sick.
So let's add Andi to our table.
Remember that the ID number
is updated automatically.
So the only fields we
need to worry about
are name, superpower, and hometown.
>> And so the way that we do that,
looking at our syntax, is we've
just got a parentheses, with comma
separated values, each of which
is a value.
So if we wanted to insert Andi into our
table, all we have to do is right Andi.
What's Andi's superpower,
people in Andi's section?
She like flight, or like
speed, or something.
What do we already have up there?
We have CS50, flight,
speed, and strength.
>> AUDIENCE: Time travel.
>> SPEAKER: Time travel, amazing.
So we've got Andi, time
travel, and her hometown.
That's a really good question.
New York City, unless someone knows.
Everyone's from New York is the
lesson to take away from today.
>> So this statement would
insert, as a fifth row,
with the superpower time travel
and a hometown of New York City.
But the optional field
is basically a way
to specify exactly which columns
you want to insert things in.
>> The way that we're doing it now,
Andi, time travel, New York City,
is going in the exact order of our
table-- name, superpower, hometown.
And if you wanted to do
something other than that,
like say you didn't know
someone's superpower,
like how I didn't know Andi's
superpower at the beginning.
So all I knew was her
name and her hometown.
What I could do is I could
do-- I'll erase this quick.
>> I want to only update the columns.
And this is where the optional
column list comes into play.
I only want to update name and hometown.
And then I will say VALUES.
I'll do Andi and New York City.
>> If I had omitted the list of columns
and just done these two things,
where would New York City have gone?
Which column would New York
City have been placed in?
People have any idea?
Superpower, exactly.
>> So this will just go in order.
And once it reaches the end of the
list, it'll just stop filling things in.
And the values that it'll stick in
all the columns will just be NULL.
So because we specified
name and hometown,
we're going to have ID 5,
name Andi, superpower NULL.
So superpower is an uninitialized value.
You won't necessarily get the
same Valgrind errors if you try
and access it.
Everything will be nicely zeroed
out, because NULL is a value in SQL.
That is a constant.
And then hometown will be New York City.
So that's the INSERT INTO command.
Before we move, there's
two more commands.
Do people have any questions about
UPDATE, about INSERT INTO, about SQL
generally before we move
onto our final bits?
People feel good, great.
Love it.
So let's talk about SELECT.
Going ditch UPDATE over here.
>> And SELECT is going to be very similar.
The goal of SELECT,
SELECT's purpose in life
is to give you a bunch of columns
that satisfy certain conditions.
And when I say satisfy
certain conditions,
your mind might immediately
go back to that WHERE clause
that came up in UPDATE.
And that clause is
exactly there in SELECT.
>> If we don't put the WHERE
clause and we say SELECT name,
hometown-- spelled that a little
wrong-- name, hometown FROM table1.
If we just say that, what SELECT
is going to give us is it's
going to give us a
double-- a table, rather.
A double array if we're
thinking about in PHP senses.
But it's just going to give us a
double array of two columns-- name,
and hometown.
And it will ignore ID.
And it will ignore superpower.
And it'll just give us every
single row of that table.
So if we just inserted
Andi, we'll have Andi.
And we'll have the original four.
If they've been updated, that will
be reflected, et cetera, et cetera.
>> So this is because we
didn't use the WHERE clause.
But we can use it in exactly the
same way we used it in UPDATE.
If we only want a table of the names
and super powers of people living
in New York, we can execute a statement
like SELECT name, superpower--
I'm just going to leave that-- FROM
table1 WHERE hometown = New York City.
>> So this goes to show that you can
get totally different columns,
and then put columns that you're not
even getting back in the WHERE clause.
We don't even want the
hometown of everyone.
But we want the name and
the superpower of people
whose hometown is New York City.
So that's something we
can do with the WHERE
clause is we can deal with columns
that we don't necessarily want back.
In the same way in UPDATE, we can deal
with columns that we don't necessarily
want to update.
We can update the city of everyone
who's name is Sam, for instance.
We can update the city of
everyone whose ID number is 2.
So just update the
city of the second row
where we don't have to deal with
necessary the common question.
>> And DELETE is, as you'd
expect, DELETE FROM table1.
And then we've got another WHERE clause.
So we can say WHERE ID = 1.
Delete the first row.
And DELETE will always delete a row,
or it will delete some number of rows.
DELETE FROM table WHERE
hometown = New York City
will delete everyone in New York City.
That's if there was a
sudden tragic plague
and you just wanted to remove
everyone from the table who
lived in a certain city
that was hit by the plague.
May they rest in peace.
>> These are the four SQL commands
that you will need to use.
You might not even need use them all.
But these are the four
that CS50 expects you
to be comfortable with going into
both quiz 1 and also pset7 and pset8.
>> There's just that table again.
In this one, Roy's superpower has
been updated to laser beams, which
is an example I did not use.
I don't know which one
Roy prefers, but strength.
Roy has a superpower of strength.
Katherine did not make it today.
That's unfortunate.
But she has super speed.
>> Well that was PHP.
Before we talk about MVC, does
anyone have questions about PHP?
Now SQL, or PHP if you suddenly have
come up with a question about PHP?
Great.
All right, we're all set then.
>> So talking a little bit
about model view controllers,
let's go back to some
of the stuff in pset7.
So what model view
controller is-- I'm not
going to save my changes to login
because I totally butchered it.
But basically we have two
separate things going on.
We have a public
directory which contains
the code that's going to be executed
and the web pages that will be visited.
And we also have this views directory.
And views contains templates.
>> This is what the function
render-- we saw the render
function in a bunch of the PHP code
that CS50 has already written for you,
that takes in certain parameters.
What that code is doing
is it's going into views,
which are sets of like
prewritten HTML code,
and it's inserting values
into certain places.
This is how when you
go into CS50 Finance,
the same header is on every page.
The same footer is on every page.
This is because the way
that render works is it'll
automatically patch in that header and
viewer which you can find in views.
>> We actually can go into header, and
look, it's an HTML file with a head.
It's got some stylesheets.
You don't need to look at CSS
for pset7 if you don't want to.
But you can modify
them if you want, make
your Finance look a little different.
>> It's got some PHP in
the header a bit to see
if there's a different title
it should put in this header.
But just some other scripts,
and links, and other things.
Head ends, body starts, and oops,
we have this weird little end bit.
And there's a div, just like
a formless kind of element
that has an idea of middle.
>> And then when we see footer,
we have the end of a div.
We have a bottom, which is
where the footer text is.
End of div, end of body, end of HTML.
>> So what render is
doing is render is sort
of patching up header, a
different PHP file that
will contain the actual things that
you'll view, like your table of stocks
if you are buying or selling stocks.
And then it'll add in the footer.
And the model view
controller idea is that we
want to separate how
things look from the code.
It's we want to separate the frontend
and the backend, where the frontend is
the stuff that the user sees, the nice
visuals-- HTML, CSS, things like that,
images, et cetera.
And the backend is PHP.
This is code that you write.
This is where the code that's
doing actual operations.
This is when you're adding
a stock to your table,
when you're buying and
selling, that's backend.
>> And we can, as you saw,
including PHP directly in HTML.
So what we could have done for
this assignment is just had
an HTML file for each page, like login.
And then on that page, just
had a huge block of PHP code,
including all of the code that
that page specifically would need.
And then we could have
done that for portfolio.
We could have done all of the buying
and selling within the individual pages.
>> But because we're rendering
separately from where
we're writing the backend
code, we can easily
change how things look without
changing every single file.
We do things like just add
a new div to the bottom
of-- Hello I modified the footer.
You can just do stuff like that.
But also, you can change
the entire visual layout
without affecting what's
going in the backend.
And you can change the
entire backend and still
have it look just like it did before.
This
>> Is the idea of model view controller.
And it's actually an imposed paradigm
in some of the programming languages
you might want to use
for final projects.
If you do iOS development,
they have views,
which is what you see on the iPhone, and
then backend as like a separate thing.
>> You can think about a little bit.
There's a lot of binaries in
computer science, which is funny,
because everything's in binary.
I didn't plan that.
That was a pun unintended.
Yes, pun not intended.
>> But like .h files and .c files, there's
a lot of separating of things that we
might not need.
So we can just edit the h files, or
someone can just see a .h file and know
exactly the functions that are in the
.c file without necessarily knowing
their implementation.
This idea of separating components
that depend on each other
but can sort of access each other
through different channels, passing
of variables, just
include statements, things
like that, this principle
helps to create applications
that can be more easily
edited by multiple people,
can be more easily changed
or modified on a big scale,
and are easier to
debug in a lot of ways.
>> Really quick, I have
a few tips for pset7,
which I'll make full screen so you not
just looking at the-- tip tip tippee.
There aren't that many tips.
>> But I mentioned PHP is hard to debug.
Double and triple check it.
If your code is just not
showing up on the page,
it's probably a PHP error, sorry.
>> You never need to look at
CSS if you don't want to.
But once you're finished, it can be
a nice little fun thing to just go in
and mess with the CSS parameters.
CSS and HTML are an example of a model
view controller style thing too, right?
You could have style tags
inside of HTML elements.
But if you sort of
outsourcing them to CSS,
they're easier to edit, and play
around with, and have fun with.
>> Treat CS50 helper
functions as black boxes.
You don't need to know
exactly what render's doing,
but trust it to always do the right
thing depending on what you pass it,
things like this.
And I would recommend
watching David's walkthrough,
going through all the
stuff, not just the todos,
but you really can treat
these as black boxes.
Don't go into these
functions looking for bugs.
>> And welcome the return
of our overlord Zamyla.
Great.
>> Are there any final questions before
we sort of bounce for the day?
Am I still live?
Great.
Hi livestream people.
Are there anymore questions?
No?
>> And then I think we're
good to go for today.
I'll stick around a little bit
afterward if people had questions
they were afraid to ask on the stream.
But otherwise, have a good day.