>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> ANDI PENG: Welcome to week 6 of section.
We deviated from our standard
section time of Tuesday
afternoon to this lovely Sunday morning.
Thank you for everyone that
joined me today, but seriously,
a round of applause.
>> That's a pretty big effort.
I almost didn't even make it
up in time, but It was OK.
So I know that all of you
have just made it to the quiz.
First of all, welcome to
the flip side of that.
>> Secondly, we'll talk about it.
We'll talk about the quiz.
We'll talk about how
you're doing in the class.
You'll be fine.
I have your quizzes for
you at the end of here,
so if you guys want to take
a look at it, totally fine.
>> So quickly before we begin, the
agenda for today is as follows.
As you can see, we're
basically rapid firing
through a whole bunch of data structures
really, really, really quickly.
So as such, it won't be
super interactive today.
It'll just be me kind of shouting
things that you, and if I confuse you,
if I'm going too fast, let me know.
They're just various data
structures, and as part
of your pset for this
upcoming week, you'll
be asked to implement one of them,
perhaps two of them-- two of them
in your pset.
OK, so I'm just going to
start with some announcements.
We'll go over stacks and queues more in
depth than what we did before the quiz.
We'll go over linked
list again, once again,
more in depth than what
we had before the quiz.
And then we'll talk about hash
tables, trees and tries, which
are all pretty necessary for your pset.
And then we'll go over some
helpful tips for pset5.
>> OK, so quiz 0.
The average was a 58%.
It was very low, and so you guys all
did very, very well in accordance
with that.
>> Pretty much, rule of thumb is if you're
within a standard deviation of the mean
especially since we're in a less
comfy section, you're totally fine.
You're on track.
Life is good.
>> I know it's scary to think that
I got like a 40% on this quiz.
I'm going to fail this class.
I promise you, you're not
going to fail the class.
You're totally fine.
>> For those of you who got over
the mean, impressive, impressive,
like, seriously well done.
I have them with me.
Feel free to come get them
at the end of section.
Let me know if you have any
issues, questions with them.
If we add up your score
wrong, let us know.
>> OK, so pset5, this is a really
weird week for Yale in the sense
that our pset is due
Wednesday at noon including
the late day, so it's actually
theoretically due Tuesday at noon.
Probably no one finished
at Tuesday at noon.
That's totally fine.
We're going to have office hours
tonight as well as Monday night.
And all of the sections this week will
actually be turned into workshops,
so feel free to pop in
any section you want,
and they'll be kind of mini-pset
workshops for help on that.
So as such, this is the only section
where we're teaching material.
All the other sections will be focusing
exclusively on help for the pset.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Where are office hours?
>> ANDI PENG: Office hours
tonight-- oh, good question.
I think office hours tonight
are in Teal or at Commons.
If you check online CS50
and you go to office hours,
there should be a schedule that
tells you where all of them are.
>> I know either tonight
or tomorrow is teal,
and I think we may have
commons for the other night.
I'm not sure.
Good question.
Check on CS50.
>> Cool, any questions regarding the
schedule for the next like three days?
I promise you guys like David
said, this is the top of the hill.
You guys are almost there.
Just three more days.
Get there, and then we'll all come down.
We'll have a nice CS-free break.
We'll come back.
We'll dive into web
programming and development,
things that are very fun compared
to some of the other psets.
And it'll be chill, and
we'll have lots of fun.
We'll have more candy.
Sorry for candy.
I forgot candy.
It was a rough morning.
So you guys are almost there,
and I'm really proud of you guys.
>> OK, so stacks.
Who loved the question about Jack
and his clothing on the quiz?
No one?
OK, that's fine.
>> So essentially as you can
picture Jack, this guy here,
loves to take the clothing
out of the top of the stack,
and he puts it back onto
the stack after he's done.
So in this way, he never
seems to be getting
to the bottom of the
stack in his clothing.
So this kind of describes
the basic data structure
of how a stack is implemented.
>> Essentially, think of a
stack as any stack of objects
where you put things onto the top, and
then you pop them out from the top.
So LIFO is the acronym we like
to use-- Last In, First Out.
And so last in to the top of the
stack is the first one that comes out.
And so the two terms
we like to associate
with that are called push and pop.
When you push something onto the
stack, and you pop it back up.
>> And so I guess this is kind of an
abstract concept for those of you
who want to see like an
actual implementation of this
in the real world.
How many of you have written an essay
maybe like an hour before it was due,
and you accidentally deleted a huge
chunk of it, like accidentally?
And then what control do
we use to put it back?
Control-Z, yeah?
Control-Z, so the amount of times
that Control-Z has saved my life,
has saved my ass, every time
that's implemented through a stack.
>> Essentially all the information
that's on your Word document,
it gets pushed and popped at will.
And so essentially whenever you
delete anything, you pop it back up.
And then if you need it back on, you
push it, which is what Control-C does.
And so real world function
of how simple data structure
can help with your everyday life.
>> So a struct is the way that
we actually create a stack.
We type define struct, and then
we call it stack at the bottom.
And within the stack,
we have two parameters
that we can essentially manipulate,
so we have char star strings capacity.
>> All that it is doing
is creating an array
that we can store whatever you want
which we can determine its capacity.
Capacity Is just the max amount of
items we can put into this array.
int size is the counter that keeps
track of how many items are currently
in the stack.
So then we can keep track of, A,
both how large the actual stack is,
and, B, how much of that stack
we filled because we don't want
to overflow over what our capacity is.
>> So for example, this lovely
question was on your quiz.
Essentially how do we push
onto the top of a stack.
Pretty simple.
If you look at it,
we'll walk through this.
If [INAUDIBLE] size--
remember, whenever you
want to access any
parameter within a struct,
you do the name of the struct.parameter.
>> In this case, s is
the name of our stack.
We want to access the size
of it, so we do s.size.
So as long as the size is not
equal to capacity or as long
as it's less than capacity,
either would work here.
>> You want to access the inside
of your stack, so s.strings,
and you're going to put that new number
that you want to insert into there.
Let's just say we will want to
insert int n onto the stack,
we could do s.strings,
brackets, s.size equals n.
Because size is where we
currently are in the stack
if we're going to push
it on, we just access
wherever the size is, the
current fullness of the stack,
and we push the int n onto it.
And then we want to make sure that
we're also incrementing size of the n,
so we can keep track of we've
added an extra thing to the stack.
Now we have a greater size.
Does this here make sense to
everybody, how logically it works?
It was kind of quick.
AUDIENCE: Can you go over
the s.stringss.strings[s.size] again?
ANDI PENG: Sure, so what does
s.size currently give us?
AUDIENCE: It's the current size.
ANDI PENG: Exactly, so the
current index that our size is at,
and so we want to put the new integer
that we want to insert into s.size.
Does that make sense?
Because s.strings, all that
is is the name of the array.
All it is is accessing the
array within our struct,
and so if we want to
place n into that index,
we can just access it
using brackets s.size.
Cool.
>> All right, pop, I pseudocode it out
for you guys, but similar concept.
Does that make sense?
If the size is greater
than zero, then you
know that you want to take something
out because if the size is not
greater than zero, then you
have nothing in the stack.
>> So you only want to execute
this code, it can only
pop if there is something to pop.
So if the size is greater
than 0, we minus the size.
We decrement the size and then return
whatever is inside of it because
by popping, we want to
access whatever is stored
in the index of the top of the stack.
Everything make sense?
If I made you guys write this out,
would you guys be able to write it out?
OK, you guys can play around with it.
No worries if you don't get it.
We don't have time to code
it out today because we've
got a lot of these structures
to go through, but essentially
pseudocode, very, very similar to push.
Just follow along the logic.
Make sure you're accessing all the
features of your struct correctly.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Will these slides and
this whole thing be up today-ish?
ANDI PENG: Always, yep.
I'm going to try to put
this up like an hour after.
I'll email David, David will try to
put it up like an hour after this.
>> OK, so then we move into this other
lovely data structure called a queue.
As you guys can see here, a
queue, for the British amongst us,
all it is is a line.
So contrary to what
you think a stack is,
a queue is exactly what
logically you think it is.
It's held by the rules of FIFO,
which is First In, First Out.
If you're the first
one in the line, you're
the first one that
comes out of the line.
>> So what we like to call this
is dequeueing and enqueueing.
If we want to add something
to our queue, we enqueue.
If we want to dequeue, or take
something away, we dequeue.
>> So same sense that we're kind of
creating fixed-size elements that we
can store certain
things, but we can also
change where we're placing
parameters inside of them
based on what type of
functionality we want.
So stacks, we wanted the last
one, N to be the first one out.
Queue is we want the first thing
in to be the first thing out.
>> So the struct-type
define, as you can see,
it's a little bit different
from what the stack was
because not only do we have to keep
track of where the size currently is,
we also want to keep track of the head
as well as where we currently are.
So I think it's easier
if I draw this up.
So let's imagine we've got a queue,
so let's say the head is right here.
The head of the line, let's
just say that's currently there,
and we want to insert
something into the queue.
I'm going to call size essentially
is the same thing as tail,
the end of wherever your queue is.
Let's just say size is right here.
>> So how does one feasibly
insert something into a queue?
What index do we want to place
where we want to insert into.
If this is the beginning of your
queue and this is the end of it
or the size of it, where do we
want to add the next object?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ANDI PENG: Exactly, you want to add
it depending on have you written it.
Either this is blank or that is blank.
So you want to add it probably
here because if the size is--
if these are all full, you want
to add it right here, right?
>> And so that's, while very, very
simple, not quite always correct
because the main difference
between a queue and a stack
is that the queue can
actually be manipulated
so that the head changes
depending on where you want
the beginning of your cue to start.
And as a result, your tail
is also going to change.
And so take a look at
this code right now.
As you guys were also asked to
write out on the quiz, enqueue.
Maybe we'll talk through why
the answer was what it was.
>> I couldn't quite fit this line on one,
but essentially this piece of code
should be on one line.
Spend like 30 seconds.
Take a look, and see why
this is the way that it is.
>> Very, very similar struct, very, very
similar structure as the previous
stack except for perhaps
one line of code.
And that one line of code
determines the functionality.
And it really differentiates
a queue from a stack.
>> Anyone want to take a stab
at explaining why you've
got this complicated thing in here?
We see the return of our
wonderful friend modulus.
As you guys will soon come
to recognize in programming,
almost anytime you need something
to wrap around anything,
modulus is going to be the way to do it.
So knowing that, does anyone want
to try explaining that line of code?
Yeah, all answers are
accepted and welcome.
AUDIENCE: Are you talking to me?
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Oh, no sorry.
ANDI PENG: OK, so let's
walk through this code.
So when you're trying to
add something onto a queue,
in the lovely case that the head happens
to be right here, it's very easy for us
to just go to the end
insert something, right?
But the whole point of a queue is
that the head can actually dynamically
change depending on where we
want the start of our q to be,
and as such, the tail
is also going to change.
>> And so imagine that this was not the
queue, but rather this was the queue.
Let's say the head is right here.
Let's say our queue looked like this.
If we wanted to shift where
the beginning of the line is,
let's say we shifted head
this way and sizes here.
>> Now we want to add something to
this queue, but as you guys can see,
it's not so simple as to just
add whatever is after the size
because then we run out of
bounds of our actual array.
Where we want to really add is here.
That's the beauty of a queue
is that to us, visually it
looks like the line goes like this,
but when stored in a data structure,
they give it as like a cycle.
It kind of wraps around
to the front the same way
that a line can also wrap
around depending on wherever you
want to beginning of the line to be.
And so if we take a
look down here, let's
say we wanted to create a
function called enqueue.
We wanted to add int n into that q.
If q.size q-- we'll call that our data
structure-- if our queue.size does not
equal to capacity or if
it's less than capacity,
q.strings is the array within our q.
We're going to set
that equal to q.heads,
which is right here, plus q.size
modulus by the capacity, which
wrap us back around here.
>> So in this example, index
of head is 1, right?
The index of size is 0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
So we can do 1 plus 4 modulus
by our capacity which is 5.
What does that give us?
What is the index that
comes out of this?
>> AUDIENCE: 0.
>> ANDI PENG: 0, which
happens to be right here,
and so we want to be able
to insert into right here.
And so this equation here kind
of just works with any numbers
depending on where your
head and your size are.
If you know what those
things are, you know
exactly where you want to insert
whatever is after your queue.
Does that make sense to everybody?
>> I know kind of a brain
teaser especially since this
came in the aftermath of your quiz.
But hopefully everyone
now can understand
why this solution or this
function is the way that it is.
Anyone a bit unclear on that?
OK.
>> And so now, if you
wanted to dequeue, this
is where our head would be shifting
because if we were to dequeue,
we don't take off the end of the q.
We want to take off the head, right?
So as a result, head is going to change,
and that is why when you enqueue,
you've got to keep track of
where your head and your size
are to be able to insert
into the correct position.
>> And so when you dequeue,
I also pseudocode it out.
Feel free to if you want
to attempt coding this out.
You want to move the head, right?
If I wanted to dequeue, I
would move the head over.
This would be the head.
>> And our current size would
subtract because we no longer
have four elements in the array.
We only have three, and then we want
to return whatever was stored inside
of the head because we want to take this
value out so very similar to the stack.
Just you're taking
from a different place,
and you have to reassign your pointer
to different place as a result.
Logically, everyone follow?
Great.
>> OK, so we're going to talk a bit
more in depth about linked lists
because they'll be very, very valuable
for you in the course of this week's
psets.
Linked lists, as you guys
can remember, all they are
are nodes that are nodes of certain
values of both a value and a pointer
that are linked together
by those pointers.
And so the struct on how
we create a node here is we
have int n, which is whatever
the value in a store or string n
or whatever you want to
call it, the char star n.
Struct node star, which is the pointer
that you want to have in each node,
you're going to have that
pointer point towards next.
You'll have the head
of a linked list that's
going to point to the rest of
the values so on and so forth
until you eventually reach the end.
And this last node is just
going to not have a pointer.
It's going to point to
null, and that's when
you know you've hit the
end of your linked list
is when your last pointer
doesn't point to anything.
>> So we're going to go a bit more in
depth regarding how one would possibly
search a linked list.
Remember what are some of the
drawbacks of the linked lists
verses an array regarding searches.
An array you can binary search, but
why can't you do that in a linked list?
>> AUDIENCE: Because they're all connected,
but you don't quite know where
[INAUDIBLE].
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah, exactly so remember
that the brilliance of an array
was the fact that we had
random access memory where
if I wanted the value from index
six, I could just say index six,
give me that value.
And that's because arrays are sorted
in a contiguous space of memory
in one place, whereas
kind of linked lists
are randomly interspersed all around,
and the only way you can find one
is through a pointer that tells you
the address of where that next node is.
>> And so as a result, the only way
to search through a linked list
is linear search.
Because I don't exactly know where
the 12th value in the linked list is,
I have to traverse the entirety
of that linked list one
by one from the head to the first node,
to the second node, to the third node,
all the way down until I finally get
to where that node I'm looking for is.
And so in this sense, search
on a linked list is always n.
It's always n.
It's always in linear time.
>> And so the code in which
we implement this, and this
is a bit new for you guys since you
guys haven't really talked about or ever
seen pointers in how to
search through pointers,
so we'll walk through
this very, very slowly.
So bool search, right,
let's imagine we want
to create a function called
search that returns true
if you found a value inside the linked
list, and it returns false otherwise.
Node star list is
currently just the pointer
to the first item in your linked list.
int n is the value that you're
searching for in that list.
>> So node star pointer equals list.
That means we're setting
and creating a pointer
to that first node inside of the list.
Everyone with me?
So if we were to go
back here, I would have
initialized a pointer that points to
the head of whatever that list is.
>> And then once you get down here,
while pointer does not equal null,
so that is the loop in which we are
going to be subsequently traversing
the rest of our list because what
happens when pointer equals null?
We know that we have--
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> ANDI PENG: Exactly, so we know that
we've reached the end of list, right?
If you go back here, each node
should be pointing to another node
and so on and so forth
until you hit eventually
the tail of your linked list,
which has a pointer that just
doesn't point anywhere other than no.
And so you basically know that
your list is still there up
until pointer does not equal
null because once it equals null,
you know that there's no more stuff.
>> So that is the loop in which we're
going to have the actual search.
And if the pointer-- do you see
that kind of arrow function there?
So if pointer points to n, if
the pointer at n equals equals n,
so that means that if
the pointer that you're
searching for on the end of each
node is actually equal to the value
you're looking for, then
you want to return true.
So basically, if you're at a node that
has the value that you're looking for,
you know that you've been
able to successfully search.
>> Otherwise, you want to set
your pointer to the next node.
That is what that line here is doing.
Pointer equals pointer next.
Everyone see how that's working?
>> And essentially you're going to just
traverse the entirety of the list,
resetting your pointer each time until
you eventually hit the end of the list.
And you know that there are no
more nodes to search through,
and then you can return false
because you know that, oh, well,
if I've been able to search
through the entirety of the list.
If in this example, if I wanted
to look for the value of 10,
and I start at the head, and
I search all the way down,
and I eventually got to this, which
a pointer that points to null,
I know that, crap, I guess 10 isn't in
this list because I couldn't find it.
And I'm at the end of the list.
And in which case you know
I'm going to return false.
>> Let that soak in for a little bit.
This will be pretty
important for your pset.
The logic of it is very simple, perhaps
syntactically just implementing it.
You guys want to make
sure that you understand.
Cool.
>> OK, so how we would be
inserting nodes, right,
into a list because remember
what are the what of the benefits
of having a linked list versus
an array in terms of storage?
>> AUDIENCE: It's dynamic,
so it's easier to--
>> ANDI PENG: Exactly,
so it's dynamic, which
means that it can expand and shrink
depending on the user's needs.
And so, in this sense, we don't need
to waste unnecessary memory because I
if I don't know how many values I want
to store, it doesn't make sense for me
to create an array because
if I want to store 10 values
and I create an array of 1,000, that's
a lot of wasted memory, allotted.
That's why we want to use a linked
list to be able to dynamically
change or shrink our size.
>> And so that makes insertion
a bit more complicated.
Since we can't randomly access elements
the way that we would of an array.
If I want to insert an element
into the seventh index,
I just can insert it
into the seventh index.
On a linked list, it doesn't
quite work as easily,
and so if we wanted to insert
the one here in the linked list,
visually, it's very easy to see.
We just want to insert it right there,
right at the beginning of the list,
right after head.
>> But the way in which we have to reassign
the pointers is a bit convoluted
or, logically, it makes sense, but
you want to make sure that you have it
completely down because
the last thing you want
is to reassign a pointer the
way that we're doing here.
If you dereference the
pointer from head to 1,
then all of a sudden the
rest of your linked list
is lost because you haven't actually
created a temporary anything.
That's pointed to the 2.
If you reassign the pointer, then the
rest of your list is totally lost.
So you want to be
very, very careful here
to first assign the
pointer from whatever you
want to insert into wherever
you want, and then you
can dereference the rest of your list.
>> So this applies for wherever
you're trying to insert into.
If you want to insert at the
head, if you want to answer here,
if you want to insert at
the end, well, the end I
guess you would just
have no pointer, but you
want to make sure that you don't
lose the rest of your list.
You always want to make sure
your new node is pointing
towards whatever you
want to insert into,
and then you can add the chaining on.
Everyone clear?
>> This is going to be
one of the real issues.
One of the most major issues
you're going to have on your pset
is that you're going to try to create
a linked list and insert things
but then just lose the
rest of your linked list.
And you're going to be like, I
don't know why this is happening?
And it's a pain to go through
and search all of your pointers.
>> And I guarantee you on this pset,
writing and drawing these nodes out
will be very, very helpful.
So you can completely keep track
of where all your pointers are,
what's going wrong,
where all your nodes are,
what you need to do to access or
insert or delete or any of them.
Everyone good with that?
Cool.
>> So if we wanted to look at the code?
Oh, I don't know if we
can see the-- OK, so
at the top all it is is a function
named insert where we want
to insert int n into the linked list.
We're going to walk through this.
It's a lot of code, a lot of new syntax.
We'll be OK.
>> So up at the top, whenever
we want to create anything
what do we need to do, especially if you
want it to not be stored on the stack
but in the heap?
We go to a malloc, right?
So we're going to create a pointer.
Node, pointer, new equals
malloc the size of a node
because we want that node to be created.
We want the amount of
memory that a node takes up
to be allotted for the
creation of the new node.
>> And then we're going to check to
see if new equals equals null.
Remember what we said?
Whatever you malloc,
what must you always do?
You must always check to see
whether or not that is null.
>> For example, if your operating
system was completely full,
if you had no more memory at
all and you try to malloc,
it would return null for you.
And so if you try to use it
when it was pointing to null,
you're not going to able
to access that information.
And so as such, we wanted to make
sure that whenever you're mallocing,
you're always checking to see if
that memory given to you is null.
And if it's not, then we can move
on with the rest of our code.
>> So we're going to
initialize the new node.
We're going to do new n equals n.
And then we're going to do
set new the pointer on new
to null because right now we don't
want anything for it to point to.
We have no idea where
it's going to put you,
and then if we want to
insert it at the head,
then we can reassign
the pointer to the head.
Does everyone follow the logic
of where that's happening?
>> All we're doing is creating a new
node, setting the pointer to null,
and then reassigning
it to the head if we
know we want to insert it at the head.
And then the head is going to
point towards that new node.
Everyone OK with that?
>> So it's a two-step process.
You've got to first assign
whatever you're creating.
Set that pointer to the
reference, and then you
can kind of dereference
the first pointer
and point it towards the new node.
Wherever you want to insert it,
that logic is going to hold true.
>> It's kind of like assigning
temporary variables.
Remember, you've got
to make sure that you
don't lose track of if you're swapping.
You want to make sure that you have a
temporary variable that kind of keeps
track of where that thing
is stored so that you
don't lose any value in the course
of like messing around with it.
>> OK, so code will be here.
You guys take a look after section.
It will be there.
>> So I guess how does
this differ if we wanted
to insert into the middle or the end?
Does anyone have an idea of what's the
pseudocode as the logical reference
that we would take if we wanted
to insert it in the middle?
So if we wanted to insert it at the
head, all we do is create a new node.
We set the pointer of that
new node to whatever the head,
and then we set the head
to the new node, right?
If we wanted to insert it in the middle
of the list, what would we have to do?
>> AUDIENCE: It would still
be a similar process
of like assigning pointer and
then assigning that pointer,
but we would have to locate there.
>> ANDI PENG: Exactly, so exactly
the same process except you
have to locate where exactly you
want that new pointer to go into,
so if I want to insert into
the middle of linked list-- OK,
let's say that's our linked list.
If we want to insert it right here,
we're going to create a new node.
We're going to malloc.
We're going to create a new node.
We're going to assign the
pointer of this node here.
>> But the problem that differs
from where the head is
is that we knew exactly
where the head is.
It was right at the first, right?
But here we've got to keep track
of where we're inserting it into.
If we are inserting our
node here, we've got
to make sure that the
one previous to this node
is the one that reassigns the pointer.
So then you have to kind of
keep track of two things.
If you keep track of where this
node currently is inserting into.
You also have to keep track of where
the previous node that you're looking at
was also there.
Everyone good with that?
OK.
>> How about inserting into the end?
If I wanted to add it here-- if I wanted
to add a new node to the end of a list,
how might I go about doing that?
AUDIENCE: So currently, the
last one's pointed to null.
ANDI PENG: Yeah.
Exactly, so this one
currently is pointed to know,
and so I guess, in this sense, it's
very easy to add to the end of a list.
All you have to do is set it
equal to null and then boom.
Right there, very easy.
Very simple.
>> Very similar to the
head, but logically you
want to make sure that the steps
you take towards doing any of this,
you're following along.
It's very easy to, in the middle
of your code, get caught up on,
oh, I've got so many pointers.
I don't know where
anything is pointing to.
I don't even know which node I'm on.
What's going on?
>> Relax, calm down, take a deep breath.
Draw out your linked list.
If you say, I know where exactly
I need to insert this into
and I know exactly how to reassign my
pointers, much, much easier to picture
out-- much, much easier to not
get lost in the bugs of your code.
Everyone OK with that?
OK.
>> So I guess a concept that we haven't
really talked about before now,
and I guess you probably
won't encounter much yet--
it's kind of an advanced concept--
is that we actually have a data
structure called a doubly linked list.
So as you guys can see,
all we're doing is creating
an actual value, an extra
pointer on each of our nodes
that also points to the previous node.
So not only do we have our
nodes point to the next one.
They also point to the previous one.
I'm going to ignore these two right now.
>> So then you have a chain
that can move both ways,
and then it's a bit easier
to logically follow along.
Like here, instead of
keeping track of, oh, I
have to know that this node is
the one that I have to reassign,
I can just go here and
just pull the previous.
Then I know exactly where
that is, and then you
don't have to traverse the
entirety of the linked list.
It's a bit easier.
>> But as such, you have doubly
the amount of pointers,
that's double the amount of memory.
It's a lot of pointers to keep track of.
It's a bit more complex, but it's
a bit more user friendly depending
on what you're trying to accomplish.
>> So this type of data
structure totally exists,
and the structure for is very, very
simple except all you're having is,
instead of just a pointer to next,
you also have a pointer to previous.
That's all the difference was.
Everyone good with that?
Cool.
>> All right, so now I'm
to really spend probably
like 15 to 20 minutes or the bulk
of the rest of the time in section
talking about hash tables.
How many of you guys
have read pset5 spec?
All right, good.
That's higher than the 50% of normally.
It's OK.
>> So as you guys will see,
you're challenge in pset5
will be to implement a dictionary
where you load over 140,000 words
that we give you and spell check
it against all of the text.
We'll give you random
pieces of literature.
We'll give you The Odyssey.
We'll give you The Iliad.
We'll give you Austin Powers.
>> And your challenge
will be to spell check
every single word in all
of those dictionaries
essentially with our spell checker.
And so there's a few parts
of creating this pset,
first you want to be
able to actually load
all the words into your
dictionary, and then you
want to be able to
spell check all of them.
And so as such, you're going to require
a data structure that can do this fast
and efficiently and dynamically.
>> So I suppose the easiest
way to do this, you
would probably create an array, right?
The easiest way of storage is you
can create an array of 140,000 words
and just place them all there and
then traverse them by binary search
or by selections or not--
sorry that's sorting.
You can sort them and then traverse them
by binary search or just linear search
and just final the words, but that
takes a huge amount of memory,
and it's not very efficient.
>> And so we're going to start
talking about ways of making
our running time more efficient.
And our goal is to get
constant time where
it's almost like arrays, where
you have instantaneous access.
If I wanted to search for anything,
I want to be able to just,
boom, find it exactly, and pull it out.
And so a structure in which
we'll be becoming very close
to be able to access constant
time, this holy grail
in programming of constant
time is called a hash table.
And so David previously mentioned the
[INAUDIBLE] a little bit in lecture,
but we're going to really
dive in deep this week
on a piece that's regarding
how a hash table works.
>> So the way that a hash
table works, for example,
if I wanted to store a bunch of words, a
bunch of words in the English language,
I could theoretically put
banana, apple, kiwi, mango, pair,
and cantaloupe all on just an array.
They could all fit in and be find.
It'd be kind of a pain to
search through and access,
but the easier way of doing this is
that we can create actually a structure
called a hash table where we hash.
We run all of our keys through
a hash function, an equation,
that turns them all into
some sort of a value
that then we can store onto
essentially an array of linked list.
>> And so here, if we wanted
to store English words,
we could potentially just, I don't
know, turn all the first letters
into some sort of a number.
And so, for example, if I wanted
A to be synonymous with apple--
or with the index of 0, and
B to be synonymous with 1,
we can have 26 entries
that can just store
all of the letters of the
alphabet that we'll start with.
And then we can have
apple at the index of 0.
We can have banana at the index of
1, cantaloupe at the index of 2,
and so on and so forth.
And thus if I wanted to search
my hash table and access apple,
I know apple starts with
an A, and I know exactly
that it must be and the hash
table at index 0 because
of the function previously assigned.
>> So I don't know, we are
a user program where
you'll be charged with
arbitrarily-- not arbitrarily,
with trying to thoughtfully
think of good equations
to be able to spread
out all of your values
in a way they can easily access
it later on with like an equation
that you, yourself, know.
So in the sense if I wanted to go to
mango, I know, oh, it starts with m.
It must be at the index of 12.
I don't have to search through anything.
I know exactly-- I could just go to
the index of 12 and pull that out.
>> Everyone clear on how a
hash table's function works?
It's kind of just a more complex array.
That's all it is.
OK.
>> So I guess we run into
this issue of what
happens if you have multiple things
that give you the same index?
So say our function, all it
did was take that first letter
and turn that into a
respective 0 through 25 index.
That's totally fine if
you only have one of each.
But the second you start
having more, you're
going to have what's called a collision.
>> So if I try to insert bury into a hash
table that already has banana on it,
what's going to happen when
you try to insert that?
Bad things because banana
already exists within the index
that you want to store it in.
Berry kind of is like, ah, what do I do?
I don't know where to go.
How do I resolve this?
>> And so you guys will kind of
see we do this tricky thing
where we can kind of actually
create linked list in our arrays.
And so the easiest way
to think about this,
all hash table is an
array of linked lists.
And so, in that sense, you have
this beautiful array of pointers,
and then each pointer in
that value, in that index,
can actually point to other things.
And so you have all these separate
chains coming off of one big array.
>> And so here, if I
wanted to insert berry,
I know, OK, I'm going to input
it through my hash function.
I'm going to end up with the index of
1, and then I'm going to be able to have
just a smaller subset of this
giant 140,000-word dictionary.
And then I can just look
through 1/26 of that.
>> And so then I can just insert
berry either before or after banana
in this case?
After, right?
And so you're going to want to
insert this node after banana,
and so you're going to insert
at the tail of that linked list.
I'm going to go back
to this previous slide,
so you guys can see how
hash function works.
>> So hash function is this equation
that you're running kind of your input
through to get whatever index
you want to assign it towards.
And so, in this example, all we wanted
to do was take the first letter,
turn that into an index, then we
can store that in our hash function.
All we're doing here is we're
converting the first letter.
So keykey[0] is just the first letter
of whatever string we're having,
we're passing in.
We're converting that to upper, and
we're subtracting by uppercase A,
so all that is doing
is giving us a number
in which we can hash our values onto.
>> And then we're going to
return hash modulus SIZE.
Be very, very careful
because, theoretically, here
your hash value could be infinite.
It could just go on and on and on.
It could be some really,
really large value,
but because your hash table that
you've created only has 26 indexes,
you want to make sure your
modulusing so that you
don't run-- it's the same
thing as your queue--
so that you don't run off the
bottom of your hash function.
>> You want to wrap it back around
the same way in [INAUDIBLE] when
you had like a very,
very large letter, you
didn't want that to
just run off the end.
Same thing here, you want to make sure
it doesn't run off the end by wrapping
around to the top of the table.
So this is just a very
simple hash function.
All that did was take the first
letter of whatever our input was
and turn that into an index that
we could put into our hash table.
>> Yeah, and so as I said before,
the way that we resolve collisions
in our hash tables are having,
what we call, chaining.
So if you try to insert multiple
words that start with the same thing,
you're going to have one hash value.
Avocados and apple, if you've
run it through our hash function,
are going to give you the
same number, the number of 0.
And so the way we resolve that is
that we can actually kind of link them
together via linked lists.
>> And so in this sense,
you guys can see kind
of how data structures that
we've been setting previously
like a raisin linked list kind
of can come together into one.
And then you can create far
more efficient data structures
that can handle larger amounts of
data, that dynamically resize depending
on your needs.
Everyone clear?
Everyone kind of clear
on what happens here?
>> If I wanted to insert-- what's a
fruit that starts with, I don't know,
B, other than berry, banana.
>> AUDIENCE: Blackberry.
>> ANDI PENG: Blackberry, blackberry.
Where does blackberry go here?
Well, we actually haven't sorted
this yet, but theoretically
if we wanted to have this
in alphabetical order,
where should blackberry go?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> ANDI PENG: Exactly, after here, right?
But since it's very difficult to
reorder-- I guess it's up to you guys.
You guys can totally
implement whatever you want.
The more efficient way
of doing this perhaps
would be to sort your linked
list into alphabetical order,
and so when you're
inserting things, you want
to be sure to insert them
into alphabetical order
so that then when you're
trying to search them,
you don't have to traverse everything.
You know exactly where
it is, and it's easier.
>> But if you kind of have
things interspersed randomly,
you're still going to have
to traverse it anyways.
And so if I wanted to just
insert blackberry here
and I wanted to search for
it, I know, oh, blackberry
must start with the index of 1, so I
know instantaneously just search at 1.
And then I can kind of
traverse the linked list
until I get to blackberry,
and then-- yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: If you're trying to create--
I guess like this is a very simple hash
function.
And if we wanted to do
multiple layers of that like,
OK, we want to separate into
like all the alphabetical letters
and then again to like another set
of alphabetical letters within that,
are we putting like a hash
table within a hash table,
or like a function within a function?
Or is that--
>> ANDI PENG: So your hash
function-- your hash table
can be as large as you want it to.
So in this sense, I thought
it was very easy, very
simple for me to just sort based
on letters of the first word.
And so there's only 26 options.
I can only get 26 options from
0 to 25 because they can only
start from A to Z. But If you wanted
to add, perhaps, more complexity
or faster run time to your
hash table, you absolutely
can do all sorts of things.
You can make your own
equation that gives you
more distribution in your
words, then when you search,
it's going to be faster.
>> It's totally up to you guys
how you want to implement that.
Think of it as just buckets.
If I wanted to have
26 buckets, I'm going
to sort things into those buckets.
But I'm going to have a bunch
of stuff in each bucket,
so if you want to make it
faster and more efficient,
let me have a hundred buckets.
>> But then you have to figure out a
way to sort things so that they are
in the proper bucket they should be in.
But then when you actually
want to look at that bucket,
it's a lot faster because there's
less stuff in each bucket.
And so, yeah, that's actually
the trick for you guys in pset5
is that you'll be
challenged to just create
whatever is the most efficient
function you can think of to be
able to store and check these values.
>> Totally up to you guys
however you want to do it,
but that's a really good point.
That the kind of logic you
want to start thinking about
is, well, why don't I make more buckets.
And then I have to search
less things, and then maybe I
have a different hash function.
>> Yeah, there's a lot of ways to do this
pset, some are faster than others.
I'm totally going to just see how
fast was the fastest you guys will
be able to get your functions to work.
OK, everyone good on
chaining and hash tables?
It's actually like a very simple
concept if you think about it.
All it is is separating whatever
your inputs are into buckets,
sorting them, and then searching the
lists that there's associated with.
>> Cool.
All right, now we have a different sort
of data structure that's called a tree.
Let's go on and talk about tries
which are distinctly different,
but in the same category.
Essentially, all a tree is instead
of organizing data in the linear way
that a hash table does-- you
know, it's got a top and a bottom
and then you kind of link off of it-- a
tree has a top which you call the root,
and then it has leaves all around it.
>> And so all you have here
is just the top node
that points to other nodes, that points
to more nodes, and so on and so forth.
And so you just have splitting branches.
It's just a different way of organizing
data, and because we call it a tree,
you guys just-- it's just
modeled out to look like a tree.
That's why we call it trees.
>> Hash table looks like a table.
A tree just looks like a tree.
All it is is a separate
way of organizing nodes
depending on what your needs are.
>> So you have a root and
then you have leaves.
The way that we can particularly
think about it is a binary tree,
a binary tree is just a
specific type of a tree
where each node only points
to, at max, two other nodes.
And so here you have distinct
symmetry in your tree
that makes it easier to kind of look
at what values you are because then you
have always a left or a right.
There's never like a left third from
the left or a fourth from the left.
It's just you have a left and a right
and you can search either of those two.
And so why is this useful?
The way that this is
useful is if you're looking
to search through values, right?
Rather than implementing binary
search in an error array,
if you wanted to be able to insert nodes
and take away nodes at will and also
preserve the search
capacities of binary search.
So in this way, we're kind of
tricking-- remember when we
said linked lists can't binary search?
We're kind of creating a data structure
that tricks that into working.
>> And so because linked lists are linear,
they only link one after the other.
We can kind of have
different sort of pointers
that point to different nodes
that can help us with search.
And so here, if I wanted to
have a binary search tree,
I know that my middle if 55.
I'm just going to create that
as my middle, as my root,
and then I'm going to have
values spin off of it.
>> So here, if I'm going to search for
the value of 66, I can start at 55.
It's 66 greater than 55?
Yes it is, so I know I mus search
i n the right pointer of this tree.
I go to 77.
OK, is 66 less than or greater than 77?
It's less than, so you know, oh,
that has to be the left node.
>> And so here we're kind of preserving
all of the great things about arrays,
so like dynamic resizing
of objects, being
able to insert and delete at will,
without having to worry about the fixed
amount of space.
We still preserve all of
those wonderful things
while also being able to preserve the
log and search time of binary search
that we were only previously
able to get a phrase.
>> Cool data structure, kind of
complex to implement, the node.
As you can see, all it
is the struct of the node
is that you have a left
and a right pointer.
That's all it is.
So rather than just
having an x or a previous.
You have a left or a right, and then
you can kind of link them together
however you so choose.
>> OK, we're actually going
just take a few minutes.
So we're going to go back here.
As I said previously,
I kind of explained
the logic behind how we
would search through this.
We're going to try
pseudocoding this out to see
if we can kind of apply the
same logic of binary search
to a different type of data structure.
If you guys want to take like a couple
minutes to just think about this.
OK.
All right, I'm going to
actually just give you the-- no,
we'll talk about the pseudocode first.
So does anyone want
to give a stab at what
the first thing you want to do when
you're starting out searching is?
If we're looking for
the value of 66, what's
the first thing we want to do if
we want to binary search this tree?
>> AUDIENCE: You want to look right
and look left and see [INAUDIBLE]
greater number.
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah, exactly.
So you're going to look at your root.
There's lots of ways you can call
it, your parent node people say.
I like to say root because
that's like the root of the tree.
You're going to look at
your root node, and you're
going to see is 66 greater
than or less than 55.
And if it's greater than, well, it is
greater than, where do we want to look?
Where do we want to search now, right?
We want to search the
right half of this tree.
>> So we have, conveniently, a
pointer that points to the right.
And so then we can set
our new root to be 77.
We can just go to wherever
the pointer is pointing.
Well, oh, here we're starting
at 77, and we can just
do this recursively again and again.
In this way, you kind
of have a function.
You have a way of searching that you
can just repeat over and over and over,
depending on where you want to look
until you eventually get to the value
that you're searching for.
Make sense?
>> I'm about to show you the actual
code, and it's a lot of code.
No need to freak out.
We'll talk through it.
>> Actually, no.
That was just pseudocode.
OK, that was just the pseudocode,
which is a bit complex,
but it's totally fine.
Everyone following along here?
If the root is null, return
false because that means
you don't even have anything there.
>> If root n is the value, so if it
happens to be the one you're looking at,
then you're going to return true
because you know you found it.
But if the value is less
than root of n, you're
going to search the left
child or the left leaf,
whatever you want to call it.
And if the value is greater than root,
you're going to search the right tree,
then just run the function
through search again.
>> And if root is null, that that
means you've reached the end?
That means you have no
more more leaves to search,
then you know, oh, I
guess it's not in here
because after I've looked through
the whole thing and it's not here,
it just might not be here.
>> Does that make sense to everybody?
So it's like binary search preserving
the capabilities of linked lists.
Cool, and so the second type
of data structure you guys
can try implementing on your pset,
you only have to choose one method.
But perhaps an alternative method to
the hash table is what we call a trie.
>> All a trie is is a
specific type of tree that
has values that go to other values.
So instead of having a binary
tree in the sense that only one
thing can point to two, you can have
one thing point to many, many things.
You essentially have arrays
inside of which you store
pointers that point to other arrays.
>> So the node of how we
would define a trie
is we want to have a
Boolean, c word, right?
So the node is Boolean
like true or false,
first of all at the head of
that array, is this a word?
Secondly, you want to have pointers
to whatever the rest of them are.
A bit complex, a bit abstract, but
I will explain what that all means.
>> So here, at the top, if you
have an array declared already,
a node where you have a Boolean
value stored at the front
that tells you is this a word?
Is this not a word?
And then you have the
rest of your array that
actually stores all the
possibilities of what it could be.
So, for example, like
at the top you have
the first thing that says true or
false, yes or no, this is a word.
>> And then you have 0 through 26 of
the letters that you can store.
If I wanted to search here
for bat, I go to the top
and I look for B. I find B in my
array, and so I know, OK, is B a word?
B is not a word, so thus
I must keep searching.
I go from B, and I look to the
pointer that B points towards
and I see another array of information,
the same structure that we had before.
>> And here-- oh, the next
letter in [INAUDIBLE] is A.
So we look in that array.
We find the eighth value,
and then we look to see, oh,
hey, is that a word, is B-A a word?
It is not a word.
We've got to keep looking.
>> And so then we look to where
the pointer of A points,
and it points to another way in
which we have more value stored.
And eventually, we get to
B-A-T, which is a word.
And so the next time
you look, you're going
to have that check of, yes,
this Boolean function is true.
And so in the sense we're kind
of having a tree with arrays.
>> So then you can kind of search down.
Rather than hashing a function and
assigning values by linked list,
you can just implement a
trie that searches downwords.
Really, really complicated stuff.
Not easy to think about because I'm like
spitting so many data structures out
at you, but does everyone kind of
understand how the logic of this works?
>> OK, cool.
So B-A-T, and then
you're going to search.
The next time you're going
to see, oh, hey, it's true,
thus I know this must be a word.
>> Same thing for zoo.
So here's the thing right now, if we
wanted to search for zoo, right now,
currently zoo is not a
word in our dictionary
because, as you guys can see, the
first place that we have a Boolean
return true is at the end of zoom.
We have Z-O-O-M.
>> And so here, we don't actually have
the word, zoo, in our dictionary
because this check box is not checked.
So the computer doesn't
know that zoo is a word
because the way that we've
stored it, only a zoom here
actually has a Boolean value
that's been turned true.
So if we want to insert the
word, zoo, into our dictionary,
how would we go about doing that?
What do we have to do to make sure our
computer knows that Z-O-O is a word
and not the first word is Z-O-O-M?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> ANDI PENG: Exactly, we
want to make sure that this
here, that Boolean value is
checked off that it's true.
Z-O-O, then we're going to check that,
so we know exactly, hey, zoo is a word.
I'm going to tell the
computer that it's a word so
that when the computer checks,
it knows that zoo is a word.
>> Because remember all these data
structures, it's very easy for us
to say, oh, bat's a word.
Zoo's a word.
Zoom's a word.
But when you're building it,
the computer has no idea.
>> So you have to tell it exactly
at what point is this a word?
At what point is it not a word?
And at what point do I
need to search things,
and at what point do I need to go next?
Everyone clear of that?
Cool.
>> And so then comes the
problem of how would we
go about inserting something
that's actually not there?
So let's just say we want to insert
the word, bath, into our trie.
As you guys can see like currently
all we have now is B-A-T,
and this new data structure
there had a pint that
pointed to null because we assume
that, oh, there's no words after B-A-T,
why do we need to keep
having things after that T.
>> But the problem arises if we do you
want to have a word that comes after
the T's.
If you have bath, you're
going to want an H right.
And so the way we're going to do that is
we're going to create a separate node.
We're not allot whatever amount
of memory for this new array,
and we're going to reassign pointers.
>> We're going to assign the
H, First of all, this null,
we're going to get rid of.
We're going to have
the H point downwards.
If we see an H, we want it
to go to somewhere else.
>> In here, we can then check off yes.
If we hit an H after the T, oh,
then we know that this is a word.
The Boolean is going to return true.
Everyone clear on how that happened?
OK.
>> So essentially, all of
these data structures
that we've gone over today, I've
gone over them really, really quickly
and not in to much
detail, and that's OK.
Once you start messing
with it, you'll be
keeping track of where
all the pointers are,
what's going on in your
data structures, et cetera.
They'll be very useful,
and it's up to you
guys to totally figure out how
you want to implement things.
>> And so pset4, of 5-- oh, that is wrong.
Pset5 is misspellings.
As I said before, you're going to, once
again, download source code from us.
There's going to be three main
things you'll be downloading.
You'll download dictionaries,
kers, and texts.
>> All those things are are
either dictionaries of words
that we want you to check
or test of information
that we want you to spell check.
And so the dictionaries
we give you are going
to give you actual words that we want
you to store somehow in a way that's
more efficient than an array.
And then the texts are
going to be what we're
asking you to spell check to make sure
all of the words there are real words.
>> And so the three blocks of
programs that we'll give you
are called dictionary.c,
dictionary.h, and speller.c.
And so all dictionary.c does is
what you're asked to implement.
It loads words.
It spell checks them, and it makes sure
that everything is inserted properly.
>> diction.h is just a library file
that declares all those functions.
And speller.c, we're going to give you.
You don't need to modify any of it.
All speller.c does is take that,
loads it, checks the speed of it,
tests the benchmark of like how
quickly you're able to do things.
>> It's a speller.
Just don't mess with it, but make
sure you understand what it's doing.
We use a function called getrusage that
tests the performance of your spell
checker.
All it does is basically test the
time of everything in your dictionary,
so make sure you understand it.
Be careful to not mess with it or
else things will not run properly.
>> And the bulk of this challenge is for
you guys to really modify dictionary.c.
We're going to give you
140,000 words in a dictionary.
We're going to give you a text
file that has those words,
and we want you to be able to organize
them into a hash table or a trie
because when we ask you to spell
check-- imagine if you're spell
checking like Homer's Odyssey.
It's like this huge, huge test.
>> Imagine if every single
word you had to look
through an array of 140,000 values.
That would take forever
for your machine to run.
That is why we want to organize our
data into more efficient data structures
such as a hash table or a trie.
And then you guys can kind
of when you search access
things more easily and more quickly.
>> And so be careful to resolve collisions.
You're going to get a bunch
of words of that start with A.
You're going to get a bunch words
that start with B. Up to you
guys how you want to resolve it.
Perhaps there's more
efficient hash function
than just the first letter of
something, and so that's up to you
guys to kind of do whatever you want.
>> Maybe you want to add
all the letters together.
Maybe you want to like do weird things
to account the number of letters,
whatever.
Up to you guys how you want to do.
If you want to do a hash table, if you
want to try a trie, totally up to you.
I will warn you ahead of time that the
trie is typically a bit more difficult
just because there's a lot
more pointers to keep track of.
But totally up to you guys.
It's far more efficient
in most instances.
You want to really be able to keep
track of all of your pointers.
Like do the same thing
that I was doing here.
When you're trying to insert
values into a hash table or delete,
make sure that you're
really keeping track
of where everything is because
it's really easy for if I'm
trying to insert like the word, andy.
Let's just say that's a
real word, the word, andy,
into a giant list of A words.
>> If I just happen to reassign
a pointer wrong, oops,
there goes the entirety of
the rest of my linked list.
Now the only word I
have is andy, and now
all of the other words in the
dictionary have been lost.
And so you want to make sure you
keep track of all of your pointers
or else you're going to get
huge problems in your code.
Draw things out carefully step by step.
It makes it a lot easier to think of.
>> And lastly, you want to be able to
test your performance of your program
on the big board.
If you guys take a
look at CS50 right now,
we have what's called the big board.
It is the score sheet of the fastest
spell checking times across all of CS50
right now, I think the top like 10
times I think eight of them are staff.
We really want you guys to beat us.
>> All of us were trying to implement
the fastest code as possible.
We want you guys to try to challenge
us and implement faster than all of us
can.
And so this is really
the first time that we're
asking you guys to do a pset that
you can really do in whatever method
you want.
>> I always say, this is more akin
to a real-life solution, right?
I say, hey, I need you to do this.
Build a program that does this for me.
Do it however you want.
I just know that I want to fast.
That's your challenge for this week.
You guys, we're going
to give you a task.
We're going to give you a challenge.
And then it's up to you guys
to completely just figure out
what's the quickest and most
efficient way to implement this.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Are we allowed to if
wanted to research faster ways
to do hash tables online, can we do
that and cite someone else's code?
ANDI PENG: Yeah, totally fine.
So if you guys read the
spec, there's a line
in the spec that says you guys
are totally free to research hash
functions on what are some
of the quicker hash functions
to run things through as
long as you cite that code.
So some people have already
figured out fast ways
of doing spell checkers, of fast
ways of storing information.
Totally up to you guys if you
want to just take that, right?
Make sure you're citing.
The challenge here really
that we're trying to test
is making sure that you know
your way around pointers.
As far as you implementing
the actual hash function
and coming up with like
the math to do that,
you guys can research whatever
methods online you guys want.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Can we cite just
by using the [INAUDIBLE]?
>> ANDI PENG: Yeah.
You can just, in your comment,
you can cite like, oh,
taken from yada, yada,
yada, hash function.
Anyone have any questions?
We actually breezed
through section today.
I will be up here to
answer questions as well.
>> Also, as I said, office
hours tonight and tomorrow.
The spec this week is actually
super easy and super short to read.
I would suggest taking a look, just
read through the entirety of it.
>> And Zamyla actually walks you
through each of the functions
you need to implement, and so it's
very, very clear how to do everything.
Just to make sure you're
keeping track of pointers.
This is a very challenging pset.
>> It's not challenging because like,
oh, the concepts are so much more
difficult, or you have to learn
so much new syntax the way
that you did for the last pset.
This pset is difficult because
there are so many pointers,
and then it's very, very easy to once
you have a bug in your code not be able
to find where that bug is.
>> And so complete and utter faith in you
guys to be able to beat our [INAUDIBLE]
spellings.
I actually haven't any written mine
yet, but I'm about to write mine.
So while you're writing
yours, I'll be writing mine.
I'm going to try to make
mine faster than yours.
We'll see who has the fastest one.
>> And yeah, I will see all of
you guys here on Tuesday.
I will run a kind like a pset workshop.
All of the sections this
week are pset workshops,
so you guys have lots of opportunities
for help, office hours as always,
and I really look forward to
reading all of your guys' code.
I have quizzes up here if you
guys want to come get those.
That's all.