>> BRIAN SCASSELLATI: Welcome
to the CS50 AI video series.
My name is Scas.
And today, we're going to be
talking about self-driving cars.
Now, I'm a little bit
embarrassed to admit that when
I was a kid a large part of my childhood
revolved around David Hasselhoff.
Now, this was before he was involved
in anything like America's Got Talent,
or involved as a lifeguard in Baywatch,
or even before he had sort of history
as a pop star in Germany.
>> In my childhood, David Hasselhoff
was the supporting actor
on a well-known television
series called Knight Rider.
And I say he was the supporting actor,
because really the star of this show
was a car, a Trans Am named
Kit, who could drive by itself.
Kit was amazing.
It could talk to you.
>> It could solve problems.
It could drive all over the place.
It also had lasers and rockets.
So it was a fantastic
vehicle to start with.
>> But this was the science
fiction of the time,
autonomous cars that
could make decisions,
that could drive along the road.
And at every point in
one of these episodes,
David Hasselhoff would
get in trouble and the car
would start driving and go and save him.
That was our science fiction.
>> Even in just the last 30
years, that science fiction
has gone from on television
and on the screen
into reality, into commercial products.
Today, we're going to talk about how it
is that autonomous vehicles are really
able to go and drive and to
absolutely amazing things.
But let's start with the history.
>> Because these self-driving cars
didn't come out of nowhere.
And in fact, the very
first self-driving cars,
the really first influential
research projects,
came out of a project called Navlab.
Navlab was a project that spanned
almost two decades at Carnegie Mellon
University.
>> And they built a variety
of different vehicles
that started out looking
like small minivans, that
were Humvees, that were eventually just
sedans, and minivans, even city buses.
And these different devices
have sensors in them,
had computational
systems put into them, so
that they could steer, and brake,
and accelerate autonomously
all on their own.
Now, these systems were
very primitive at the start.
>> And they relied upon very
specific lane markings.
So the most impressive system that
they had built was part of Navlab five.
And in 1995, this
vehicle, it was minivan,
drove from Pittsburgh to San
Diego, almost 3,000 miles.
And 98% of the time, the only
thing controlling the steering
was the computer.
>> 98% of the time, it was
completely autonomous
as it drove almost from coast to coast.
Now, that's incredibly impressive.
And when we think about that,
there's a lot for us to consider.
>> What kinds of sensors was it using?
What kind of decision
was it really making?
What was that other 2% of the time?
>> We're going to try to get to
some of these issues today.
And as we look at them,
we're going to try
to uncover what it is that
the structure underneath
and how the computation is directly
driving these applications.
Now, Navlab was a tremendous success.
And it was the basis of all of our
modern thoughts about autonomous
vehicles.
>> But self-driving cars didn't really
become well-known and popular
until in 2005 DARPA, as part of
their grand challenge effort,
put together a program to try
to build an autonomous vehicle.
And they made this a challenge.
They put a $2 million prize
out there with the idea
that some really smart research
team would come along and be
able to claim this $2 million prize.
>> Now, the prize wasn't
going to be easy to get.
In order to get the
prize, you would have
to build a vehicle that
with no human intervention
was able to drive 150 mile
course through the rough terrain
of the desert.
And that was a lot task.
>> And at the time, people thought that
they were really crazy in doing this.
So the first meeting of the
grand challenge was in 2004.
And out of that 150 mile course, the
farthest, the best team that they had,
went about 11 miles before
the system failed completely.
>> Now, to give you an idea
of how difficult that is,
that 11 miles was seen as an
absolute phenomenal success.
But DARPA wanted more.
And so they offered this same
prize the following year.
>> And just one year later,
the technology had
advanced to the point where not just one
system was able to complete the course,
but five different robot
cars finished that course.
The fastest one finished 132
miles in under seven hours.
That was a robot called Stanley.
>> Stanley was built by the
Stanford racing team.
And as you can see at
the top, it had a number
of different sensors up on the
hood, up on the top of the vehicle,
and all throughout.
Using a combination of cameras,
infrared, and regular light,
using radar and sonar systems on board,
using laser range finders to detect
obstacles, this vehicle was able
to navigate over very rough terrain
autonomously steering,
autonomously breaking, autonomously
applying the gas.
>> That was a real achievement.
Today, we see this happening
even as a grander scale.
Many of you have heard of
the Google self-driving car.
And these vehicles have logged over 1.2
million miles in the last few years,
no human intervention whatsoever.
>> In fact, every time
that the Google car has
been involved in any kind of accident,
it's either been because it was parked,
or because some human was
so interested in what it
was doing that they ran into the car.
So with all of these systems,
we see this complexity emerging.
And in this very short
period of time, we've
gone from the realm of science
fiction to commercial reality.
>> So let's start to take
these systems apart.
Let's try to understand how it is that
they work, what do they actually doing.
To do that, we're going to
use the same kinds of skills
that we've talked about in class.
Whenever you see a problem,
what we're going to try to do
is to try to decompose it.
>> Start with the simplest
form that we can.
And then build outward
from that simple form.
So that leads us to the question, what
is the simplest form of autonomous
driving?
At what point is a computer
actually in control of my car?
>> Now, the answer may surprise you there.
Because almost every vehicle sold
today in the US or Europe or anywhere
actually is partially
an autonomous vehicle.
Using systems like anti-lock brakes,
these systems are really autonomous.
>> That is, when I step on the break,
what I'm doing is I'm asking the car
please break now.
I'm not actually directly
stepping on something that
applies the brake pad to the rotor.
And the whole point of anti-lock brakes
is that at some point along the way
I'll be able to press down on the break.
>> But the car will recognize
that the wheel is slipping.
And it will throttle that break signal,
so that the brake doesn't lock up.
These anti-lock brake systems are,
in a way, making decisions for you.
>> And really, they're the ones that
are in charge of the braking system.
You're making a request.
But you're not actually in control.
>> So we could try to recognize this and
break it down into the component parts.
And we could think about it as
a little bit of pseudocode code.
That is, while I'm
stepping on the brake,
while I'm applying pressure
to the brake pedal,
anti-lock brake system
is checking continuously
to see is each of these wheels slipping.
>> And using some internal
sensors within the car,
they're detecting whether
or not the wheel is actually
stopping or whether it's sliding.
And if it's sliding, the anti-lock
brake systems disengages the brakes,
and then lets it go.
And when the wheels stop
sliding, it reapplies them.
>> That is, I'm making a request.
I'm stepping on the brake.
But the actual breaking is being
decided by this small piece of software.
So really, all of our cars are
already autonomous vehicles.
>> Now, that's not what we think about
when we think about autonomous vehicles.
We think about cars where I can
take my hands away from the wheel,
and we can just let it go.
Now, that's not happening on a
grand scale everywhere yet today.
>> But there are pieces of
that that are starting
to come into the commercial sector.
Since 2003, Toyota, and following
that many other manufacturers,
everyone from Ford and
Lincoln to Mercedes Benz,
has been offering some type
of intelligent parking assist.
That is, there are sensors
in the car, typically
ultrasonic sensors for short
range detection of obstacles,
that are able to recognize where
there are cars, vehicles, people,
any type of obstacle around the vehicle.
>> You then press a button on the dash
and ask the car, please park now.
You issue a request.
The autonomous system then takes
over and using those sensors
is able to guide the car into
a particular parking position.
In some of these models, there's
a parallel parking version
and a backing into a spot version.
>> And each of these different applications
evokes a different piece of software.
Now, that software
isn't anything strange
or isn't anything that you
can't understand at this point.
It's just following
these sensor signals.
>> If there's something to
close on the left-hand side
and I have space on the right,
then I'll steer a little bit,
so that I can move over to the right.
Many of the early parking systems
would control the steering angle,
but require the user, the human driver,
to actually step on the accelerator
or step on the break.
More modern systems actually control
that completely by themselves.
>> So for example, in a Mercedes
S Class vehicle right
now, you can pull alongside where
you'd like to park, press a button,
and it will parallel park for you
without your hands on the wheel
or your feet on the pedals.
Now all of these systems
rely upon the sensors
that they are building
into these vehicles today.
And whether we use those sensors
for detecting potential obstacles
and alerting the user or whether we use
those sensors to detect an obstacle,
and then automatically steer away,
that's just a matter of software.
>> In fact, just a few
weeks ago, Tesla, who's
been building fantastic vehicles with
all of these sensors in them for years
now, issued a software update.
And that software update allowed
the vehicles for the first time
to enter an automatic driving
more, an auto pilot they called it.
This auto pilot allowed the vehicle
to detect collisions and automatically
break, to follow another vehicle
that's in front of it, matching speed,
to stay within the lanes, to look with
cameras, both infrared and visible
light, and to be able
to say whether or not
you're drifting out of your lane or
not, adjust the steering appropriately,
and even to change lanes
when the user signals.
>> All of these different features were
just a matter of a software update.
That is, all of these
users woke up one morning
to find this new software
available in their vehicles.
Because the sensor systems
were already there.
>> Now, in all of these cases,
we're seeing these software
based systems becoming
more and more prevalent.
They're out there in
commercial products already.
And the future is that we're
going to see more of that.
>> In fact, just this
year, Freightliner was
able to unveil an autonomous truck,
an autonomous tractor trailer,
that they're testing legally
on the road in Nevada.
These vehicles, again,
follow a predetermined route.
They stay within their lane.
>> They accelerate and
decelerate in response
to obstacles or traffic conditions.
And they even obey some of the
other niceties of the road.
All of these systems are
becoming more and more complex.
>> But they're still not quite autonomous.
They're still not
quite doing everything.
That is, they're still
requiring a human driver
to be present to make
some high level decisions.
>> And one of the things that we're
going to see in the next five years
are a variety of legal
and ethical questions
that revolve around the software
being built for these driverless cars.
How is it that a driverless
car should respond if it's
surrounded by a group of people?
What happens if the driverless
car is skidding on the road
and you can steer towards a crowd
of 10 people or a crowd of 7 people?
What should the car do?
>> In all of these cases, there's a rich
variety of questions to be asked.
And they are not just software
questions, legal questions,
ethical questions,
philosophical questions.
And they are ones that we as a
community will have to address.
>> So I'll leave you with one last
thought, this one from Randall Munroe,
of XKCD, one of my favorite comics.
It's not just that we're going to see
these vehicles being built and being
designed with software.
But we're going to see people
try to exploit them as well.
>> How is it going to be when someone
can, over Wi-Fi, download a patch
or upload a virus to your car?
What kinds of things will happen then?
This one's a little bit
more playful of an example.
But these are the questions
we're going to deal with soon.
>> Thanks for joining me.
I hope you've enjoyed it.
And we'll see you next time.