DOUG LLOYD: In this video we're going
to talk about the Transmission Control
Protocol, TCP.
If you haven't watched the
video on internet protocol, IP,
you may wish to do so
before watching this video
because the two are pretty interrelated.
>> So, the internet protocol,
again, a quick summary,
that's the protocol
that moves information
from a sending machine to a receiving
machine through the network.
>> So what's TCP?
While just moving from a sending
machine to receiving machine,
isn't the full story.
We also know that our program,
our computers, for example,
are running multiple programs,
and have multiple services
running on those machines.
And so, if we want to get a packet,
or information to a specific program,
on a specific machine,
we need more information
than just what IP allows us to get
information from point A to point B.
>> So, TCP can be thought of
as directing the packet
to the correct program, or the correct
service, on the receiving machine.
And so it's important to, as you might
expect, know where it's supposed to go,
and what the packet is
for at the same time.
And so, frequently, when you talk about
transmission control protocol, TCP,
you really often hear it in the
context, TCP slash IP, or just TCP/IP.
These two protocols are so
interrelated that, they're basically
treated as a single unit.
But they are two separate protocols
that do two separate things.
>> Again, IP is responsible for getting
it from one machine to another.
And TCP is responsible for
getting it to the correct program,
or the correct service on a machine.
And it does something
else that IP doesn't do,
which is guarantee delivery.
>> So, if we now couple a machine's IP
address with the so-called port number,
and a port number is how a specific
service, or utility, or program,
is identified on a machine.
If we now have an IP
address plus a port number,
now we can uniquely identify
a particular service
running on a particular machine.
>> So that's why TCP and IP are
so frequently interrelated,
because that port number
on its own doesn't really
mean anything if you need a
port number, and the machine
that you're talking about.
What machine is supposed to be using
this particular port, for example.
>> The other thing that TCP does, as
I said, is it guarantees delivery.
So, in addition to
specifying the port number,
it also indicates how many
packets, the internet protocol, IP,
has split the data into.
And it orders those packets so they
can be reconstructed on the receiving
machine, even if they received-- in a
different order than they were sent.
Which can happen because IP
is a connectionless protocol,
and so different packets can take
different paths through the system.
>> Some of these port numbers
are very commonly used,
and they've been standardized
across all computers,
like, pretty much every
computer manufacturer now.
So something called FTP,
the file transfer protocol,
which is used to transmit
files, as you might expect,
from one machine to another,
that uses port 21 conventionally.
Email, SMTP, uses port 25.
DNS, the domain name system, which we
talked about in our internet primer
video, uses port 53.
If you're ever browsing
the web, you're pretty much
always using port 80, unless
you're browsing the web securely,
secure web browsing, using port 443.
>> So what's this TCP/IP process?
What's happening with both
of these protocols together?
Well, let's talk about it.
When a program wants to send data,
TCP helps break it into chunks,
and communicates those packets to
the computer's networked software.
So it takes the data and it
wraps information around it
that indicates what port
is supposed to go to,
and what order that
packet is out of all.
So make packet one of 10, two
of 10, three of 10, and so on.
>> IP gets those data chunks that
have been wrapped with TCP,
and wraps more information about
where the packet is supposed to go.
We might call this the IP
layers surrounding the packet.
So, it's sort of, like,
one of those nesting dolls.
We have the data in the
middle, and then TCP on top of,
telling it where the
data inside of TCP is
supposed to go, to what port
or what service on a machine.
Around that is the IP layer.
What IP address, what machine,
is actually getting this.
>> So then, that packet that's been
wrapped with all those layers,
is sent through internet protocol
through the system of routers, getting
from point A to point B. When the
receiving machine, or device, gets
it, it looks at the IP
layer, it says, yup that's
my IP address, so it takes
off, sort of cracks the egg,
and takes off the IP layer.
Then it sees that there's
a TCP layer, and it says,
OK, looks like this is
going to port x, or port y.
And apparently it's
packet number eight of 15.
So that's good to know.
So then it can take that information,
take off the TCP layer now,
knowing that it's for port x,
and it's packet number eight,
and get at the data inside.
And it can prepare the data to
be organized in the correct way.
And once all of the
data is received, TCP
can hand it off to the correct
service, and say, here you go.
Here's the data that you received.
That process might look
something like this.
So let's send an email from
a sender to a receiver.
And let's say this
email is pretty small,
so we only need to break it into
four packets, and we'll call them A,
B, C, and D. Well, we want to move
that first packet what happens?
Well, we take that chunk of data,
the data that is part of packet A,
and around that we're going
to wrap it with a TCP layer.
Emails, you may recall,
are sent via port 25,
and we have four chunks of data,
here, that we're going to be using,
and this is the first of them.
So maybe our TCP layer contains
information about, well, we're
going to port 25, and this
is packet number one of four.
>> Around that, so now we have all that
information bundled up together,
we're going to say where we want it
to go, what machine, what IP address
is supposed to get this packet.
And that's part of the IP layer.
And there's other information
in there as well, such
as the return address in
case something goes wrong,
it knows where to send
information back, and so on.
>> But the IP layer goes
around all of that.
That entire thing is bundled
together, as one big unit,
and sent through an IP transfer.
So it gets routed through the router
network, using internet protocol.
And the receiver receives
the entire thing.
And then it can start to
deconstruct what's happening here.
It looks at the IP layer, the
outside layer of this data,
and says, yep, that's my IP
address so we can discard that.
I can, kind of, ignore it,
doesn't need it anymore,
and it can look one level deeper.
It sees that, OK, this is data that
is intended to be received on port 25.
It's apparently the first part of four.
So, I'm going to keep that in
mind, and look at the data,
and slot it roughly where
I think it's going to go.
Now, because of the internet protocol
it's not necessarily the case
that the next packet the
receiver gets, is packet two.
In fact, the next
thing the receiver gets
might be packet number
three because these packets
took different paths because of
different traffic on the network.
And so, I'm not going to go
through the diagram of building it
up again, but packet three
moves, gets stripped away
of all of its layers, the
IP layer, the TCP layer,
and the data gets put in the right spot.
And then, let's say it
receives packet four.
>> Now let's say, that's it, it
doesn't get any more data.
What is it going to do?
IP doesn't do anything for us.
But TCP does.
TCP knows, well, I've received one of
four, three of four, and four of four.
I'm not getting any more data.
So something has gone wrong.
But I can guarantee delivery.
I know that packet
number two is missing.
And so TCP can now make a request,
sort of, in the reverse direction.
Bundling up its request
in much the same way,
and sending it via IP,
which, I know, could
lead to some sort of infinite loop of
everybody dropping packets on the way.
>> But suffice it to say that TCP
says, I'm missing a packet.
I need to send information
back to the sender.
Fortunately the sender's IP address is,
sort of, bundled up in the IP layer.
It's part of-- it's the return
address on the envelope.
And say, I'm missing packet number
two, can you please resend it.
When the sender receives
that information,
it doesn't have to send
the entire email again.
It only needs to send that individual
piece of it that was missing,
so we could send packet number two.
And when it gets it, now TCP says,
I have all four pieces of data
that I need.
So, I can assemble them together, and
take this entire block of information
and pass it along to port 25, where
it will be interpreted as an email.
And that-- in this way we've
now send an email from sender
to receiver using TCP/IP.
So, as I said, if at any point
along the way something went wrong,
TCP can deal with it.
It can make a request that the
information gets sent back to it.
And it can reconstruct the message.
And once it's reconstructed the message
from all the packets it's received,
then it can organize them and
deliver them to the correct service.
>> So that's TCP in a nutshell.
That's how we guarantee
delivery of information.
Remember the TCP
frequently works with IP,
so these two protocols
really do go hand in hand.
We discussed them in several videos
here because they do different things,
but they're so interrelated, they
you'll usually use them together.
>> I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.