DOUG LLOYD: As you start
working with functions,
another thing is going to become
really important to understand,
which is the concept of variable scope.
So scope is a
characteristic of a variable
that defines from which functions
that variable can be accessed.
>> There are two primary scopes in C,
local variables and global variables.
Now, local variables can only
be accessed within the functions
in which they're created.
They can't be accessed by every other
function that exists in your program,
only the function in
which it was created.
Global variables, on the
other hand, can be accessed
by any function in the program.
And the reason for that is
because they're not created inside
of any particular function.
We declare them outside of
all of the functions, which
means that every function knows where
it is and can access and manipulate it.
>> So far in the course you've pretty
much been working exclusively
with local variables.
Here's an example of a very, very
simple main function and a very simple
additional function that we've written.
In this case, x, which
I've colored green just
to highlight the locality or
the scope of that variable,
is local to the function triple.
main cannot refer to x at all.
It doesn't know what it is.
No other function, in fact, if we
had additional functions in here,
could refer to x.
>> Similarly, results which I've
colored blue, is local only to main.
Only main knows what
the variable result is.
triple cannot use it.
>> Now as I mentioned,
global variables do exist.
If you declare that variable
outside of any function,
all of the functions in the
program can refer to it.
So in this case I've highlighted in
green a global variable declaration.
In this case, the
variable being declared
is called global, just to
be extremely clear about it.
It is of type float.
And I assign it the value 0.5050.
>> You'll notice that in main and in
triple, I am able to refer to global.
And in fact, if I go through the program
as indicated, main first calls triple,
triple multiplies global by 3, which
sets its value to 1.5-something,
1.51 or something like that, and
then main also prints out the value
of global.
So main will not print out 0.5050, it
will print out global times 3, 1.51.
So you've got to be careful when
you're working with global variables.
While they're very flexible in
being able to pass information
around so that every
function can use it,
it also can have some
dangerous consequences
if one function changes
the value of a variable
before you expect it to be changed.
>> Why does this distinction matter?
Why do we care whether some variables
are local and others are global?
Well, for the most part, local variables
in C are what's called passed by value
when we make a function call.
What does that mean?
>> Well, when a variable is passed
by value, the callee, which
is another way of saying the function
that is receiving the variable that
gets passed in as an input, it actually
doesn't receive that variable itself.
It receives its own
copy of it to work with.
This is a really important distinction.
We just saw a second ago
that with global variables,
if we manipulate the global
variable in one function, the effect
in that one function carries
through to every other function.
>> But with local variables,
that's not true.
Each function when it
receives variables as input
receive copies of those variables,
not the variables themselves.
So what is the side effect of that?
That means that the variable in
the caller, the function that
is making the function call, is
unchanged unless you override it.
>> For example, in this code
foo is not changed at all.
Int foo equals 4, call triple
of foo, inside of triple,
we would expect that foo would
be multiplied by 3 and returned,
but there's actually no effect.
>> Here though, a very subtle difference.
This does have the effect we want.
Do you see why?
We're overriding foo in main this time.
>> So int foo equals 4, foo equals
triple foo, when we make that call,
triple gets its own copy
of foo, its own copy of 4.
It says return 4 times 3, or whatever
variable gets passed in times 3.
And then we assign the return
value of triple to foo again.
So this actually would overwrite foo.
This is the only way to do
this with local variable.
So now if we add another
line of code here
at the end of main to
print out the value of foo,
it would in fact print out 12.
>> Variable scope is generally
not too much of a problem
if you name all of your
variables different things.
But it can get kind of nasty
if the same variable name
appears in multiple functions,
which will happen a lot.
If you ever do work in
the real world where
you are working on collaborative
programs and people in different teams
are working together to write the same
program or the same set of programs,
they'll frequently reuse variable
names, particularly common ones
like x, y, i, j, and so on.
>> But when variables have
the same name, scope issues
can get a little trickier to parse.
For example, do you know
what would be printed out
at the end of this particular program?
Take a minute.
Pause the video and read
through this program.
You can see at the top we
have a function declaration
for a function called increment.
That function takes a single
parameter, an integer which we call x.
And it outputs an integer.
That's the return type at the beginning.
>> Then we have main, a couple of lines
of code in main, the last of which
is a print statement.
And remember, that's the question here.
What is actually going to be
printed at the end of this function?
And then we actually have the
definition of increment below.
>> So take a minute, step through
the code, trace things out.
Do you know what will be printed at
the end of this particular program?
>> All right.
Hopefully, you've taken a few seconds
to try and parse this one out.
Let's do it together.
>> So I've crossed out increment's
declaration at the top there.
It was kind of a distraction.
It's not its own variable.
It doesn't have its own scope.
It's just a function
declaration, so for purposes
of trying to parse out what's
happening in this program,
we might as well just avoid it.
>> Now we have in this case, the
reason this problem is tricky
is because we have local variables in
both main and increment, each of which
is called x.
And of course the crux of this issue is
trying to suss out which x gets changed
and how does it get changed.
So I've colored every instance
of x that's local to main red.
And I've colored every instance of
x that's local to increment blue.
>> Notice in that third line
of main, y equals increment
x, that increment is not being
passed main's x, or the red x.
It's getting passed a copy of it.
And it's only going to work with
that copy of it, the blue x.
If you're mathematically
inclined, you might
have instead thought of this as x sub
m for main and x sub i for increment.
But it's the same idea.
x sub m, or the red x's
in the previous slide,
are the variables that are local--
is the instance of x rather that
is local to main, and x sub i, or the
blue variables in the previous slide,
are the instances of x that
are local to increment.
>> So, were you able to figure out what
this function printed at the end?
I'm Doug Lloyd, and this is CS50.