>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -He's lying.
>> -About what?
>> -I don't know.
>> -So what do we know?
>> -That at 9:15, Ray
Santoya was at the ATM.
-Yeah.
So the question is, what
was he doing at 9:16?
>> -Shooting the 9 millimeter at something.
Maybe he saw the sniper.
>> -Or was working with him.
>> -Wait.
Go back one.
>> -What do you see?
>> -Bring his face up full screen.
>> -His glasses.
>> -There's a reflection.
>> -It's the Nuevitas baseball team.
That's their logo.
>> -And he's talking to
whoever's wearing that jacket.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50 and this is a bit more
of [INAUDIBLE] with which you're
dabbling with problem set four.
Today we start to look a little more
deeply at these things called pointers,
which even though it's
a pretty arcane topic,
it turns out that it's going
to be the means by which we
can start building and assembling
much more sophisticated programs.
But we did it on last Wednesday
by way of some claymation first.
So this, recall, is
Binky and we used him
to take a look at a program that
didn't really do anything interesting,
but it did reveal a few problems.
So to begin today, why don't we walk
quickly through a few of these steps,
try to distill into human's terms
exactly what's going on here
and why this is bad, and then move on
and actually start building something
with this technique?
So these were the first
two lines in this program
and in layman's terms, what
are these two lines doing?
Someone who's reasonably comfortable
with what's declared on the screen?
What are these two lines doing?
It's not all that
different from week one,
but there is some new special symbol.
Yeah?
Back there.
>> AUDIENCE: Declaring pointers?
DAVID MALAN: Say again?
AUDIENCE: Declaring pointers?
DAVID MALAN: Declaring pointers and
let's refine it a little bit more.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
address x and then y.
DAVID MALAN: And then address.
So specifically what we're doing
is we are declaring two variables.
These variables, though, are going
to be of type int star, which
more specifically means
they are going to store
the address of an int,
respectively, x and y.
Now are there any values?
Are there any actual addresses in these
two variables at this point in time?
No.
It's just so-called garbage values.
If you don't actually assign a
variable, whatever was in RAM
previously is going to fill with zeros
and ones both of those variables.
But we don't yet know
what they are and that's
going to be key to why Binky
lost his head last week.
>> So this was the claymation
incarnation of this
whereby you have just two variables,
little circular pieces of clay,
that can store variables, but as
the wrapped up arrows suggest,
they're not actually pointing
to anywhere known per se.
So then we had this line, and this
was new last week, malloc for memory
allocation, which is just a fancy way
of telling the operating system, Linux
or Mac OS or Windows,
hey, give me some memory,
and all you have to tell
the operating system
is what when asking it for memory.
It's not going to care what
you're going to do with it,
but you do need to tell the operating
system what by way of malloc.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: How much?
DAVID MALAN: How much?
How much in bytes, and so, this, again,
a contrived example, is just saying,
give me the size of an int.
Now, the size of an int
is four bytes or 32 bits.
So this is just a way of
saying, hey, operating system,
give me four bytes of memory
that I can use at my disposal,
and specifically, what does
malloc return with respect
to that chunk of four bytes?
AUDIENCE: Address?
DAVID MALAN: The address.
The address of that chunk of four bytes.
Exactly.
And so that's what's stored ultimately
in x and that's why we don't really
care what the number of that
address is, whether it's ox1 or ox2
or some cryptic hexadecimal address.
We just care pictorially
that that variable x is now
pointing to that chunk of memory.
So the arrow represents a pointer, or
more specifically, a memory address.
But again, we don't typically care
what those actual addresses are.
Now, this line says
what in layman's terms?
Star x gets 42 semicolon.
What does this mean?
You wanna go?
Don't scratch your neck.
>> AUDIENCE: The address of x is at the 42.
>> DAVID MALAN: The address of x is at 42.
Not quite.
So close, but not quite, because there's
the star that's prefixing this x.
So we need to tweak a little bit.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: The value that the
pointer x is pointing to is 42.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
The value that the pointer x is
pointing to, let's say, shall be 42,
or put another way, the star
x says, go to whatever address
is in x, whether it's 1 Oxford
Street or 33 Oxford Street
or ox1 or ox33, whatever
that numeric address is,
star x is the dereferencing of x.
So go to that address and
then put the number 42 there.
So that would be an
equivalent way of saying that.
So that's all fine and then
we would represent the picture
as follows where we've added
the 42 to that chunk of four
bytes on the right-hand side, but
this line was where things went awry
and Binky's head popped
off at this point,
because bad things happen when
you dereference garbage values
or you dereference invalid
pointers, and I say invalid
because at this point in the
story, what is inside of y?
What's the value of y based
on the past few steps?
Yeah?
What's that?
>> AUDIENCE: An address.
DAVID MALAN: An address.
It should be an address
but have I initialized it?
So I haven't yet.
So what is known to be in there?
It's just some garbage value.
It could be any address from zero to
2 billion if you have two gigs of RAM,
or zero to 4 billion if you've
got four gigabytes of RAM.
It's some garbage value,
but the problem is
that the operating system,
if it hasn't given you
that chunk of memory specifically
that you're trying to go to,
it's generally going to cause what
we've seen as a segmentation fault.
So in fact, any of you who have
struggled at problems at office hours
or in problems that's more
generally with trying to figure out
a segmentation fault,
that generally means
you're touching a segment of
memory that you shouldn't be.
You're touching memory that
the operating system has not
allowed you to touch, whether it's
by going too far in your array
or starting now, whether
it's because you're touching
memory that just is some garbage value.
>> So doing star x here is
sort of undefined behavior.
You should never do it because odds
are, the program's just going to crash,
because you're saying,
go to this address
and you have no idea where
that address actually is.
So the operating system is likely
going to crash your program
as a result and indeed, that's
what happened there to Binky.
So ultimately, Binky fixed
this problem with this.
So that program itself was flawed.
But if you sort of forge ahead
and execute this line instead,
y equals x just means whatever
address is an x, also put it in y.
>> And so pictorially, we've
represented this with two arrows
from x and from y pointing
to the same place.
So semantically, x is equal
to y because both of those
are storing the same
address, ergo pointing at 42,
and now, when you say star
y, go to the address in y,
this has an interesting side effect.
So the address in y is the
same thing as the address in x.
So if you say go to the address
in y and change the value to 13,
who else is affected?
X is, point D, so to speak,
should be affected as well.
>> And indeed, how Nick drew this picture
in claymation was exactly that.
Even though we follow the pointer
y, we ended up in the same place,
and so if we were to print
out x or y's pointee,
then we would see the value of 13.
Now, I say pointee to be
consistent with the video.
Programmers, to my
knowledge, never actually
say the word pointee,
that which is pointed
at, but for consistency
with the video, realize
that's all that was
meant in that situation.
So any questions on claymation
or pointers or malloc just yet?
No?
All right.
>> So without further
ado, let's take a look
at where this has actually
been used for some time.
So we've had this CS50 library
that's got all of these functions.
We've used GetInt a lot, GetString,
probably GetLongLong earlier
in my PSet one or so, but
what's actually been going on?
Well, let's take a quick look
underneath the hood at a program that
inspires why we give you the CS50
library, and indeed as of last week,
we started taking those
training wheels off.
So this is now sorted
of a postmortem of what
has been going on
inside the CS50 library,
even though we now will start moving
away from it for most programs.
>> So this is a program called scanf 0.
It's super short.
It just has these lines, but it
introduces a function called scanf
that we're actually going to see in
a moment inside of the CS50 library,
albeit in a slightly different form.
So this program on line 16
is declaring a variable x.
So give me four bytes for an int.
It's been telling user,
number please, and then
this is an interesting line that
actually ties together last week
and this.
Scanf, and then notice it takes a
format string, just like printf,
%i means an int, and then it takes a
second argument which looks a little
funky.
It's ampersand x, and to recall,
we only saw this once last week.
What does ampersand x represent?
What does ampersand do in C?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: The address of.
DAVID MALAN: The address of.
So it's the opposite
of the star operator,
whereas the star operator says, go to
this address, the ampersand operator
says, figure out the
address of this variable,
and so this is key, because
scanf's purpose in life
is to scan the user's
input from the keyboard,
depending on whatever he or she
types, and then read that user's input
into a variable, but we
saw in the past two weeks
that that swap function that we
tried effortlessly to implement
was just broken.
Recall that with the swap function,
if we just declared A and B as ints,
we did successfully swap the
two variables inside of swap
just like with the milk and OJ,
but as soon as swap returned,
what was the result with respect
to x and y, the original values?
Nothing.
Yeah.
Nothing happened that time, because
swaps change only its local copies,
which is to say, all
this time, whenever we've
been passing in arguments
to functions, we're
just passing copies of those arguments.
You can do with that
whatever you want with them,
but they're going to have no
effect on the original values.
So this is problematic if you
want to have a function like scanf
in life, whose purpose is to scan
the user's input from the keyboard
and then fill in the blanks, so to
speak, that is, give a variable like x
a value, because if I were
to just pass x to scanf,
if you consider the logic of last
week, scanf can do whatever it wants
with a copy of x, but it couldn't
permanently change x unless we give
scanf a treasure map, so to speak,
where x marks the spot, whereby
we pass in the address of x so that
scanf can go there and actually change
the value of x.
And so indeed, all
that this program does
if I make scanf 0, in my source
5m directory, make scanf 0,
dot slash scanf, number
please 50, thanks for the 50.
>> So it's not all that interesting,
but what's indeed happening
is that as soon as I call
scanf here, the value of x
is being permanently changed.
Now, this seems nice and
good, and in fact, it
seems like we don't really need
the CS50 library at all anymore.
For instance, let's run
this once more here.
Let me reopen it for a second.
Let's try a number please and
instead of saying 50 like before,
let's just say no.
OK, that's a little weird.
OK.
And just some nonsense here.
So it doesn't seem to
handle erroneous situations.
So we need to minimally start
adding some error-checking
to make sure that the user has
typed in an actual number like 50,
because apparently typing words
isn't detected as problematic,
but it probably should be.
>> Let's look at this version now that's
my attempt to reimplement GetString.
If scanf has all this
functionality built in,
why have we been dabbling with these
training wheels like GetString?
Well, here is perhaps my own
simple version of GetString
whereby a week ago, I might have said,
give me a string and call it buffer.
Today, I'm going to start just
saying char star, which, recall,
it's just synonymous.
It looks scarier but it's
the exact same thing.
So give me a variable called buffer
that's going to store a string,
tell the user string please,
and then, just like before,
let's try to borrow this lesson scanf
%s this time and then pass in buffer.
Now, a quick sanity check.
Why am I not saying
ampersand buffer this time?
Infer from the previous example.
AUDIENCE: Char star is a pointer.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly,
because this time, char
star is already a pointer, an address,
by definition of that star being there.
And if scanf expects an address,
it suffices just to pass in buffer.
I don't need to say ampersand buffer.
For the curious, you could
do something like this.
It would have different meaning.
This would give you a pointer
to a pointer, which is actually
a valid thing in C, but for
now, let's keep it simple
and keep the story consistent.
I'm just going to pass in
buffer and that's correct.
The problem though is this.
Let me go ahead and run this
program after compiling it.
Make scanf 1.
Damn it, my compiler's
catching my error.
Give me one second.
Clang.
Let's say scanf-1.c.
OK.
There we go.
I need it.
CS50 ID has various
configuration settings
that protect you against yourself.
I needed to disable those by
running clang manually this time.
So string please.
I'm going to go ahead and type
in my favorite hello world.
OK, null.
That's not what I typed.
So it's indicative of
something being wrong.
Let me go ahead and type
in a really long string.
Thanks for the null and I don't know
if I'm going to be able to crash it.
Let's try a little copy
paste and see if this helps.
Just paste a lot of this.
It's definitely a bigger
string than usual.
Let's just really write it.
No.
Damn it.
Command not found.
So that's unrelated.
That's because I pasted
some bad characters,
but this turns out is not going to work.
>> Let's try this once more, because
it's more fun if we actually crash it.
Let's type this and now, I'm
going to copy a really long string
and now let's see if we
can crash this thing.
Notice I omitted spaces and
new lines and semicolons
and all funky characters.
Enter.
And now the network's just being slow.
I held down Command-V too long, clearly.
Damn it!
Command not found.
>> OK.
Well, the point is
nonetheless the following.
So what is actually going
on with this declaration
of char star buffer on line 16?
So what am I getting
when I declare a pointer?
All I'm getting is a four byte value
called buffer, but what's inside of it
at the moment?
It's just some garbage value.
Because any time you declare a variable
in C, it's just some garbage value,
and we're starting to
trip over this reality.
Now, when I tell scanf,
go to this address
and put whatever the user types in.
If the user types in hello
world, well, where do I put it?
Buffer is a garbage value.
>> So that's kind of like an arrow
that's pointing who knows where.
Maybe it's pointing
right here in my memory.
And so when the user
types in hello world,
the program tries to put the
string hello world backslash 0
in that chunk of memory.
But with high probability, but
clearly not 100% probability,
the computer is going to then crash
the program because this is not
memory I should be allowed to touch.
So in short, this program is
flawed for exactly that reason.
I'm fundamentally not doing what?
What steps have I omitted, just like
we omitted with Binky's first example?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Memory allocation?
>> DAVID MALAN: Memory allocation.
I haven't actually allocated
any memory for that string.
So we can fix this in a couple of ways.
One, we can keep it simple
and in fact, now you're
going to start to see a blurring
of the lines between what
an array is, what a string is, what a
char star is, what an array of chars
is.
Here's a second example
involving strings and notice
all I've done on line
16 is, instead of saying
that buffer is going to be a char
star, a pointer to a chunk of memory,
I'm going to very proactively give
myself a buffer for 16 characters,
and in fact, if you're familiar
with the term buffering,
probably from the world of videos,
where a video is buffering, buffering,
buffering.
Well, what's the connection here?
Well, Inside of YouTube
and inside of video players
generally is an array
that's bigger than 16.
It might be an array of size one
megabyte, maybe 10 megabytes,
and into that array does your browser
download a whole bunch of bytes,
a whole bunch of megabytes of
video, and the video player,
YouTube's or whoever's, starts
reading the bytes from that array,
and any time you see the
word buffering, buffering,
that means the player has
gotten to the end of that array.
The network is so slow that it hasn't
refilled the array with more bytes
and so you're out of bits
to display to the user.
>> So buffer is an apt term here in that
it's just an array, a chunk of memory.
And this will fix it
because it turns out
that you can treat arrays as though
they are addresses, even though buffer
is just a symbol, it's a
sequence of characters, buffer,
that's useful for me, the programmer,
you can pass its name around
as though it were a
pointer, as though it
were the address of a chunk
of memory for 16 chars.
So that's to say, I can pass
the scanf exactly that word
and so now, if I make this program,
make scanf 2, dot slash scanf 2,
and type in hello world,
Enter, that time--
>> Hmm, what happened?
String please.
What did I do wrong?
Hello world, buffer.
Hello world.
Ah, I know what it's doing.
OK.
So it's reading up
until the first space.
So let's cheat for just a moment and
say I just wanted to type something
really long like this is a long sentence
that's one, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine,
10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.
OK.
It is indeed a long sentence.
So this sentence is
longer than 16 characters
and so when I hit Enter,
what's going to happen?
Well, in this case of the
story, I had declared buffer
to actually being an array
with 16 chars ready to go.
So one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight, nine, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14,
15, 16.
So 16 characters, and now, when I
read in something like this is a long
sentence, what's going to happen is
that I'm going to read in this is a long
S-E-N-T-E-N-C-E, sentence.
>> So this is deliberately
a bad thing that I
keep writing beyond the
boundaries of my array,
beyond the boundaries of my buffer.
I could get lucky and the program
will keep on running and not care,
but generally speaking, this
will indeed crash my program,
and it is a bug in my
code the moment I step
beyond the boundaries
of that array, because I
don't know if it's
necessarily going to crash
or if I'm just going to get lucky.
So this is problematic because in
this case, it does seem to work
and let's tempt fate here, even though
the IDE seems to tolerate quite a bit
of--
>> There we go.
Finally.
So I'm the only one that can see this.
So I just had a lot of fun typing
out a really long actual phrase
that it certainly exceeded
16 bytes, because I
typed in this crazy long multi-line
phrase, and then notice what happened.
The program tried printing it
and then got a segmentation fault
and segmentation faults is when
something like this happens
and the operating system says
no, cannot touch that memory.
We're going to kill
the program altogether.
>> So this seems problematic.
I've improved the program whereby
at least have some memory,
but this would seem to confine
the function GetString to getting
strings of some finite length 16.
So if you want to support longer
sentences than 16 characters,
what do you do?
Well, you can increase the
size of this buffer to 32
or that seems kind of short.
Why don't we just make
it 1,000 but push back.
What's the response intuitively of
just avoiding this problem by making
my buffer bigger, like 1,000 chars?
By implementing GetString this way.
What's good or bad here?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: If you bind up a lot
of space and you don't use it,
then you can't reallocate that space.
DAVID MALAN: Absolutely.
It's wasteful insofar as if you don't
actually need 900 of those bytes
and yet you're asking for
1,000 in total anyway,
you're just consuming more memory on
the user's computer than you need to,
and after all, some of
you've already encountered
in life that when you're
running lots of programs
and they're eating up lots of memory,
this can actually impact performance
and the user's experience
on the computer.
So that's kind of a lazy solution,
for sure, and conversely,
it's not only wasteful, what problem
still remains, even if I make my buffer
1,000?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: The string is length 1,001.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
If your string is length 1,001,
you have the exact same problem,
and by my argument, I would
just then make it 2000,
but you don't know in
advance how big it should be,
and yet, I do have to compile my program
before letting people use and download
it.
So this is exactly the kind of
stuff that the CS50 library tries
to help us with and we'll only glance
at some of the underlying implementation
here, but this is CS50 dot C. This
is the file that's been on CS50 IDE
all these weeks that you've been using.
It's pre-compiled and you've
been using it automatically
by nature of having the
dash L CS50 flag with clang,
but if I scroll down through all of
these functions, here's GetString,
and just to give you a
taste of what's going on,
let's take a quick look at
the relative complexity.
It's not a super long
function, but we didn't
have to think all hard about
how to go about getting strings.
>> So here's my buffer and I
apparently initialize it to null.
This, of course, is the
same thing as char star,
but I decided in
implementing the CS50 library
that if we're going to
be completely dynamic,
I don't know in advance how big of a
string users are going to want to get.
So I'm going to start
with just an empty string
and I'm going to build up as much
memory as I need to fit the user string
and if I don't have
enough, I'm going to ask
the operating system for more memory.
I'm going to move their string
into a bigger chunk of memory
and I'm going to release or free the
insufficiently large chunk of memory
and we're just going
to do this iteratively.
>> So a quick glance,
here's just a variable
with which I'm going to keep track
of the capacity of my buffer.
How many bytes can I fit?
Here's a variable n with
which I'm going to keep
track of how many bytes are actually in
the buffer or that the user has typed.
If you've not seen this before, you
can specify that a variable like an int
is unsigned, which as the name suggests,
means it's non-negative, and why would
I ever want to bother specifying
that an int isn't just an int,
but it's an unsigned int?
It's a non-negative int.
What does the [INAUDIBLE] mean?
>> AUDIENCE: It's describing an amount
of memory that can be [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So if I say unsigned, this is actually
giving you one bit of extra memory
and it seems kind of silly, but if you
have one bit of additional memory, that
means you have twice as many
values you can represent,
because it can be a 0 or a 1.
So by default, an int can be roughly
negative 2 billion all the way
up to positive 2 billion.
Those are big ranges, but
it's still kind of wasteful
if you only care about
sizes, which just intuitively
should be non-negative or
positive or 0, well then,
why are you wasting 2 billion
possible values for negative numbers
if you're never going to use them?
So by saying unsigned, now my int can
be between 0 and roughly 4 billion.
>> So here's just an int C for reasons
we won't get into just now as
to why it's an int instead
of a char, but here is
the gist of what's going
on, and some of you
might be using, for instance, the
fgetc function even in PSet four
or thereafter, we'll see it
again in problem set five,
fgetc is nice because as the name
kind of, sort of arcanely suggests,
it's a function that
gets a character and so,
what's fundamentally different
about what we're doing in GetString
is we're not using
scanf in the same way.
We are just creeping along step-by-step
over whatever the user has typed in,
because we can always allocate one
char, and so we can always safely
look at one char at a time, and
the magic starts to happen here.
I'm going to scroll down to
the middle of this function
just to introduce briefly this function.
Much like there's a
malloc function, there's
a realloc function where realloc
lets you reallocate a chunk of memory
and make it bigger or smaller.
So long story short and with
a wave of my hand for today,
know that what GetString
is doing is it's sort
of magically growing or
shrinking the buffer as the user
types in his or her string.
>> So if the user types a
short string, this code
only allocates enough
memory to fit the string.
If the user keeps typing
as I did it again and again
and again, well, if the
buffer's initially this big
and the program realizes, to
wait a minute, I'm out of space,
it's going to double
the size of the buffer
and then double the size of the buffer
and the code that does the doubling,
if we look at it here, it's
just this clever one-liner.
You might not have seen this syntax
before, but if you say star equals,
this is the same thing as
saying capacity times 2.
So it just keeps doubling
the capacity of the buffer
and then telling realloc to give
itself that much more memory.
>> Now, as an aside, there
are other functions in here
that we won't look into any detail
other than to show in GetInt,
we use GetString in GetInt.
We check that it's not
null, which, recall,
is the special value that
means something went wrong.
We're out of memory.
Better check for that.
And we return a sentinel value.
But I'll defer to the comments as to
why and then we use this cousin of scanf
called sscanf and it turns out
that sscanf, or string scanf,
lets you take a look at the line that
the user has typed in and let you
analyze it essentially and what I'm
doing here is I'm telling sscanf,
analyze whatever the user has
typed in and make sure %i,
there is an integer in it, and we won't
get into today exactly why there's also
a %c here, but that in a nutshell allows
us to detect if the user has typed
in something bogus after the number.
So the reason that GetInt and GetString
tell you to retry, retry, retry
is because of all of
that code we've written,
it's kind of looking at the user's input
in making sure it's entirely numeric
or it's an actual floating
point value or the like,
depending on what value
function you're using.
>> Whew.
OK.
That was a mouthful
but the point here is
that the reason we had
those training wheels on
is because at the lowest level,
there is just so many things that
can go wrong that we wanted
to preemptively handle
those things certainly in the
earliest weeks of the class,
but now with PSet four and PSet five and
beyond will you see that it's more unto
you but also you're more capable
of solving those kinds of problems
yourself.
Any questions on GetString or GetInt?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Why would you double
the capacity of the buffer
rather than just increasing
it by the exact amount?
>> DAVID MALAN: Good question.
Why would we double the capacity
of the buffer as opposed
to just increasing it
by some constant value?
It was a design decision.
We just decided that because it tends to
be a little expensive time-wise to ask
the operating system
for memory, we didn't
want to end up getting into
a situation for big strings
that we were asking
the OS again and again
and again and again in
rapid succession for memory.
So we just decided, somewhat
arbitrarily but we hope reasonably,
that, you know what, let's
try to get ahead of ourselves
and just keep doubling it so that
we minimize the amount of times
we have to call malloc or
realloc, but a total judgment
call in the absence of knowing
what users might want to type in.
Both ways could be arguable.
Arguably good.
>> So let's take a look at a couple
of other side effects of memory,
things that can go wrong
and tools that you can
use to catch these kinds of mistakes.
It turns out all of you, even though
check50 has not told you as much,
have been writing buggy
code since week one,
even if all check50 tests are
passed, and even if you and your TF
are super confident that
your code works as intended.
Your code has been buggy or
flawed in that all of you,
in using the CS50 library,
have been leaking memory.
You've been asking the operating system
for memory in most of the programs
you've written, but you've
never actually given it back.
You've called GetString
and GetInt and GetFloat,
but with GetString, you've
never called unGetString or Give
String Back or the like, but we've seen
that GetString does allocate memory
by way of malloc or this
function realloc, which is just
very similar in spirit,
and yet, we've been
asking the operating system for
memory and memory again and again
but never giving it back.
>> Now, as an aside, it turns out that
when a program quits, all of the memory
is automatically freed.
So it's not been a huge deal.
It's not going to break the
IDE or slow things down,
but when programs do
generally leak memory
and they're running for a long time.
If you've ever seen the stupid little
beach ball in Mac OS or the hourglass
on Windows where it's kind of
slowing down or thinking or thinking
or just really starts
to slow to a crawl,
it very possibly could be
the result of a memory leak.
The programmers who wrote
the software you're using
ask the operating system for memory
every few minutes, every hour.
But if you're running the
software, even if it's
minimized in your computer
for hours or days on end,
you might be asking for more and more
memory and never actually using it
and so your code might be, or
programs might be leaking memory,
and if you start to leak memory,
there's less memory for other programs,
and the effect is to
slow everything down.
>> Now, this is by far one of
the most atrocious programs
you will have opportunities
to run in CS50 insofar
as its output is even more esoteric than
clang's or make's or any of the command
line programs we've run before but
thankfully, embedded in its output
is some super helpful tips that
will be useful either for PSet four
or certainly PSet five.
So valgrind is a tool
that can be used to look
for memory leaks in your program.
It's relatively simple to run.
You run valgrind and then, even
though it's a little verbose,
dash dash leak check
equals full, and then dot
slash and the name of your program.
So valgrind will then run your program
and at the very end of your program
running before it quits and
gives you another prompt,
it's going to analyze your
program while it's been running
and tell you did you leak
any memory and better yet,
did you touch memory that
didn't belong to you?
It can't catch everything, but it's
pretty good at catching most things.
>> So here's an example of my having run
this program, having run valgrind,
on a program called
memory, and I'm going
to highlight the lines that are
ultimately of interest to us.
So there's even more distractions
that I've deleted from the slide.
But let's just see what this
program is capable of telling us.
It's capable of telling us things
like invalid write of size 4.
In other words, if you touch memory,
specifically 4 bytes of memory
that you shouldn't have,
valgrind can tell you that.
Invalid write of size 4.
You touched four bytes
that you shouldn't have.
Where did you do that?
This is the beauty.
Memory dot c line 21 is where you
screwed up and that's why it's helpful.
Much like GDB, it can help
point you at the actual error.
>> Now, this one's a little more
verbose, if not confusing.
40 bytes in 1 blocks are definitely
lost in loss record 1 of 1.
What does that mean?
Well, it just means you asked for
40 bytes and you never gave it back.
You called malloc or you called
GetString and the operating system
gave you 40 bytes, but you never
freed or released that memory,
and to be fair, we've never show
you how to give back memory.
Turns out there's a super
simple function called free.
Takes one argument, the thing
you want to free or give back,
but 40 bytes, apparently,
in this program
have been lost at line
20 of memory dot c.
>> So let's see this program.
It's super useless.
It only demonstrates
this particular error.
So let's take a look.
Here is main and main, notice, calls
a function called f and then returns.
So not all that interesting.
What does f do?
Notice I didn't bother with a prototype.
I wanted to keep the code
as minimal as possible.
So I put f above main and
that's fine, certainly,
for short programs like this.
So f does not return anything and does
not take anything, but it does do this.
It declares, much like
in the Binky example,
a pointer called x that's going
to store the address of an int.
So that's the left-hand side.
In English, what is the
right-hand side doing?
Anyone?
What is this doing for us?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
times the size of an int
which is 10 times that [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Good and let me summarize.
So allocate enough space for 10 integers
or 10, what's the size of an int,
it's four bytes, so 10 times 4 is
40, so that right-hand side that I've
highlighted is give me 40 bytes and
store the address of the first byte
into x.
And now lastly, and here's where
this program is buggy, what's
wrong with line 21 based on that logic?
What's wrong with line 21?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: You can't
index into x [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
I shouldn't index into x like that.
So syntactically, that's OK.
What's nice is, much like you
can treat the name of an array
as though it's a pointer, similarly
can you treat a pointer as though it's
an array, and so I can syntactically
say x bracket something, x bracket i,
but the 10 is problematic.
Why?
>> AUDIENCE: Because it's not inside.
>> DAVID MALAN: It's not
inside that chunk of memory.
What's the largest value I should
be putting in those square brackets?
9, 0 through 9.
Because of zero indexing.
So 0 through 9 would be fine.
Bracket 10 is not good and
but, recall though, every time
I seem to try to make CS50 IDE
crash by typing in bogus values,
it doesn't always cooperate,
and indeed, you often
get lucky just because the
operating system doesn't
notice that you ever so slightly
pass some chunk of memory,
because you stayed within technically
your segment, but more on that
in an operating systems class,
and so something like this
could very easily go undetected.
Your program's never going to crash
consistently but maybe once in awhile.
>> And so let's try valgrind
on this, and here's
where we'll get overwhelmed
by the output momentarily.
So make memory valgrind leak check
equals full dot slash memory.
And here's why I promise
this would overwhelm.
Here's what valgrind, here's what
a programmer, some years ago-
decided it would be a good idea
for the output to look like.
So let's make sense of this.
So all the way on the left-hand
side for no good reason
is the process ID of the program
we just run, the unique identifier
for the program we just ran.
We deleted that from
the slide, but there
is some useful information in here.
>> Let's scroll up to the very top.
Here's where we began.
So it's not all that much output.
Here's that invalid write
of size 4 on line 21.
Well, what was line 21?
Line 21 was exactly
this and it makes sense
that I'm in validly
writing 4 bytes because I'm
trying to put this integer,
which could be anything,
it just happens to be
zero, but I'm trying
to put it at a location
that doesn't belong to me.
Moreover, down here, 40 bytes in one
blocks are definitely lost in record 1.
That's because when I call malloc
here, I never actually free the memory.
>> So how can we fix this?
Let me go ahead and be a little safer
and do 9 there and let me here free x.
This is the new function for today.
If I now rerun make memory dot slash,
let's run valgrind on it again,
maximize my window and hit Enter.
Now, it's good.
They bury the good news
in all of this output.
All heap blocks were free.
We'll come back to what the heap
is, but no leaks are possible.
So this is just another
tool for your tool kit
with which you can start to
find now errors like that.
>> But let's see what
more can go wrong here.
Let's transition now to
actually solving a problem.
As an aside, if this will relieve a
little bit of confusion or tension,
this is now funny.
Yeah.
That's pretty good.
Because pointers are
addresses and addresses
are generally by convention
written with hexadecimal.
Ha, ha, this is funny now.
Anyhow, so let's now
actually solve a problem.
This has been super,
super low-level thus far,
and we can actually do useful
things with these low-level details.
>> So we introduced a few weeks
ago the notion of an array.
An array was nice because
it's hard to clean up our code
because if we wanted to write a
program with multiple students
or multiple names and houses and
dorms and colleges and all of that,
we could store everything more
cleanly inside of an array.
But propose one downside
of an array thus far.
Even if you've not suffered it yourself
in a program, just instinctively,
what is a bad thing
about an array, perhaps?
I hear some murmurs.
AUDIENCE: It's difficult
to change the size.
DAVID MALAN: It's difficult
You can't change the size
of an array, in fact, per se
in C. You can allocate another array,
move everything from the old one
into the new, and now
have some extra space,
but it's not like a
language like Java or Python
or any number of other
languages with which some of you
might be familiar where you
can just keep adding things
ad nauseam to the end of an array.
When you have an array of
size 6, that is its size,
and so much like the idea earlier
having a buffer of a certain size,
you have to guess out of the gate
what size do you want it to be?
If you guess too big,
you're wasting space.
If you guess too small, you
can't store that data, at least
without a lot more work.
>> So today, thanks to pointers, we can
start stitching together our own custom
data structures, and in
fact, here is something
that looks a little more
cryptic at first glance,
but this is what we'll call a linked
list, and its name kind of summarizes
it.
It's a list of numbers, or in
this case, a list of numbers,
but it could be a list of anything, but
it's linked together by way of arrows,
and just take a guess
with what technique
are we going to be able
to stitch together,
sort of like popcorn with a thread,
a linked lists rectangles here?
Its numbers?
What's the underlying language feature?
>> AUDIENCE: A pointer.
>> DAVID MALAN: A pointer.
So each of these arrows here represents
a pointer or just an address.
So in other words, if I want
to store a list of numbers,
I can't just store it if I want
the ability to grow and shrink
my data structure in an array.
So I need to have a little
more sophistication,
but notice that this
picture kind of suggests
that if you've just got little threads
connecting everything together,
probably isn't that hard to make space
in between two of those rectangles
or two of those nodes, as we'll start
calling them, put in a new node,
and then with some new thread, just
ditch the three nodes together,
the first one, the last one, and the one
that you just inserted into the middle.
>> And indeed a linked list,
unlike an array, is dynamic.
It can grow and it can
shrink and you don't
have to know or care in advance how
much data you're going to be storing,
but it turns out we have to be a little
careful about how to implement this.
So first let's consider how we implement
one of these little rectangles.
It's easy to implement an int.
You just say int n and then
you get 4 bytes for an int,
but how do I get an int, call it n,
and then a pointer, let's call it next.
We could call these
things anything we want
but I need a custom data structure.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Ampersand [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID MALAN: So ampersand we will use to
get the address of a node potentially.
But we need another
feature of C in order
to give me the ability to create
this custom rectangle, this custom
variable if you will, in memory.
AUDIENCE: A struct.
DAVID MALAN: A struct.
Recall from last week, we introduced
struct, this relatively simple keyword
that lets us make things like this.
C did not come with a data
structure called student.
It comes with int and float and char and
such, but it doesn't come with student,
but we can create a student data type,
a student structure, with this syntax
here.
And you'll see this again and again.
So don't worry about
memorizing the keywords,
but the keyword that's important is
just the fact that we said struct
and then we called it student and inside
of the student was a name and a house
or a dorm or the like.
>> And so now today, let's propose this.
I've added a few words, but if I want
to implement this rectangle that's
got both an int and a
pointer, you know what, I'm
going to declare a struct called node.
I'm also, inside of it, going to say
that a node, this rectangle, has an int
and we'll call it n and
it has a next pointer.
And this is a little verbose,
but if you think about it,
the arrows that were in the picture
a moment ago are of what data type?
Where each of those arrows is pointing
to what type of data structure?
It's not pointing just to an int per se.
It's pointing to the
whole rectangular thing
and that rectangular thing,
we said, is called a node.
And so we kind of have to
recursively define this such
that a node, we shall say,
will contain an int called n
and a pointer called next and the
type of data structure to which
that pointer points is apparently
going to be struct node.
>> So this is annoyingly verbose
and just to be pedantic,
the reason why we can't
just say this, which frankly
looks a lot more readable,
is because recall that C read
things top to bottom, left to right.
It's not until we get the semicolon
that the keyword node actually exists.
So if we want to have this sort of
cyclical reference inside of the data
structure, we have to do this, where
we say struct node at the top, which
gives us a longer way of describing this
thing, then inside we say struct node,
and then at the very last line
we say, all right, C, by the way,
just call this whole damn
thing a node and stop
using the keyword struct altogether.
So this is just sort of a syntactic
trick that ultimately lets us create
something that looks exactly like this.
>> So if we assume now we can
implement this thing in C,
how do we actually
start traversing this?
Well, in fact, all we have to do is
iterate from left to right and just
kind of insert nodes or delete nodes
or search for things wherever we want,
but to do this, let's go ahead and make
things a little more real because this
has been super low-level thus far.
Would anyone literally like to be first?
OK.
Come on up.
What's your name?
>> DAVID: David.
DAVID MALAN: David.
Nice to meet you.
Me too.
All right.
And we need a number 9.
Not as good as first, perhaps.
OK, number 9.
A number 17, please.
Let me go back a little farther.
Number 22, please, and
how about farther back
if I can see any hands
with all the light or no.
Someone's being volunteered right there.
Do you want to come up?
Your forearm is forcibly going up.
OK, 17.
22.
26 is coming down.
Would anyone else like to
forcefully-- Come on up.
An actual volunteer.
>> So very quickly, if
you guys could arrange
yourselves just like
the nodes on the screen.
Thank you.
And you'll be 26.
All right and quick introductions.
So I'm David and you are also?
DAVID: David.
DAVID MALAN: And you are?
JAKE: Jake.
SUE: Sue.
ALEX: Alex.
RAPHAEL: Raphael.
TAYLOR: Taylor.
DAVID MALAN: Taylor.
Excellent.
So these are our volunteers
for today and go ahead
and shift a little that way,
and just go ahead and keep
holding your numbers as you are or your
first sign and using your left hand,
go ahead and just implement
these arrows, just
so that your left hand is literally
pointing at whatever you should point
at, and give yourself some room so that
we can visually see your arms actually
pointing, and you can just point
sort of at the ground is fine.
>> So here we have a linked list of one,
two, three, four, five nodes initially,
and notice we have this special
pointer at the beginning who's
key because we have to keep track
of the whole length list somehow.
These guys, even though they're left
to right, back to back in memory,
they can actually be anywhere
in the computer's memory.
So these guys could be
standing anywhere on the stage
and that's fine, so long as they're
actually pointing at one another,
but to keep things
clean and simple, we'll
just draw them left to right like
this, but there could be massive gaps
in between those nodes.
>> Now, if I want to actually insert some
new value, let's go ahead and do this.
We have an opportunity now
to choose another node.
Say let's start off with mallocing 55.
Would someone mind being malloc?
OK, come on up.
What's your name?
RAINBOW: Rainbow.
DAVID MALAN: Rainbow?
All right.
Malloc Rainbow.
Come on up.
So now we have to ask ourselves
algorithmically where we can put 55.
So all of us know,
obviously, where she probably
belongs if we're trying
to keep this sorted
and if you guys could take one
step back so we don't fall off
the stage, that would be great.
So actually, Rainbow,
start over here with me,
because we as the computer now can
only see one variable at a time.
So if this is the first node.
Notice he's not a node,
he's just a pointer,
and that's why he's drawn to be
only the size of a pointer, not
one of those full rectangles.
So we're going to check at each
iteration is 55 less than 9?
No.
Is 55 less than 17?
Less than 22?
Less than 26?
Less than 34?
And so now, obviously
Rainbow belongs at the end.
So to be clear, and what
was your name, Taylor?
>> TAYLOR: Taylor.
DAVID MALAN: So among Taylor's
left hand and Rainbow's hands here,
whose hand needs to point at what in
order to insert 55 into this list?
What do we need to do?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Taylor's hand
needs to point left.
>> DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So inserting a node
into the end of the list
is pretty simple because Taylor just
has to point, instead of at the ground
or we'll call it null,
null is sort of the absence
of a pointer or a special
zero pointer, you're
going to point with your left
hand at Rainbow and then Rainbow,
where should your left
hand probably point?
Down.
It's not good if her hand is sort
of pointing off here or sort of any
which way.
That would be considered
a garbage value,
but if she points to
some known value, we'll
call it zero or null, that's OK
because we have a term in this
and we know the list now is complete.
>> So what's another
relatively simple case?
Could we malloc 5?
Come on up.
What's your name?
TIFFANY: Tiffany.
DAVID MALAN: I'm sorry?
DAVID MALAN: Tiffany.
All right.
Tiffany has been malloced
with the value 5.
Come on up.
This one's relatively easy too, but
let's consider order of operations now.
It was pretty easy
with Taylor at the end.
Number 5 is of course less than 9,
and so we have David, we have Tiffany,
and what was your name?
>> JAKE: Jake.
>> DAVID MALAN: Jake.
Tiffany, Jake, and David.
Whose hand should be updated first?
What do you want to do here?
There's a couple possible ways, but
there's also one or more wrong ways.
>> AUDIENCE: Start with leftmost.
>> DAVID MALAN: Start with the leftmost.
Who's the leftmost here then?
AUDIENCE: First.
>> DAVID MALAN: OK.
So start with first and where do you
want to update David's hands to be?
AUDIENCE: Towards the 5.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So David, point at five
or Tiffany here, and now?
>> AUDIENCE: Tiffany points to the 9?
DAVID MALAN: Perfect, except Binky's
head just kind of fell off, right?
Because what's wrong with
this picture literally?
AUDIENCE: Nothing is pointing.
DAVID MALAN: Nothing is
pointing to Jake now.
We've literally orphaned 9
and 17, and we've literally
leaked all of this memory, because by
updating David's hand first, that's
fine insofar as it's correctly
pointing at Tiffany now,
but if no one had the
foresight to point at Jake,
then we've lost the
entirety of that list.
So let's undo.
So that was a good thing to
trip over but let's correct now.
What should we do first instead?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Tiffany should point at the 9?
DAVID MALAN: I can't
get that close to you.
Who should point at the 9?
>> AUDIENCE: Tiffany.
>> DAVID MALAN: All right.
So Tiffany should first point at the 9.
So Tiffany should take
on an identical value
to David, which seems
redundant for a moment,
but that's fine because now, second
step, we can update David's hand
to point at Tiffany, and then if
we just kind of clean things up
as though this is kind of spring-like,
now that's a correct insertion.
So excellent.
So now we're almost there.
Let's insert one final
value like the value 20.
If we could malloc one final volunteer?
Come on up.
So this one's a little more tricky.
But really, the code we're
writing, albeit verbally,
is just like having a bunch
of if conditions now, right?
We had a condition
checking if it belongs
at the end, maybe the beginning.
We need some kind of loop to
find the spot in the middle.
So let's do that with what's your name?
>> ERIC: Eric.
>> DAVID MALAN: Eric?
Eric.
Nice to meet you.
So we have 20.
Less than five?
No.
Less than nine?
Less than 17?
No.
OK.
He belongs here and
your names again are?
SUE: Sue.
DAVID MALAN: Sue.
ALEX: Alex.
DAVID MALAN: Sue, Alex, and?
ERIC: Eric.
DAVID MALAN: Eric.
Whose hands need to get updated first?
>> AUDIENCE: Eric.
OK.
So Eric's should point at where?
At 22.
Good.
And now what's next?
Sue can then point at Eric
and now, if you guys just
make some room, which is fine
visually, now we've done the insertion.
So let's now consider a question but
thank you so much for our volunteers.
Very well done.
You can keep those, if you like.
And we have a lovely parting gift if
you'd each like to take a stress ball.
Let me just pass this down.
So what is the takeaway of this?
This seems to be amazing
insofar as we have now
introduced an alternative to an
array that is not so confined
to an array of some fixed size.
They can grow dynamically.
>> But much like we've seen in weeks
past, we never get anything for free,
like surely there's a trade-off here.
So with an upside of a linked
list, is this dynamism?
This ability to grow and frankly,
we could have done delete
and we could shrink as needed.
What price are we paying?
Twice as much space, first of all.
If you look at the picture, no longer
am I storing a list of integers.
I'm storing a list of
integers plus pointers.
So I'm doubling the amount of space.
Now, maybe that's not such
a big deal 4 bytes, 8 bytes,
but it could certainly add
up for large data sets.
What's another downside?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: We have to
traverse them one-by-one.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
We have to traverse them one-by-one.
You know what, we gave up this super
convenient feature of square bracket
notation, more properly
known as random access,
where we can just jump
to an individual element
but now if I still had
my volunteers here,
if I wanted to find the
number 22, I can't just
jump to bracket something something.
I have to look over the list, much
like our searching examples linearly,
to find the number 22.
So we seem to have paid a price there.
But we can nonetheless
solve other problems.
>> In fact, let me introduce
just a couple of visuals.
So if you've been down to
Mather's Dining Hall recently,
you'll recall that their
stacks of trays like this,
we borrowed these from
Annenberg before class.
So this stack of trays, though,
is representative actually
of a computer science data structure.
There is a data structure
in computer science
known as a stack which very nicely
lends itself to exactly this visual.
So if each of these trays isn't a
tray but like a number and I wanted
to store numbers, I
could put one down here,
and I could put another down here,
and continue stacking numbers
on top of one another, and what's
potentially helpful about this
is that what's the implication
of this data structure?
Which number can I pull out
first most conveniently?
The most recently one put on there.
>> So this is what we would call in
computer science a LIFO data structure.
Last in, first out.
And we'll see before long why
that might be useful but for now,
just consider the property.
And it's kind of stupid if you think
about how the dining hall does it.
Every time they clean trays and
put the freshest ones on top,
you could have a previously clean
but eventually very dirty and dusty
tray at the very bottom
if you never actually
get to the bottom of that
stack, because you just
keep putting the new and
the clean ones on top of it.
The same thing might happen
in a supermarket too.
If you have a display case
of milk and every time CVS
or whoever gets more milk,
you just shove the milks
you already have to the back and
you put the new ones up front,
you're going to have some pretty nasty
milk at the end of the data structure,
because it's always at the bottom or
equivalently it's always at the back.
>> But there's another way to think about
lining up data and for instance, this.
If you're one of those people who likes
to line up outside of Apple stores
when a new product comes
out, you're probably
not using a stack data
structure because you
would alienate everyone else who is
lining up to purchase some new toy.
Rather, you're probably using
what kind of data structure
or what kind of system
in the real world?
Hopefully it's a line, or more
properly or more British-like, a queue.
And it turns out a queue is also a
data structure in computer science,
but a queue has a very
different property.
It's not LIFO.
Last in, first out.
God forbid.
It's instead FIFO.
First in, first out.
And that's a good thing
for fairness' sake
certainly when you're lining
up super early in the morning.
If you get there first, you
want to get out first as well.
>> And so all of these data
structures, queues and stacks
and bunches of others, turns out you
can think of this as just an array.
This is an array, maybe
a fixed size 4, but it'd
be kind of nice if we could just pile
trays almost infinitely tall if we
have that many trays or numbers.
So maybe we want to
use a linked list here,
but the trade-off is going to be
potentially that we need more memory,
takes a little more time, but we
don't limit the height of the stack,
much like Mather's display case
might limit the size of the stack,
and so these are design decisions or
options available to us ultimately.
So with these data
structures, we've started
seeing new upper bounds potentially
on what previously was super fast
and where we'll leave
off today and where
we'll hope to get to
is on Wednesday, we'll
start to look at a data
structure that lets us search
through data in log end time again.
And we saw that, recall, in week zero
and one with binary search or divide
and conquer.
It's coming back and better yet,
the holy grail for this Wednesday
will be to come up with the
data structure that runs truly
or theoretically in
constant time, whereby
it doesn't matter how many
millions or billions of things
we have in the data structure, it will
take us constant time, maybe one step
or two steps or 10 steps,
but constant numbers of steps
to search through that data structure.
That indeed will be the holy grail
but more on that on Wednesday.
See ya then.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]