>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID MALAN: This is CS50.
This is the start of week nine.
And this is what would have
been Mr. Boole's 200th birthday.
So this is the fellows
to whom we've alluded
quite some times about using
Boolean variables true and false,
1 and 0 and such.
And this was Google's
tribute to him today.
He would have turned 200.
So if you'd like to
join us for CS50 lunch,
take a look at the link
on the course's website.
And such faces and friends as
these await you here in Cambridge.
Faces like these await you in New Haven.
And, in fact, Ken in
New Haven kindly made
what's called an animated GIF of Eli
here at a recent lunch-- a GIF is yet
another graphical file format,
with which you're familiar-- that
looks a little something like this.
So just a sequence of-- OK.
No one here in Cambridge is laughing.
But in New Haven, this
is really funny, right?
All right.
>> So do join us there.
Here at Harvard,
specifically, this Wednesday,
if you're a sophomore or freshman even--
or even junior-- thinking of making
a switch into computer
science, know that there'll
be a CS advising fair this
Wednesday, shortly after class
at 4:00 PM in the computer
science building Maxwell Dworkin.
We'll put this on the course's
website by tomorrow, as well.
Donuts, I'm told, will be served.
>> All right.
So funny story-- I was poking
around on the internet,
and I found some old archives
of my former website.
And it turns out-- around this
time, it seems very timely
since I gather that the UC elections
are about to gear up again.
So I ran for UC, lost miserably.
And maybe this was in part why.
So this was my website at the time.
For some reason, I thought it was
a good idea, before telling people
what my platform was and why they
should vote for me, that they have
to click to enter to find out that
information, which in retrospect is
kind of creepy.
I don't really know what that was.
>> But it certainly didn't
help my campaign.
I also found that by senior
year-- I had this Muppet calendar.
Muppets were kind of in vogue back then.
Or maybe they weren't.
I had a Muppet calendar back then.
And I thought it'd be cool to name
my computer on Harvard's network
frogman.student.harvard.edu.
At the time, we all had uniquely
identifiable host names.
And you could choose some vanity
name instead of your own name.
And I went with frogman for some reason.
>> And then I started-- I spent a lot
of time clicking through these links
this morning.
And this was my about page,
which now kind of seems adorable.
But it also testifies to just
how far technology has come.
I mean, back in the day,
a 486 was something.
These days, it's super, super,
super slow and well less
than you might have in your
own pockets these days.
There's more on there that
was even more embarrassing.
So I'll leave it at that.
But that was my first
foray into web-- oh, no.
That wasn't.
My first real foray into web programming
was this site, which I just forgot.
At some point, I learned how to
make repetitive background images.
And so I found this tiling effective,
like hockey player, football, and golf
ball, or whatever that is
for the Frosh IMs website.
And this was actually, genuinely the
first web-based project I took on--
I think maybe sophomore
year, junior year--
after taking CS50 and CS51, one
of the common follow-on classes.
I noticed in looking
through the archives
that one of my successors and
friends, Lee, kind of changed
the copyright to himself.
But this was indeed something that
I should own the embarrassment to.
But at the time, this
was the first website,
as I said a few weeks ago,
by which freshman could
register for intramural sports here.
And so it turns out
that background images
like that are not such a good idea.
But the web was new, and
we were all experimenting.
And this is what I
apparently did at the time.
All right.
So without further ado, we switch
gears today to give you, really,
the final piece that you might find
especially useful for final projects
but also that will start to
make the whole world wide web
feel a little bit more understandable.
Indeed, we're going to introduce
one more programming language
called JavaScript that's similar
and different in different ways
from languages we've looked at thus far.
>> So C, recall, is this compiled language.
You've got to run it through a compiler.
You get source code to object
code, or zeroes and ones.
And those are zeroes and ones that
your CPU, Central Processing Unit,
actually understand.
PHP, by contrast, isn't
a compiled language.
It's a what?
It's an interpreted language.
So there's some program
called an interpreter that
has to read it-- top to
bottom, left to right--
and figure out what all of
your syntax does and means,
whether it's a loop or a condition
or any other number of programming
constructs.
So that's an interpreted language.
>> Then we introduced HTML.
And HTML's not even a
programming language.
We'd call it what?
A markup language, which is just
a sort of fancy way of saying it
doesn't have programming constructs like
we saw even back in the day of Scratch.
There are no loops.
There are no conditions.
It really is a language
about marking up your data
and formatting it or
structuring it in some way.
>> CSS, meanwhile, similarly
not a programming language.
It's even more aesthetically oriented.
And it allows you to sort of fine-tune
things like font size and colors
and placement and all of that.
Then we had
>> SQL.
So SQL is indeed a programming
language in some sense,
albeit tailored
specifically to databases.
But even though we only introduce you to
select and insert and delete and update
and a couple of others,
turns out you can actually
write functions or
procedures, as they're
called, in SQL that look and act
quite like PHP and C functions.
So know that those exist.
But we don't even bother with them
as we just scratch the surface here.
And then JavaScript, the last of
our languages formally introduced.
So JavaScript, too, is
an interpreted language.
And those familiar, do
you want to distinguish it
with some characteristic
from both C and PHP?
What makes it different?
>> AUDIENCE: It's not compiled.
>> DAVID MALAN: Say again?
>> DAVID MALAN: It's not compiled.
So it, too, is interpreted.
So it's not compiled.
But that makes it a little like PHP.
But it's still different from
PHP in some striking way,
at least in the way we'll use it.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: It runs client-side.
>> DAVID MALAN: It runs
client-side, usually.
That's indeed the distinguishing
characteristic for us right now.
C was server-side in the sense
that we did everything in CS50 IDE.
PHP thus far has been
server-side insofar
as it, too, gets interpreted--
not compiled, but interpreted--
inside CS50 IDE, which of course is
just a server or servers in the cloud.
>> But JavaScript, even
though you you're going
to start writing it for, say, pset
eight and maybe final projects-- you're
going to right it in
CS50 IDE and save it
in files within CS50 IDE, CS50 IDE
and, in turn, the cloud servers
on which it's hosted, are not going
to interpret or execute your code.
Rather, it's going to be sent in
unaltered form down to the browser.
And it's then going to be IE
or Chrome or Firefox or Safari
or whatever that actually interprets
it, top to bottom, left to right.
So the key distinguishing
characteristic for today
is that JavaScript is client-side
and PHP, for instance,
has been server-side.
Now, this has interesting implications
for, like, intellectual property
and who can actually see your code.
And indeed, you can go
on the web and see most
any code that someone has
written in JavaScript.
Sometimes it's readable,
sometimes it's obfuscated.
But more on that in due time.
>> So JavaScript, nicely enough, is
super similar, syntactically, to C.
And much like PHP,
there's no main function.
If you want to start writing
JavaScript code, as you'll see today,
you just start writing it.
But it is, you'll see, particularly
useful in the context of web browsers.
However, my little
disclaimer-- usually earlier--
was to say that you can increasingly
today use JavaScript server-side
using a fancy framework called Node.js
that some of CS50's own applications
are written in.
Check 50 actually uses Node.js.
But we're going to focus on
JavaScript client-side here on out.
>> So here is a set of conditions in PHP.
Sorry, in-- actually, that
statement, too is correct.
Here is also a set of
conditions in JavaScript.
Syntactically, it is
identical to C and to PHP.
Mr. Boole's expressions are,
similarly, syntactically
identical to both C and PHP.
We also have switches in
JavaScript that look identical.
We have for loops that are
structured identically,
while loops, do while loops.
>> This one's a little different.
PHP had the for each construct
that you might be using
or will use in pset seven, perhaps.
JavaScript has this special version of
for where you literally say something
like for variable key in object, which
is a very succinct way of saying,
if I've got an object-- and we'll
talk about these again in a moment--
and I want to iterate over all
of the key value pairs inside,
I don't have to figure out how to
numerically index them with zero, one,
two, three.
>> I can literally say this.
And on each iteration, JavaScript
for me will update the variable key
to be the first key, then the next key,
then the next key, then the next key,
and so forth.
And I can get at its value by treating
an object in JavaScript, as we'll see,
as though it's an
associative array in PHP.
Indeed, if you finally wrapped your
mind around what an associative array is
in PHP, you can think of it for now as
identical to an object in JavaScript.
But that's a bit of
an oversimplification.
>> Arrays look, nicely enough, identical
to PHP except for one character.
There's one thing missing here
that we did see last week with PHP.
What's omitted?
Yeah?
No dollar sign.
So we're back to a
more normal world where
variables don't have dollar signs.
But you do prefix them
with var, typically.
And var means variable.
And much like PHP is loosely
typed-- whereby there are types,
there are numbers and strings
and floats and so forth--
JavaScript similarly has types.
But it's loosely typed in that we the
programmers don't have to specify them.
We just have to be aware
that different types exist.
>> Variables, meanwhile-- here's how
we might declare "hello, world"
as a string.
Notice it's identical to
PHP but no dollar sign.
And this is something we'll
start seeing more today,
whereby you have an object
with keys and values.
And if you want to try
to infer from last week--
the syntax is a little different.
But a little sanity check-- how many
keys does this object seem to have?
So I see four.
I see two.
>> So it's actually two.
So this is a collection
of two key-value pairs.
The key is symbol whose value is FB.
The key is price whose value is 101.53.
So those are two key-value pairs.
And remember, PHP-- and this is again
just sort of syntactic difference.
It's not all that
intellectually interesting.
PHP might have written this same
thing as follows-- quote, equals.
And I change these to square brackets.
And then I change this to
a quoted word, "price."
And then I don't use a colon.
What did I use last week?
Yeah, the equal sign
arrow funky notation.
>> And then I did the same thing here.
Same thing here.
And that's all.
So it's fine if this hasn't
really sunk in to memory just
yet because it's really
intellectually uninteresting.
It's just syntactic differences.
But the ideas are exactly the same.
Inside of this variable
quote in JavaScript
is a collection of key-value pairs,
one of which is symbol, one of which
is price.
And I can get at those values
with the following syntax.
Just like in PHP, I could
do something like-- let
me make this box a little bigger.
Just like in PHP, I could
make this-- oh, dammit.
Come on.
>> Just like in PHP-- OK, we'll
just use the presenter notes.
Just like in PHP, I can
do $quote$quote["symbol"],
and this will get me
the value of "symbol."
In JavaScript, it's going to be
identical, whereby I can just do this.
The only thing that's
missing is the dollar sign.
>> So nicely enough, then, there's
not all that much new syntax.
So what today we focus on, really, is
some of the ideas and the applications.
And the first such
application that you might
have seen if you dived into pset
seven already is this syntax.
So in pset seven, if you've
seen or not seen it yet,
know that there's a file that we give
you called config.json-- JavaScript
Object Notation.
Why?
We wanted to be able to provide you with
a template with some key-value pairs.
We wanted to be able to give you a list
of the host, the name of the server.
We wanted to give you a
placeholder for your username
and a placeholder for your password.
If you're not seeing
this yet, not to worry.
More on this in pset seven
[? spec. ?] And then,
obviously, we want you
to fill in the to-dos
because when you log into
CS50 IDE, each of you
have your own username and password.
>> So we could've used a half a dozen
or more different file formats.
We could have used a .txt file.
We could used a CSV file.
We could've used an
INI file, an XML file,
a whole bunch more acronyms that
you might not have ever heard.
It's kind of arbitrary
at the end of the day.
But super popular these days is a text
format called JSON-- JavaScript Object
Notation-- that looks like this.
It's a little cryptic,
but notice the patterns.
You start with an open curly
brace, and you end with the same.
Inside of that is something.
It's a key-value pair.
So this is an object that I'm
looking at on the screen here
that has one key, which has one value.
And just inferring based on the
previous pattern, what's the key here?
Database, the thing to
the left of the colon.
>> Now, the value happens to be
a multiple lines this time.
But the value starts with a curly
brace and ends with a curly brace.
So what would you propose is the
type of the value of database?
A dictionary or, just more
succinctly, an object.
Right?
This is kind of a data structure that
can use other structures within itself.
So if this whole thing we're
calling an object-- and an object
is just a bunch of key-value pairs-- the
value of database itself is an object.
The value of database has a whole bunch
of key value pairs, the first of which
is host, then name, then
username, then password,
each of whose values, meanwhile, it's
just a boring string in double quotes.
>> So even if that's not
super clear just yet,
know that this is just a
standard, fairly boring way
of storing data in a standard format.
But the common mistakes you
might make, even in pset seven,
are little stupid things, like if you
accidentally omit the comma there.
That's going to result in the file
not necessarily being readable.
If you accidentally omit things like the
quotes, it's not going to be readable.
So it's a pretty nitpicky file format,
but it's one that's super common.
And we happen to use it, even though
you don't use any JavaScript otherwise,
in pset seven.
>> All right.
So remember this picture.
We talked about, in HTML, that
the code might look like this.
This is the HyperText Markup Language
[INAUDIBLE] for just "hello, world."
But then we proposed a
while back that if it helps,
you might want to start thinking
about this already as a tree.
In fact, the indentation that we
use just for readability's sake
or for style's sake on
the left can kind of
be translated into this tree, where you
have some special root node that we'll
generically called document, below which
is the root HTML element or tag, HTML,
which then has two
children, head and body.
>> And then in turn, head has a title.
And title has a text value.
And body similarly has a text value.
So if you're comfortable saying
that yes, you could take this HTML
and draw a picture like
this, the right-hand side
is a nice mental model because now
that we have JavaScript, a programming
language that browsers can
execute and interpret for you,
it turns out that what
we're about to do in code
is start to manipulate this
tree structure in memory.
We don't have to build
the tree in memory.
We don't have to do sort of
pset-five-style data structure
complexity.
The browser, nicely enough, upon
interpreting HTML top to bottom,
left or right, is literally going to
hand us the equivalent of a pointer
to that entire tree for free.
It does all of the hard work.
That's what Mozilla and Apple
and others have done for us.
>> And with JavaScript are we going to
be able to control and change and do
interesting things to
that tree, otherwise known
as a DOM or Document Object Model.
What kinds of things?
Well, it turns out that
in JavaScript, there's
this laundry list of
events that can take place.
And we haven't really used that
word since week zero and pset
zero when we talked about Scratch.
Most of you probably didn't use
an event in your Scratch project.
But you might recall
the simple Marco Polo
example, where we had two
sprites, one of whom said, Marco.
The other of whom then, upon listening
and hearing that event, said, Polo.
If not, feel free to
look back that far back.
>> But this is just to
say, and you can kind of
infer from the names of these
things, JavaScript, it turns out,
is going to give us a way to listen
for mouse going down or mouse going up
or key going down or key
going up or onsubmit onselect
or onresizing something.
In other words, any physical action
that a human can take with a browser
that you do every day, you can write
code for that listens for those events
and then does something appropriate.
>> For instance, if you use Google Maps,
what happens if you click and move
the mouse, typically?
If you click and drag?
Yeah?
Exactly.
The map starts to move.
So you can sort of see what's
over here, what's over there.
And how does Google implement that?
Well, presumably, they're
using a couple of these event
listeners, one that
says, listen for on mouse
down-- so when the user physically
pushes his trackpad or his or her mouse
down.
And then we're looking for
something like movement
or some other event that
allows us to capture drag.
And in fact, drag is similarly in this
dot dot dot list of possible options.
>> So this is going to be a powerful
way to start responding to the user
even before he or she actually clicks
something explicit like submit.
But we're going to introduce
a couple topics to get there.
But first, let's transition
to some actual code.
So I'm going to go
ahead and open up dom-0,
which is a very simple example
here that if I zoom in simply
has this input here for me.
And I'm going to go ahead and type in
"David" for my name and click Submit.
>> And then, albeit sort of cheaply, I
have this prompt that pops up that says,
"hello, David!"
So this is kind of
like our "hello, world"
that we did awhile back in C and
even in PHP because I've dynamically
outputted my name.
I can do someone else's name here.
I could simply change this to,
like, Hannah, click Submit.
And indeed, the little pop-up changes.
>> Now, pop-ups are one of the
most abused features of the web.
And in fact, back in
the day pop-up blockers
came into vogue because you
would go to some website--
perhaps a questionable place--
that would then suddenly
start peppering your screen
with a whole bunch of pop-ups.
And so this ability to pop up
windows in front of the user
has not been particularly
well-received by humanity.
So that's why you see
this prevent thing,
which just makes this whole thing ugly.
So we're going to need a
better way to prompt the user.
But for now, that seems to work.
So just intuitively, what
seems to be happening here?
I go ahead and click Submit, and
then something's happening, clearly.
But what's not happening that did happen
last week any time I clicked Submit?
What didn't happen on the screen?
Sorry?
Reload.
The URL didn't change at all.
I said this was dom-0,
and I'm still at dom-0.
Normally, we'd get changed to some other
URL, like register.php or the like.
>> But even when I dismiss
this thing by clicking OK,
notice that the URL
stays completely put.
And, in fact, if I'm a little
skeptical, let me open up Chrome.
Let me open up the Network tab.
And notice it's blank at the moment.
Let me go ahead and resubmit Maria.
There's no network traffic whatsoever.
So there's no HTTP.
>> So indeed, if I look at the source code
for this-- let me close this window
and go to View Source.
Interesting.
It looks like there's some
new tags, among them script.
So let's take a look within CS50
IDE exactly what I sent to the user.
>> So here is-- let's
focus on the HTML only.
Here's the bottom half of dom-0.html.
And notice that it's got a title,
a head tag, a body tag, a form tag.
But what jumps out to you as
different, especially if you've never
written any JavaScript yourself.
Let me scroll a little
to the right here.
I've got an input,
another input for submit.
I've got an ID, which is kind of new.
But we did see this with CSS.
What else is definitely new?
Yeah?
Nice.
>> All right.
So where it says onsubmit,
notice what seems to follow.
This is an attribute
in HTML nomenclature.
Its value is this quoted string here.
And this looks a little
weird at first glance.
It's not HTML.
It's not CSS.
This is, as you might guess, JavaScript.
So it seems that built into this
web page is a function called greet.
And I'm inferring that just
because it's a word, greet.
It's got an open paren,
close paren, semicolon.
Looks like a C function,
looks like a PHP function.
>> And indeed, it's going to
be a JavaScript function.
Then I'm returning false.
We'll come back to
that in just a moment.
But where is this function defined?
Well let me scroll up
to the top of the file.
And even though it's a long line,
it's relatively straightforward.
Let me zoom out here and
focus on these four lines.
>> So in JavaScript, just
like PHP, you just
say, literally, the word "function,"
the name of the function,
and then parentheses with any
arguments-- no arguments in this case.
And there's no return type
in JavaScript, just like PHP.
So it's a little looser than C.
Open curly brace, close curly brace.
Built into JavaScript is a function--
not a recommended function--
but a function called alert
whose sole purpose in life
is to pull up that pretty ugly
prompt that we saw a moment ago.
>> Now this is kind of a mouthful.
What's going on here?
So let's start to
highlight everything here.
That's the same argument to alert.
And what's going on?
This just looks like a string.
And it turns out, unlike PHP and unlike
C, it doesn't matter in JavaScript
if you single quotes or double quotes.
They'll be equivalent.
And frankly, it's just
popular these days
for JavaScript programmers to always
use single quotes for some reason.
It's just the thing to do.
But we could use double quotes, as well.
>> So plus is a new character.
But those of you who've done
this before, what does plus mean?
Yeah.
Concatenate.
So we saw this in PHP.
There's just the dot
operator in PHP that
will concatenate two strings together.
C was a pain in the neck to do this.
Recall from pset six, which was
an especial pain in the neck,
you would have to use
something like strcat
after allocating memory
on the stack or the heap.
You had to jump through hoops
just to concatenate two strings.
In JavaScript, it's super simple.
Just use the plus operator between them.
>> So the complex-looking
thing seems to be this
because at the end of
this whole string, I just
concatenate on an exclamation point.
So if what was popping up was
"hello, David," "hello, Hannah,"
"hello, Maria," and so forth, clearly
that middle thing in between the two
pluses must give me access to what?
What's in there for sure?
Yeah.
So I'll pretending here the
answer their name, right?
So their name popped up in the final
result. So what does this mean?
Well, I proposed earlier in that
picture that the so-called DOM
has this special root element
way up top called document.
And now, it turns out, that's going
to be a special global variable
in JavaScript, built into which is a
whole bunch of useful functionality.
Among the useful functionality is the
ability to get at any descendant node.
Those squares or rectangles or ellipses
are just nodes in a tree, so to speak.
>> So it turns out that built into
JavaScript's document object
is a function, otherwise known as a
method, that's called getElementById.
The syntax for calling
a function in JavaScript
that is inside of an object or a
variable is just with the dot notation.
And we saw this in C
what the struct syntax.
You see this in pset seven, kind of,
sort of, when you see CS50::query.
The colon colon in PHP is another
way of calling a function that's
inside of some object.
>> But for now in JavaScript,
it's just a dot.
And so this function,
nicely enough, kind of
says what it does-- get element by ID.
An element is just another name
for a tag or node in the DOM.
And so get element by ID "name"
means this-- here's my HTML.
And based on this HTML, what
node or what HTML tag am I
going to programmatically be handed
by calling document.getElementById?
>> Yeah, exactly.
I'm going to get the input
element there whose ID is "name."
So specifically, you can
think of this function,
getElementById, as a way of giving
back a pointer to that specific node
in the tree.
We haven't drawn this
tree, but it's a way
of getting access to that
rectangle or that rectangle
by uniquely identifying it via its ID.
>> Now, why is this useful?
Well, it turns out
that once you've gotten
that node, that rectangle from the
picture, that node inside of it,
in turn, has a whole bunch of
properties-- key-value pairs
or data, one of which is called value.
So literally, it's kind of a
mouthful to explain the whole thing.
But at the end of the day,
all this does is give you
a string that the user typed in
in this hierarchical fashion.
But I don't like a
couple of these things.
Or rather, there's some curiosity still.
All of that seemed to work.
Why do you think I returned
false after calling greet?
This looks a little ugly, that
I have two statements there
separated by semicolons.
Take a guess.
If I removed return false, what
might happen, just instinctively?
Sorry, say again?
>> Open a bunch of Windows.
So potentially maybe something
like that would happen.
What else?
Might submit a request where?
To the same page.
So, in fact, that's that
the closer answer here,
even though, unlike
in the past, I've not
specified the action attribute,
which normally we have to do.
Turns out there's a default.
If you don't specify action,
it's like saying quote, unquote
or the name of the file itself,
which in this case would
be like dom-0.html.
It's just kind of inferred,
or rather implied.
>> And so if I don't do this, let's notice.
Let me save this.
And I've removed return false.
Let me go back to this
example and force reload it.
And you might have seen me suggest
this on CS50 Discuss a bunch of times.
If anything's ever acting funky and the
browser's not behaving as you expect,
oftentimes you'll want to hold
Shift and then click Reload.
That will force every file to reload
and not use your browser's local cache
or copy so that now, let me go ahead and
open up my Inspector, the Network tab.
I'm going to click
Preserve Log because I
don't want it to delete the rows
once I get whisked away elsewhere.
>> Let me go ahead here and
type in Andi, click Submit.
All right.
That seems as expected.
It says "hello, Andi."
Let me click OK.
Interesting.
Notice that the page changed,
albeit to the original page.
Notice the URL kind of changed.
It added a question mark,
which is usually an indicator
that we tried to submit something.
And then at the bottom,
even more explicitly,
here is the actual HTTP request,
which got a response of 200 that
brought me back here.
>> So this is not what
we want to do, right?
Because I don't want to
reload the whole page.
I instead wanted to return
false so as to short circuit
the browser's default behavior, which
was, of course, to submit the page.
>> So let's take a look at a
marginally better example.
This is dom version one.
And notice the following.
It's OK if you don't grok
all of the lines of code.
But what is fundamentally different
about this implementation?
I'll stipulate it behaves the
same, does the same thing.
What have I obviously done differently?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So the function is defined differently--
in other words, absent from the form,
up there on line 7-- or
rather, line 8-- no longer
do I have the onsubmit attribute.
In the previous example, I had this.
And then I literally wrote my code here.
And then I said return false.
And if it didn't rub
you the wrong way yet,
it should start to insofar
as, just like in HTML,
when we started to co-mingle it
with CSS in style attributes,
it just started to get a little
messy or feel a little wrong.
>> Similarly here, if
you start taking HTML,
and then you automatically
plop some JavaScript code
in the middle of a quoted string, it's
not going to be very maintainable.
Right?
It's not even obvious at first
place where the JavaScript code is.
So it would be really nice as
a principle of better design,
let's keep our HTML completely
separate from our JavaScript.
>> So to do that, what we've
done here is the following--
we simply use HTML for markup only.
And so in version one of this, all
I have is a form with a unique ID.
And then down here, I'm taking advantage
of a special feature of JavaScript
whereby I can have what's
called an anonymous function.
So it turns out that if I call
document.getElementById of 'demo'
that's like giving me a pointer to
this node in my tree, the form element,
so to speak.
>> Now, I just know from
knowing a bit of HTML
now we're having read some online
reference, that a form element supports
a whole bunch of event listeners-- in
other words, the laundry list of event
listeners that we saw a moment ago.
I know from reading the documentation
that onsubmit is a valid event
listener for a form element.
>> So once I know that,
it's safe for me to do
the following-- get that node
from the tree, the form element,
and access its so-called
onsubmit property.
So the dot just means
this is a property,
like a special value inside of it.
And what data type am I
assigning, apparently,
to onsubmit, which is
effectively a variable inside
of that node in the tree?
It's a field inside of that struct.
What's the data type?
>> A function, yeah.
So it turns out that PHP has this.
And even though we
didn't tell you about it,
C also has function pointers, the
ability to pass and assign functions
as variables' values themselves.
And we're not going
to regress back to C.
But for now, it turns out that
on the right-hand side here,
even though it looks a little
funky, this means, hey browser,
give me a function.
I'm not going to even bother giving
it a name because I'm literally
going to assign let's call it
the address of this function
immediately to onsubmit.
In other words, browser, you don't need
to know what this function's called.
You just need to know
where it is in memory.
And so it suffices just to
have an equal sign there
and not to bother naming this, like
foo or greet or any other word.
And now this is just a stylistic thing.
I could move this curly brace
onto the-- sorry-- next line
like we usually do CS50.
But in JavaScript, it's
actually stylistically common
to just keep the curly brace, the
first one, on that first line.
>> But hereafter, there's
nothing interesting.
That open curly brace just
demarcates the start of my function.
The function is now
identical, except I've
included the return false
inside of this function.
Because it turns out--
and you would only
know this from reading
the documentation--
that if the function that you assign
to the onsubmit handler returns false,
the browser just knows and agrees
not to submit the form to a server.
If it returns true, it will submit
it to a server for reasons we'll see
are useful in just a moment.
>> And then the semicolon after
the curly brace there just
means I'm done defining the function.
You know what to call as soon
as you hear a submission.
All right.
This is still arguably kind of ugly.
So what more can we do?
>> Well, it turns out then in
version two, which is the last--
and we'll just glance at this.
At the risk of making
it uglier, it turns out
that there's a library in
the world called jQuery.
And jQuery is a super
popular JavaScript library
that's so popular that most
any JavaScript-- it's not
uncommon for people to confuse
jQuery with JavaScript.
Why?
JavaScript itself has very
verbose ways of doing things--
document.getElementById, dadadadadada.
You end up having very
long lines of code.
>> So a fellow named John Resid,
who actually works for a startup
up these days, came out
with this library years
ago that many people have contributed
to called jQuery that changes
the syntax in the following way.
And just so you've seen this,
because you'll invariably
see this if doing a
web-based final project,
this would be the equivalent way of
implementing that same function using
this special library.
>> Now, rather than tease
it apart in its entirety,
let's just look at some patterns.
This syntax appears to have
how many anonymous functions
or nameless functions
or AKA lambda functions?
Two, right?
And you know that, even if
you're not super comfy with this,
just by the fact that it
says function() twice.
>> And it turns out that
what this code is doing--
and we'll refer to online references,
ultimately, for some help with this.
This just means that when
the document is ready,
go ahead and register
the following function
as the submit handler for the HTML
element whose unique idea is demo.
And then, when that happens,
call these two lines of code.
And this is, tragically, a more
verbose way of saying return false.
And we mentioned this just because
you'll see code like this online.
And it's nothing to be daunted by.
But rather, keep in mind that what's
going to be common in JavaScript
is this paradigm.
And so that's why we show it for now.
All right.
So without dwelling too
much on that syntax,
are there are any questions on
these examples or ideas thus far?
All right.
So let's use this for something useful.
Making a web page that just says hello,
so and so isn't all that interesting,
not to underwhelm.
This one's not going to be beautiful,
but it is going to do something useful.
Let me go back to my directory
here and open up, say, form-0.html.
>> So suppose this is the freshman
intramural sports registration page
without any CSS or any sense of design.
And I want to go ahead and
register here with a password.
And I'm going to agree to the terms
and conditions and click Register.
And now the website says, "You are
registered! (Well, not really.)"
That seems like it worked, but
let me go ahead and force reload.
>> And let me say, no, you don't
need my actual email address.
Or maybe we'll just say mail in there.
Password will be, like, 12345.
And then, just because I'm
an idiot, now it's 123456789.
And I'm not going to check your box.
>> Hmm.
All right.
So there's several opportunities
for improvement here.
And you know, or will see in pset
seven, that you can write code--
and you'll have to write
code in PHP-- to defend
against these kinds of user
errors because the user clearly
has not cooperated.
And he or she has not given you all the
values you wanted or even in the format
that you wanted them.
So you'll see in pset seven that
we could certainly have some
if conditions that say
if the email address
isn't a username@something.edu,
we could just
say sorry and apologize to the user
much, like you might be in pset seven.
Or if they haven't checked that box,
turns out in PHP, you can detect that,
too.
And certainly if the passwords
don't match as in register.php
for pset seven, you can detect that.
But that's a pain in the
neck in that now they request
us to go all the way to the server.
The user is informed of the error.
And at least unless you use
some fancier techniques,
now they have to click the back arrow.
Wouldn't it be nice, like
a lot of websites today,
if you had more immediate
feedback, instantly?
>> In other words, let me go to version
one, which is going to be no prettier.
But it does have this feature.
Malan, 12345, 123456789, not
going to check the box, Register.
Passwords do not match.
So even though this pop-up is ugly--
we can replace this eventually
with something like Bootstrap,
which you'll see in pset seven
is a very popular library-- I did
detect that the passwords do not match.
All right.
Well, let me fix that as the user.
Let me go ahead and say 12345, 12345.
Still not checking the agreement.
You must agree to the
terms and conditions.
So why?
>> If we've already posited
that there's a way,
and we've required you in
pset seven to detect error
conditions like this
server-side, why should I
bother also doing this in JavaScript?
What's an argument in
favor of adding what
you're about to see as some--
there's additional complexity.
>> Maybe there is no upside.
What could it be?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Oh, interesting.
Potential exploits.
So sure, if you're not handling
erroneous user input that great,
maybe it's all the better if it
doesn't even reach your server.
I would push back there and
say, you should probably
fix both of those problems.
But that's fair.
What else?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
This code, as we said before, is
interpreted on the client-side.
It doesn't bother the server,
which means it doesn't
impact the server's load or capacity.
And now, for little old me,
this has no meaningful effect
because I have one user right now.
>> But if you're any
website of decent size,
especially the biggest, like Facebook,
the more you can keep people off
of your server the better
because a server, of course,
only has a finite amount of RAM,
a finite number of gigahertz,
a finite number of things
it can do per unit of time.
So if there are more people in
the world hitting your server,
accidentally logging
incorrectly, just as well if you
can keep that load off your server.
Plus, especially on a mobile
device-- if you've ever
log into my.harvard or
Yale's netid or the like,
there's this the latency with a lot of
websites like that whereby it takes,
like, a damn second or two sometimes.
And then, my God, if you mistype,
then you have to hit back and redo it.
So there's latency, especially
on slower network connections.
But JavaScript, because
it runs on the client
and doesn't need to go back and forth
across a potentially slow internet
connection, you can get
nearly instantaneous feedback.
>> So let's look at this.
Let me open up form-0 and
look at the HTML here.
And let's just see what's going on.
This is a form whose
action is register.php.
I'm just using get so
that I could see the URL.
But for passwords, we'd surely want
to change this to post in reality.
Here's an input field of type text.
Here's another input
field of type password.
Here is, if you've never seen,
an input of type checkbox.
>> But there's no JavaScript
here whatsoever.
This is just HTML that
goes to register.php.
But in version one, where I
started to get those pop-ups,
let's see what actually happens here.
In version one, what
I'm going to see-- I
thought I could stall enough
with enough words, but I ran out.
>> In version one-- there we go.
In version one, notice the following--
and is not the best implementation,
but it's my first.
Notice that below the
form, I have a script tag.
And a script tag means,
hey, browser, here
comes some code in,
typically, JavaScript.
And now, notice what I'm doing.
On line-- I can barely
read it-- line 32, it says,
var form-- so give me
a variable called form.
And then get document.getElementId
of "registration."
What is this?
Well, let me rewind up here.
And notice, ah, I gave the form element
an arbitrary but descriptive idea
of registration.
So this gives me a variable that
allows me to grab that node,
that rectangle in the tree called form.
form.onsubmit means, hey browser,
register an event listener
on this form.
In other words, when this form is
submitted, execute the following code.
It doesn't need a name because
why do you need to know the name?
You just need to know
what to execute, ergo
it's an anonymous or lambda function.
And that function is
all of these lines here.
And now, to be honest, even though you
might not have ever written JavaScript
before, it's just C and PHP logic.
So if form.email.value==" "--
so if the email field is blank,
yell at the user with "You must
provide your email address."
Else if form.password.value
is blank yell at the user,
"You must provide your password."
>> More interestingly logically,
if form.password.value does not
equal form.confirmation.value--
where did confirmation come from?
Let me rewind.
Well, I called this input
field here password.
And I called this one here confirmation.
I could have called it
password two or anything else.
I'm just logically checking
that these two are the same.
Else-- it turns out this is Mr. Boole
again-- a Boolean value, the check box.
So if I say, exclamation point--
if not form.agreement.checked,
yell at the user as well.
>> So this syntax you'll see is
very common in JavaScript,
where you have this dotted notation.
You start with an object here.
You dive in deeper to a to
a property like password.
And then you get at its actual value.
And again, here is the input.
Here is the name password.
And its value is whatever the
human has actually typed in.
>> So in all of these
cases, I returned false.
But if not, I return true.
And so now we see a
compelling use of when
you would return false to
stop what the user's doing
and make him or her choose
again or type again.
Otherwise, we return true.
>> And let me introduce one
other variant of this just
to seed some understanding thereof.
Well, in version 2 of this, form-2--
I'll do it with a wave of a hand.
This is, for those curious,
the jQuery version,
those of you who might want to
dabble in that particular library.
But let's start-- and any questions?
Let me pause for moment because
that was fast and a lot.
>> But the nice thing here is that all
of the code is pretty much the same.
The new stuff is what is the dom?
What are these rectangles?
What are these nodes?
What's an anonymous function?
What's an event handler?
But thankfully, most of that is just
full circle from, say, week zero.
All right.
So something slightly more interesting?
Well, first of all, let me go
ahead and open up Google Maps.
And you'll notice that for a
moment, on the split second,
notice what happens when
I click fast enough.
And this connection at Harvard is so
fast that you don't really notice it.
But what do you kind of sort of see
if I click and drag really fast?
Those of you watching online,
if you slow this to 0.5x speed,
you can see this better.
>> What was happening just
before I clicked and dragged?
Let me try here-- let me do
something else, like 90210.
Let's go far away.
That was really fast, too.
How about Disney World?
There we go.
OK.
What did you see for a split second?
Just, like, squares, right?
Placeholders for tiles?
>> Well, what's going on here?
Google Maps is a nice example of
this technology that's called AJAX.
And this is where we'll start to
use the JavaScript in a particularly
alluring way.
Back in the day, there was
this website called MapQuest.
And I should have taken a
screenshot of this from the 1990s,
where if you wanted to
look up here on the map,
you would literally click an arrow
up at the top that showed you
a different square of the map.
If you wanted to move left, you
clicked an arrow that showed you
a different square of the map.
And some websites still do this today.
But even MapQuest has gotten
better, like Google Maps.
>> Instead, what's better these
days is websites that use AJAX.
AJAX-- otherwise known as
Asynchronous JavaScript and XML,
which is just a fancy way of saying
a technology or technique that
allows a browser using JavaScript
to make additional HTTP requests
after the page has been loaded.
So what does this mean?
Well, it would be kind
of annoying in Gmail
if every time you wanted
to check your mail,
you had literally hit Control-R or
Command-R or click the Reload button
and the whole darn page would reload.
Right?
It would flash white
probably for second.
You would see the stupid progress bar.
And just to see if you have new
mail, the whole web page and the URL
you're at would have to reload.
>> But that's not what happens in Gmail.
Right?
When you get a new email in
Gmail, what happens on the screen?
It just shows up, right?
It just magically appears
as a new row in the table.
That actually involves a
decent amount of complexity.
In fact, if you think about this tree,
which even though is a simple one here,
Gmail-- and I'd have to look
at the code to be sure--
probably has an HTML table or maybe
an unordered list that it renders
each of your inboxes emails as.
>> And so if you imagine this there
is a tree in memory when you're
using Gmail that looks kind of sort of
like this, when Google realizes, ooh,
you have a new email, it doesn't
want to rebuild the whole tree.
Rather, it wants to find the node in
the tree that represents your inbox
and just insert a new node.
>> So very similar to pset five, where you
had to insert nodes into a hash table,
similarly does Google, via
JavaScript code that it has written,
traverse this tree, figure out where
is that inbox part of the window,
and then insert a new row.
And a new row just means one
or more new nodes in a tree.
>> And so AJAX is this technique
that allows for exactly that.
Once you've visited a URL,
however crazy long it is,
and once the page has
been loaded, you can still
grab more data from the
internet-- whether it's
an email or a tile of a map--
grab it behind the scenes
and then insert it into the page
so that the human doesn't really
have to wait for it.
>> Facebook Messenger works the same way.
Any number of other websites--
oh, actually, even this.
I mean, this is, frankly, kind of
an annoying feature these days.
If I start searching for cats-- this
is kind of a horrible user experience.
It just starts searching for me.
Well what is it doing?
The URL hasn't really changed
since I started typing.
But what's going across the
wire-- OK, hmm interesting.
What's going across the
wire here just gets weirder.
>> OK.
So let me go ahead and inspect
element and go to the Network tab
and try to make this
technical and less about cats.
As I type, literally, cats
and-- what's happening
per-- I'm not going to click that.
All right.
So down here, what's happening every
time I type a character, apparently?
Like, low level?
What's happening with each of those
characters I'm typing at my keyboard?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Each of those characters is
going to Google, one at a time.
They are building up a string
on their server that represents
everything I've typed in thus far.
And every time I type
another character, they
use their secret sauce of a
search algorithm and figure out,
does he mean this cat page
or this cat page or the like?
So in some sense, it provides me with a
better experience in that I don't even
need to complete my thought.
And indeed, it's a useful
thing, autocomplete in general.
If their algorithms are good enough
and if my searches are obvious enough,
I don't have to type the whole word.
They're going to tell me what it
is I'm actually searching for.
So what Google calls instant
search is just using AJAX,
using code that allows them to request
additional content via a web browser
behind the scenes using this
new language, JavaScript.
So we have a couple minutes left.
And let me call up my buddy
Colton up onto the stage,
since it seemed
particularly fun last time
to introduce a technology
that some of you
have expressed an interest
in for final projects.
We thought it'd be fun to bring
up a volunteer, though, today
to show you an addition to
this that allows you-- yeah,
I saw this hand first.
Come on up.
Very well done.
Good job.
I'm going to project this on
the screen in just a moment.
What's your name for everyone?
>> EFA: I'm Efa.
>> DAVID MALAN: Etha?
>> EFA: Efa.
>> DAVID MALAN: Efa?
>> EFA: Yeah.
>> DAVID MALAN: Nice to see you.
All right.
Let me get this ready.
Come on over to the
middle with Colton here.
What Colton has in his hands
today is a remote control.
So rather than just stand there in a
three-dimensional world looking around
as Colton did, now Efa can
actually walk around by going up,
down, left, and right like a
Nintendo or Xbox controller.
EFA: I'm going to fall off the stage.
DAVID MALAN: I will
stand roughly over here.
But that is a risk.
OK.
So go ahead and put those on.
Let me go ahead and
switch to the screen here.
Let me dim the lights.
And Colton, let me
come stand next to you.
>> Do you want to explain here
with the mic what we're doing?
Here you go.
>> COLTON: Sure.
So right now we're
loading up the Oculus,
I guess operating-- not operating
system, but the main program, where
you can access all the games and
apps that are in your library.
So right now, it should say
tap the touchpad to begin.
Touchpad's going to be on the
right side of the headset.
So go ahead and tap--
EFA: Oh, man.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, there you go.
The quality Efa is seeing
is much higher quality.
This is just the Wi-Fi here.
COLTON: So what you're
going to want to do
is look towards the top
right of the screen.
Yep, that game on the very top right.
And then when you're selecting
it, tap the touchpad again.
I think its Dreadhalls.
And then here is a-- here, let
me hold your glasses for you.
>> So I just gave him a controller.
So now he can control the game.
He can move around and stuff like that.
So go ahead and look up to the top.
You should see New Game.
So go ahead and you can do that.
Now, you should be able to control
yourself with the controller,
as well, as soon as
the game loads up here.
This might be a little bit scary.
>> EFA: Now you tell me.
OK.
>> COLTON: All right.
So confirm that you can move around.
OK.
You can move around.
Perfect.
So if you look down, you have a map.
Map shows you where you are.
You can look around the room.
You can completely turn around.
Yeah, exactly.
Turn around.
>> So look to your left.
I think there's something you can
pick up on a barrel in the room.
>> EFA: How do I get the
map out of the way?
COLTON: Look up.
Just look up.
All right.
There you go.
Now go ahead and just turn around.
So look farther to your left.
Keep moving left.
Keep looking left.
Keep going.
Yeah.
>> EFA: Oh, that way.
>> COLTON: Yeah.
Walk towards it with the controller.
There you go.
Now it should say pick it up.
Pick it up.
All right.
Now, let's get out of this room.
Go ahead and walk to that door.
So you're going to hold-- it says
hold the button to force it open.
So go ahead and hold the button.
Yep, forcing it open.
All right.
Good job.
Now we're walking out of the room.
So I'm going to leave the rest up
to you and see what you find out.
EFA: I'm not going in the dark room.
Oh, wait.
Now I have to go down the dark hall?
OK, I'm going back [INAUDIBLE].
COLTON: All right.
Some more items to pick up.
Looks like some coins.
That's a lock pick.
So if you find a locked
door, you can use that.
Are you scared?
>> EFA: Not yet.
COLTON: OK.
>> Pretend-- yeah.
Just pretend you're
actually standing there.
And if you turn around--
you've got to get used to it.
But it makes sense.
DAVID MALAN: And while Efa continues to
play, since we could do this all day,
we can all tip-toe out here.
But we do have two other pairs,
if you'd like to come up and play.
Otherwise, we will see
you next on Wednesday.
Thank you to our volunteer today.
[APPLAUSE]
>> [MUSIC - "SEINFELD THEME"]
SPEAKER 1: Well, I'm
putting a new PL mount on.
I just changed the OLPF--
>> SPEAKER 2: So what
exactly are you doing?
>> SPEAKER 1: Well, each one of these--
here, I'll show you this one in here.
You can see it right here.
>> SPEAKER 3: I think I'm good with these.
You want some more?
>> SPEAKER 4: No, I'm good. [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER 3: No, [INAUDIBLE].
Have some.
SPEAKER 1: Different color.
SPEAKER 2: OK.
SPEAKER 1: So ultimately what it
does is it adjusts the color of--