>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> SPEAKER: Welcome back, everyone.
This is CS50.
And today, we have a lot of
interesting things to talk about.
First, though, I have to remind
you of a few administrative things.
This week is quiz one, Wednesday
or for the Yale section
on Tuesdays and Thursdays, on Thursday.
There are quiz reviews
tonight at Yale, 5:30 to 7:00.
At Harvard, they recorded one yesterday.
And everyone can watch that online.
>> Also, this week or early next week,
we have our last CS50 lecture.
[GROANS] I know.
It came so soon.
Yale students will have a live
lecture here in the law school
auditorium on Friday.
There will be cake.
Harvard students will have the
last lecture in Sanders on Monday.
There will also be cake.
>> Also, this week on Friday, for those
of you who are coming to New Haven,
we have the CS50 Expo.
We have more than 30
different groups registered
to show you everything
from autonomous sailboats,
to systems that recognize
digital portraits, to computer
music and computer-produced music.
So please join us.
I think it's going to be a great time.
>> Today, though, we get to
continue talking about AI,
about artificial intelligence.
And one of the things that
we're going to get to today
is the idea of how to
use AI to solve problems.
Now, as always, let's start
with something simple.
And we're going to start
with a simple idea.
And that's using search.
>> So imagine for a minute that I
have a task that I need to perform.
And I'd like to have that task
automated by some software agent.
Imagine that I'm trying to book a set
of flights from, let's say, Boston
to San Francisco.
I could go through and I could use
one of the wonderful online search
tools, which is going to do
basically the same process that we're
going to walk through today.
But if you didn't have that
tool, what would you do?
>> Well, you could look and
see and say, I'm in Boston.
What flights are available to me?
Now, maybe I have three
possible flights out of Boston
that will fit the time
when I need to leave.
I could fly to Chicago.
Or I could fly to Miami.
Or I could fly to New York.
I could then look from each
one of those destination cities
and think about what locations
I could possibly reach
from each of those individual cities.
>> So maybe from Chicago, I can get
a direct flight to San Francisco.
That's excellent.
Or I could get a flight to Denver.
Now, maybe that flight to San Francisco
is the perfect solution for me,
but maybe not.
Maybe I'm looking for something
that's a little bit cheaper
or a little bit better for my schedule.
And so I could look for what other
possibilities might be out there.
So I could look at Denver.
And from Denver, well, maybe
I can get a flight to Austin.
And from Austin, maybe I can get a
flight to Phoenix, and from Phoenix
to San Francisco.
Now, I'm not done yet.
Because maybe there's a
direct flight from New York
to San Francisco that's perfect for me.
Or maybe there's a flight from Miami
through Denver that's a lot cheaper.
So I still have to go.
And I still have to look at all of those
cities that I haven't investigated yet.
I have to exhaustively check all of
the possibilities that I might have.
>> So from New York, maybe I can get a
flight to Nashville, and from Nashville
to Austin.
And then I know where I am.
And then I know from Austin, I can
fly to Phoenix, and from Phoenix
to San Francisco.
If I fly first to Miami, though,
maybe I can get a flight from Miami
to Nashville, or from Miami to Austin.
>> And now I've tried all
of the possibilities.
I've built up this graph that
shows me all of the possible routes
that I might be able to take.
When we represent these
kinds of problems,
we're not going to represent
them explicitly as this graph,
because that graph doesn't represent
the history of where we've gone.
Knowing that I flew from
Phoenix to San Francisco
doesn't tell me whether I came via
Nashville, or via Denver, or via Miami.
>> So what I'll do instead is
I'll take this same problem,
and I'll represent it as a tree.
And at the root of the tree, at the
top, I'll put the place that I started,
Boston.
And from Boston, I'll look at
all of the possible locations
that I can travel to.
Well, in this case, I had three,
Chicago, New York, and Miami.
And then I'll explore each of
these children in the tree.
>> From Chicago, I saw
that I had two flights.
I could fly directly to
San Francisco or to Denver.
Now San Francisco, that's my goal.
That's my destination.
That's going to be a leaf of this tree.
That is, I'm never going to go
somewhere after San Francisco.
From Denver, though,
I can fly from Denver
to Austin, from Austin to Phoenix,
and from Phoenix to San Francisco.
And now again, I've reached a leaf.
>> I could then go back to the next
city that I haven't fully explored.
That would be New York, go
back up to the top of my tree,
come down to New York.
From New York, I can fly to
Nashville, from Nashville to Austin,
from Austin to Phoenix, and
from Phoenix to San Francisco.
And finally, one city I
haven't looked at yet, Miami.
>> Well, from Miami I said I had two
possibilities, Nashville or Austin.
If I fly to Nashville, well then I fly
from Nashville, to Austin, to Phoenix,
to San Francisco.
If I fly to Austin, I fly Austin,
to Phoenix, to San Francisco.
And now I have a tree.
It's a complete tree.
It's all of the possibilities and
all of the paths that I could take.
That is, if I start at the
root of the tree at the top
and I go down to one of the
leaves, it tells me not only
where I'm going to
end up, San Francisco,
but it tells me the route that
I need to take to get there.
>> Now, which one of these is the best?
Well, nothing about this
problem yet tells me
which of those is the best solution.
Maybe I care the most about
how much time I'm in the air,
or the distance that I'm flying.
In that case, Chicago to San
Francisco might be the shortest number
of miles in the air.
>> Maybe I care about cost.
And we all know direct flights
are usually more expensive.
So maybe if I take this
kind of backwards route
through Miami, Nashville,
Austin, Phoenix, maybe then
I get a lower price.
But I could optimize on any
criteria that I care about.
Who's got the best in
flight Wi-Fi, or which
airports have the best food available.
And each of those might
give me a different solution
that I see as being the best.
>> These kinds of problems,
where we're going
to build out this tree of
possibilities, and then
look at each of those
individual paths, and examine
which of those fulfills
a criteria for us,
we're going to call
those search problems.
And we have lots of
algorithms, some of which
we've seen already, to go
and explore those trees.
We could do it in the way that I
just did, a depth-first search,
going down as far as we can until we
hit a leaf, and then coming back up,
and going right back down.
Or we could do what's
called breadth-first search.
We could expand everything
at the top, and then
everything one line
underneath that, and then
everything one line underneath that.
Those search trees
are fundamental to AI.
But they don't quite get
it right all the time.
In fact, in a lot of the cases
that we really care about,
we want to build a tree,
but we don't actually
get to make all of the decisions.
>> These are situations called
adversarial search, also known
as how to write game playing
systems and get paid for it.
But these are the kinds
of systems where I
might get to choose when I go from
Boston, which city I go to next.
But after that, someone else might get
to make the decision about where I fly.
So to build these
kinds structures, we're
going to have to take a slightly
different approach to it.
We're not going to be able to
just search through the tree
anymore, because we're not
the one that's in control
of each of those decision points.
>> So let's imagine a simple
game like tic-tac-toe.
I could start with a
completely blank board.
And in tic-tac-toe,
X gets to play first.
And so I could think about all the
possible moves that X could make.
And if I'm the one playing
the X, that's great.
I have nine possible
moves that I can make.
I could put an X in any one
of those nine positions.
>> And then from each of those, I
could imagine what happens next.
Well, in this case, the other
player would get to take a turn.
O would get to take a turn.
And from each of those, there
would be eight different places
that O could place their marker.
>> Let's say I decided that I was
going to put an X in the center.
That always seems like
a good opening move.
I could look at underneath that, the
eight possible moves that O makes.
Now, if I'm playing X, that's wonderful.
I get to choose which one I
go to, the one in the middle.
But now O gets to choose.
And I don't have control
over that decision.
>> But from each of those
possible board positions,
there's then another
set of possibilities.
When it comes to be
my turn again, I would
get to pick and say, well,
if O moves into the, well,
the middle spot on the left, then
I have a set of possibilities
where I can take my next move.
From those, I could consider all of
the possibilities underneath them.
And then O would get
to choose among those.
>> And I could keep building this
tree out until I got to the point
where either someone
wins the game-- that's
got to be considered a leaf node--
or the board is completely full
and no one has won.
And that's also going to be a leaf node.
That's going to be a tie.
>> But the tricky thing with this is
if this were just a regular search
problem, I'd be able to
say, well, X should go here.
And O should go way over there.
And then X should go over here.
And then O should go way over there.
And then X can get three
in a row, and I win.
And the game would be over
in five moves, three for me,
two for my opponent.
But I don't always get to choose that.
>> So instead, what we're
going to have to do
is we're going to have
to have a new strategy.
And the strategy that
game-playing algorithms often use
is what's called minimax.
The central idea of
minimax is that we're
going to pick the move that gives
our opponent the worst possible set
of moves that they can make.
It doesn't do me any good
to choose a move where
I might be able to win after
that, because my opponent isn't
going to give me that chance.
They're going to choose some
terrible outcome for me.
So I'm going to make the
move that forces my opponent
to do something better for me.
All right.
Let's see how that plays out.
So here's our algorithm in pseudocode.
We're going to generate
the entire game tree.
We're going to build
the entire structure.
And then we'll go through.
And at the very bottom at each of the
terminal nodes, at each of the leaves,
we'll evaluate how
valuable is that to me?
And we're going to value things that
are good for me as being positive.
Things that are not good for me
will be less positive, or zero,
or even negative.
>> So in tic-tac-toe, maybe
a win for me is good.
That's a one.
And a tie is zero.
And something that's a loss for
me, maybe that's a negative one.
All that matters is that the better
it is for me, the higher the score
it receives.
From those possibilities at the
bottom, then we'll filter upward.
And when it's my chance to choose
among a set of alternatives,
I'll choose the one that's
got the highest score.
>> And whenever it's my
opponents turn to choose,
I'll assume that they're going to
choose the one with the lowest score.
And if I do this all the way
up to the top of the tree,
I'll have chosen a path that gives
me the best outcome that I can get,
assuming that my opponent
makes all the right moves.
>> All right, so let's see
this in action first.
And then we'll actually
look at the code for it.
So imagine I have this big tree.
And now I'm not playing tic-tac-toe.
I wanted to give you
something a little bit richer.
So I've got some game where
there's many different scores
that I could have at the end.
And so I build this complete tree.
And I get to move first.
I'm at the root of the tree.
>> And I get to choose that-- so I get
to maximize across that first node.
And then my opponent gets to go.
And then I get to go once more.
So down at the bottom, I have a set of
possibilities that I can choose from,
different terminal states of the game.
If I'm down in that
far left hand corner,
and I see that I've got a choice
between an eight, a seven, and a two,
well, I'm the one that gets to choose.
So I'm going to choose
the best one of those.
I'm going to choose the eight.
>> So I know that if I ever
get down to that point,
I'll be able to get that eight points.
If I end up at the next point
over, the next node over,
a nine, a one, or a six, well, I'm
going to choose the best of those.
I'll choose the nine.
If I have a choice between
two, and four, and one,
I'll choose the four, the highest.
>> Now, if I look at the level
above that, my opponent
is the one gets to make that choice.
So my opponent gets to
choose, do I want to give him
the thing that's going
to get him eight points,
or do I give him the thing that's
going to give him nine points,
or the thing that's going
to give him four points?
And my opponent, being
rational, is going
to choose the minimum of those,
is going to choose the four.
>> And I can do this
through the entire tree.
I can go down to that
middle set of three.
And I can choose between
one, three, and five.
And I get to choose.
So I choose a five.
I can choose three, nine, or two.
I get to choose, so I choose the nine.
Six, five, or two, I choose.
I get to choose the six.
Level above that, who gets to choose?
Who gets to choose?
The other guy, my opponent.
So they choose five,
nine, or six, which one?
>> AUDIENCE: The five.
>> SPEAKER: They choose the five.
They get to choose the minimum.
And then the last one,
choose one, two, or three.
I get to choose, so I choose three.
Nine, seven, or two, I choose nine.
And 11, six, or four, I choose 11.
My opponent then chooses three,
nine, or 11, chooses the minimum.
He gives me a three.
And then finally at the top of
the tree, I get to choose again.
And I get to choose between
a four, a five, or a three.
So I take the five.
>> If I got to control everything, I'd
take the path that led to the 11.
But I don't get to make that choice.
If I go down that path.
My opponent will force me into
the choice that leads to a three.
So the best that I can do is
to take that middle branch,
make that choice that's eventually
going to lead me to five points.
That's what minimax does.
>> All right.
Let's take a look at that.
So here in the CS50
IDE is a program that
implements minimax to play tic-tac-toe.
We're going to build
up a representation.
We're going to have two opponent--
or two players, our computer
player and a human player.
Player number one will be playing
the O. That'll be the machine player.
They get to move second.
And the other player, our
human player, will be X.
>> And to make my life a
little simple, I'm going
to label that player negative one.
So I can just multiply
by negative one to swap
between one player and the other.
All right, so let's take a look at
what we're actually going to do.
We're going to define our board.
It's going to be, well, we're going
to allow it to be three by three,
or we can even play
five by five or seven
by seven tic-tac-toe if you'd
like, based on some dimension D.
>> And we'll have a couple
of helper functions
that'll do things like
initialize the screen-- or sorry,
initialize our variables, clear the
screen, draw the board on the screen,
one that checks a board
to see whether or not
there's a winner, one that
parses through the command line,
just to help out, one that reads in
input, and one function called minimax.
And that's the one
we'll care most about.
But let's look first at the main.
>> What do we do?
Well, we're going to
parse our command line,
just read in and see what
dimension board we'd like to have.
We'll initialize our board.
And then we'll enter one
big wild loop, repeatedly
accept moves until the game is
won, or there's no moves left.
Every time we go through that
loop, we'll clear the screen.
We'll draw the board on the screen.
And we're deliberately sort of
abstracting these away as subroutines,
so that we don't have to worry too much
about the details of how they happen.
>> You'll have the code later today.
And if you want to look through
and find out, you can see them all.
But we'll draw a board on the screen.
And then we'll check and
see, do we have a winner?
Has someone won this game?
If they have, we'll print
out a victory message.
And we'll end the game.
>> We'll also check and
see if there's a tie.
It'll be easy to see if there's a tie.
It means that all the spaces are full,
but there hasn't been a winner yet.
We can declare a tie and be done.
Then the real meat-- if
it's a machine player,
we'll allow that
machine player to search
through using this minimax algorithm,
to find the best move that it can.
And then we'll put that move up.
>> Otherwise, if it's a human player,
we'll read some input from the human.
And then whether it's the human
player or the machine player,
we'll do a couple little
bits of error checking,
make sure it stays within the boundaries
of the actual dimensions of the board
that we have, make sure
that that space is empty,
that no one's put a
piece in there already.
And then we'll just put
a piece on the board,
change the player to the next layer, and
increment how many moves have happened.
>> That's the main loop for
our tic-tac-toe game.
Minimax, then, is exactly
the algorithm that we before.
The only adjustment that
we've made so that we
can play higher
dimensional boards is we've
kept this extra parameter called depth.
And depth just says, if I'm
searching downward through that tree
and I get so far down
beyond some level depth
that I just don't want
to go any further,
I'm going to stop and just
evaluate the board at that point.
I'll check and see if there's a winner.
If there's a winner, I return them.
Otherwise, I'll go through a loop.
And I'll say, for all of
the possible locations
that I could possibly
take as my move, I'll
build a hypothetical board that
includes my move on that board,
and then recursively calls minimax.
>> If it's my move, I get to find the
one that's got the largest score.
If it's my opponent's move, we find
the one that's got the minimum score.
And everything else is
just record keeping.
All right, so let's see this run.
Actually, maybe we can
get a couple of volunteers
to come up and play tic-tac-toe.
[INAUDIBLE] one, and one
more, two, right there.
Come on up.
>> So let's go ahead and
restart this completely.
So, hi.
>> AUDIENCE: Hi.
>> SPEAKER: What's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Gorav.
SPEAKER: Gorav.
>> AUDIENCE: I'm Layla.
>> SPEAKER: And Layla, and Layla, sorry.
Come on up.
Gorav, we're going to have you go first.
And I'm going to ask you to be a not
terribly good tic-tac-toe player.
OK, so all the pressure is off on you.
Let's see, though, that our machine
player can actually do something smart.
So go ahead.
You're going to type in which coordinate
you would like to put your X in.
A0, OK, and the machine has gone
right away and put its mark in A1.
>> Put the O on the board.
All right, now go ahead.
Where would you like to go?
C2.
Our machine player has taken
the middle square, blocked you.
So that was a good,
smart thing for it to do.
You've blocked it.
That's excellent.
It takes the corner there.
>> And it's going to force you to
take the one last space, B0.
And the game ends in a tie.
But it played a reasonable
game against you, right?
All right, thanks very much, Gorav.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> All right, Layla, we're going
up the game on you here.
>> AUDIENCE: Oh, great.
>> SPEAKER: We're going to give
you four by four tic-tac-toe.
Now, in four by four, you have to win
with four in a row, not three in a row.
And it's all yours.
So Layla took D1.
We're now going to follow
our computer player here.
Three by three tic-tac-toe is the kind
of thing that is easy for all of us.
But it's still nice to see the
computer player making smart moves.
Four by four gets to
be a little trickier.
>> Nicely done.
All right, so Layla's finished off.
Oh, and we should have ended there.
But let's do one more up here.
So Layla, thank you.
Nicely done.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> So our tic-tac-toe player goes
through and finds locations,
solves them using this minimax.
And I had a depth setting
on that so that it
wouldn't run too fast,
which is probably why
Layla was able to go nicely ahead
as she did, and did very well.
But these systems that just
go through and brute force
go deeper, and deeper, and deeper,
and keep finding the solution
that they need, those kinds of systems
are quite successful at these, well,
standard board games.
>> And in fact, if we look at a
three by three tic-tac-toe game,
this is basically a solved problem.
And this is a wonderful diagram
from Randall Munroe at XKCD,
showing which move you should
take, given your opponent's moves.
This is something that we could
easily specify ahead of time.
But what happens as we get to more
complex games, more intricate games,
where there are bigger boards, more
possibilities, deeper strategy?
>> It turns out that this
brute force searching still
does reasonably well, except
when you get to the point
where that tree is so large
that you can't represent it all.
When you can't compute the entire tree,
when you can't go forward and push
yourself to the point where you've
gotten the entire tree in memory,
or whether you can get it
in memory and it will just
take you way too long to search through
it, you have to do something smarter.
>> In order to do that, you
have to do two things.
First, you have to find some
way of limiting your depth.
Well, that's OK.
We can find some nice, bare minimum
and say, you can only go so deep.
But when you do that, that means you
have these partially incomplete boards.
And you have to choose, do I like
this partially incomplete board,
or this partially incomplete board?
>> And on our four by
four tic-tac-toe game,
our computer player got down
to the bottom and it said,
I've got two different boards.
Neither one is a win.
Neither one is a loss.
Neither one is a tie.
How do I choose between them?
And it didn't have a
smart way of doing that.
>> We see this kind of
evaluation happen all the time
as we get into more complex games.
Chess is a great example.
In chess, we have, first
of all, a larger board.
We have far more pieces.
And the positioning of these pieces
and the way that these pieces move
is critically important.
So if I want to use minimax,
I need to be able to specify
and say, this board, where
no one has won or lost yet,
is somehow better than this other
board, where no one has won or lost.
>> To do that, I might do
things like I might just
count how many pieces do I have
and how many pieces do you have?
Or I might give different
pieces different points.
My queen is worth 20 points.
Your pawn is worth one point.
Who has more points total?
Or I might consider things like,
who's got the better board position?
Whose turn is it next,
anything that I can
do to evaluate more accurately
which of these possibilities
is better without
exhaustively considering
every move that could come after that.
>> Now to make that work,
one of the things that's
going to become really important
for us is not just moving straight
down to a particular depth
limit, but being able to say,
one of these ideas that I
have is so bad that it's
not worth considering
all of the possible ways
that things can go from bad to worse.
To do that, we'll add into minimax
a principle called alph-beta.
And alpha-beta says,
if you have a bad idea,
don't waste your time trying to
find out exactly how bad it is.
>> So here's what we're going to do.
We're going to take the same
principles that we had before,
the same minimax type
of search, only we're
going keep track, not only of the
actual values that we have, but we'll
keep track of the best possible
value that I could get,
and the worst possible
outcome I could have.
And any time the worst possible
thing is looking likely,
I'll abandon that part of the tree.
And I won't even bother
looking at it anymore.
>> All right, so imagine that we start
with this same exact game tree.
And now we're going to go
down again, all the way down
to that bottom left corner.
And in that bottom left corner, we
look and we evaluate this board.
Maybe it's a four by four tic-tac-toe
board, or maybe it's a chess board.
But we look at it, and we evaluate
it, and we get a value of eight.
>> At that point, we know that
we are going to get at least
eight points from this bottom decision.
It doesn't matter what the other
two are, that seven and that two.
They could be any values
they wanted to be.
We're going to get at
least eight points.
All right, but we could
go ahead and check.
Maybe one of them is better than eight.
>> We look at the seven.
Is that better than eight?
No, that doesn't change
our opinion at all.
We look at the two.
Is that better than eight?
No, that doesn't change
our opinion at all.
So now we know we've exhausted
all of the possibilities there.
We're not going to get
anything better than eight.
We're going to get exactly eight.
>> And so we change that node and
say, that is now a certainty.
We go up one level above that.
And now we know something
about that minimization level.
We know that we're never going to get
more than eight points if we go down
that direction.
Because even if those
other two branches turn out
to be fantastic and worth
thousands of points each,
our opponent will give us the
minimum, and give us the eight.
All right, well, let's see.
We'll keep going down that path.
We go down to that middle on the left.
We look down and we see there's a nine.
We know that we're going to get
at least nine points by going down
that middle road.
And at this point, we can just pause.
And we can say, look, I
know in the level above,
I'm going to get no more than eight
points by going down this direction.
But if I went down the middle
path instead of the left path,
I would get at least nine points.
>> My opponent is never going to
let me go down that middle path.
They get to choose.
And they're going to choose the
path to the left towards the eight,
rather than down the middle towards
what's at least nine points.
So at that point, I'll stop.
And I'll say, you know what?
I don't have to look any
more down in that direction.
Because I'm never going to get there.
>> I can skip over that one,
and I can skip over that six,
because that's never going to happen.
So I'll go down and I'll
consider the next possibility.
I go down there and I say, I see a two.
I know if I get to here, I'm
going to get at least two.
OK.
I keep going.
I see a four.
I know I'm going to get at least four.
There's still a lot between
four and eight, though.
So I keep going.
I look down and I see there's one.
All right, I know if
I go down this path,
I'm going to be able to choose the four.
What's my opponent going to do?
Between something that gives me
eight, something that gives me four,
and something that
gives me at least nine,
well, he's going to give me the four.
And I know now at the
very top, I'm going
to be able to get at least
four points out of this game.
>> The whole idea of alpha-beta
is to cut off parts the tree so
that I don't look at them anymore.
But it still looks like I've been
looking at a lot of the tree.
Let's keep going down.
We'll go down the next one now.
Down at the bottom, I find a one.
I know I'm going to get at least one.
I keep looking.
>> I find a three.
I know I'm going to get at least three.
I keep going.
I find a five.
I know I'm going to get five
if I get down in that path.
And I also know then
that my opponent, if I
choose the middle of
the three big choices,
he's going to give me
something that's five or less.
>> OK.
I can keep going there.
I can look down and I
can say, what am I going
to get if I go down the middle path?
I'm going to get, well, three there.
I'm going to get something
that's at least three.
There's still things between
three and five, so I keep looking.
Oh, a nine, I'll definitely
take that over a three.
I'm going to get at least nine
if I go down that middle path.
>> Now my opponent stops and says,
look, there's no point anymore.
I know that my
minimization opponent, he's
going to give me the thing that's
less than or equal to five,
rather than the thing that's
greater than or equal to nine.
I stop.
I don't look any more at that.
I keep going.
>> I look down on this one.
Down to the bottom, I find a six.
I know I'm going to get at least six.
And what can I do?
I can stop.
Because there's a choice between
something that's at least six
and something that's
less than five, he's
going to give me the thing
that's less than five.
And now I know I'm going
to get exactly that choice.
I'm going to get that five choice.
>> I go back up to the top.
Which am I going to
choose between something
that's greater than or equal to four,
or something that's equal to five?
I'm going to take something
that's at least five.
I go down the last path, all
the way down to the bottom.
There's a one.
OK, at least I'm going to get one point.
I keep going.
Two, oh, that's better than one.
I'm going to get at least two.
I find a three.
I know I'm going to get three.
>> And the point above that,
my opponent is going
to give me something that's
less than or equal to three.
And now I can stop.
Because in the choice between me being
able to get a five and my opponent
giving me something less than three,
I'm always going to take that five.
So I don't evaluate that
bottom part of the tree at all.
>> Now, this may seem minor.
But when little bits of arithmetic,
greater than and less than,
can cut away entire parts of
this exponentially growing tree,
that leads to a huge
amount of savings, savings
that are large enough that I
can start playing competitively
at more complex games.
>> All right, if we look at the size
and complexity of different games,
tic-tac-toe was our easy example.
We've got a small board, three by three.
We get, at most, an average of
about four different choices
as we go through the game.
We have somewhere around 10 to the
fifth possible different leaves.
And building a tic-tac-toe
player, well, we just did it.
It's easy.
>> If we go up to something more
complex, like Connect Four.
Do you remember this game where
you drop the little tokens in?
It's a six by seven board,
not that much bigger, still
has about the same branching
factor as tic-tac-toe.
I have about four choices
where I can put things in.
But now, I've got a lot more
leads, 10 to the 21st power.
That's something that's easy
enough that we solve it right away.
>> Checkers, more complex-- you
got an eight by eight board.
You're only on half of
them at any time, though.
You've got a branching
factor that's about 2.8.
Well, we've got a couple
moves you can take.
You've got about 10 to the 31st leaves,
larger, and larger, and larger spaces.
As I have to search through
those bigger and bigger spaces,
that's when things like alpha-beta and
being able to cut away entire branches
becomes essential.
>> Now, checkers was easy enough in 1992.
A computer program called
Chinook beat the world checkers
champion, Marion Tinsley.
And since then, no
human master player has
been able to beat the best
computational systems.
If we look at something like chess, now
again, we have an eight by eight board.
But we have much more complex
pieces, much more complex movements.
We have a branching factor of about
35, 35 possible moves on average
that I can take, and a state
space, a number of leaves
that's grown to 10 to the 123rd power,
enormous numbers of possibilities.
>> Even still, modern processors
are able to do this successfully.
In 1995 and then in 1997, a computer
program called Deep Blue built by IBM
that ran on a giant supercomputer
beat the current world champion,
Garry Kasparov.
This was a turning point.
Today, though, that same processing
power sits on my MacBook.
>> Processing speed keeps
getting faster and faster.
We can evaluate more and more
boards quicker and quicker.
But more importantly, we have better
evaluation functions and better pruning
methods.
So we can search the
space more complexly.
The biggest of the board
games that we can think of,
something like Go that's
got a 19 by 19 board,
now suddenly, we're past the point
where computational systems can win.
There's no computational
system out there
that can beat a professional Go player.
The best systems today rank it about
the sort of good amateur level.
So there's still quite a bit out
there that you can't get to yet.
>> All right, these
traditional board games,
these kinds of systems where we
build this minimax, whether it's got
alpha-beta or not, these algorithms work
because there are certain constraints.
We have perfect information
about the world.
We know where all the pieces are.
The world is static.
Nobody gets to move the
pieces around while I'm
sitting there thinking, taking my turn.
There's an action space that's discrete.
I can put my pawn here,
or I can put my pawn here.
I'm not allowed to put my pawn on
the line in between the two squares.
>> And finally, the actions
are deterministic.
I know that if I say,
rook to knight three,
my rook is going to end up at knight
three, as long as it's a valid move.
There's no uncertainty about that.
Now, as I go to more
different kinds of games,
we have to break those assumptions.
>> What if I go to something
like classic video games?
Here's a selection of video
games from the Atari 2600.
What do I have up there?
I've got Frogger, Space
Invaders, Pitfall, and Pac-Man.
What kinds of environments
do I have here now?
Which of these assumptions
do I have to break?
>> Well, it depends on the game.
I could play chess on the 2600, and
it would be just like it was before.
For most of these systems, there's
complete knowledge about the world.
There's completely
deterministic actions.
But usually, the world's
no longer static.
That is, while I'm sitting there
waiting, something is moving.
The ghosts are coming to get me.
The scorpion is following me underneath.
The space invaders are
coming closer and closer.
How well can we do against these?
>> A few years ago, Google
had a project called
DeepMind, where they trained a computer
program to play Atari 2600 games.
And if you think this isn't serious
business, the results of their study
were published in Nature, so
just about as good a publication
as you can possibly get.
And here's how well they performed.
>> They have an algorithm that sat
and watched just the screen inputs.
It got no instructions whatsoever
about the rules of the game.
And it was supposed to figure out,
based its score, how well it was doing.
This was a system that used something
called reinforcement learning.
That is, it looked at its score.
And if it got a good score, it said,
I should remember those things.
And I should do those again.
And if it got a bad score, it said,
I shouldn't do those things again.
>> This is the performance
of those trained systems
allowed to play for a
few hours on each game,
compared against professional gamers.
So for all of the games that are
to the left side of this line,
this self-trained computer program
outperformed the professional gamers.
And for everything to the
right, the professional gamers
were still the best.
For something that knew
nothing about the rules, that
knew nothing about the structure of the
games, this is impressive performance.
And this is what we're able to do today.
>> OK, you say, but if we
think about AI in games,
normally we think about the
things that we can actually
sit down and play against.
If I sit down and I play
StarCraft, or I play Free Sieve,
the computer opponent is the
person controlling the Zerg,
or controlling the other civilization.
How do those players
actually find their moves?
>> Well, these games are structured
much the same way as our board games,
these games that we'll
collectively call four X games,
explore, expand-- forget the ones.
What are they?
Explore, expand, and extinguish,
I think is the last one.
But they're basically
exploration and conquer games.
Typically, the computer opponent
there has limited information.
They don't know exactly what's
going on behind that fog of war.
They don't get to see what
you have in your inventory.
>> There's an environment that is dynamic.
Everything is changing all the time.
You don't get to sit and
wait to take your move.
But most things are still discrete.
I have to put my city here.
Or I have to put my city here.
And everything is deterministic.
When I say, move my unit here, my unit
moves here, unless an obstacle suddenly
comes into play.
Now, that's not all computer
games that are out there today.
>> If I go and I play a first person type
game, something like Thief or Fallout
or Skyrim, or Halo, now
I have computer opponents
that are out there that have
a very different situation.
They have, again, limited information.
They only can see a
certain field of view.
The environment is still dynamic.
Things are changing all the time.
>> But now I have a much more
continuous action space.
I can be just peeking a
little bit out of the doorway.
And some games, my
actions are stochastic.
I get to try to jump over that wall,
but I've got a chance of failing.
These types of games are getting closer
and closer to the kinds of controllers
that we build in robotics.
>> In robotics, we have to assume
that we have limited information.
We have sensors that
tell us about the world.
We have an always-changing,
dynamic environment.
We have a world in which space is
continuous, rather than discrete.
And our actions, when we try
them, have a chance of failing.
And in fact, modern game
controllers for your Halo opponent,
or for those NPCs in Skyrim, basically
run small robotics architectures.
>> They sense the world.
They build a model of the world.
They compute based upon a set of
goals that they'd like to accomplish.
They plan actions based
on what they know.
And those are exactly the same kinds
of systems that we build in robotics.
So these architectures, to
bring this back together,
are often quite the same.
>> So let's see if we can see that.
Let's go back to our
tic-tac-toe example.
And I'm going to ask a couple of my
post-docs to come up and help me.
So Chen Ming, and Alessandro, and
Olivier, if you guys would come up.
And I'm going to need
a couple of volunteers
>> OK, I saw a hand up right
there in the middle.
Let me take one more, somebody
further in the back maybe.
All right, over there.
Come on up.
All right.
So let's take that cover down.
And if you guys would come right
back around here for me, fantastic.
>> So this is a robot called Baxter.
And Baxter is a robot that's a
commercial platform, designed
by a company called Rethink.
And this robot is designed
for small-scale manufacturing.
But today we're going to
use it to play tic-tac-toe.
Now, this robot is also something
that's relatively unique.
Because if I were standing anywhere
close to a standard factory automation
system, I'd be in very grave
danger of being injured.
>> Baxter, however, is designed to be
relatively safe to interact with.
And so I can push on this robot.
And you can see it's a little
bit flexible as it moves around.
And I can reposition it
where I'd like it to go.
Now in a normal robotic system,
we would have a set of joints here
that would be directly
responding to position commands.
And they wouldn't necessarily care
if they were moving through open air,
or if they were moving
through my ribcage.
>> OK.
And typically, if you were
here with an industrial system,
you would go nowhere near it.
There would be yellow
safety tape all around it.
This system has a
slightly different design
to be friendlier and easier
for people to interact with,
in that in each joint, there's a spring.
And rather than controlling
an exact position,
we control a certain amount of
torque, a certain amount of force,
that we would like to be on that spring.
All right, so let me
take our volunteers here.
Hi, what's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Louis.
>> SPEAKER: Louis.
Nice to see you.
And?
>> AUDIENCE: David.
>> SPEAKER: David.
Nice to meet you.
If you guys would wait
right here for a second,
I'm going to give you
a chance to do this.
So this robot, if you come up
and if you push gently on it,
you're going to see that
it moves a little bit.
And if you grab it right
here on the wrist just
above where those buttons are, it
looks like you should grab the buttons,
but grab right above it instead, you'll
be able to very gently manipulate it
through space.
Louis, you want to give it a try?
So give it just a little
push to start with.
And then if you put your fingers
right there and hold onto to it,
because it will move for you then.
All right, you want to give it a try?
Come on up.
So give it just a gentle
push there to start.
You can feel what it's like.
And then if you grab it right there,
you'll be able to maneuver at around.
>> OK.
So typically, this kind of a robot would
be used for small scale manufacturing.
And I'm going to move this arm just
down out of the way a little bit here.
But today, we're going to use the
same tic-tac-toe playing system
based on minimax that we built earlier.
OK?
So, you guys are each
going to play a game.
Louis, you're going to be first.
Let me just hold up here for a second.
I'm going to have you stand right
here, just so everybody can see you.
Are you guys set up here?
>> ROBOT: Welcome.
Let's play tic-tac-toe.
Do not grasp your token before
I say that it is your turn.
I start the game.
It is my turn.
SPEAKER: Now, if you could take one of
your pieces and go ahead and place it.
ROBOT: It is your turn.
[LAUGHTER]
It is my turn.
It is your turn.
SPEAKER: The human race is
counting on you here, Louis.
>> ROBOT: It is my turn.
>> SPEAKER: So Baxter
successfully blocked here.
>> ROBOT: It is your turn.
It is my turn.
It is your turn.
SPEAKER: And we'll let Baxter
finish out its last move here.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> ROBOT: That's a tie.
I will win next time.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> SPEAKER: All right,
thanks very much, Louis.
Thank you.
You can go this way.
>> ROBOT: I start the game.
SPEAKER: So let me explain
to you one more little
bit before we get our rematch here.
What exactly is happening?
So the robot has a camera up top here.
And it's looking down at the board.
And it's seeing whether
it's got a red O or a blue
and white X. As those get placed on the
board, that's basically the same input
that we would be reading in from
our data structure from our screen.
It's running the same
minimax algorithm to be
able to find where to
place a good token.
>> And then we're giving a command about
where we'd like a token to be placed.
The arm is moving out.
It's using a vacuum gripper to apply
some suction to that wooden piece,
pick it up, move it to the right
spot, and then release the suction
and drop it.
All right, we're going
to give it one more shot
with a slightly smarter player here.
You ready?
All right, if you'd stand right up
here and give a-- turn out this way
so you can see everybody.
And then [INAUDIBLE].
>> ROBOT: It is my turn.
>> SPEAKER: Baxter will start.
It is your turn.
It is my turn.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> SPEAKER: [WHISPERING] Just
let him go ahead and win.
ROBOT: It is your turn.
SPEAKER: That's OK.
>> ROBOT: It is my turn.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> I win.
>> I start the game.
>> SPEAKER: All right, thank you very much.
All right, I think we've got time for
one more excellent tic-tac-toe player,
someone who can put this thing to
match, who knows what they're doing.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> Who's going to be our champion here?
All right, your friends volunteered you.
That's good enough for me.
Tell me your name again.
AUDIENCE: Tamir.
SPEAKER: Tamir, nice to see you.
All right, again, we're going to put you
right up here so everyone can see you.
You are our representative
in this match now.
Baxter is one and oh and oh.
Or sorry, one oh and one.
And it's up to you here.
Baxter will get to move first, though.
So.
ROBOT: It is my turn.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> It is your turn.
It is my turn.
It is your turn.
>> [LAUGHTER]
ROBOT: It is my turn.
SPEAKER: It's a lot harder when
you're standing up here, folks.
[LAUGHTER]
ROBOT: You humans are so easy to beat.
[LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE]
SPEAKER: Thanks very much.
ROBOT: I win.
I start the game.
>> SPEAKER: All right, so thanks very
much to Olivier, and to Alessandro,
and to Chen Ming.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> I want to make one last point.
So Baxter at the very
end there, cheated.
And that was unexpected.
One of the fantastic
things about AI is that we
do work in AI so that we can build
really interesting and intelligent
devices.
But we also do work in AI
because it tells us something
about how humans are intelligent.
>> One of the favorite
studies from my lab is
looking at what happens when
machines unexpectedly cheat.
We did this originally not with
Baxter playing tic-tac-toe,
but with a smaller robot named Nao,
who played rock-paper-scissors.
And sometimes after
playing lots and lots
of boring rock-paper-scissors games,
the robot would throw a gesture,
lose, and then suddenly change
its gesture and say, I win.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> Now, sometimes we'd also have the robot,
just as a control, throw a gesture,
win, and change its gesture
to lose, throw the match,
cheat in order to lose.
And that is not nearly as compelling.
The robot that cheats
in order to win people
respond to as if it is
out to get them, like it
is actively seeking their destruction.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> It becomes an agent.
It is like a person.
It has belief and intention.
And it's not good intention.
And the robot that throws the
game is just malfunctioning.
It's just a broken device.
Let me show you a couple of examples
of that from a few of our participants.
So here's cheating in order to lose.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-[INAUDIBLE] win.
Let's play.
>> -Wait, what?
>> -[INAUDIBLE] win.
Let's play.
>> [INAUDIBLE] win.
>> SPEAKER: And here's cheating to win.
>> -Yes, I win.
Let's play.
>> -You can't do that.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> -Yes, I win.
-You cheated.
You cheated now.
>> -Yes, I win.
>> -Hey, you cheater.
You cheat, super cheat.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> SPEAKER: These different
reactions rapidly
change our perception of the device.
Does that mean that
we deliberately build
machines that cheat because that's
the best engineering that we can do?
No, but it tells us something
really interesting about people.
That thing that cheats you and
steals your victory, that's
something that's alive, that's
animate, that's out to get you.
It has mental state.
It has belief.
It has intention.
>> That thing that hands the
game to you, that's not.
That's just malfunctioning.
This is in many ways why it's
easy to throw the game with kids.
But if you try to cheat them
and sort of claim victory
when, you know, just to shorten the
game, they'll catch you right away.
These kinds of effects that
we see coming out of AI,
they teach us a lot about ourselves.
>> All right, that's it for today.
Thanks very much to David and
the Harvard production team
for coming down.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> We'll see you for quiz one,
and then for one last lecture.
Have a great day.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J MALAN: Well, we probably need
to introduce some kind of encryption,
right?
Because then the headers of
these HTTP requests will be
scrambled so that anyone
trying to sniff your traffic
won't actually be able to see them.
So what's the solution to this problem?
Well, we need to actually introduce
encryption into the formula,
so that when that person is
transmitting data from A to B,
we can securely send--
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> The information in a way that the
adversary can't, in fact, see it.