>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> SPEAKER 1: This is CS50 and
this is the end of week seven.
Today is perhaps where we
really teaching you languages.
We introduced in the past couple of
weeks HTML and CSS, neither of which
are programming languages.
And indeed, even though we didn't
look at nearly all of the tags
that HTML comes with and nearly all
of the properties that CSS comes with,
that's kind of it for HTML and CSS.
We'll just generally
start assuming that you
understand the general ideas
of tags, and attributes,
and pages being sent
from client to server.
>> Because today we start to look at
another programming language, PHP.
We're going to do this super fast.
We're not going to teach you PHP per se,
much like we didn't aspire to teach you
C, per se, but rather programming.
And indeed, one of the
goals for this course
is not to teach you C,
or HTML, or CSS, or PHP,
or any number of other
buzz words or acronyms,
but rather the computer science
and how to program fundamentally.
And indeed, today we start to take
those training wheels off all the
further by flying through a
language called PHP, as follows.
>> Here is what this language looks like.
It turns out that there is no need for
a main function in a program written
in a language called PHP.
So that already sounds a little simpler
than C, with which we're familiar.
It turns out that if you
want to declare a variable,
you do it almost identically to C. But
there's clearly one difference here
when I declare a string,
or maybe two differences.
What looks different?
>> AUDIENCE: The dollar sign.
>> SPEAKER 1: Yes, there's dollar
sign, which we've never seen before.
And what is missing?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> SPEAKER 1: Yeah, there's no data type.
So it turns out that PHP is what we
call a loosely typed language, where
C is strongly typed.
Loosely typed just means that
there are different data types,
there are strings, and ints, and floats.
But the computer figures that out.
You the human programmer
don't have to figure it out.
So all you have to do
to declare a variable is
dollar sign, the name of your
variable, and then, for instance,
quote unquote, hello world.
>> Well this is what a
condition looks like in PHP.
Any differences?
No.
So it turns out these are identical.
And you might have fewer
branches or more branches,
but the syntax turns
out exactly the same.
Boolean expressions can
be ordered together.
Boolean expressions
can be anded together.
You still have switches.
Even if you haven't used
these, these do exist in C
and they're functionally
equivalent in PHP.
>> And in fact, in PHP they're
a little more powerful.
In C, you can only compare certain
data types like ints and chars,
whereas in PHP you can actually compare
full fledge strings without having
to worry about pointers and the like.
So here's a for loop.
This is just pseudocode
code, if you will.
But structurally it's identical to C.
>> Here's a while loop, pseudocode
therefore-- identical to C.
Here's a do while loop-- identical.
And so there's kind of
this pattern here whereby
there's a few other syntactic
features we're indeed going to see.
In fact, here is a nice
way in PHP whereby,
if you want to iterate
over an array, and you
don't want to jump through the
mental and syntactic hoops of having
int i equals 0, i less
than n, i plus plus-- which
is just a lot of annoying syntax.
You can say a little more
fluidly for each numbers
as number, where in this case
dollar sign numbers, I'm assuming,
is like an array called numbers.
And then I'm assuming number,
singular, is going to be a variable.
>> And what PHP will do for me as I iterate
over this loop is, on each iteration,
it's going update the variable number to
be the ith element in numbers, plural.
So it just handles all of that for me.
No square brackets, no
dollar sign, no semi-colons.
It's just a little simpler.
Well, if you want an
array, it turns out you
can do something pretty similar to
C. The syntax is a little different.
But here's an array called
dollar signed numbers.
And I use, in PHP, square
brackets, it turns out.
And we're going to see these again
in JavaScript-- yet another language.
I just use square bracket notation
to have a comma separated list
of integers, in this case.
But that gives me an array.
>> But even more powerful in PHP,
we also have what are generally
called associative arrays.
And a lot of languages
have these as well.
The thing about C arrays
is that the indexes
for an array, the thing that you
use in square brackets via which
you access elements, must be what?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> SPEAKER 1: They have to be numbers or
integers, specifically from zero on up.
Well, in PHP, and, it turns
out, in other languages,
you can start to have
indexes that are not numeric.
But they're actually words or
phrases, so that rather than
try to remember where something
is, or stored in a variable i,
you can actually use a word and say
that-- you can say a word like this.
>> So dollar sign quote is the
name of a variable here.
This is somewhat funky syntax
that's associating two key value
pairs for this variable.
Specifically, this is giving me
an array that is of length 2.
But the indexes are not 0 and 1.
The indexes are quote unquote
symbol and quote unquote price.
And the values of those indexes,
respectively, is FB for Facebook
and $79.53, when I last
checked a price for this.
>> What does that mean?
Well, it means that
instead of writing code
like this, where I used to do something
like dollar sign-- or rather, in C
I wouldn't even have a dollar sign.
I would do something
like quotes and then
I would do bracket i to get at some
arbitrarily numerically indexed value.
Starting today in PHP, if you
want to get at some value,
we sort of have more
semantic expressiveness.
Just a fancy way of saying we can
just call things what they are.
>> And if you want to get
at something symbol,
now you literally do
quote unquote symbol
in square brackets
instead of a mere number.
So it's a nice convenience.
And that's sort of it for now.
There's bunches of
other features in PHP.
And indeed, PHP comes with
the proverbial kitchen sink.
Dozens, hundreds of functions come with
PHP-- so many more than came with C.
>> And that's not intended to
overwhelm but rather help
you realize that we no
longer have to write code
that's sort of down here conceptually.
Now we can just start taking advantage
of much more advanced features
that languages like PHP have.
So we don't have to worry about
moving things around in memory.
We don't have to worry about malloc
and all of these lower level,
powerful details that you will wrestle
with, if not struggle with, pset5,
but you can begin to
soon take for granted.
>> In fact, let's write a super
simple program in PHP, as follows.
I'm going to go head into CS50
IDE here, and what I'm going to do
is create a new file, that very simply
is going to be called hello dot PHP.
So instead of dot c, it's
going to be called dot PHP.
And then in this file,
I can start typing.
But it turns out that the
one thing I have to know
is that any PHP file in general, needs
to start with some special syntax.
Similar in spirit to HTML, but again,
PHP is a programming language, not
a markup language.
>> So every file, and it's sort
of stupid looking I'll admit.
Open bracket, question mark, PHP.
And that's just the
language's way of saying,
hey, computer here comes some code
written in a language called PHP.
And then at the very end of your file,
you do kind of sort of the opposite.
You don't write PHP again, you just
do question mark, angle bracket.
And then anything you put inside
of these two tags, so to speak,
will be, or should be, PHP code.
>> So let's do something super simple.
I'm going to go ahead and do print
def, hello world, backslash n, save.
And now at my prompt, I'm going to
do, make hello-- no, I'm going to do,
dot slash hello.
No, dot slash, hm.
So something's different.
And indeed, this is a key difference
between PHP and languages like C. C
was a so-called compiled language.
What did it mean for C to be compiled?
What was the implication?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Wrote it into machine code
so it could be run by the computer.
>> SPEAKER 1: Exactly.
We have to first convert it into
so-called machine code, zeros and ones,
before it will actually be executable
and understood by the computer.
By Intel inside.
By the CPU inside of the computer.
PHP, by contrast, is what's called
an interpreted language, which
means that you don't compile it
into zeros and ones, machine code,
you instead leave it as source code.
And you instead pass it as input
to a program, an interpreter
that someone else wrote
years ago that understands it
line by line, character for character.
So in other words,
humans out there wrote
a program that will look
at your code line by line,
and figure out what
the computer should do,
without converting it
directly to zeros and ones.
>> So if it sees a for loop,
this so-called interpreter
is going to be like, all right, I should
do something again and again and again.
What should I do?
Let me look at the next line.
And it truly interprets it line by line.
So to execute it, I don't use make.
I don't use dot slash in this case.
I instead do PHP, which is
the name of a program, a.k.a.
An interpreter, that's
pre-installed in CS50 IDE,
and now I need to pass a
command line argument, which
is quite simply the name of the
file that I want to interpret.
Or more casually, that I want to run.
And if I hit Enter, there we have it.
Hello world.
Now it turns out that I
used print def deliberately
to bridge us from C to PHP.
Most PHP programmers, as you'll see,
don't even bother using print def.
They just use a function called
print, which C did not have.
And so if I rerun it now, it actually
behaves functionally the same.
I can't use the percent s
and percent i and so forth,
but there are other ways
in PHP of doing that.
But this is only to
say that syntactically,
other than some weird things up
top, and some weird characters down
at the bottom, the concepts now of
programming in this other language
are going to be exactly the same.
>> In fact, let's do one other example.
So I'm going to go ahead
and close this file.
Let me create another one that
I'll call conditions 1 dot PHP.
So no zero, because what I did
was I looked back a few weeks ago,
we had a file called
conditions 1 dot C. And what
I did was converted it in my
head, and in here on paper,
and soon on the course's
website, line by line into PHP.
>> So in the C version, we did something
like string s gets get string.
So it's a little different
to do that in PHP.
Instead, I'm just going
to do, or rather, I
might have done int n gets get
int, in this example earlier.
So instead of that, I'm going to do n
gets read line, I'd like an integer,
please.
So this is just my prompt.
And so it turns out, and
I would only know this
from having read or seen the function
before, read lines of function in PHP
takes an argument that is a prompt
for the human, and its purpose in life
is to read a line of text
that he or she types in.
And then it stores that
text into the variable n.
>> And now I might want to do something
like I did weeks ago, in like week
one of the class.
If n is greater than
zero, then, I'm going
to borrow that syntax we just saw,
print def, you picked a positive number,
backslash n.
Else if n equals equals zero, I'm
going to go ahead and say, print def,
you picked zero backslash n.
Else, the case here should
of course be, print def,
you picked a negative number.
>> And we can certainly implement
the logic of this thing
in a bunch of different
ways, but the point here
is that syntactically,
barely anything is new.
It's just the dollar sign and
a new function and read line.
But fundamentally, what's new
now is I'm interpreting this.
I'm passing it as input
to another program.
So if I want to run this, if
I didn't make any mistakes,
I'm going to run PHP, of
conditions 1 dot PHP, Enter,
I'm going to type in the number 50,
and let's assume for now it works.
Because the logic is the
same stuff as week one.
>> All right, so that's pretty
underwhelming, right?
We could do this in any
number of languages.
Let's do something way more powerful.
Let's finish problem set five.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to create a file
called dictionary dot PHP,
and inclined as you might be
to scramble down lots of notes,
the notes will only help
you if you're allowed
to implement problems set five in PHP.
But we'll see how quickly now we
can implement that same problem set.
>> So in dictionary dot PHP, I am going
to assume that there is already
a file in the world called speller.
And indeed, I did this in advance,
and we won't walk through this line
by line, but if you're
curious later and really want
to wrap your mind around the
differences between c and PHP,
literally compare this file,
speller, from today's source code
that we'll post later
today, against p set
five speller dot c that we give you,
and it's almost the same line by line.
There's some more dollar signs.
A couple functions are
a little different.
But it's a nice way
of sort of seeing how
you translate one language to another.
And it's almost identical line for line.
But I'm going to assume that that
exists, and what I'm going to do here
is try to blow your
mind by reimplementing
the entirety of problem set five way
faster than you've been doing thus far.
So for instance, I'm going to first
declare a global variable called size,
and set it equal to zero.
Now that's not much savings.
Odds are you implemented
size pretty much the same,
or hint hint, will tonight or tomorrow,
just using a global variable called
size, and setting it equal to zero.
That's not a particularly
amazing spoiler.
>> So what were your data structures of
choice, those of you who have dived in
and read the spec, what data structures
have most of you have been using?
A hash table or try, maybe
some variants thereof.
So implementing a hash table at least,
is kind of a lot of lines of code,
right?
And not all of them might be
functional at this point in the week,
but that's fine.
Because in PHP, if I
want a hash table, done.
Right?
So that variable that I've
just declared is obviously
called dollar sign table,
per the introduction before.
>> But I really just want, at
the end of the day, an array.
But not a numerically indexed
array, because that's like week two
stuff, when we talked about arrays.
I want a hash table.
But a hash table is really
just a concrete way of saying,
you want an associative array.
You want to be able to
associate keys with values.
Keys with values.
What is a dictionary, really?
Well it's a whole bunch of keys.
Words like apple, pear, and banana,
and all of these English words
that we hand you.
>> And the values that you're effectively
inserting into your dictionary
are either true, or the absence, false.
In other words you are inserting
a whole bunch of key value pairs,
apple, true, pear, true, banana, true.
So that when you retrieve or look
up that data in your hash table
with your check function, you're
either getting back an answer,
yes, I found it in my complex
hash table, or no, it's not there,
so you return false.
>> So to do that, all I need is the data
structure like I proposed before.
I just need to be able
to associate words
like, quote unquote, symbol,
with a value like, true.
So there's my hash table.
Let's actually use it.
So there's a few functions
I need to implement.
I'm going to go ahead and bite
off a function called size.
It takes no arguments.
I don't have to bother with
the word, void, in PHP.
I'm simply going to return size.
>> And as an aside, PHP has
this minorly annoying detail,
where if something's global, you have to
tell the function in which you're using
it, hey, this is a global variable.
So, minor stupidity, but you
have to do it nonetheless.
>> So what about load?
I'm going to implement
a function called load
that takes in the name of a dictionary,
just like in problem set five.
And before I proceed,
notice that I haven't
been typing quite the same things.
What's obviously different in PHP about
how you declare a function versus C?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: No return type.
And indeed, that's the case, PHP
insofar as it's loosely typed,
is also a little sloppy in that sense.
You don't specify as the programmer
what this function returns.
You would have to actually look
at the code to figure that out.
Or read the comments
or the documentation.
So pluses and minuses of
these kinds of decisions.
But I do have to say
the key word, function.
And when we learn
JavaScript in a couple weeks
we're going to see the same thing
again, but it's the same idea.
The name of the function, its argument
or arguments or lack thereof, and now
here is the implementation.
>> So I'm going to cut some corners just
to be dramatic for just a moment.
But I'm going to go ahead and say this.
This is how I can load
a file into an array.
There is a function in PHP called file.
You hand it the name of a file.
It hands you back an array, inside
of which is every line from the file.
From zero, one, on up
to n minus 1 lines.
That's it, right?
There's no f read.
There's no f get s.
There's no percent s.
There's no headaches.
There's no feof.
All of that stuff with which
you've been wrestling perhaps,
with p set four and five, goes away.
>> So I just read those lines into
the file, and then you know what?
If I want to iterate over those words,
I can do, for each lines as line.
Remember that this was kind of a clever
way of iterating over an array, index
by index, and on each iteration calling
the current line, dollar sign line.
And right here I'm going to go and
say table, bracket, line, gets true.
>> In other words, this is how I
insert into my hash table in PHP.
I say dollar sign table, which
is my associative array that was
empty per the line of code up above.
I then index into it
not, using a number,
but literally using the
keyword that I care about.
Maybe it's apple or pear
or banana or whatever,
but specifically I'm indexing
into it like I proposed earlier.
I take the name of my
associative array, and then I
use quote unquote in the
square brackets with a string,
instead of an actual number.
>> And so that's it.
The load function is done.
Once that loop iterates, I've put
everything into the hash table.
Now small disclaimer, there's a
couple things I do need to fix.
And the version I'll post online
will have all of the nuances,
but it's mostly just going to be some
error checking and some minor tweaks.
But that's indeed the gist of it.
If I now want to implement
the function called
check, which expects a
word as its argument,
how might I go about doing that?
Well, I'm simply going to say, if
inside of my table, at location word,
if is set.
So if there is--
actually, you know what?
I'm going to do it in
a bit of pseudocode.
But the idea is the same.
If that equals true, return true.
All right.
Else-- you can kind of see where
this is going-- to return false.
Done.
Check is done.
>> Pretty nice, right?
And so what is this really getting at?
And this too, I cut some corners.
Look at the version online
for all of the slight nuances.
But that's the gist of it.
Index into your
associative array, a.k.a.
Hash table, see if there's a value
there, if it's set to true, and if so,
return true.
So we've whittled down
all of the complexity.
So kind of mind blowing, right?
I won't bother finishing it with unload,
because in fact-- oh, you know what?
Yeah, let's finish it with unload.
>> Unload in a hash table might look
like function unload, return.
OK so that's unload.
Because there's nothing
to unload, right?
There's no malloc.
I didn't explicitly ask the
operating system for anything.
I just started using variables.
And so this too is a manifestation of
features of higher level languages.
So again, most of this term
we've been dealing down here
with C. Super low level.
You can see the computer's memory.
You can touch anything you
want in your computer's RAM,
for better or for worse.
>> Up here, we're going
to give up that power.
But my god, look how
much less code I wrote.
In fact if I weren't talking
and talking over my typing,
we would have been done with
this example five minutes ago.
So what's the price being paid?
Well let's take a look.
Let's take a look.
I'm going to go ahead and run CS50.
Let me first go into
today's examples where
I have the texts directory as before.
I'm going to run the solution that
it comes with problem set five called
speller, which is in CS50's account.
>> And I'm going to run it on something
big like the King James Bible,
just so that we really put the
staff solutions to the test.
Now sometimes the internet's a
little slower, a little faster,
might take a while to scroll.
But it took a total of .56 seconds
to spell check the King James
Bible using the staff solution.
So pretty good.
Yours might be much slower,
and that's totally fine.
But it is correct here.
So that's the staff solution.
If I go in and clean up the PHP version.
And I'm going to do a little
like baking show thing.
We're going to take the code I wrote
earlier, so it's perfectly correct.
Because the code I wrote is not going
to be perfectly correct just now.
But if I run the PHP version,
what do I have to give up today?
Took me five minutes to
implement p set five, I claim.
What price have I paid?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Speed.
SPEAKER 1: Speed.
What do you mean?
>> AUDIENCE: It's going to take longer.
>> SPEAKER 1: All right.
Let's see.
It's going to take longer,
not to write, but to run it.
Yeah.
So let's try this.
So here I'm going to go ahead and do
PHP of speller, and because the file's
called speller.
So I'm not running the
dictionary, recall,
I'm running the program called speller.
I'm going to pass in the same
file, King James the fifth.
It's flying by.
This could just be internet speed,
so don't read too much into that.
But it does feel longer for sure.
1.26 seconds.
>> Now that's still pretty
damn fast, right?
And the only reason that felt like
more like three, or four, or five
seconds, that's just because
the internet was being slow.
The computer time spent was 1.26
seconds, versus I think 0.56.
So more than twice as slow.
Now that's still pretty darn
fast, but it's a manifestation
of, indeed, that exact price.
>> Because we're interpreting
in the code line by line,
and that program PHP is reading my
code top to bottom, left to right,
it has to do more thinking.
It has to kind of convert
it inside of itself
to the corresponding machine
code on the fly, so to speak,
even though the mechanics
are a bit different.
Instead of just feeding to the
Intel CPU the raw zeros and ones
that it understands natively.
>> So absolutely, hands down,
we have paid a price.
And code written in a language
like PHP tends to be slower.
But my god.
So now when I spell check my
file, I spend an extra 0.7
or so seconds vs 20 hours to implement
a faster spell checker, right?
It's kind of a trade off.
And if you're just starting p
set five, might not be 20 hours.
Might be far fewer than that.
But it's a trade off, for real.
And if you're running code on really big
data sets, or on even older hardware,
those kinds of differences
can certainly add up.
>> Any questions thus far?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: Sorry, can
you say it once more?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: You're giving up time.
Well, so yeah.
You are saving time by
not having to compile it,
if that's what you're asking.
And indeed, in CS50,
most of the programs,
even though they might take a while
to write, they're relatively short.
Few dozen, few hundred lines of code,
and so they compile pretty quickly.
But when you start
writing bigger programs,
like if you're Microsoft or you're
Google and writing really big programs
in C, or C++, or similarly compiled
languages, could take many seconds,
or even minutes or longer to
compile millions of lines of code.
And there too, that
difference is going to add up.
>> And in fact, once we
transition today, same day
today, to web programming
using PHP, you're
going to find it just so much
more pleasurable to write code
when you don't have to do these stupid
steps like change to your terminal
window, type make hello, re
run it, reload the window.
Just so many stupid
mechanical steps that
just get in the way of doing
the interesting, the fun work.
And indeed we throw that away with PHP.
And we can interact
with it more rapidly.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: Sure.
Can I clarify what it
means to be interpreted?
When you compile a language
like C, it goes down
as we said to machine
code, zeros and ones.
And Intel decided years ago that
certain patterns of zeros and ones
represent addition, or subtraction,
or print, or other basic operations.
In the world of an interpreted language
like PHP, or JavaScript, or Python,
or Ruby, or bunches of
others, instead someone
has written an
interpreter-- in this case,
it's also called PHP, identical to the
name of the language-- that essentially
has a big loop in it that iterates
over all of the lines of the code
that I feed it as input, like hello
dot PHP, or dictionary dot PHP.
>> And then you can think of their big
loop as having a lot of conditions.
And those conditions say, if the
human has written the keyword for,
start doing his or her
code again and again.
Or if the human has
written the line of code,
if, only execute their
next line conditionally.
So it's truly like interpreting
it in a human sense, line
by line, and that just takes time.
It takes overhead.
And so that's a price--
good question-- we pay.
So let's do another demo
that's a little more dramatic.
There is, I'd say, a ballpark this at
a 90% probability of failing horribly,
but you will be amazed
with 10% probability.
So every year we try
to do this, whereby we
try to write a program that goes through
problem set zero, for which you've
submitted your phone numbers and a
lot of other demographic information,
and we programmatically
send you a text message.
And then everyone's phone
starts beeping or vibrating,
and it's just amazing, because
well, look at what computers can do.
>> This rarely works correctly
it seems, in large part
because I typically get blacklisted
by Gmail or some other service
for actually trying to do this on scale.
But funny thing is too, since we
don't have everyone here today,
fun fact the last time we
tried this two years ago,
I think I wrote a program
that sat in a loop iterating
over all the students in the class,
and each of them a text message,
and it said something like,
why aren't you in lecture?
Love, CS50 bot.
>> You have no idea how many apologetic
and sort of painful emails
I've received in response from the
n minus 100 people who weren't here
that day.
And even funnier, more shameful story--
you know, let's put it out there.
It's already on video a few years back.
So you will soon see me
write a for loop, whereby
it's very easy to write a bug in that
for loop, such that the first time
through the loop, you
send one text message.
>> The second time through the loop I
should have sent one more text message,
and then one more text
message, and one more.
But it turns out if you make a typo
when programming, sometimes you
can write programs that send one
text message, then two text messages,
then three text messages to everyone
who's already received a text message.
And as you know, doing something,
plus something, plus something,
plus something, is big O of a lot
of text messages, or n squared,
or at $0.10 a text message, $20,000.
>> Thankfully I hit Control-C before that
happened, but I did owe at least one
of your predecessors $20 for the
200 some odd text messages that,
not only went to his phone, but
also it was like an older flip phone
so it like pushed out of his
memory every other personal text
message he had actually gotten.
So we have one goal
today, not to do that.
Maybe turn on airplane mode.
All right.
So let's go into a
program here callled--
that I will call text dot PHP.
And in advance, I've got two files here.
I made a file for just staff, that's got
all of the staff's info, all the names
from the course's website.
And then for now I just put
some fake numbers 555-1212.
So these wouldn't actually go anywhere.
But notice the inside of this CSV file,
which we talked about briefly before
in the context of file IO.
>> What's a CSV file?
Comma separated variables.
And this is kind of like a very
lightweight database, if you will.
There's kind of sort of four columns
in this file, and there jagged,
but the commas essentially
represent columns in the file.
The first column is the TF or CA's name.
Second column is their last name.
Third column is their phone number.
And fourth column apparently is--
fourth column is apparently what?
OK, so it's their carrier.
So Verizon, or Sprint, or what not.
And if I misspoke earlier, CSV.
Comma separated values is CSV here.
>> So what can I do with this?
Well this is just a big text file,
and it's kind of long, right?
Like this is going to
be kind of annoying.
And it turns out, though, that if I
want to send a text message to, let's
say Alex here.
Let me go into my browser
and exit the full screen mode
just so I can toggle back and forth.
It turns out, let's see, if I go in
here, and log into Gmail, all right.
Don't look at this part.
Just I get to see.
of course the livestream can
still see what I'm doing.
All right.
>> So here is just Gmail with
John Harvard's account.
So if I want to send a
text message to Alex,
I can of course compose a message.
And it turns out, and I've
tested it with Alex before here,
so you can append a certain domain
name to people's phone numbers,
because there exists in the world
things called SMS to email gateways.
Which is a fancy way of saying all
of us who have mobile phones that
have phone numbers, of course,
there probably is for your carrier,
a certain suffix like at
Vtext.com for Verizon text message
dot com, that you can append to your
own personal phone number, and then
you or friends, or your parents can
text you at that particular address.
>> And Verizon has a server, an email
server, that upon receiving this email,
looks at the numeric part and then
uses whatever special industry magic
they have to actually send it out over
the airwaves to your particular cell
phone.
Now this is nice because I don't
really know how to send a text message
or to write code yet
for my mobile phone,
and you might do exactly that for
a final project, but for now all
I have is my laptop here.
So I want to iterate over that CSV
file, line, by line, by line, by line,
grab each of the staff's phone numbers,
and their carrier and programatically,
concatenate, that is, connect the phone
number with the appropriate domain name
and then send an email.
>> So that's a lot of steps.
And good luck doing that in C.
It is a nightmare of a situation
to open a file, to read it
line, by line, by line, as you
are seeing, or may soon see
with problem set five, if not
problem set four, and then
to dynamically concatenate
two strings together, because in C,
to take two strings and combine them,
what do you minimally
need to do most likely?
You need to declare more memory, right?
And ask, malloc, can I have more memory?
So I can put half of this
here, half of this here.
It's just so many steps.
And by that point you've lost
interest in the stupid little demo
where you make everyone's phone beep.
Let's do this sort of PHP
style, whereby we just
start using more of that kitchen sink.
>> And the ideas are
fundamentally the same,
but we don't have to worry too
much about that lower level.
So let's see how I might
go about doing this.
And just so that I don't
repeat past mistakes,
I've written some notes for myself here.
And let's see if I can walk us
through some of the fundamental steps,
and then for time's sake we'll
perhaps cut some corners in the end.
I'm going to go ahead and do open
bracket PHP to start this file.
And I'm going to go ahead and do this.
File handle, as you'll
soon see, actually
calls a function called f open.
And remember this opens a file.
And the quote, unquote,
r means what, again?
Just open it for read.
Now in p set for, you did this.
And handle could be anything,
fu, bar, bas, any variable name.
But generally a computer
scientist would call an open file,
giving you a file handle,
something to hold onto so to speak.
I'm just going to do
some error checking.
So if the handle is false, just like
in C, I'm going to do something like,
could not open file, backslash n.
And then I'm just going
to go ahead and exit.
And it turns out, in PHP,
I'm not inside a function.
There's no main function here.
So I don't return, per se.
I exit.
Which is essentially the same thing.
And I'm exiting with one y probably.
One just means an error of some sort.
It's non-zero, so it's an error.
>> All right, so if I'm down here now
in my program I have opened the file.
I'm going to go ahead and declare
an array called addresses,
and in C I would have to know the
size of the array in advance, right?
Or I would need to declare this
is a pointer, and then use malloc.
And then every time I read
through another row in the file,
I'm going to need to malloc
more memory, malloc more memory.
That's a pain in the neck.
And thankfully, PHP, and Ruby,
and Python, and JavaScript, they
will grow your arrays
for you automatically.
No more malloc.
No more memory management.
The computer takes care of that.
But the price you pay.
It's a little slower.
And for a program like this
we're not going to notice.
We're going to send 100 text messages.
For instance not going to feel it.
IT really only starts to
matter your language of choice
when your data or your programs
get really, really sizable,
as will be the case more so
with our web based stuff.
>> But for now let's forge ahead.
While it turns out there's a
function in C called f get CSV.
File get CSV, that takes a
file handle as its argument,
and it proceeds then, row, by
row, by row, to read in a row.
So it just reads a line
of text from the file.
But what's nice about this function,
it doesn't just hand me a line of text.
It looks for those commas,
and parses the line.
And to parse the line means to split
it on certain values in this context.
>> In other words, dollar sign
row is a variable that's
going to give me a bunch of indexes.
This is going to be the
first column in my CSV.
This is going to be the second
column, this is going to be the third,
and this is going to be the fourth.
Because recall, and Excel the not
cooperate the last time we did this,
but if I download staff dot CSV.
Whoops, not rename.
If I download staff dot
CSV, and try opening it,
I've already registered-- oh I
didn't update Excel since last time.
You'll see that in staff dot
CSV, I have four columns.
So when I read in the
first row for Abby here,
dollar sign row 0 is Abby,
dollar sign row one is Lyons,
dollar sign row two is her number,
and then her phone's carrier.
>> So that's all.
And that's nice, because I
don't have to now figure out
where all of those commas actually are.
So I'm going to go ahead and
do this, given that definition,
I'm going to say that her name is
in row bracket zero, as promised.
And I'm going to grab-- and
actually, you know what?
I'm not going to worry about
her name, in this case.
I'm going to keep it simpler.
I'm going to do her number is
in row bracket two, I think.
And her carrier was in where?
Row three, one over.
So nothing new there.
It's just zero indexing into an array.
>> And now, I'm going to do the following.
If the carrier equals equals AT&T--
I'm just going to have a loop--
I want to create an email
address that looks like this.
It's going to be 617-555-1212
at, what is it, text.ATT.net,
is what I want to do.
So how do I do this?
I'm going to do the following.
Her address is going to be her number,
and now, let me go ahead and do this.
This is some funky syntax.
I could do the percent s trick,
but I can actually just do this.
>> So this is a PHP thing, but
let's consider what I'm doing.
Dollars sign address on
the left, just a variable.
Give me a variable.
I don't have to specify the type.
PHP will figure it out.
On the right hand side,
what's the data type
of that whole thing on
the right hand side?
Looks like a string,
because there's double
quotes on the far left and far right.
Now there's some funky new syntax here.
There's the curly braces,
and the dollar sign number.
But take a guess what is that syntax
probably telling PHP to do for me?
Yeah.
Just insert the value there.
So no percent s.
We could use print f, or s
print f or something like it,
but PHP and a lot of
higher level languages,
you're going to see that you could
do the same thing functionally, maybe
six different ways.
And so it starts to become
a matter of design or style.
So this is just a cryptic looking way
of saying, give me an email address,
but plug-in the number in
between these curly braces.
And the curly braces will not
end up in the final address.
>> Now we can skip over some of
these lines for time's sake.
So if a carrier equals
equals verHorizon-- whoops,
Verizon-- I want to do something
very similar, where the address gets,
quote, unquote, number at text.ATT.net.
And then I can do the same kind of
thing for the rest of the carriers.
But I'll just do dot, dot, dot for now.
And now let's suppose that
I want to add array, push.
I want to add to the
array, called addresses.
>> This address, this is how you
add something to an array in PHP.
You don't need to do malloc.
You don't have to resize the array.
You just say array, push.
What do you want to push-- what array
do you want to push something onto?
Addresses.
What you want to push onto addresses?
Address.
And in fact, if you
really want to be clever,
some syntactic sugar
for this, so to speak,
which just means how can you do this in
the prettier way, would be to do this.
That too has the effect of growing
the addresses array by size one,
and then plop that additional
email address into it.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> SPEAKER 1: A typo on the
else if-- oh, carrier.
That's OK.
It also won't like my failure to
implement part of this program
later on.
But thank you for catching.
One more bug.
Thank you.
We want this to be Vtext.com.
Yes.
All right.
So where does this leave us?
We've written the code to open the file.
We have a loop to iterate
over the rows in the file.
We have code that adds to my
array, one at a time, the correctly
formatted email address.
So all that really remains is to send
an email to each of these people.
>> So I've gone ahead and
readied myself as follows.
What I'm going to do here is-- and let's
go ahead and skip to some actual code,
which looks like this.
So here is the pre-baked
version I wrote earlier.
And notice I finished
implementing Sprint.
I finished implementing T-Mobile.
I finished implementing Virgin Mobile.
And I will apologize in advance.
There's a few carriers that
some students in the class have
that I didn't bother enumerating
in the if condition here.
So not all the texts will go out.
But let's see what else I need to do.
I close the file, just
like in p set four.
>> And this is new syntax.
And we'll see a little
bit of this over time,
especially with p set seven and eight.
But this is syntax for creating
a special type of structure.
It turns out there's a library that
comes with PHP, called PHP mailer.
Its purpose in life is to
programmatically send emails.
It's code someone else wrote that
makes it easier for us to send emails,
so we don't have to keep
going back and forth to Gmail,
and pasting in people's email addresses.
There's a whole bunch of lines here
that honestly, I just kind of copied
and pasted from the documentation.
And in fact, if you're
curious, I left all
of the URLs of the documentation
in the code that we'll post later.
And notice that among
the things I'm doing
is, I'm telling this library,
use Gmail's server, right?
SMTP we talked briefly about when we
were at Yale about being simple mail
transfer protocol.
It's the protocol that
servers used to send email,
and that's-- Gmail has one of those.
A port, this is the TCP port number.
It's fine if you
haven't seen 587 before.
Just know that from the documentation.
Here's my username.
I'm going to use the CF50 bot.
And in a moment, I'm just going to
type in the bot's actual password.
And then down here, notice what remains.
>> I set my from address
to be bot at CS50.net.
I think I won't regret sending a
text message to 800 people that
says, miss you, love CS50 bot, perhaps
for those who couldn't make it today.
And then in line 76, what do I do?
This kind of looks like C. So for i
equals 0, n equals-- now count is new.
It turns out that if you want to get
the number of things in an array,
you don't have to remember it anymore.
You can just ask a
function called count,
and it will tell you how many
addresses are in that array.
>> And then I'm going to add
the address to the email.
And I know this from
using the documentation.
There's an add address function.
And now notice there
is one piece of syntax.
We've seen this before
in C. Similar in spirit.
You can think of dollar sign
mail as a variable, which it is.
But it's a struct inside of
which are not only properties,
variables if you will.
But it turns out that in PHP, which
is an object oriented programming
language, like Java if you took APCS.
>> Dollar sign mail, if you want to--
it also has functions inside of it,
or methods.
So this is to say that
special PHP mailer
library, if I've got a variable thereof,
if I want to call a function that
comes with that library,
for today's purposes,
just know you use the arrow notation.
There's no dot notation.
It's just the arrow.
But that's not a pointer.
It's just borrowed from C's syntax.
So call add address inside of
this library's object or variable.
>> All right.
This is the magical line.
That's how I send an email.
That is the equivalent of opening up
Gmail, typing it out, and hitting send.
But it's going to instead send an
email to this address, with this body,
from the CS50 bot.
And now key line.
This line was absent in like 2011
when I think I last tried this.
That line there, of course,
clears the addresses.
So logically, if I
don't clear the address
after each iteration, the first
email or text message goes to Alice,
the second goes to
Alice and Bob, the third
goes to Alice and Bob and Charlie,
hence the very expensive mistake
I made that year.
>> So let's see.
Are there any questions
before we send you all a text
message with 10 percent probability?
Any questions?
All right.
Let's me go in here and change
the password to what should work,
will likely get blacklisted by Gmail.
So they might not all go
out, since they probably
don't like us sending 800 emails
in a for loop all at once.
Since that's not
particularly human behavior.
>> Oh, I'm going to change one other thing.
Up at the top, I'm going to sent--
change the file to students dot CSV.
And I won't open this, but this is an
identical CSV file with not 100 staff,
but 800 students, just
from Harvard, because Yale
has October recess this week.
And it seems like kind of a jerk thing
to do to text all of them as to why
they're not in class on holiday.
That's OK.
Just Harvard students
today inside of that file.
And now let's go back
to my terminal window.
I'm kind of nervous.
>> OK so now I'm going to go into the
directory, and PHP text dot PHP.
How about one brave volunteer?
So I don't want this on me.
OK, come on up.
What's your name?
MAYA: Maya.
SPEAKER 1: Maya.
Come on up, Maya.
All right.
Let's see if this works.
I put my own email address in the
file-- my own phone number in the file,
so that hopefully I'll get one as well.
Nice to meet you.
MAYA: Likewise.
SPEAKER 1: So all you have to do is
hit Enter to send 800 text messages,
if I didn't screw up.
Nice.
Could take a while, statistically,
until we get to an email address--
a text message that's
in the room right now.
Let's linger and see.
>> AUDIENCE: [WHISTLING]
>> SPEAKER 1: Oh, yes.
>> AUDIENCE: Oh, gotcha.
>> SPEAKER 1: For loops are-- this
is not slow because of PHP.
This is slow because Gmail
is throttling us and not
letting us send more than
like one email per second.
Anything?
This was a hard thing for me to test at
home with just me and my one phone, so.
Is that hopefully from the bot?
Yes?
No?
Say yes.
It's from a friend?
Awkward.
OK.
Pretty sure it's working though.
Uh oh.
They black-- oh, wait a minute.
Oh, you know what?
One moment please.
Only Maya and I-- Mia, was it?
MAYA: Maya.
SPEAKER 1: Maya, are going to
know what I did wrong here.
Oh, wait a minute.
I think I just sent 100
text messages to 555-1212.
Stand by.
I can't win any year.
OK.
Maya?
Fix that in post production.
Dammit!
Following from address.
OK, stand by.
Sorry.
It's painful every year.
OK, one moment.
This is good.
I am instead going to do this.
Print address.
OK, stand by.
Print addresses, bracket i.
Yeah, I like that.
Dollar sign-- OK I'll explain what I'm
doing in a moment, after I've run this.
Every year.
OK, here we go.
I have just-- and I don't want
to show everyone's phone number,
but Maya can confirm
with a nod of the head,
that she sees everyone's
phone number in the class
that I'm going to copy into
a program called Gmail.
And if in Gmail, what do we want to say?
Miss you.
Love-- that's not from me.
I haven't even hit send yet.
So let's go ahead and do
this, if I can zoom in.
OK.
So I'm using a program called Gmail now.
If Maya, you'd like to
click the Send button,
we will simulate what that
code should have done.
>> Anything?
>> [BEEPS]
>> AUDIENCE: Yep.
>> SPEAKER 1: Yes?
Salvation?
>> AUDIENCE: Yep.
SPEAKER 1: Miss you.
And I'm going to send out the rest.
I sent out half because I didn't think
Gmail would let those go through.
So just remember, today is the day
that you learned that I can use Gmail.
That was horrifying.
A big applause to Maya.
Thank you.
All right, so.
what
>> [BEEPS]
>> We got a few beeps, yes?
All right.
Now I'm going to get 700 really
unhappy emails back from classmates.
So at least we'll see
if that was worth it.
So what went wrong?
I'll figure out what went
wrong after the fact,
but just look how easy
it was to do that in PHP.
So what can we actually do now that
we have this expressiveness of PHP.
That was-- that was horrible.
All right.
So that was what should have gone out.
This was me testing this morning on my
phone, actual screenshot of my phone.
>> But now let's consider why
we're actually introducing
all of this stuff in the first place.
So the goal is not to
write these programs that
are written at the command line, right?
So I wrote a simple
hello program, I wrote
a little program that does conditionals,
and used a read line and so forth.
And in theory, I just wrote
a program that sent out
800 text messages, give or take 800.
And that program was all
still run at the command line.
And that of course is
not the web, right?
The goal now is to start using
what I claim is an easier to use
language, daresay a more
powerful language in terms
of the features that
come with it, to start
writing code that generates web pages.
>> So last time and last week,
we talked about HTTP and HTML.
And what's nice about HTML
is that it's just pure text.
And text is certainly
something that you can
print by literally calling the print
f function, or the print function.
And indeed, that's what PHP is
now going to allow us to do.
So among the examples we
have in today's source code,
in addition to some of the code
that I put up there a moment ago,
we have programs like this for instance.
Froshims, or Freshman
Intramural Sports, was actually
one of the first extracurriculars
I got involved with years ago.
And my roommate and I, with
some other kids on campus,
used to run the froshims program.
I'm getting my text messages now.
>> Now so we, back in the day, so this
was 1996 or so, there was an internet,
but there was no process-- there
was no website for froshims.
And so if you wanted to sign up for
soccer or volleyball or whatever,
you would fill out this thing
called a piece of paper,
and you would walk across Harvard
yard, and you would slide it
into the mail slot of the proctor, who
was in Wigglesworth, one of the dorms.
And this were you registered.
And he or she would then
compose an email to you
manually, much like I
just did here with Maya,
and then you would be confirmed
as having been registered.
>> So this was like low
hanging fruit, so to speak.
It was kind of stupid that
we were using paper for this.
I wanted us to be able
to just go on a website,
or have the freshmen go on a
website, register for sports,
and just automate a lot of this stuff
by putting their names and emails
and so forth into a database.
And in fact, the very first version
of the website, using super ugly HTML,
might have looked something like this.
It was actually, ironically, more
embarrassing looking than this back
then.
But I used a programming language.
Not PHP, but rather called Perl,
which is an older language,
but very similar in spirit.
And I just completely
taught it to myself.
And it took me a while to figure it out,
asking lots of questions of friends.
But the ideas there
were exactly the same.
Because what PHP was really designed
for is not the command line stuff
we just played with,
but for web programming.
>> It's really tied in its feature
set to the web, as follows.
This is froshims.
And if I wanted to
register in this form,
this is quite ugly,
certainly, but let me go ahead
and be a less comfortable student,
and whatever sport for Matthews,
click Register.
What I want to be able to do is
submit information from a form,
not to Google's server like
we did last time, completely
cheating by using their backend, I
want to implement my own backend code.
Which means write PHP
code that lives at a URL
that form data can be submitted to.
>> And then your code,
written in PHP on a server,
can then respond to that user input.
Like his or her name, or comfort level,
or dorm, and then do something with it.
In this case, I just
stupidly printed it out
as text, which is not all that pretty.
But you could certainly
imagine, if you know HTML,
and you'll soon know how to generate
HTML with print f, and print,
and similar functions, you can certainly
generate a prettier web page that says,
hey David, you are now registered.
You're a less comfortable
student from Matthews, right?
>> You can just use a whole bunch of %ses,
or the curly braces and dollar sign
notation I used a moment ago, to
generate text that's more user friendly
than this.
So let's take a look at this one file.
Froshim zero dot PHP looks like this.
When I reload CS50 IDE,
froshim zero looks like this.
This is froshim zero dot PHP.
And what do you notice about this file?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: Sorry, a little louder?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] It's all in HTML.
And in fact, it is, because
what's interesting about PHP
is that it was designed
to be, for better
or for worse, intermingled
with HTML code.
And in fact, even though this
file, froshim zero dot PHP,
has a PHP comment at the top
of it, it's all just HTML.
But by contrast, if I open up, let's
say, register zero dot PHP, which
just has a big comment at the top.
This too looks almost entirely
like HTML, except for what?
Line, what, 21 looks a little weird.
>> But notice I'm entering PHP mode
with open bracket question mark PHP.
Then I've got some stuff.
And then at the end of that line
almost I have, question mark PHP.
And this is what I mean by intermingled.
You can write HTML that you just
want the server to spit out.
But if you want to do something
dynamic partway through the page,
like insert my name or
dorm or comfort level,
I can use a function
like print r, which is
print recursive, which just means
print out this variable, formatting it
however you want.
It's really not for
human purposes, it's just
for debugging or diagnostic purposes.
So that's how I did that.
>> If I instead go froshims two dot PHP,
notice that the action of this form
is not registered zero dot PHP as the
old-- the previous one actually was.
But it's registered two dot PHP.
So let's look at how this one
behaves a little differently.
If I go into version two.
If here, if I register as David, less
comfortable, from dorm of Mathews,
register.
So this time it said, you
are registered, not really.
Let's see what I did here.
If I look at register two dot
PHP, this has some more PHP code.
It's a little cleaner, although it
still wraps a little long on this line.
Notice here.
I print out my HTML tag, my head tag,
my title tag, the head, the body.
>> And then I start to say
things like enter PHP mode.
And so that tag, open bracket
PHP-- question mark PHP says,
hey, server, execute-- interpret
the following stuff as PHP
until you see the end tag.
And even though you might not know any
other PHP than you've seen thus far,
you can kind of read
it pretty intuitively.
If name is empty, or comfort is
empty, or dorm is empty, what do I do?
What do I say to the user?
You must provide your name,
comfort, and dorm, and so forth.
Else, I say you are
registered, well not really.
>> And I say not really
because there's no database.
I'm not doing anything with the data.
I'm just throwing it away
for demonstration purposes.
Now I kind of skimped over line 22.
There's more syntax
there, but dollar sign
underscore post is kind of interesting.
And this is what's nice about PHP.
In PHP, you have what are called
a few super global variables.
They are sort of even more
important than global variables.
And these, all capitalized
as such, come with PHP.
So if you have a server that has a
web server installed, like Apache,
and you install the language
support for PHP, all of a sudden you
can start using these super
global variables in your code.
>> And what's nice about
PHP is that if you just
write a file that ends in dot
PHP, put it on a web server,
and then you submit a form to it
via that action tag and a form tag,
that action attribute in the
form tag, PHP and the web
completely figures out how to grab
all of those key value pairs out
of the URL like question
mark q equals cats,
it will figure out how to q and cats.
If you submit a photo, or a username,
or a password to like Facebook,
PHP will figure out for you
where all of that data is.
And it will just hand
you an associative array
called dollar sign underscore post,
or dollar sign underscore get,
depending on whether you're
using get or post submissions.
And it will just hand you
a super global variable,
so that if you want to get at the name
that the user submitted via that web
form, you literally just say the name
of the super global variable, quote,
unquote, name.
And quote, unquote comfort,
and quote, unquote dorm.
And we're going to be able to do
this and so much more with PHP.
And even though this was
a whirlwind glance at it,
we'll dive in much more next week.
We'll introduce a database
so that you're actually
going to start implementing
your own e-trade based--
like website in just a week's time.
So we'll see you next time, and
hope you got the text messages.
Bye.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> [DOOR OPENING]
>> SPEAKER 2: Hey.
SPEAKER 3: What's up?
SPEAKER 2: What are you doing?
SPEAKER 3: Working on a problem set.
SPEAKER 2: Nice.
High five.
>> [HIGH FIVE]
>> What are-- uh, what are you doing here?
SPEAKER 3: Just hanging out.
Just got back from the gym.
I couldn't help but
notice when we high-fived,
that you have pretty rough hands.
Do you go to the gym?
>> SPEAKER 2: No.
No.
>> SPEAKER 3: Dude, you look pretty big.
Which is bad, because everyone knows
8-ball is the big man on campus.
High-five.
>> SPEAKER 2: Uh, no.
No, I think I'm good.
I think I'm good.