>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID MALAN: This is CS50, and
this is the start of week eight.
And we're so excited to welcome
back, big surprise, CS50's own Ramon
Galvan, a rising senior who has been
spending the past several months
since July in LA, in Hollywood,
literally working on a brand new TV
show called Colony, the creator of which
is actually a Harvard alum himself.
And so we're very excited to see this
debut on the USA network this January.
So stay tuned for that, and for
more Ramon for the weeks to come.
>> Know now that the end is near.
And what this means is that there's not
all that much left of CS50, sad to say.
We have just three problem
sets left-- there's
problem set six-- which is in
your hands now or soon will be,
due later this week-- is meant to bridge
our worlds of the command line, where
we've spent most of our time using
C, and the world of web programming.
Well, you'll see a lot of ideas
borrowed from the command line work,
but also a lot of new
and interesting ideas
that are also going to be germane for
mobile applications and for technology,
more generally, with which you
guys are all familiar nowadays
on laptops and phones and the like.
>> So you'll implement not
a web page, or a website
per se, but an actual web server.
You will write the rest of a web server
written in C, whose purpose in life
is to receive HTTP requests, those
virtual envelopes we keep talking
about, and actually respond either with
some static content-- like a dot HTML
file, or a dot JPEG or
any other number of files,
or even a PHP file whereby your web
server is going to interpret that PHP
code and spit out the results.
Now, we've provided you with
quite a bit of framework
for it-- indeed the
distribution code for problem
set six is over 1,000 lines long, a
lot of which is comments, to be fair--
but this is really meant
to be an opportunity
to get your hands dirty diving
into a fairly large project
that we've very specifically
carved out pieces of for you,
so that really when you exit CS50 and
enter the real world of programming
and want to dabble in
any number of projects,
you'll have much greater
comfort downloading some source
code, some open source
project on the web,
and diving in and making
changes that you see fit.
Problem set seven is going to be about
making your own web-based application
that takes dynamic input and
produces dynamic output in the form
of a etrade.com-like website.
And problem set eight will focus on yet
another language known as JavaScript.
>> Meanwhile, the final
project is on the horizon.
The so-called pre-proposal
is due a week from today.
Pre-proposal-- per the specification,
which is on CS50's website--
is a pretty casual opportunity for
you to send a pretty succinct email
to your teaching fellow
just to apprise him
or her of what you're thinking, to
use him or her as a sounding board.
And have a sanity check--
whether you're thinking
about biting off too
much or maybe too little,
or maybe you have no idea whatsoever
and want to engage in a conversation.
>> Thereafter is a proposal
and status report,
the so-called CS50 hackathon here in
Cambridge for Harvard and Yale students
alike.
The final project's
implementation is then due.
And then a CS50 fair here, in Cambridge,
as well as another in New Haven.
So the proposal, take a look at
the website for those particulars.
>> But more excitingly, too, is an
opportunity to get your hands dirty,
and your minds open to a whole
bunch of topics and tools
and techniques that are ancillary
to the course's core syllabus,
but nonetheless related.
And also wonderful stepping stones to
doing really cool final projects that
go well beyond material we've covered
formally in problem sets or in lecture.
So go to CS50's website for
the whole roster of seminars.
If you don't register yet, that's fine.
Go ahead and sign up still and we will
follow up with a live streaming link,
the day and time is on the website.
And everything will be
recorded and put online
if you can't make the
particular days and times.
>> As to what lies ahead thereafter-- well,
of course, there's the CS50 hackathon.
This photo, recall, from week zero taken
around 4 AM one evening in years past.
The CS50 fair, which again
will take place in both cities.
And then, just to plant the
seed, even though we still
have a month plus left of semester, if
you'd like to join CS50's own teaching
staff, and you want to start
thinking about becoming a CA,
or teaching fellow, know that
we'll start talking more about that
later this semester.
But pictured here is
most of this year's team.
>> And so, PHP-- and I was so sad
last week that [? Allyse ?] kindly
went to the effort of getting
us these wonderful props
that I didn't end up using, so it
really just looked kind of stupid
that we had a shovel sitting here all
day last Wednesday, and a little spoon.
But this was my metaphoric
way of trying to paint
the picture of why we're transitioning
from C to a language like PHP.
And the same could be said of any
number of languages-- Java, Python, Ruby
or bunches of others-- but whereas in
C, for instance, writing a program in C
might typically be like
taking a spoon like this
and digging a hole in the
ground, in the sand or the dirt.
PHP allows you to take much
bigger bites out of the problem,
writing far less code
using a far smaller tool,
because there's so much more
functionality pieced in.
>> Now, if we were really dramatic,
we'd have something to shovel
here, but so be it.
Meanwhile, the other
metaphor we came up with
is, of course, you could
use something like a wrench
to hammer in something like a nail.
But of course, the right
tool to use is going
to be not so much the
language called C--
and now I just annoyed
[? Sanders, ?] probably,
we'll fix that later-- so
the right tool to use often
is not going to be
this lowest level tool.
And indeed, C is not a language that
most of you are ever going to use,
or should necessarily use again.
>> And in fact, a little
secret-- the only time
I use C myself is pretty much between
September and December of every fall
semester.
And that's because we
use it as an opportunity
to teach the fundamentals
of programming,
and with it computer
science fundamentals, data
structures, algorithms and the
like-- but very quickly will you
see now that the syntax
and the ideas underlying C
are so wonderfully
transferable to more modern
higher level languages, like
PHP and Python and Perl and Java
and Objective-C-- actually, not so much
Objective-C-- but Swift, these newer
languages that many of you will
then dabble with you final project.
>> So without further ado, let's actually
use PHP to solve some problems.
Recall that early on, last
week, we just used CS50 IDE,
we wrote a dinky little program
that just said, "Hello world."
And then I saved it in
a file called hello.php.
And then I ran this command.
>> And why?
In English, what's going on here?
What was I doing when
I ran this command?
>> Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: There's some function PHP
that reads what's in-- understands that.
DAVID MALAN: Good, there's some function
PHP-- and let me be more specific,
there's a program called PHP, a.k.a.
An interpreter, that understands
the contents of hello.php,
and interprets it top to
bottom, left to right,
and does what those commands say.
The commands in hello.php, of course,
is just source code-- functions
and variables and loops and
the like, that we ourselves
have started writing in PHP.
>> But unlike C, which is
a compiled language,
PHP you just write it, and run it.
You skip that middleman step of
converting it to zeros and ones,
and then running it.
And so what is an upside of this?
Why are we skipping the step?
Why do more modern languages
tend to skip this step?
What was the benefit?
>> Or just intuitively?
Even if we've not
written much PHP before,
what's beneficial about not
compiling your code do you think?
No?
Not committing?
Scratching your head?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: More dynamic.
>> DAVID MALAN: More dynamic?
What you mean?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, good, so
depending on the input,
you don't have to compile it each time.
And it really is as
simple as that-- what
is the point of continuing
to compile your code?
This is just a step that's
making-- this is requiring,
for the past several
weeks, twice as many steps
as just running your program.
It's been useful in seeing that you
see some error messages and so forth,
but it's still just an annoying step.
>> And so programmers realized
over time, why don't we
start writing languages that don't
need that fairly mechanical step,
so that can just write
your code and run it.
But what was the price
that we saw we paid
last week, with one particular example?
Yes?
>> Speed.
So [? what's ?] interpreters
a little slower,
in that zeros and ones are
nice and fast for a computer
to understand, because the
Intel CPU, or whatever it is,
just understands what's going
on with those patterns of bits.
Whereas an interpreter
is a program that really
has to read the Ascii source
code that you have written,
and convert it, so to speak, or
figure out how it converts ultimately
to zeros and ones.
So it just takes a little
bit of a performance hit.
So it's a bit of a trade-off.
Now if we do this over here, let me
go ahead and do an example as follows.
If I go in here, new file, I'm going
to save this again is hello.php.
And now I'm going to go ahead
and say, "print hello world"--
and recall that I can use print, I don't
have to use print-F. And now down here,
if I do PHP of hello.php, huh-- I
don't seem to have interpreted it.
What did I do wrong?
>> AUDIENCE: The angled bracelets.
>> DAVID MALAN: Yeah, you need
that angle bracket up top.
So it's kind of annoying, but
you get used to it quickly.
If I have to write PHP code, I
generally need to tell the program,
or tell the interpreter, hey
PHP, here comes some PHP code.
And then for good measure, I would
close this not with this, but rather
with just question mark angle
bracket, so that now down here,
if I run this again, now
I get the desired result.
>> Now let's do a slight optimisation,
just so that you've seen it before.
This is kind of annoying that I
have to run PHP space hello.php,
because in the past I
could just write dot slash
program name, which is kind of nice.
It's kind of a better user experience.
>> So it turns out you can do this
in PHP with the following-- I
can use this fairly cryptic
incantation at the top here,
which is generally called a shebang,
whereby this is a sharp symbol,
so to speak, this is a bang
or an exclamation point.
And this now is the path to a program
on a typical Linux system that
is called environment, or env.
And this line-- long story
short-- line one just
says, hey computer, find the PHP
interpreter for me in the environment,
find it in your memory, so to speak.
>> And what's nice now, is
that if I go down here,
I can do dot slash
hello dot php, or-- hmm.
Permission denied.
Well, you'll see even more of this
with problem set seven, if you
haven't already, with permissions.
It turns out that I need
to execute this command
called [? chamod ?] for change
mode-- a plus x hello.php.
I need [INAUDIBLE] this one additional
step which is telling my computer,
make hello.php executable.
And now watch what happens-- dot
slash hello.php, it just runs.
I don't need to specify
the interpreter anymore.
And I can make it even prettier,
still, if I rename this thing.
If I move hello.php to just
Hello-- so notice in the top left,
the program's name is
indeed now just Hello.
Now I can make it look like a C program,
even though it's written in PHP--
or frankly any number
of other languages.
>> So marginal enhancement,
no functional difference.
But it's just a little curiosity
now, so that you can write programs
in any language, and the user doesn't
have to know or care what those are.
Well, let's look at a more
compelling example now
that I whipped up in advance.
And this is called quote.php.
And it's available online.
And notice that it's pretty short--
but it's a command line program that's
going to look up stock prices
for me, which is actually going
to be germane to problem set seven.
>> So let's see what I'm doing.
At the very top I've got the
open bracket question mark PHP.
Then I've got this line, whereby I am
requiring a file called functions.php--
we're going to see
more on this in a bit,
but this is like C's
version of sharp include,
where you want to go
include another file.
PHP calls it require, though it
also has an include function.
And it turns out that function.php is
just something I wrote before class.
I put it in the same directory, because
I wanted to factor out some code
that we might want to use elsewhere.
>> Meanwhile, you can probably
infer what's going on here.
This is a little different from C-- but
what do I mean by ensure proper usage?
Translate this more technically.
Under what circumstances am I
quitting the program, or exiting?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: When you don't have
two command line arguments.
>> DAVID MALAN: When I don't have
to command line arguments.
And remember that one of those
arguments is the program's name itself.
And the second is going to be
another word I type after the prompt.
So just like C, this
is my way of checking,
did the user cooperate and
run the program as I intended?
Now, there's something
a little different
with C-- first of all we
have this dollar sign,
and what does a dollar
sign denote in PHP?
Just a variable.
That's all-- just a variable followed by
whatever you want to actually call it.
Notice there is something
missing from my PHP program,
just like it was missing last
week, versus C, which is what?
>> A types, but also something else.
There is no something
function-- main function.
There's no main function.
You just start writing
your code without having
to worry about a fairly arbitrary
convention of naming some default
function main.
So arg C is just really
a global variable
that the interpreter
makes available to me.
Now, this is interesting.
So look up stuff.
Dollar sign stock is on the
left, that's my variable.
On the right hand side,
there's apparently
a function in PHP called lookup that
I'm passing my last command line
argument to-- whatever the word is.
And we'll see how this
works in a moment.
>> And then lastly I'm reporting the price.
I'm printing out one
share of such and such.
And remember, this is the
way in PHP-- a way in PHP--
where you don't have to do
the dollar sign S anymore.
You can just use curly braces
and plug in some variable.
You don't have to worry about
using printf in the same way.
>> And as an aside, when you put a variable
inside of double quotes like this,
you are using a fancy technique
called variable interpolation.
It just means plug the variable in here.
And as an aside, some of you who come
from other programming backgrounds,
you may not use single quotes
around strings to do this.
You must use double quotes for
variable interpolation to work.
Otherwise you'll literally
see those curly braces.
>> So lastly, let's go ahead and run this.
Let me make my terminal a little bigger.
Let me go ahead and run
inside of my quote directory.
[? CDsource ?] [? AM ?]
[? quote ?] PHP quote dot PHP,
and I'm going to search for something
like GOOG, which is its ticker symbol,
and one share of its new name,
Alphabet Inc, cost $717, as of today.
All right, if we want to
run this again, anyone
have another stock ticker
they want to look up?
>> Microsoft I think is
this one, MSFT-- $53.
I think Yahoo is maybe that.
And Facebook is that.
>> So what is this program doing?
The magic seems to be embedded
in that lookup function.
So let's take a quick look.
>> It turns out that doesn't come
with PHP, it's in functions.php.
And we won't go through
this in great detail,
but notice the operative word here is
that on line six of functions.php--
I literally say function.
I specify the name of my function.
I then specify any
arguments, or parameters,
I want that function to take-- no types.
And then I implement it.
>> And I'll wave my hand
at the implementation,
since it's fairly advanced right
now, but we'll see it again actually
in a week in problem set seven.
But I can clean this up, too.
I also included in
today's code a version
of quote, which has no dot PHP file.
Because what is presumably at the
top of the program called just quote?
That so-called shebang-- the
fairly cryptic incantation
that says find PHP and then
run it on my code here.
>> All right, so that brings
us to where we left off
last time-- albeit with
some more advanced examples.
Any questions thus far about
PHP or what we're doing?
No-- all right.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Inside the
HTML files, do you--
[? do you ?] [? just call it ?]
a [INAUDIBLE] PHP file?
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
In a web context, which we're
literally about to transition to,
you don't use the so-called
shebang at the top,
because the web server-- often a
program called Apache or Microsoft
IIS, Internet Information Server, or
any number of other web server software,
knows that when it sees
a dot PHP file, that it
should run the interpreter on it.
It doesn't look at that first line.
So this first line trick
is just when you're
writing command line programs--
which we won't do super often,
but it's our way of bridging
our C examples to now our PHP.
>> So let's indeed bridge this world
from the command line world to the web
by doing the following.
Let me go ahead and draw
over here for just a moment.
So if we have a web server, or rather
if we have my laptop over here,
which I'll draw like this.
And here we have the
internet in some form.
And then over here, we have
a server in a building--
this is how the internet
works-- and in here
is a server with some lights maybe.
What's actually going on
between these two connections?
>> So in this building is a web server.
That's just a computer
that's running some operating
system-- maybe the free software called
Apache, which CS50 IDE is running.
So you can actually
think of this building
as being the building in
which CSt0 IDE is stored.
That's where all of you have
accounts, where all of you
have your own web server
running, all of you
have your own unique URLs,
as we started to discuss,
and you'll see more in P. set six.
>> Here's my laptop somewhere
else on the internet.
And so when I visit a URL that belongs
to me, that internet traffic is going
over to the server, the server's
receiving an HTTP request--
like a get index.html and it's
replying to that web page.
So that's the general paradigm.
Whereas everything up
until now today, everything
was happening only in the
confines of this building.
I was using my laptop, but
I was connected to CS50 IDE,
so all of those programs I was running
was inside of that server, itself.
>> But now, let's start reusing PHP
to write some actual programs that
are served up by a web server.
And to do this, I'm going to go
into a whole bunch of examples
that introduce this idea here.
So this is kind of a fancy way of
describing a programming paradigm.
>> And in fact, as you exit CS50
or work on final projects,
or take some follow
on class, you'll start
to see that the world--
especially having grown up
with languages like C
that are super low level--
realize that there's better
ways of writing software.
There are certain
patterns you can follow,
certain ways of organizing your files
and ways of naming your functions,
so that long story short,
the world has come up
with a whole bunch of acronyms
and names for ways of programming.
These are just techniques you might use.
>> And one of them is called MVC,
for Model View Controller.
And this is just, for
now, an overly complicated
way of saying how you should lay out
a PHP-based website, in our case.
How do you organize your files,
how do you organize your logic,
in a way that makes it easier to
write more complicated websites?
And indeed, we'll quickly
get there with p-set seven.
>> So in the world of MVC, you're going
to see that our code can generally
be characterized as either model code,
or controller code, or view code.
And I'm going to
oversimplify it as follows--
the controller is the
brains of your program,
it's where all of the
interesting logic happens.
So everything we've been
writing thus far in class,
is kind of like controller
code-- it's controlling
your program, your loops, your
conditions, your functions
and variables and all that.
>> Views, now, are going to be a little
more obvious in the world of the web.
A view is the aesthetics
of your website.
It's what the user sees-- the images,
the HTML tables, the HTML tags, and all
of that, all of the fluffy aesthetic
stuff that isn't that hard to write,
but is just what you're generating,
is the so-called view, the aesthetics.
And model, ultimately, is going
to be database stuff-- which
we'll start diving into all
the more this Wednesday.
So controller is the logic,
view is the aesthetic stuff,
and model is going to be where
we store our actual data.
>> So let's look at this more concretely
with the following example.
I'm going to go into my directory here
of today's source code-- all of which
is available online.
And I'm going to go into version zero.
And here is-- let's call it the
version zero of CS50's website.
There's not much here at all.
It's a very simple web page that's
probably using what HTML tags-- just
guess from past examples?
>> What's that?
H1-- probably for that big bold
title, that logo up top, CS50.
And what else is at play?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Unordered list.
DAVID MALAN: Unordered list-- so the
UL tag and maybe a couple of LI tags.
And if you don't remember these,
it honestly doesn't matter.
These are fluffy sort of
implementation details of HTML
that you quickly look up
and you're back on your way.
We'll focus more on the programming
ideas that are the juicier pieces.
>> So let's just take a quick
look at the HTML-- and indeed
if I open up the view source here, yup,
that's exactly what's going on here.
There's an UL tag.
Nested inside of that is to LI tags.
And then I borrowed the URL
of the actual syllabus here.
>> And then in the
lectures.php is apparently
another dynamically generated page
that's going to have, let's see-- ah,
the first two weeks of lecture.
So week zero and week one, let's
look at this-- if I view page source,
also super simple.
These are leading to two pages
called week0.php, and week1.php.
So consider now what's happening.
>> When I click on week0.php, my laptop
is making a request for week0.php.
The web server, a.k.a., CS50 IDE,
is receiving that virtual envelope.
It's seeing a message
like, get week0.php.
It is then interpreting the file, top
to bottom, left to right-- the file
called week0.php-- and
spitting out the results.
So inside of this file,
week0.php, must be
the controller logic that is generating
this HTML, and we'll soon see that.
>> But for now, let me click on week zero,
and now we have Wednesday and Friday,
and now we have the slides
slowly from week zero.
And you might recall
this from way back when.
So that's all this website is doing.
>> So let's consider how it's doing this.
I'm going to go back into the
source code here, in CS50 IDE,
and I'm going to open up index.php.
At the top of this file
is a bunch of comments.
And then in the middle of this file, it
turns out, is no PHP code whatsoever.
Because if you don't have any of the
open bracket question mark PHP tags,
you're free to just put HTML.
>> Because what the PHP
interpreter is supposed to do,
is when it reads this file--
top to bottom, left to right--
it only interprets code it sees between
those angle brackets question mark.
And anything else that it doesn't
recognize as PHP, it just spits out.
And HTML Is among the stuff
it will just spit out.
>> So this file could have
been called index.html,
but I'm naming everything
dot PHP as a stepping stone.
Lectures.php-- similarly
underwhelming, it's just some HTML.
Week0.php, similarly just some HTML.
>> But now let's put on the
proverbial engineering hat,
and consider how we can improve this.
It's not hard to do this, but I kind
of devolved into copy and paste.
And in fact, if I make week two, you
know what I'm probably going to do?
I'm going to go to week1.php, I'm
going to highlight everything.
I'm going to copy it, paste it
into a new file called week2.php,
tweak some URLs, and be on my way.
>> So based on what we've
seen in C already,
this doesn't feel right, hopefully.
Copy, paste rarely the right solution.
So what can we start
to do to improve this?
Where are the opportunities
for better design?
>> By the time I get to
week eight, it's going
to be really annoying
if I want to change
the font of every one of
my pages, or if I want
to change the structure of the layout.
So where's the opportunity
for better design?
Well, let's consider what's
shared across all of these files.
>> Here's week one, here's week
zero, here's lectures.php,
here's index.php-- what is the same and
what is different, roughly speaking,
in each of these files?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, good.
So there's a pattern, surely, whereby
every time I choose lecture I,
I should be generating a
very similar looking page.
And so perhaps I can leverage
the fact that really,
we deliberately numerically
indexed our lectures--
if I can put even more
words in your answer.
And what is the only thing, really,
that's changing between week one--
and let me scroll down so it's
roughly in the same place--
so here is week zero,
roughly at the top.
Here is week one, week
zero, week one, week zero.
OK, literally if you know
no program whatsoever,
this is now just like a
pattern matching game.
So what's different?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Good, so the title
is changing, ever so slightly.
Zero is going, of course, to one.
Same thing's happening in the H1 tag.
And we don't quite see it as easily,
because the URLs are a little long.
But those URLs are changing slightly.
>> But what's not changing is, dare I
say, most of the contents of the page--
the HTML tag's the same, the head is
the same, the title is almost the same,
the body is the same, and
almost everything else
is the same except for
those little tweaks.
So how can we go about
factoring some of this out?
>> Well let me propose exactly
that in the next version.
So here in version one, I have the exact
same files, plus a couple of others.
Here's index.php-- and even if
you've never seen PHP before,
what am I probably doing to solve this
problem-- based on what you see here?
Yeah, is that a slight commitment?
No?
Yes, go on.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: Yep.
>> DAVID MALAN: I need you to
speak just a little louder.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, good.
And I think-- it was
hard to hear you-- but I
think what you're getting at is that
the tags that were common up top,
and the tags that were common on the
bottom, have now been factored out,
or relegated to what files?
Header.php and footer.php--
and we're going
to make some tweaks to
address the concern you just
raised about the numbers changing, for
instance, if I heard you correctly.
>> But that seems to be the gist of it.
If there was a huge amount of
redundancy at the top of the page,
and a huge amount of
redundancy at the bottom,
let's literally just highlight
and cut that content out,
put it in a separate file-- just like
the idea of CSS, where we factored out
very similar aesthetics, put
it in a separate dot PHP file,
use the require mechanism-- which
is like C sharp include-- which
is essentially like saying go
grab the contents of header.php,
and copy and paste them here.
>> But what this means is that now in
index.php, I have those two lines.
In lectures.php, I also
have those two lines.
In week0.php, I also
>> So now, if I want to change
the title of all of my pages,
or I want to change the
fundamental structure,
I can change it now in just one place,
or two places-- header and footer,
respectively.
Now the code's starting to look
a little more cryptic, right?
But if you think about what the page
is doing-- if I'm requesting week0.php,
just like on the drawing over
here-- when week0.php is requested,
what does that mean?
>> Literally, this file is
requested by the browser.
The web server-- a.k.a.
CS50 ID-- grabs this
file, week0.php, and reads
it top to bottom, left to right.
On line one, it immediately encounters
open bracket question mark PHP, require
header dot PHP, and so
what the PHP interpreter
does-- that's built into the web
server, because we preconfigured
it for you-- it automatically goes
into header.php, copies the contents,
pastes them here.
>> But then the interpreter encounters
question mark close bracket,
so it's all done thinking.
Now it just blindly spits
out lines two through seven,
because it's just raw HTML.
Gets to line eight, and does that
same magic again-- opening the file,
grabbing the contents, and
requiring them or pasting them
right then or there.
>> But I just alluded to a bug.
This is a partial step backward,
because if we look in header.php,
I've kind of cut a corner.
What feature did I give up in order
to gain this arguable better design?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I kind
of cut a nontrivial corner.
You pointed out that what was changing
was the title, the number in the title,
and the number in the H1.
So my solution was, OK,
let's just rename the page,
and not deal with that
problem whatsoever.
So that's a partial
step backwards for sure.
>> But what is noteworthy here
is that what I have done
is otherwise factored
out all the common stuff.
And in footer.php, notice I factored
out all of that, albeit lesser,
common stuff.
So I need to somehow now be able to
take another step forward, and fix
that title issues.
So let's do that.
>> Let me go into my second version
here, which, again, has the same files
except for one new addition.
And it's a little more
verbose, but let's see if we
can tease apart what's going on here.
So instead of requiring
header.php, and footer.php,
I seem to be only requiring one
file-- called, of course, helpers.php.
And let me stipulate now,
what's inside of helpers.php
is just a bunch of functions
that I wrote, just like before.
But I called it helpers.php.
>> Now apparently, in
line three and 10, I'm
calling two functions--
render header, render footer.
Those don't come with
PHP, I wrote those myself.
And I put them in helpers.php.
>> Now, we've only seen this syntax
once, and it was super brief.
But this is apparently an argument
to render header, the function.
Why do I know that?
Well here's a close paren,
here's an open paren.
And of course, just like in C,
anything between those parentheses
is an input-- or an
argument to the function.
>> What is the data type of this argument,
based on what I've highlighted?
What do those square brackets
indicate, based on last week?
Yeah, it's an array--
specifically an associative array.
And this syntax admittedly
is a little funky,
but this is just passing
in one key value pair.
The key is, quote unquote
title, and the value is CS50.
>> If we had done this
in C, it might instead
look more like this,
just quote unquote CS50--
or actually it would be curly
braces, or something like that in C,
where the key is zero,
and the value is CS50.
But again, in PHP, even though the
syntax is, again, a little weird,
it allows you to pass in
words instead of numbers
to associate keys with values.
>> So what does this all mean?
If I go into helpers.php,
let's look at this function.
renderHeader.php, rather
renderHeader is my function,
and I know that because I see
the function keyword here.
This is new from C-- it apparently
takes an argument called data--
but I could have called this
anything, but I called it data,
just to be a little clean-- and
just take a guess, especially
if you've programmed in some other
higher level language before, something
above C, conceptually.
>> What does equal open bracket
square bracket probably mean?
Or what might it mean?
We've not seen this in C. Yeah?
>> An empty array.
Specifically, this means that if
the user does not call renderHeader
with an argument, I'm still going
to have an argument called data,
but its default value is
going to be an empty array.
So it's just a nice convenience.
I don't have to yell at the user,
or say you used my function wrong.
I can just give the user a default
value, if I don't particularly care.
Now this function, I'm
going to wave my hands at.
But this extract function allows
us to pass these variables in data
into header.php in the following way.
And this is the last piece,
I think, of funky syntax.
Here is my new version
of header.php-- it
used to say, literally, open
bracket title CS50, and that was it.
And same thing for the H1.
>> Now it apparently says
something pretty funky.
And let me simplify this
for a moment as follows.
This is what I've
changed my title to be.
However, it's getting a little ugly
to constantly open brackets with PHP,
and then use the print function.
It turns out that PHP has a shorthand
notation for this, which is just
an equal sign, which is technically a
function called echo instead of print,
but it's the same thing, effectively.
>> That just looks better.
It's just a syntactic
sugar, if you will,
that makes my code look a little better.
But it turns out, and
we'll see this again
before long, we have to call this
annoyingly long function called
HTML special chars in
PHP, because it turns out
there are certain inputs
that the user might give us,
or that users might give us,
that are going to break our site.
But we'll see that next
week with JavaScript.
But for now, just know that
this file, headers.php, simply
takes the title that
I passed in, it make
sure it's safe to be injected into a web
page, and it spits it out as my title
and as my H1.
So if I go into this version now,
notice that lectures has its title back,
week zero has its title back, and
indeed, the HTML I'm generating
is identical to what my first version
was-- except for my whitespace,
because I've started formatting
my code a little differently.
But I've generated all
the code I care about.
So let me pause for
just a moment and see
if there's any questions
or confusion I've created.
All right, so let's twist
a little harder here
to see if there's an
opportunity for improvement.
Helpers.php also had this
function, called renderFooter.
And what's noteworthy about
renderHeader, and renderFooter?
And again, for today's purposes, know
that the extract function is just
my way of passing arguments
into header.php and footer.php.
>> Sorry?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I only
changed the require line.
So literally, I've committed the sin
of copying and pasting, yet again.
It's not a huge number
of lines, but come on--
if I'm copying and pasting everything
just to change one little word,
and the one little word that Alan points
out is footer here, versus header here.
Otherwise, everything is
identical, except for,
of course, the function's names.
So what could we do better?
>> Well let me open up this version
here, whereby in helpers.php,
why don't I just get a
little smarter about this?
Write slightly more complicated
code, but call it render?
So what have I fundamentally changed?
>> It takes an argument now--
two arguments, data still.
And then what's the first
name probably being used for,
based on what you're reading here?
Even if some of the syntax is still new.
What is dollar sign template?
>> Sorry?
>> AUDIENCE: Header or footer.
>> DAVID MALAN: Header or footer.
So apparently, I decided that if
the only thing that's changing
is what template I want
to print-- and by template
I mean this is blueprint for
code that I want to output,
but I want to plug in some
values-- so if it's only header
or footer, why don't I parameterize
that and call the argument dollar sign
template?
And then this funky syntax allows me
to create a path in a variable here.
>> So dollar sign path is a variable.
What does this syntax
do, if you're familiar?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
If template is, quote unquote,
header, or if template is,
quote unquote, footer, that line there
that I've highlighted, line eight,
is simply taking that name, like header,
and concatenating it with dot PHP.
So we didn't have this operator
in C. This dot operator is
an amazing thing in PHP-- if you're
familiar with JavaScript or Java,
you can use the plus
sign to do concatenation.
>> In C, it is a pain in the neck--
and I'm so sorry, in p-set six,
you're going to have to do
this-- it is a pain in the neck
to concatenate strings.
Why?
Well, because if you've got
a string that's this long,
and another string that's this long,
you can't just plug them together.
What do you instead have to do in C?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: You have to malloc
memory, or use an array on the stack.
And you actually have to
make that array big enough
to fit this plus this,
plus the backslash zero.
Then concatenate them together using
stir cat or manually with a for loop,
or any number of techniques.
And we show you a couple in p-set six.
>> It's a pain in the neck.
And this is truly what I mean about
this versus this-- like C versus PHP.
You just get so much more
functionality for free,
so that you can focus,
ideally, on the fun
part of coding, the
project you want to solve,
rather than the low level minutiae.
>> So this just generates header.php or
footer.php based on which one I call.
And indeed if I go
into index.php, notice
all that's changed-- Instead of
calling render header or render footer,
I'm calling render, followed by the
name of the template that I want to do.
And you'll see this, too,
in problem set seven,
whereby we allow you to use the
same function to make bunches
and bunches of different web pages.
>> So rather than dwell too
much more on those details--
which you'll see again in
problem set seven-- let's look
at now the beginning of a solution
to a more interesting problem.
Thus far, nothing we've
done has saved data.
In fact, the only time we've ever saved
something we've done in this class
is when we had a very simple demo awhile
back, whereby we used file IO in C,
and I think I typed in my name, and
Hannah's name, and Maria's name,
or maybe Andy's name, and
then we saved a CSV file--
comma separated values file.
>> And we used fopen-- I think
we used fprintf as I recall,
and we saved a file.
Now, that is the simplest
form of a database.
If you want to make a website for the
Frosh IMs program, whereby freshmen
can register for a sport, you ideally
want to do something with that data.
Last week, we did nothing
with the data-- we just said,
you are registered, not really.
Or maybe I emailed the
proctor, and that was it.
>> But it would be nice if I could
give that proctor a CSV file,
like an Excel file.
Or better yet, it would
be nice if I could
put those users' names and
dorm names and all of that
into a database that
just lives on forever,
until I choose to delete the data.
A database that allows
me to query information.
And indeed, that's what a database is.
>> We introduce today, and
next week, too, a technology
called SQL-- a Structured Query
Language, which is another language.
It's essentially a programming
language, but for databases.
And a database for now, just
think of as a super fancy version
of Microsoft Excel, or Google
Spreadsheets, or Apple Numbers.
It's generally a program that allows
you to store a whole bunch of data
in rows and columns, quite
like you might in Excel.
>> But what's nice, especially if
we're not super familiar with Excel,
what SQL allows you to do is query this
information by writing lines of code
where you can, even if your
database has a million rows in it,
you can find things super fast.
In fact, Excel is particularly
bad at large data sets.
And in fact, up to a few
years ago, turned out
Excel would only allow you to store
up to 65,535 rows of data-- which
sounds like a lot, but at the
time I was a grad student,
and I remember tripping over
this because I was generating
CSV files for my research and I
wanted to analyze them quickly
by just opening up in Excel.
Of course, my computer just crashed,
because I had more than 65,000 rows.
>> But where did the 65,535 come from?
What was Microsoft doing, presumably?
If you're good with your powers of two?
Yeah, they were using a 16-bit
value to represent the row number.
And two to 16 is 65,536--
minus one, because if you
zero index means that was the
most number of rows I could have.
And it was just a design decision.
By saving 16 bits, they limited me
to 16,000 rows, instead of 4 billion,
which I could have had ideally.
But for now, we're going to
introduce this more in a web context.
And what's nice about SQL is that even
though it's pretty powerful and pretty
sophisticated, it really boils
down to four key operations, four
key functions, if you will-- select,
for retrieving data, searching
for data; delete or deleting data;
insert for adding rows to the database;
and updating.
So if you have ever used Google
Spreadsheets, Apple Numbers, Microsoft
Excel, you have executed,
most likely, all
of these operations as a human by
just using your keyboard and mouse--
inserting data, using your eyes
to select or search for data,
or update data, or delete data.
>> So what does this mean?
Well, pre-installed in CS50
IDE is a program called MySQL.
It's a free, open-source
database that's super popular.
Facebook, for instance, uses it to this
day, among other tools that they use.
And a lot of very popular websites use
it in large part because it's fast,
and because it's free.
Though certainly alternatives exist.
And some of you might dabble with
alternatives for final projects.
>> This is a screenshot, meanwhile, of
a web-based tool called phpMyAdmin.
It is a coincidence that
this web-based tool is also
written in a language, PHP,
but what it's meant to do
is give us a web-based
interface to a database.
Because MySQL typically is
something, historically, you
would interact with only
with a command line.
And it would be super
annoying and arcane to have
to type textual commands to select
data, insert data, and delete data.
So some people on the internet
wrote a web-based program
that just let us manage
the data in our database.
It's like double clicking on Excel, and
running a web-based version thereof.
>> And what you're going to use this for
ultimately next week, not in p-set six,
but is to build something
called CS50 Finance, which
is going to have a database of
users, with user names and passwords,
dollar amounts that they
have in their bank accounts.
It's going to be
something you use to store
the symbols and the quantities
of stocks that users
have bought using virtual
dollars that you'll give to them.
And it's going to allow users
to register for your site,
so that even your friends
can tune in to your website
and actually register,
log in, and play around
and try to find fault in your code,
and try to find bugs in your website.
And they'll simply register by
adding themselves, effectively,
via code you write to your database.
>> For instance, this is a quick screenshot
of what a database might look like.
This was from one of
last year's solutions--
this is like a mini Excel
file, stored in our database,
stored in this software called MySQL.
On the left hand side, I've apparently
given every user a unique number.
In the second column, I've given
everyone a user name-- my own
among them.
And on the right hand side,
I've given them a hash.
>> Now this is actually a password,
but it's not a plain text password.
It's a encrypted password, if
you will, or a hash password.
Which we'll come back to before long.
>> But if you've ever read
an article about how
your password at some bank or some
website might have been compromised,
it can generally mean one of two things.
So this is just an excerpt of six users.
All of you now can figure
out via hacking or cracking
what our six people's passwords are.
But if you've ever gotten
an alert or an apology
from a company or website saying,
sorry, a hacker broke into our database,
you should probably change your
password, what might that mean?
>> Well, one, could mean the
company has been more moronic,
and has been storing your password
in a column like this, unencrypted.
Which means the adversary,
who stole the database,
literally knows your
username and password.
That's the worst possible scenario.
And as you'll see in p-set
seven, so easy to avoid.
There is absolutely no excuse for that
form of stupidity in today's internet.
Two-- and we'll find some articles
to testify the fact that this still
happens, nonetheless--
two, maybe the adversary
stole this version of the database.
Which is still kind of bad, because now
they know that I have six customers,
I know the user names
of those six customers,
and I know the encrypted
versions, or the hashed versions,
of those six customers' passwords.
But any of you who might
have done [? Hacker 2 ?]
where you cracked passwords, or took
a look at that version of the problem
set, why is it still a little worrisome
if the adversary knows your hash
passwords?
>> AUDIENCE: Because they could
enter the whole dictionary
into the hash function.
And if your password is a dictionary
word, [? they can just match-- ?]
>> DAVID MALAN: Exactly, the adversary
can just write code, like some of you
did for [? Hacker ?] 2,
whereby you iterate over
all of the words in the dictionary,
or all possible combinations of A
through Z and one through nine--
which sounds like a lot, and it is.
But for a computer,
it's pretty darn fast.
And in fact, that was the
point of [? Hacker 2, ?] was
to take stuff that
literally looks like this,
and reverse engineer
what it actually was.
>> So we'll look at how we can
store this more efficiently.
Turns out, thankfully in MySQL,
there are going to be data types.
And one of the fun parts about
database design, to be honest,
is actually deciding for yourself
how should you represent the data?
Should you represent a phone number as
an int, like a big number, or a long?
Or do you actually do it
as a sequence of chars?
And there can be very
non-trivial impacts of this.
>> In fact, one of the
earliest, fun germane stories
is when Mark Zuckerberg was building
Facebook, it was originally written in,
and still is largely written in PHP.
And one of the biggest challenges
they faced early on was scaling.
When they kept adding school after
school after school, to my knowledge,
one of the original solutions
was essentially to copy and paste
some of the databases
and some of the code,
so that Harvard was
running on its own server,
and MIT was running on its own server.
And this was why, for some
of you who might recall,
you couldn't have friends
in other networks.
>> You probably don't have friends at
MIT or Harvard 10 or so years ago,
but you couldn't span networks
for partly that reason.
And one of the biggest challenges for
Mark and for companies like Facebook
is actually handling hundreds
and thousands and millions
of requests per second.
So the things we'll start
talking about this week
are really going to be germane to
writing good software, and popularly
successful tools that
can handle lots of users.
>> So we'll talk about things
like indexing and searching,
but that is it for today.
We will see you for more on Wednesday.
>> [MUSIC - "SEINFELD" THEME]
DAVID MALAN: You can to
it, and subtract from it.
And you don't have to stick with
some pre-determined amount of memory.
Well, what's that going to be called?
>> SPEAKER 1: Well, what's going on?
SPEAKER 2: What do you mean?
He's giving a lecture.
DAVID MALAN: And we can use a
function called malloc to memory--
>> SPEAKER 1: Why aren't his arms moving?
>> SPEAKER 2: Well that's--
you know, that's normal.
It's just like he has just
big sausages hanging there.
>> SPEAKER 1: That's normal?
>> SPEAKER 2: Yeah, I think we
just assume he accidentally
replaced his deodorant with superglue.