>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: This is like
a freshman seminar today.
OK.
So very rainy out.
This tends to happen on Wednesdays,
but all the more opportunity
for questions today.
So let's start off actually
with the film in just a moment.
But we'll start grandly as always.
>> This is CS50, and this
is the end of week 4.
So if you've ever watched
TV or a movie wherein
there's some computer experts and
the police, or FBI, or some agency
is trying to catch some
adversary, well, you've
probably heard the expression "enhance,"
whereby that technician somehow
magically zooms in infinitely
far to see the criminals
identity or the license plate number
in even the shimmer of a mirror
or the glint of someone's eye.
So indeed, let's take a look at
a few such scenes from Hollywood.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-OK, now let's get a good look at you.
>> -Hold it.
Run that back.
>> -Wait a minute.
Go right.
>> -There, freeze that.
-Full screen.
-OK, freeze that.
-Tighten up on that, will you?
-Vector in on that
guy by the back wheel.
-Zoom in right here on this spot.
-With the right equipment, the image
could be enlarged and sharpened.
-What's that?
-It's an enhancement program.
-Can you clear that up any?
-I don't know.
Let's enhance it.
>> -Enhance section A6.
>> -I enhanced the detail,
and-- I think there's
enough to enhance,
release it to my screen.
-I enhanced the reflection in her eye.
>> -Let's run this through
video enhancement.
-Edgar, can you enhance this?
>> -Hang on.
>> -I've been working on this reflection.
>> -Someone's reflection.
-Reflection.
-There's a reflection of the man's face.
-The reflection.
-There's a reflection.
-Zoom in on the mirror.
-You can see a reflection.
-Can you enhance the image from here?
-Can you enhance him right here?
-Can you enhance it?
Can you enhance it?
>> -Can we enhance this?
>> -Can you enhance it?
-Hold on a second, I'll enhance.
-Zoom in on the door.
-Times 10.
-Zoom.
-Move in.
-More.
-Wait, stop.
-Stop.
-Pause it.
-Rotate us 75 degrees
around the vertical, please.
-Stop.
Go back to the part
about the door, again.
>> -Got an image enhancer that can bitmap?
>> -Hey, maybe we can use the Pradeep
Sen method to see into the windows.
-This software is state of the art.
>> -The eigenvalue is off.
>> -With the right
combination of algorithm--
>> -He's taken elimination
algorithms to the next level,
and I can use them to
enhance this photograph.
>> -Lock on and enlarge the z-axis.
>> -Enhance.
-Freeze and enhance.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: All right, so
all of those are actually words.
They're just strung together in a
way that's not actually sensible.
And, in fact, CS50 and courses like it
tends to ruin a lot of TV and movies
for you.
Because when those computer experts
are rattling off terms and saying
fancy things like
eigenvectors, and the z-axis,
and any number of other
actually more technical terms,
they're really just stringing
words together all too often.
Is that one of our hopes is that,
as a side effect of taking courses
like this, will more people in the
world actually be able to weigh in
and just ever so slightly influence the
quality and accuracy of those films?
>> In fact, let's take a look at reality.
So here is the staff photo of
Mary, one of our teaching fellows.
And suppose she is
suspected of something.
And yet, there's a glimmer of
some piece of evidence in her eye,
or in the reflection of her eyeglasses.
Well, if we do exactly as the films
propose, wherein we zoom and "enhance",
this is how much information
is in Mary's face
when you capture an image
with that original resolution.
>> And, in fact, you can see these dots.
And these are what are
called pixels, P-I-X-E-L-S,
which is just a square typically
that is a dot that composes an image.
And back in the day, and actually even
today with some of today's LED TVs
or LCD TVs, if you've got
one in your room or at home,
if you go up super close to it, and
especially if it's a somewhat older TV,
you can probably even see these dots
and that's what compose an image.
>> And there is no more
information than this.
We could "enhance", in the sense of
smoothing things over and sort of
inferring kind of, sort of what
color should be next to Mary's eye
so that it's not actually so pixelated.
But if I keep zooming in, there
is the bad guy in her eye.
Like that is all the
information we have.
You cannot create
information out of nothing.
There's only a finite
number of bits there.
>> So in Problem Set 4, where
you have an opportunity
to play with this kind of world.
In Problem Set 4, you'll explore the
world of graphics, and forensics,
and actually write code
that recovers lost images.
You'll write code that
manipulates existing images
and ultimately understand what's
going on underneath the hood.
>> And, it turns out, it's actually
not all that complicated.
For instance, if we wanted to
represent a smiley face where
with these black pixels,
or these black dots,
well, we could simply represent
them as truly a bitmap.
And if you had ever heard that
expression bitmap, perhaps
it now starts to make a
little more sense today.
>> We already know what a bit is.
It's 0 or 1.
And a map is just something
like a piece of paper
that gives you directions and has
maybe a grid of x- and y-coordinates.
So here is a bitmap.
It's a map of bits
whereby a 1 is apparently
going to represent a white pixel, and a
0 is going to represent a black pixel.
But we could certainly flip it around.
It doesn't really matter so
long as we're consistent.
And here is how, in binary-- inside
of a computer's memory, or even inside
of a file on your hard
drive-- could you store
the simplest of smiley face images.
But what are we, of course,
lacking in this image?
Color, right?
It's an obvious next step or
enhancement to improve this with color.
So unfortunately with just a single
bit, 0 or 1, we could represent color.
That could be red, or blue, or
black, or white, or green, or pink,
or any pairs of colors.
But for simplicity's sake, we'll
just assume black and white.
>> So what logically do we need if we
want to implement color in an image?
What do we have to do?
Like if the limiting factor here
is that with one bit you can only
represent two states, 0 or 1, white
or black, what do you want to do?
AUDIENCE: More data.
DAVID J. MALAN: More bits,
yeah more data, more bits.
And, indeed, that's exactly how
color images are represented.
Rather than use a single bit, a
0 or 1 for each pixel, each dot,
you just use multiple.
Maybe use 8, maybe, more commonly
use 24, and indeed, in Problem Set
4, will you play with a file
format that uses 24 bits typically.
>> But most of you are probably
familiar with JPEGs.
If you've ever taken
a photo on your phone,
or uploaded or seen something on
Facebook, or Flickr, any number
of photo-based websites, you've
probably seen a JPEG image before.
And it turns out, this is the file
format we're going to use in PSet 4,
whereby you're going to
have to recover images
that I've accidentally deleted from a
corrupted memory card in the camera,
if you will.
>> And it turns out that even though
JPEG is pretty sophisticated--
it's much more sophisticated
than the black and white dots
we saw a moment ago, because there's
actually fancy algorithms that
are used to compress a JPEG, so
that you can have a really nice,
quality picture but using
relatively few bits.
And we'll come back to
compression before long.
It turns out that the first
three bytes in a JPEG image--
no matter what you've taken a photograph
of-- are the values 255, 216, 255.
>> In other words, if you just
see that pattern of bits,
represented here as three
bytes, or 24 bits total,
with high probability you can infer that
you are looking at it this first three
bytes of a JPEG.
And this is what's known
as the signature of a JPEG.
A lot of file formats
out there tend to start
with certain patterns of 0s and 1s,
so that Windows, and Mac OS, and iOS,
and Android know what kind of file they
are, in addition to the so-called file
extension that a lot of files have.
If you have .jpg, that's
another clue to the computer.
>> So let's now look at this
a little more technically.
We know the decimal
system is 0 through 9.
We know binary is 0 and 1.
And if you think back to PSet
0, we had you wrestle with,
for a little bit, something
called hexadecimal,
where you have 16 digits,
instead of 10 or instead of 2.
And those digits, by convention,
are 0 through 9 and then a
through f, where f represents what
decimal number, just as a quick sanity
check?
So, 15.
And a must represent 10, just by
nature of the ordering that I've given.
It's just an arbitrary convention,
but it's quite standard.
>> So if we look at this pattern
of three bytes-- let's
just start to look at it in
a manner consistent with how
computer scientists generally
look at and think about files.
You can certainly think about
files in 0s, and 1s, and decimal,
but in reality, we tend to use binary
or more typically hexadecimal--
back from PSet 0.
So let me propose that 255, 216, and 255
are just these patterns of 0s and 1s.
And you can check this if you
want to do the math from Week 0.
But, for now, just assume
that this is indeed correct.
I've just rewritten three decimal
numbers as three binary values.
Now what I'm going to do is
just add some white space,
just for readability's sake.
And notice, I'm just going
to move things apart.
So before, after, before, after.
I'm doing nothing interesting other
than just spreading things out so
that notice each set of eight
bits is now two sets of four bits.
This is useful because hexadecimal
is particularly fashionable
because each hexadecimal digit 0 through
f, or more specifically 0 through 15,
can be represented
with exactly four bits.
In other words, in hexadecimal if you
want to represent a 0, it's just 0000,
four zeros.
And if you want to represent 15,
it's 1111, which is four bits.
And if you do the math,
if this is the ones place,
this is the 16s place,
that's going to give you--
rather that's going
to-- sorry, in binary,
that's going to give you 15, ones place,
twos place, fours and eights place.
So let me propose that that
set of four bits on the left
is what we're going to call f.
It's the biggest number you
can represent with four bits.
And we already know from hexadecimal,
f is the biggest digit in hexadecimal.
We've got another f there,
two more over there.
And for now, just take on faith
that I have done the math right
and that the left half
of those bits, 1101,
is the same thing as d in hexadecimal.
And the right hand, 1000, is just 8.
>> And that one's easy to see, right?
The 8 represents-- is right
underneath that eights place.
So we have one in the eights column
and nothing in the fours, twos or ones.
So now more conventionally, humans tend
to write hexadecimal digits like this,
you just squish them together,
and then you prefix them with 0x.
It means nothing other than
a visual clue to a human--
here comes a hexadecimal value-- because
it might not otherwise be obvious.
>> Which is to say, ultimately, that
the pattern of zeros and ones,
or the pattern of hexadecimal
digits equivalently that you're
going to start looking for
in Problem Set 4 is this--
and the Problem Set 4 spec will walk
you through this in more detail--
but realize as sort of arcane as
this might look at first glance,
you're going to start seeing this a lot.
And in fact, even in GDB, the
debugger we introduced on Monday
and Dan introduces in PSet 3, is going
to often show you hexadecimal values
just because they tend to be more
conventional than decimal or binary
in the world of computers.
Now let's put this into context.
Many of you might remember this
picture here, which came from what?
Vista, so even earlier than
that, Windows XP did this debut.
So this is a beautiful landscape.
And in fact, if you poke around online--
I think it's a Wikipedia article,
wherein someone very amazingly went out
found this location in the world set up
his or her camera in
precisely the right place--
and this today looks like-- but
it's exactly the same setting.
This image, though, is in a file
format called bitmap, b-m-p.
And we're going to take a super
quick glance at what that means.
>> But bitmap is just a different way of
representing images still using pixels
in 0s and 1s, ultimately.
But at quick glance, it has
a more interesting signature
at the beginning of the file.
It's not just three
bytes, rather there's
a whole bunch of patterns of bytes
that have predetermined meaning.
For instance, somewhere in the
first few bytes of a bitmap image
is going to be the size of the
image, the width of the image,
the height of the image, so
useful metadata, if you will.
Useful information that Photoshop
or any graphics program you're using
might actually care about.
>> So more on this in
Problem Set 4, but this
is only to say that
at the end of the day
all the file formats you've been using
for years-- Microsoft Word files,
Numbers files, Excel files,
any number of file formats
that might have some
known file extension
are just 0s and 1s underneath the hood.
And humans have decided
what the conventions are,
what patterns of 0s and 1s represent
a Word file versus an Excel file,
versus any number of other file formats.
So in PSet 4, you'll have an
opportunity to play with that.
>> But what does it mean to have a struct.
This is actually a nice segue now
into C, which has only a couple
of additional features that
we haven't looked at yet.
It's a pretty small language and one of
the nice features about C is a struct.
For instance, if you
wanted to represent-- let's
say you wanted to have a variable that
represents a student in some program.
Maybe you were writing a course
registration program, or core shopping
tool, or something like that.
What are pieces of data related
to a student that come to mind?
Like a student is
represented with what values?
Yeah?
You have a name as a student.
What else does a typical student have?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So, sorry.
>> AUDIENCE: Age.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: An age or
birthday equivalently, yep.
What else?
AUDIENCE: ID number?
DAVID J. MALAN: So an ID number, maybe
a phone number, maybe a dorm, or house,
or college, or something like that.
Any number of pieces of data that
you might have in your contacts list
is what might define a student.
So if we wanted to do this, in code,
we might do something simple like this.
We might have a program so that
has let's say, int main(void).
And if I want to represent a
student I might have, for instance,
a string called name for that student,
a string called dorm for that student,
maybe an int called ID for that student.
And because I'm using string, I
need to go back and put up CS50.h.
Maybe I'm going to need stdio.h.
So let me preemptively do those and I'm
going to call this student.c for now
and save this.
>> And now I can do something
with these variables.
And we're just going to write
that as a comment in pseudo code,
because it's not interesting
what we do for now.
OK, so this is a program that
somehow stores a student.
What do I want to do if I
want to store two students?
So my first instinct is going
to be all right, wait a minute,
if I have another student why don't I
just do string name 2 , string dorm 2,
int id2.
And we've done gone
down this road before
and what was our solution to what seems
to be kind of a hackish copy paste
job here?
AUDIENCE: An array.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
we could use an array.
Right this very quickly
becomes unwieldy.
You have to sort of arbitrarily
start naming all of these variables.
And you, the human, have to keep
track that OK name2 corresponds
with dorm2 corresponds with id2.
It just becomes a mess.
So it's a lot easier,
recall from a few weeks ago,
to just having to called string names
and maybe give us three of those.
And then maybe we have
string dorms and have
three of those, or with a constant,
int ids and have three of those.
But even now this feels
a little sloppy, right.
We're talking about students and yet
I'm really dwelling on the low level
implementation details.
The student is a name and a dorm and ID.
>> Why can't I just declare a variable
called student and call it s.
And if I want another student,
why don't I just call it t.
Or if I want a whole bunch
of students, why don't I just
say I have a whole class of
students, and it's three of them.
In other words, why can't I come
up with my own data type, called
Students, inside of which is
a name, is an ID, is a dorm,
is any number of other fields.
And it turns out you
can do exactly that.
>> So C has this feature called struct.
That's a language feature that
allows us to do exactly this.
I'm going to go ahead
and open up structs.h
where we're going to see the
following definition of a student.
It turns out--and this one's even
simpler than the one involving an ID
a moment ago.
If you want to come up with
your homemade data type,
and in addition to int, and char and
float and all these others that exist,
you can do so by literally
writing typedef struct,
then some curly braces,
inside of which you
list the variables you want to
associate with this new custom data
type like a name and a dorm,
and then after the curly braces
you give a name to the new data type.
So, for instance, student.
>> And what's nice about this now is that
if we look at the corresponding code,
the convention, first
of all, is to put this
in a file called something dot h,
a header file, which we haven't
started using ourselves too much.
But we're going to start
using quite a bit now.
And what we can do with this,
ultimately, in these few lines of code
is declare exactly that
data type, a student.
And now let's use it.
>> I'm going to now go into
a file called structs1.c.
And let's take a look at a
few characteristics here.
So the stuff up here is
mostly familiar, and we'll
come back to what is not
familiar in just a moment.
This of course is including my own
header file, which is new as well,
except for PSet 3 where,
recall, we have helpers.h.
So you might recall #include helpers.h.
>> Why though am I using quotes
instead of angled brackets?
When do I choose between them?
Almost always I seem
to use angled brackets.
And then, all of a sudden on
line six I'm using double quotes.
Why might that be?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: That's an actual, what?
AUDIENCE: That's in your IDE.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
that's in my actual IDE.
And let's not dwell on the IDE, because
that's just a tool that I'm using.
That's in my current
directory, specifically.
So structs.h is my own file
not installed in the IDE,
in the operating system itself,
rather it's in my current directory.
So the convention is if you want
to include your own header file,
you just use double quotes.
>> What do we call this thing in
line 8, generally speaking?
This is what?
#define something.
This represents constants, right?
If you want to have a
value in your program
that you use a whole
bunch of times, it's
good convention to factor it out,
declare it, with the hash symbol
define, then, by convention, in all
uppercase word-- though it's not
strictly necessary, but
it's human convention
to capitalize constants
so that they jump out
at you visually-- space and
then the value you want to be
equivalent to that constant's name.
No semicolon, but you simply
follow that pattern there.
>> So what am I doing in this actual code.
So let's take a look at
the main program here.
In line 12 because I
have included structs.h,
I now have magically at my
disposal a new data type.
I don't just have access to int,
and char, and float, and string,
and blue and others.
I now have access to
a student data type.
So in line 12, I'm combining two
ideas-- one a custom data type and two,
using an array.
And so in this program if
I want to actually support
three different students
in my program, I
can simply say give me a variable
called students, each of which
is of type students, which
is my custom data type.
And, specifically, give me
three of those in my array.
>> So now what do we do in this program?
Here's just a for loop iterating
from 0 to 3, because that's
what the value of students is.
I'm just prompting the user
give me the student's name.
And then in line 17, we
have a mostly familiar line.
We have our old friend
GetString on the right.
And what piece of syntax
is apparently new,
if you've never programmed in C before,
and have never used the structs?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: The .name.
DAVID J. MALAN: The .name.
But this isn't too much of a leap,
because now students bracket i
gives you the i-th student.
And if you want to dive
inside of that structure,
you just use a single period and
then the name of the variable inside,
or the property inside that
you want to get access to.
Similarly then, if I then prompt the
user, give me the student's dorm,
you can similarly store that
string in the dorm variable inside
of that student structure.
>> And now things get a little fancy.
And this is going to look
at perhaps a lot quite soon.
But you'll see this far more in PSet
4, so let's just glance at it now.
It turns out that in line 23 through
38, what do you think I'm perhaps doing?
I've removed the comments
for today, but the version
of the code online for
reference has all comments.
What do I seem to be doing?
>> AUDIENCE: Saving the file with all
the information that the user entered.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
exactly, this is a new way
that we're seeing two,
another feature of C,
whereby I can create my own files.
Thus far, almost every program
you've written is stateless.
As soon as it's done running, that's it.
There's no memory or recollection of it.
There's no file saved.
But if you do want to
save input that has
happened, like in a game or a program
like this, it turns out we can do so.
And you'll see this more
in PSet 4 and in Section.
But this line 23 essentially
creates a file called students.csv.
And you might have seen this before.
Even if you've never studied CS before,
CSV is comma-separated variables.
It's like a very poor man's
version of an Excel file,
which means that it could be opened
in Excel and in Apple Numbers,
and it has rows and columns.
But it's not a proprietary
format like Microsoft or Apple's.
It's just commas separating the
values that we'll see in a moment.
>> And just take a guess.
In line 23, at the very
end, my second argument
to this new function called
f open for file open is w.
What might w denote?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: It lets you write to the file?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It lets
you write to the file.
So there's a couple of variants
that we can plug in here.
But if you just want to read
the file, that is look at it
and read it into memory, you
just use quote unquote "r".
If you want to write to the
file, you use quote unquote "w".
There's also append and
a couple of other things
if you want to modify existing files.
Now we're going to keep seeing this
thing, then we'll come back to line 24.
NULL, it turns out, is
a special value that
can be returned by certain functions
if something has gone wrong--
if the file doesn't exist,
if you've run out of memory,
or a bunch of other errors.
But for now, let's just assume that this
is just conventional error checking.
Here in line 26, I'm iterating
from 0 to 3 over all my students.
And this is kind of sort
of a new function, fprintf,
but just take a guess.
If printf is just print
a formatted string,
what does fprintf probably mean?
AUDIENCE: Print to a file.
DAVID J. MALAN: Print a
formatted string to a file.
That's what the additional
f means is file.
And the new first argument has to be
the variable that represents your file.
Then we just have a format
string just like printf.
And even though this
syntax is new, this just
means plug in the student's name,
plug-in the student dorm, and then
with fclose, close the file.
And then lastly-- this is new
and we'll come back to this
before long-- I'm freeing
the student for reasons
that happened up above there.
But we'll come back
to that before long--
that's because of how GetString is
actually working underneath the hood.
>> So let's take a quick look here.
If I type ls in my directory,
notice that I do not
have a file called students.csv,
just not there, does not exist.
So if I now compile this program,
make structs-1, . /structs-1,
and I'm going to go ahead and type in
Andi , who lives in Berkeley at Yale.
We're going to have Rob who
lives in Thayer these days.
And let's come up with where
is, I think, Maria is in Mather,
if I have remembered correctly.
>> So nothing seems to happen.
But if I type ls now,
there is students.csv.
Let's go ahead and open students.csv.
This is again a very
lightweight file format.
But I've simply adopted a convention
that I have two rows and columns here.
The first column is
people's first names.
The second column is the student's
dorm, or college, or house, or whatnot.
And now I've saved this
permanently in a file.
>> So it's not all that interesting.
But this is just a stepping stone now
to being able to persist information
permanently.
So let's see now what more we can
do with these and other features.
But first, any questions?
That was a lot, and that was fast.
But you'll see a lot
more in PSet 4, as well.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Is there a way to
continue adding names to that file?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
Is there a way to continue
adding names to that file?
Yes.
And, in fact, if you end
up re-opening the file,
you would use quote
unquote "a" for append,
which would just add a new line, a
new line again and again, exactly.
Good question.
Other questions?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: If you ran the
program again right now,
would it keep adding names to the
file or would it open up a new file?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Ah, good question.
If you ran the program again right
now, maybe typed in new names,
would it add to the file
or overwrite the file?
The latter, because I'm
not using append mode.
And because I'm just blindly
opening the file for writing,
it's just going to overwrite the file.
So I would indeed need to do is append,
if I want to actually have a long term
database.
>> Now CSV is useful, frankly, even
for like if you're writing--
and we'll eventually see this
later in the semester when
we use CSVs for other purposes.
If you want to store all of the people
who have registered for some event,
or signed up for your student
group, or something like that,
storing the data in this kind
of format is super convenient.
Because literally, if I
were to download this file.
I could double-- and
let's actually try this
if I have Excel or Numbers on here.
>> I'm going to right-click
or control-click my file.
Whoops.
Right-click or control-click my file.
Come on, my mouse isn't cooperating.
Download-- I'm going to
download all the files here so
just so I can grab this one.
And let's see if this works
students.csv-- first time
I've activated.
Now they want to see my contacts.
Now, I need to register.
See how easy it is to use CSVs?
Yes, keep it up to date.
OK, now we're ready for class.
OK, oh, what's new?
OK, close.
That was magical.
OK, now we have to update.
And now, it forgot what
file I originally opened,
but what a-- there we go.
OK, so now we have an Excel file.
Thank you.
>> OK, so what I did was the easy part.
Of course I could have pre-installed
Excel, or Numbers, or whatever program.
But this is nice, because
now I can manipulate
the data in a standard format.
>> So now let's context
switch to where we left off
last time, which was to start
to take off training wheels.
But first, you didn't
see this earlier lunch
is again happening here at Fire and
Ice in Cambridge, Sitar in New Haven.
Sign up on CS50s website ASAP
to join CS50 students and staff.
>> So we took training wheels
off on Monday as follows--
string has been declared in
CS50s library for some time.
And it's nice, because it allows
us to talk about variables as being
complete words and sentences and more.
But it turns out string does not exist.
That is just a synonym, or an alias,
that we have created for something that
actually is a little more
technical called a char*.
>> And indeed, we saw an example
of a program on Monday
that didn't behave quite as we expected.
This was the file, compare-0.
And recall that compare-0, if
I recompile Monday's program
and run compare-0 and type in mom in
lowercase, and mom in lowercase again.
The program insisted I
type different things,
even though mom, all in
lowercase, is identical visually.
So what was the short answer
for why the computer thinks
those two strings are different?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Right.
So, mom, the first time
I type it in, is being
stored somewhere in my computer's
memory but in a different location
than the second time I type in mom.
Now it certainly could be optimized.
The computer could be smart and
realize these two strings, hey,
they're identical.
Let me not redundantly store it.
But computers don't do that
optimization unless you tell them to.
So, by default, they're
just going to end up
in two different places in memory.
And so to be more clear, when
we compared the two strings,
the first was called s,
the second was called
t, what specifically was I
comparing here on line 13?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: It's the place in memory
that the variable will point to.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly, I was
comparing the place in memory
that those variables pointed to.
So specifically, if mom was at
byte number 1, and 2, and 3,
and 4-- because remember the backslash
0 needs to be all the way at the end.
And the other instance of mom, m-o-m,
was at address 10, 11, 12, and 13.
I was comparing 1, that address,
that location in memory,
against 10, which is
obviously not the same.
1 is not 10.
>> So this is nice in that
it's pretty straightforward.
But it's problematic insofar as
we can't seem to compare strings.
So fundamentally--
and at this low level,
if you wanted to implement
a program to compare
two separate words that the
user has typed in for quality,
do they line up char for
char, just in general terms,
what do we need to do, apparently?
It's not sufficient just to
look at those two addresses.
What do we need to do?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Iterate through
the string [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, let's
iterate through the string.
Let's use a for loop, a while loop, or
whatever you're most comfortable with.
And if we've got two strings somewhere
in memory, let's look at each's
first character, then each's second
character, then third, and fourth,
and fifth, until we hit
what special sentinel value?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, the backslash
zero, at which point in either string
we can decide that's it.
Have we matched every single character?
If not, return false.
If so, return true.
And so that's exactly what this version
of the program compare-1.c does.
It is identical to what we
looked at Monday except that I've
gotten rid of the word string-- though
that has no functional impact-- all
I'm doing now is removing
some visual training wheels,
but to see clearly that
s and t are addresses.
And that's what the star,
the asterisk, represents
is an address, otherwise known
more technically as a pointer.
>> So when I declare s on
line 9 and say char* s,
that doesn't mean give me a string.
That means give me a variable whose
purpose in life is to store an address.
Because I am about to put the
address of a string into it.
And indeed, GetString, to be
clear, does not return a string.
It does not return mom
backslash zero, per se.
What does GetString specifically
and precisely return?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: An address, the
address of the first character
in some string it has gotten.
And so now we're seeing
a special keyword again.
And, I alluded to this earlier.
This is going to be good convention
that we'll see again and again now.
I'm checking to make sure that
s is not null and t is not null.
Because based on my really
quick mention earlier,
what might mean if GetString returns not
an address but N-U-L-L, which is again,
some special value?
>> AUDIENCE: Error.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It's an error.
Something went wrong.
And what typically
might happen, especially
with strings-- which might be
of unknown length in advance--
maybe the computers'
out of memory, maybe
you typed in such a
long word or sentence
or pasted such a huge essay
there's just not enough memory.
And so GetString can't return
the address of the whole thing,
so it just returns nothing.
And it says an error has happened
by returning the special NULL value.
It's the zero address, so to speak.
>> Now it turns out C comes with a
function that does that iteration.
We don't have to implement this with
a for loop or a while loop ourselves.
We can use a function,
called succinctly,
stir comp, or string compare, whose
purpose in life is to do exactly that.
You give it two pointers, two addresses,
and it will go to those addresses
and then compare letter for
letter for letter for quality,
stopping only when what is true?
When intuitively should stir comp
stop iterating, just to be clear?
When it hits a backslash 0 in either
string, at which point it can decide
has everything matched, or
has there been a discrepancy?
>> So, if we run this now and try
our little capitalization game,
so make compare-1, ./compare-1, and
type mom in lowercase both times.
Now it's the same thing.
And if I do it again with
lowercase and then maybe uppercase.
Now it indeed distinguishes
between upper and lowercase.
So not all that hard or
magical, but it does now explain
what's going on underneath the hood.
>> So what more can we extract
from this kind of lesson?
So let's take a look at this.
I'm going to go ahead and write a
quick program here called copy-0.
And now let's go ahead and actually
let's do this-- with copy-0,
take a look at what I've got here.
I first tell the user, say something.
Then I get a string
and I stored it in s.
Then I check if s equals
equals NULL, just return 1.
So this is just standard error checking.
Nothing interesting has happened.
And in fact, if we get rid of the error
checking, this looks like week 1 code
at the moment.
But I've started to get a
little better about that.
>> Now in line 16, a week ago, maybe
even a couple days or minutes ago,
you might say line 16 is
creating a variable called t
and copying s into it.
And that's a perfectly
reasonable takeaway.
But be more precise now.
What is happening in line 16?
What is getting copied
from right to left?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Is t getting an address of s?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly, t
is getting the address of s.
So to be clear now, if I go
back to that earlier example
and I draw out the thing I've typed in.
And what I've typed
in-- here's s, and here
is what I've typed in somewhere in
memory, mom and then a backslash
0 that's added for me.
What I stored in here, recall,
this is at location 1, 2, 3, 4,
this is what's currently in s.
So if on line 16, I say give me
another variable called t and store
in at the value of s, what
gets stored here will not mom
but rather just the number 1.
>> So if we look ahead in this program
now, what's going to happen?
So notice that there's
this function you might
have used this some time ago for Caesar,
or Vigenere, or maybe not at all.
I claim with my printf, I'm
going to capitalize the copy t.
First in line 19, quick sanity
check, strlen checks the length of t.
Because I don't want to
try to capitalize something
if there's no string there.
If the user just hit Enter,
there's nothing to capitalize.
So I don't want to do line 21.
So line 21 is capitalizing
which letter, apparently, in t?
>> AUDIENCE: m?
DAVID J. MALAN: It looks
like it's copying which one?
AUDIENCE: m.
DAVID J. MALAN: Uh, m.
OK, so the first m,
because notice that I'm
passing to toupper, which
if you've never seen it it's
just a function to
capitalize as its input.
t bracket zero means give
me the zero character of t.
And so how does this
picture change, to be clear?
What needs to get rewritten or changed
with respect to s and t and mom
backslash zero.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
so this one here simply
needs to get changed to-- fix this--
needs to get changed to a capital m.
But now, look later in the
program, if I print out
s and t as I clean here, watch what's
going to happen printing out s and t.
So make copy-0, ./copy-0.
Let me go ahead and type
in mom in all lowercase.
Notice both the original and
the copy have been capitalized.
Why?
Well, s and t are both pointing to,
if you will, the same chunk of memory.
And frankly, this is getting
really uninteresting-- the fact
that we're using address zero here.
I mean, I don't really care
where stuff is in memory.
Sorry I'm erasing a little too much.
But I don't really care
where things are in memory.
And so, indeed what
programmers tend to think about
is that when you talk about
an address, or a pointer,
who cares where it is in memory.
I don't care if it's at
byte one or one billion.
I just care that this
variable is effectively
pointing at that chunk of memory.
And so, henceforth, rather than quibble
over arbitrary memory addresses, let's
just start to draw pointers
as pointers, as arrows.
So what s and t really are,
according to this program,
because of how I created t,
it's just two separate variables
pointing at the same chunk of memory.
And we don't care where they are.
So we can abstract away that detail.
>> So how do I fix this?
If I want to write a version of the copy
program that actually copies the string
and capitalizes only the
copy, just intuitively,
what's got to be an
ingredient to our solution?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: We need a what?
AUDIENCE: Chunk of memory.
DAVID J. MALAN: We need
another chunk of memory, right?
We don't know how to
do it yet, necessarily.
But I kind of need this to happen so
that the original mom in lower case
ends up in that extra chunk of memory.
And then when I change the copy, I
don't want to change this copy here.
I instead want to change only this
copy so that the original is unchanged.
>> So, let's see how we might do this.
In copy-1, which has already
been stripped of comment,
but is commented online.
We instead do the following-- these
lines are identical, get me a string
and call it s.
But now let's look at one of our most
complex but the last of the complexity
for awhile, line 16 does exactly this.
So if your comfy with the
picture we just drew--
give me a new chunk of memory,
copy everything into it,
let's see how we translate that to code.
>> So line 16, on the left hand side,
char* t gives me this box over here.
That's all it does.
On the right hand side,
m alloc, or malloc,
is memory allocation, super fancy,
a cryptic way of just saying
give me a chunk of memory.
How much memory do we need?
Well, is kind of a big expression.
But let's see what it says here.
So this, of course, is give
me the string length of s.
So, mom it should be what?
So just three, right?
mom is three characters.
You don't count the
backslash zero when you
talk about the length of a string it's
actually the human visible letters.
So mom, so this gives me 3.
But wait a minute, I'm now adding 1.
Why do I actually want to
allocate 4 bytes and not just 3?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: For the sentinel value?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly,
for that sentinel value.
For the backslash zero,
I need 4 bytes total.
So I need the length
of the string plus 1.
And then just for good measure--
even though on this system,
it's always going to be 1-- I'm saying
multiply this by the size of a char.
Turns out sizeof is
an operator in C that
just tells you the
number of bytes that's
required for a certain data type.
It doesn't work for arrays,
typically, sometimes it does.
But in the general case, no.
But it will tell me how many bytes a
char is, which turns out is always 1.
So this is like multiplying by 1.
>> So super cryptic looking line of code.
But all it does is gives
me a chunk of memory.
But does it seem to be copying
anything into that memory?
Not yet.
And so what do I on line 22, and
23, 24, 25, well, I simply do this.
And this is sort of
old school stuff now.
This is like PSet 2, where
you're just moving things
around in memory, or rather in strings.
>> So I'm iterating from 0 to
the length of the string s.
And I'm copying the i-th character
in s into the i-th character in t.
And because I, the programmer, made
sure to allocate exactly as many bytes
as I need, it's perfect
one-to-one relationship.
And I copy mom in
lowercase to the new one.
And then lastly, I do this line.
And so the effect is only
to capitalize this t here.
So a lot to absorb, but
if you just consider
what's really going
on underneath the hood
is just moving these
bytes around, all that
is needed to solve this problem is
just to give us this chunk of memory.
Now at the risk of
overwhelming, let me show
one other example that's almost
identical, except for this one
line of code.
So this is the hacker version
of this program, if you will.
But let's just distill
it into what's going on.
Line 24 used to be this t
bracket i gets s bracket i.
Now, I'm changing this to
the much more cryptic star t
plus 1 equals star s plus 1.
>> So what's happening and why
do we have a star character?
We've seen the star before, and
it's being used differently here.
We previously saw char*, now I'm seeing
a star at the beginning, and that's OK.
Because it turns out we
can kind of infer just
from those first
principles what's going on.
So just to be clear, what is s?
Last week, it was a string.
That doesn't suffice anymore.
What is s, specifically?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It's a pointer.
It's the address of the
first character we typed in.
OK, what is t?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: The
address of the first byte
in t, that chunk of memory reallocated.
So it turns out that when we
iterate from 0 on up to the string
length-- first of all, i
starts off at 0, because
of this old school for loop thing.
So just for simplicity, let's
assume that the first line of code
is really just this, right.
If i is zero, adding zero
to something presumably
is not going to have an effect.
>> So what is this saying?
It turns out that the star
operator in this context
is the dereference
operator, which is just
a fancy way of saying go
to the following address.
So if s is the address of the first
character in this chunk of memory,
*s means go there.
And because we've drawn
the picture in this way,
you can adopt the
following mental model.
If this is s, and you say *s, *s
kind of like chutes and ladders,
if you remember the game from childhood,
is like follow that arrow and go
to the address.
>> *t is the same thing.
So start here, go to its chunk.
I can't just draw on
this screen that way.
*t means to go here.
And then, the for loop is just
saying move this character here,
move this character here,
move this character here.
But how do I do that incrementation?
I need to undo what I just deleted.
This is what's generally called
pointer arithmetic, which
means math with addresses.
>> If, in this for loop,
I keep incrementing i,
and s is an address and t is an
address, if I just keep adding 1,
that just means keep moving forward,
and forward, and forward in the memory.
It's like Oxford Street, the
street that the CS building is on.
The CS buildings is at 33 Oxford Street.
So if you were to do 33
Oxford Street plus 1,
that brings you to 34 Oxford
Street, then 35 Oxford Street,
then 36 Oxford Street, whatever those
buildings actually are--if they exist.
And so, that's all we're doing
here with pointer arithmetic.
>> So it's a super arcane way
of expressing ourselves.
But all that's happening
underneath the hood
is just following these addresses,
like following a map, if you will,
or following arrows like
we've drawn on the screen.
OK, a lot to digest.
Any question on syntax, concepts,
pointers, malloc, or the like.
Yeah, over here first.
>> AUDIENCE: So where that
says *t equals toupper *t,
is that going to capitalize
all the letters or just--
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Ah,
really good question.
So in this line here, 31,
is this going to capitalize
the first letter or all of the letters.
So let's answer that by going
back to first principles.
And first principles here I mean
just go to the basic definitions
of what's involved.
So toupper's a function
that capitalizes a char.
That's all.
*t means go to the first--
go to the address in t.
So, in the picture, if this is the chunk
of memory we allocated with malloc,
and this is t, *t means go here.
>> Meanwhile, you're passing
that value, lowercase m
to toupper, you're getting back
capital M, where are you putting it?
You're putting it in that same location.
And so by that logic of those
basic definitions it's only
capitalizing the first letter
unless you iterate with i or a
for loop or a while loop, it's not going
to do anything more than you ask it.
Good question.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Why did you use the
dereference method rather than
the array?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Ah, good question.
Why would you use the dereference
method instead of the array method?
No particular reason, to be honest.
And, in fact, for this
kind of example, right,
I'm just arguing making the
program more complicated,
more eyes are glazing over,
people are checking out
because this looks super arcane, but
even though it's doing the same thing.
And so, frankly, this is an
unnecessarily visually complex solution
to the problem.
>> It's still good design,
five out of five for design,
whether it's in the bracket
notation or the pointer notation.
But-- especially when we get
later in the course in PSet 5
when we implement that dictionary that
I've mentioned a couple of times--
we'll actually care about the
low level memory addresses
that we really understand
what's going on.
>> But, for now, it turns out that this
line of code here square brackets
don't really exist.
They are what's called
syntactic sugar, which
is just a weirdly cool way of saying the
compiler converts square brackets to be
that mathematical expression.
So it's a human convention
to be able to just write
these very user-friendly brackets.
But what the compiler, clang,
is really doing any time
you write what's highlighted in line
24, underneath the hood it's really
converting it to this.
It's just more pleasurable as a human
to read and write code like line 24.
But eventually those
training wheels too come off
when one's own comfort gets stronger.
>> All right, so recall then that this
was the sort of biggest problem
we ran into.
And that's what sparked this whole
damn conversation about pointers,
and addresses, and copying things.
It was because we tripped over
this stupid, stupid issue, whereby
I implemented logically-- with Lauren
up here on the demo and the orange juice
in the milk-- a perfectly
algorithmically correct function
for swapping two variables'
values, but the damn thing
didn't have any persistent, or
permanent, effect on my code.
>> And why was that?
In a nutshell, why is this
implementation of swap
logically correct, but has no impact
on the variables that are passed to it,
like x and y for main?
What was the gist of the issue?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Because variable made
copies of variable in the pass
through function.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly, when you pass
variables into a function, or arguments
into a function, they're
passed by copy, which
means you get an identical looking
pattern of bits for both x and y,
called here a and b.
And you can do anything
you want with those copies,
but they're going to have no
effect on the calling function.
And, in fact, we drew that
picture on the screen, recall
last time, whereby if you
really think about what's
going on underneath the hood-- if
this is your computer's memory,
and down here is the chunk of
memory being used for main,
this is the chunk of
memory being used for swap,
and so even if main has
two variables, x and y,
swap might have identical looking
values, both of which are 1 and 2,
but they're completely
different chunks of memory.
>> So we need a solution to this.
And frankly, it would seem that we now
have a solution to this problem, right.
If we now have the ability to
manipulate things by way of addresses
and, sort of chutes and ladders
style, follow these arrows
and go anywhere we want
in memory, couldn't we
solve this problem by
passing from main to swap
not the values we want to
swap, but just intuitively
what could we pass to swap instead?
>> [INTERPOSING VOICES]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Why don't we just
pass it the addresses, right?
Why don't we give swap a
treasure map, if you will,
that leads it to the
actual values x and y.
Let's swap, actually change
those original bits, rather than
just passing copies of the bits.
And so, in fact, that's what's
going to be the solution.
This version here is
clearly bad and flawed.
And now, at first glance, it just looks
like we added a bunch of stars randomly
and crossed our fingers
that it would compile.
But, it would now compile.
>> But let's see what these things mean.
And, unfortunately, the authors of
C could have chosen another symbol
to make this a little
clearer, but the star operator
has different meaning in
two different contexts.
And we've seen both,
but let's distinguish.
>> So up at the top there,
when I have changed a and b
from being int's in the bad
version to int stars, a and b,
previously, were integers.
What are a and b now in
the good, green version?
They're addresses.
Addresses of what, to be clear?
Addresses of integers.
So the fact that I'm
saying int star means
this is the address of
an integer, specifically.
>> So now notice in the lines of code,
something else has changed too.
tmp stays the same, because
it's just the temporary integer,
no memory magic there.
But a now needs a star.
And, in fact, every
other mention of a and b,
notice that all that's
changing from red to green
is that I'm prefixing
those variables with stars.
Because I don't want to copy a and b.
Because if I just copy a and b and swap
a and b, what am I actually swapping?
Just addresses, I want to swap
what's at those addresses.
I want to go there.
And so the star operator
inside of my function,
not inside of the parameter list,
means you go to those addresses
and actually change those values.
>> So what does the picture
now look like instead.
Well, if instead I'm passing
in for a and b not 1 and 2--
I actually need to add
one other definition here.
So suppose that this chunk
of memory is at location 10.
>> This is at location 11, but this
is a bit of a simplification,
I now have two choices do I pass x
and y or do I pass their addresses?
If I pass their addresses
like this, I just
now need to implement
swap per the green code
so that when it sees a and when it
sees b, it doesn't just copy a and b
and move the milk and orange juice.
The milk and orange juice
metaphor now breaks down,
because those are cups
of liquid and not maps.
We instead need to go
to address 10 and we
need to go to address 11, and
then perform that swapping logic.
>> So the logic is the same, but
we need a slightly different way
of accessing those variables.
And so in the end, what the
program has to look like is this.
In swap.c literally copied
and pasted the green version.
But I need to make one change.
It's not sufficient just to change swap.
What other line of code
do I need to change?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Where it takes the arguments.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Where
it takes its argument.
So if I scroll up to main, I
can't just pass in x and y,
and, I promise, the last
piece of new syntax today.
I need to pass in not x and
y but the address of x and y.
And it turns out, the symbol
that the authors of C chose
is if you use an ampersand here, not to
be confused with the bitwise ampersand,
if you use an ampersand
here and an ampersand here,
this figures out for you,
what's the address of x,
maybe it's 10, what's the
address of y, maybe it's
11, and passes those in instead.
>> So a lot to absorb all at once.
But let's see now quickly in
our remaining four minutes
where things can go awry.
And as an aside, actually
I took this picture,
TF took this picture a year or two ago.
So this is the back corner
of Eliot Dining Hall.
Pointers are perhaps the hardest
topic that we cover in CS50.
So if you worry the sort
of slope is like maybe it's
more of a hockey stick
like this, realize
we're kind of nearing a peak in
terms of the conceptual complexity.
>> And I bring up this
photo, because I swear
to god, in fall 1996, when I took
CS50 with my teaching fellow,
Nishat Mehta, he sat me down in the
corner of the Eliot D. Hall over lunch,
or dinner, or something to try
to help me understand pointers.
And this is where I was weeks after
it was introduced in lecture when
I finally understood pointers.
And I'm hopeful that this
will click far sooner for you.
But realize this absolutely among
the more sophisticated topics
we've looked at.
But it's among the most powerful.
And when you get it, it's really all
just going to finally come together.
So rest assured it doesn't
need to all sink in today.
>> So here's the last program
we're going to look at.
And we're going to end with a
quick three minutes of claymation
made by our friend, Nick Parlante.
Here's a program, that on the top two
lines declares a variable x and y.
Both of which are addresses
of integers, AKA pointers.
We then allocate enough
memory to store an int
and store the address
of that memory in x.
So, it's even simpler
than the example before.
Give me four bytes of memory,
that's the size of an int,
and put that address in x.
This line here means
go to the address in x
and put the meaning of
life, the number 42 there.
But this line worries me.
Star y means go to the address in y,
and put the unlucky number 13 there.
Why is it dangerous, at this point
in the story-- albeit rapidly told
in our waning minutes
here-- why is it bad
for me to say, go to the address in y?
>> AUDIENCE: You haven't [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: I haven't
put anything in y.
So what is the value of y,
at this point in the story?
We have no idea.
It's some garbage value
and nor does Binky know.
If we could end on this note.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -Hey, Binky, wake up.
It's time for pointer fun.
>> -What's that?
Learn about pointers?
Oh, goody.
>> -Well, to get started, I guess we're
going to need a couple pointers.
>> -OK.
This code allocates two pointers
which can point to integers.
>> -OK, well I see the
two pointers, but they
don't seem to be pointing to anything.
>> -That's right.
Initially pointers
don't point to anything.
The things they point to are
called pointees and setting them up
is a separate step.
>> -Oh, right, right.
I knew that.
The pointees are separate.
So how do you allocate a pointee?
>> -OK, well this code allocates
a new integer pointee,
and this part sets x to point to it.
>> -Hey, that looks better.
So make it do something.
>> -OK, I'll dereference the pointer x to
store the number 42 into its pointee.
For this trick, I'll need my
magic wand of dereferencing.
>> -Your magic wand of dereferencing?
Uh, that, that's great.
>> -This is what the code looks like.
I'll just set up the number and--
>> [POP SOUND]
>> -Hey, look there it goes.
So, doing a dereference on x follows
the arrow to access its pointee.
In this case, to store 42 in there.
Hey, try using it to store the number
13 through the other pointer, y.
>> -OK.
I'll just go over here to y,
and get the number 13 set up.
And then take the wand of
dereferencing and just--
>> [BUZZER SOUND]
>> -Oh, hey that didn't work.
Say, uh, Binky, I don't
think dereferencing
y is a good idea, because setting
up the pointee is a separate step.
And I don't think we ever did it.
>> -Hmm, good point.
>> -Yeah, we allocated the pointer, y, but
we never set it to point to a pointee.
>> -Hmm, very observant.
-Hey, you're looking good there, Binky.
Can you fix it so that y points
to the same pointee as x.
>> -Sure, I use my magic wand
of pointer assignment.
>> -Is that going to be a
problem, like before?
>> -No, this doesn't touch the pointees.
It just changes one pointer
to point to the same thing--
>> [POPPING SOUND]
--as another.
>> -Oh, I see.
Now y points to the same place as x.
So, wait, now y is fixed.
It has a pointee.
So you can try the wand of
dereferencing again to send the 13 over.
>> -Oh, OK, here goes.
>> -Hey, look at that.
Now dereferencing works on y.
And because the pointers are sharing
that one pointee, they both see the 13.
>> -Yeah, sharing, uh, whatever.
So, are we going to switch places now?
>> -Oh, look we're out of time.
>> -But--
>> -Just remember the three pointer rules.
Number 1, the basic structure
is that you have a pointer,
and it points over to a pointee.
But the pointer and
pointee are separate.
And the common error
is to set up a pointer
but to forget to give it a pointee.
>> Number 2, pointer dereferencing
starts at the pointer
and follows its arrow over
to access its pointee.
As we all know, this only works if there
is a pointee, which kind of gets back
to rule number 1.
>> Number 3, pointer
assignment takes one pointer
and changes it to point to the
same pointee as another pointer.
So after the assignment,
the two pointers
will point to the same pointee,
sometimes that's called sharing.
And that's all there is to it, really.
Bye-bye now.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: That's it for CS50.
Thanks to Professor Nick Parlante.
We'll see you next week.
>> [ELECTRONIC MUSIC PLAYING]