>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID MALAN: This is CS50, and
this is the start of week 10.
And you might remember this
image from a few weeks back
when we talked about
the internet and how
it's actually implemented physically.
And you might recall that there's
actually a whole bunch of cables
as well as wireless
technologies that interconnect
all of the nodes or routers and other
such technologies on the internet.
And a lot of that is underseas.
>> Well, it turns out that those
underseas cables are a bit of a target.
And today's lecture is entirely
about security, not only
the threats that we all face
physically, but also virtually,
and also, toward tail end
today, some of the defenses
that we as users can
actually put into place.
>> But first, one of the first and
perhaps most physical threat--
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-Could Russia be planning
an attack on undersea cables
that connect global internet?
>> -Russian ships and submarines
lurking near undersea cables
that carry almost all
of the world's internet.
>> -The entire internet is
carried along these cables.
>> -First of all, what is the
internet doing underwater?
Last time I checked, I'm not
supposed to get my computer wet.
Second, if you ask me how the internet
travels from continent to continent,
I would've said satellites
or lasers, or, honestly,
I probably would have
just said the internet.
>> And what happened to the cloud?
I was told there was a cloud.
Remember?
Hey, let's put that in the cloud.
It was like the internet was a vapor
of information that circles the Earth,
and your computer was like a ladle
that scooped out what you needed.
>> But it turns out the internet
is actually underwater
because these cables carry more than
95% of daily internet communications.
And US intelligence worries that
in times of tension or conflict,
Russia might resort to severing them.
It would be the biggest disruption
to your internet service
since your upstairs neighbor
put a password on his Wi-Fi.
OK?
Try his dog's name.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: Before we turn now to
some of the more virtual threats,
a couple of announcements.
So our friends a
CrimsonEMS are currently
recruiting for new EMTs,
Emergency Medical Technicians.
And this is actually something
particularly close to my heart.
>> A long time ago, I
remember being in an Ikea
shortly after graduation, actually.
And as I was exiting the store, this
little boy who was in a stroller
started turning literally blue.
And he was choking on some piece
of food that had presumably
gotten stuck in his throat.
>> And his mother was panicking.
The parents around them were panicking.
And even I, who had a bit of familiarity
with EMS just by way of friends,
completely froze.
And it was only thanks to something
like a 15-year-old lifeguard who
ran over and actually knew what to
do instinctively and called for help
and actually pulled the
boy out of his stroller
and actually addressed the situation.
>> And for me, that was a turning point.
And it was that moment in
time where I decided, dammit,
I need to have my act
together and actually know
how to respond to these
kinds of situations.
And so I myself got licensed
years ago as an EMT.
And through graduate school
did I ride on MIT's ambulance
for some period of time as well
as have kept up my license since.
>> And actually, to this day, all
of CS50 staff here in Cambridge
are actually certified in CPR,
as well, for similar reasons.
So if you're at all
interested in this, there's
never going to be enough time in
the day to take on something new.
But if you want a New Year's
resolution, do join these guys here
or consider reaching out to the
Red Cross for certification,
either here or in New Haven, as well.
>> So CS50's last lunch is this Friday.
So if you've not yet joined us, or if
you have and you want one more time,
do go on CS50's website to
fill out the form there.
Know, too, that our friends in
Yale, Professor Scassellati,
has been producing an AI, artificial
intelligence, series for us
that will start to debut
this week on video.
So especially if you are interested
in pursuing a final project somehow
related to artificial intelligence,
natural language processing,
even robotics, realize that these will
be a wonderful inspiration for that.
>> And just to give you a teaser
of this, here is Scaz himself.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -One of the really great
things about computer science
is that with even only
a few weeks of study,
you're going to be able to understand
many of the intelligent artifacts
and devices that populate
our modern world.
In this short video
series, we're going to look
at things like how Netflix is able
to suggest and recommend movies
that I might like, how it is that
Siri can answer questions that I have,
how it is that Facebook
can recognize my face
and automatically tag
me in a photograph,
or how Google is able to build
a car that drives on its own.
>> So I hope you'll join me for this short
series of videos, the CS50 AI series.
I think you'll find that you know
much more than you thought you did.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: So those will appear on
the course's website later this week.
Stay tuned.
And in the meantime, a few
announcements as to what lies ahead.
So we are here.
This is in our lecture on security.
This coming Wednesday, Scaz and Andy,
our head teaching fellow in New Haven,
will be here to look at
artificial intelligence
itself for a look at
computation for communication--
how to build systems that use
language to communicate from ELIZA,
if you're familiar with this
software from yesteryear, to Siri
more recently and to Watson, which you
might know from Jeopardy or the like.
>> Then next Monday, we're
not here in Cambridge.
We're in New Haven for a second
look at artificial intelligence
with Scaz and company--
AI opponents in games.
So if you've ever played against
the computer in some video game
or mobile game or the like, we'll
talk about exactly that-- how
to build opponents for games,
how to represent things
underneath the hood using trees
from games like tic-tac-toe
to chess to actual modern
video games, as well.
>> Sadly, quiz one is shortly thereafter.
More details on that on CS50's
website later this week.
And our final lecture at Yale will
be that Friday after the quiz.
And our final lecture at Harvard
will be the Monday thereafter,
by nature of scheduling.
>> And so in terms of milestones,
besides pset eight out this week;
status report, which will be a
quick sanity check between you
and your teaching fellow;
the hackathon, which
will be here in Cambridge for students
from New Haven and Cambridge alike.
We will take care of all
transportation from New Haven.
The implementation of the
final project will be due.
And then for both campuses
will there be a CS50 fair
that allows us to take
a look at and delight
in what everyone has accomplished.
>> In fact, I thought this would be a good
moment to draw attention to this device
here, which we've used for
some amount of time here,
which is a nice touch screen.
And actually, last
year we had a $0.99 app
that we downloaded from the Windows app
store in order to draw on the screen.
>> But frankly, it was very cluttered.
It allowed us to draw on the
screen, but there were, like,
a lot of icons up here.
The user interface was pretty bad.
If you wanted to change
certain settings,
there were just so many damn clicks.
And the user interface--
or, more properly,
the user experience--
was pretty suboptimal,
especially using it in
a lecture environment.
>> And so we reached out
to a friend of ours
at Microsoft, Bjorn, who's actually
been following along with CS50 online.
And as his final project,
essentially, did he very graciously
take some input from us as to exactly
the features and user experience
we want.
And he then went about building
for Windows this application here
that allows us to draw--
oops-- and spell on the-- wow.
Thank you.
To draw and spell on this screen here
with very minimal user interface.
>> So you've seen me, perhaps, tap up
here ever so slightly where now we
can underline things in red.
We can toggle and now
go to white text here.
If we want to actually delete
the screen, we can do this.
And if we actually prefer a
white canvas, we can do that.
So it does so terribly little
by design and does it well.
So that I futz, hopefully,
far less this year in class.
>> And thanks, too, to a protege of his
am I wearing today a little ring.
This is Benjamin, who was
interning with Bjorn this summer.
So it's a little ring.
It's a little larger than my usual ring.
But via a little dial on
the side here can I actually
move the slides left and right, forward
and back, and actually advance things
wirelessly so that, one, I don't have
to keep going back over to the space bar
here.
And two, I don't have to have
one of those stupid clickers
and preoccupy my hand by holding
the damn thing all the time
in order to simply click.
And surely, in time, will the hardware
like this get super, super smaller.
>> So certainly, don't hesitate
to think outside the box
and do things and create
things that don't even
exist yet for final projects.
Without further ado,
a look at what awaits
as you dive into your final
projects at the CS50 hackathon
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> [SNORING]
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
So the Stephen Colbert clip
that I showed just a moment ago
was actually on TV just a few days ago.
And in fact, a couple of the other clips
we'll show today are incredibly recent.
And in fact, that speaks to the
reality that so much of technology
and, frankly, a lot of the ideas
we've been talking about in CS50
really are omnipresent.
And one of the goals of
the course is certainly
to equip you with technical skills so
that you can actually solve problems
programmatically, but two, so that
you can actually make better decisions
and make more informed decisions.
And, in fact, thematic throughout the
press and online videos and articles
these days is just a frightening
misunderstanding or lack
of understanding of how technology
works, especially among politicians.
>> And so indeed, in just a bit we'll
take a look at one of those details,
as well.
But literally just last
night was I sitting
in Bertucci's, a local
franchise Italian place.
And I hopped on their Wi-Fi.
And I was very reassured
to see that it's secure.
And I knew that because it says
here "Secure Internet Portal"
when the screen came up.
So this was the little prompt
that comes up in Mac OS
or in Windows when you connect to
a Wi-Fi network for the first time.
And I had to read through their terms
and conditions and finally click OK.
And then I was allowed to proceed.
>> So let's start to rethink what all of
this means and to no longer take for
granted what people tell us when we
encounter it with various technology.
So one, what does it mean that
this is a secure internet portal?
What could Bertucci's
be reassuring me of?
AUDIENCE: The packets sent
back and forth are encrypted.
DAVID MALAN: Good.
The packets being sent back
and forth are encrypted.
Is that in fact the case?
If that were the case, what would I
have to do or what would I have to know?
Well, you'd see a little
padlock icon in Mac OS
or in Windows saying that
there is indeed some encryption
or scrambling going on.
But before you can use an encrypted
portal or Wi-Fi connection, what
do you have to usually type in?
A password.
I know no such password, nor
did I type any such password.
I simply clicked OK.
So this is utterly meaningless.
This is not a secure internet portal.
This is a 100% insecure internet portal.
There's absolutely no encryption going
on, and all that is making it secure
is that three-word phrase
on the screen there.
>> So that means nothing,
necessarily, technologically.
And a little more
worrisome, if you actually
read through the terms and conditions,
which are surprisingly readable,
was this-- "you
understand that we reserve
the right to log or monitor traffic to
ensure these terms are being followed."
So that's a little creepy, if Bertucci's
is watching my internet traffic.
But most any agreement that
you've blindly clicked through
has surely said that before.
>> So what does that actually
mean technologically?
So if there's some creepy
guy or woman in back
who's, like, monitoring
all the internet traffic,
how is he or she accessing
that information exactly?
What are the technological
means via which
that person-- or
adversary, more generally--
can be looking at our traffic?
>> Well, if there's no encryption, what
kinds of things could they sniff,
so to speak, sort of detect in the air.
What would you look at?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: The packets being sent
from your computer to the router?
>> DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
The packets being sent from
the computer to your router.
So you might recall when
we were in New Haven,
we passed those envelopes, physically,
throughout the audience to represent
data going through the internet.
And certainly, if we were throwing
them through the audience wirelessly
to reach their destination, anyone can
sort of grab it and make a copy of it
and actually see what's
inside of that envelope.
>> And, of course, what's
inside of these envelopes
is any number of things,
including the IP address
that you're trying to
access or the host name,
like www.harvard.edu or
yale.edu that you're trying
to access or something else altogether.
Moreover, the path, too-- you know from
pset six that inside of HTTP requests
are get slash something.html.
So if you're visiting a specific page,
downloading a specific image or video,
all of that information
is inside of that packet.
And so anyone there in Bertucci's can
be looking at that very same data.
Well, what are some other
threats along these lines
to be mindful of before you
just start accepting as fact
what someone like
Bertucci's simply tells you?
Well, this was an article--
a series of articles
that came out just a few months back.
All the rage these days are
these newfangled smart TVs.
What's a smart TV, if you've
heard of them or have one at home?
AUDIENCE: Internet connectivity?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah,
internet connectivity.
So generally, a smart TV is a
TV with internet connectivity
and a really crappy user
interface that makes
it harder to actually use the web
because you have to use, like, up,
down, left, and right or something
on your remote control just
to access things that are so much
more easily done on a laptop.
>> But more worrisome about a smart TV,
and Samsung TVs in this particular case,
was that Samsung TVs and others
these days come with certain hardware
to create what they claim is a
better user interface for you.
So one, you can talk to
some of your TVs these days,
not unlike Siri or any of the
other equivalents on mobile phones.
So you can say commands,
like change channel,
raise volume, turn off, or the like.
But what's the implication
of that logically?
If you've got the TV in your living
room or the TV at the foot of your bed
to fall asleep to,
what's the implication?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: There might be something
going in through the mechanism
to detect your speech.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: That could
be sent via internet.
If it's unencrypted,
then it's vulnerable.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
If you have a microphone built
into a TV and its purpose in life
is, by design, to listen
to you and respond to you,
it's surely going to be
listening to everything you say
and then translating that to
some embedded instructions.
But the catch is that most of these
TVs aren't perfectly smart themselves.
They're very dependent on
that internet connection.
>> So much like Siri, when
you talk into your phone,
quickly sends that data across
the internet to Apple servers,
then gets back a response, literally
is the Samsung TV and equivalents
just sending everything you're
saying in your living room
or bedroom to their servers just to
detect did he say, turn on the TV
or turn off the TV?
And God knows what
else might be uttered.
Now, there's some ways
to mitigate this, right?
Like what does Siri and what
does Google and others do
to at least defend against
that risk that they're
listening to absolutely everything?
It has to be activated
by saying something
like, hey, Siri, or hi Google or
the like or OK, Google or the like.
>> But we all know that those
expressions kind of suck, right?
Like I was just sitting--
actually the last time
I was at office hours at Yale, I think,
Jason or one of the TFs kept yelling,
like, hey, Siri, hey, Siri
and was making my phone
do things because he was too
proximal to my actual phone.
But the reverse is true, too.
Sometimes those things just
kick on because it's imperfect.
And indeed, natural
language processing--
understanding a human's phrasing and
then doing something based on it--
is certainly imperfect.
>> Now, worse yet, some
of you might have seen
or have a TV where you can do
stupid or new-age things like this
to change channels to the left or
this to change channels to the right
or lower the volume or raise the volume.
But what does that mean the TV has?
A camera pointed at you
at all possible times.
>> And in fact, the brouhaha around Samsung
TVs for which they took some flack
is that if you read the terms and
conditions of the TV-- the thing
you certainly never read when unpacking
your TV for the first time-- embedded
in there was a little disclaimer
saying the equivalent of,
a you might not want to have personal
conversations in front of this TV.
And that's what it reduces to.
>> But you shouldn't even
need to be told that.
You should be able to
infer from the reality
that microphone and camera literally
pointing at me all the time
maybe is more bad than good.
And frankly, I say this
somewhat hypocritically.
I literally have, besides those cameras,
I have a tiny little camera here
in my laptop.
I have another one over here.
I have the in my
cellphone on both sides.
So lest I put it down
the wrong way, they
can still watch me and listen to me.
>> And all this could be
happening all the time.
So what's stopping my iPhone or Android
phone from doing this all the time?
How do we know that Apple and
some creepy person at Google,
aren't listening in to
this very conversation
through the phone or conversations
I have at home or at work?
>> AUDIENCE: Because our lives
aren't that interesting.
>> DAVID MALAN: Because our
lives aren't that interesting.
That actually is a valid response.
If we're not worried
about a particular threat,
there is a sort of who
cares aspect to it.
Little old me is not going
to really be a target.
But they certainly could.
>> And so even though you see some
cheesy things on TVs and movies,
like, oh, let's turn on the grid and--
like Batman does this a lot, actually,
and actually can see Gotham, what's
going on by way of people's cellphones
or the like.
Some of that's a little futuristic,
but we're pretty much there these days.
>> Almost all of us are
walking around with GPS
transponders that is
telling Apple and Google
and everyone else that wants to
know where we are in the world.
We have a microphone.
We have a camera.
We're telling things like Snapchat and
other applications everyone we know,
all of their phone numbers,
all of their email addresses.
And so again, one of the takeaways
today, hopefully, is to at least pause
a little bit before
just blindly saying, OK
when you want the
convenience of Snapchat
knowing who all of your friends is.
But conversely, now Snapchat
knows everyone you know
and any little notes you might
have made in your contacts.
>> So this was a timely one, too.
A few months back, Snapchat
itself was not compromised.
But there had been some
third-party applications
that made it easier to save
snaps And the catch was
that that third-party service
was itself compromised,
in part because Snapchat's service
supported a feature that they probably
shouldn't have, which allowed for
this archiving by a third party.
>> And the problem was that an archive
of, like, 90,000 snaps, I think,
were ultimately compromised.
And so you might take some comfort in
things like Snapchat being ephemeral,
right?
You have seven seconds to look at
that inappropriate message or note,
and then it disappears.
But one, most of you
have probably figured out
how to take screenshots by now, which
is the most easy way to circumvent that.
But two, there's nothing stopping the
company or the person's on the internet
from intercepting that
data, potentially, as well.
>> So this was literally
just a day or two ago.
This was a nice article headline on a
website online. "Epic Fail-- Power Worm
Ransomware Accidentally Destroys
Victim's Data During Encryption."
So another ripped from the
headlines kind of thing here.
So you might have
heard of malware, which
is malicious software-- so bad software
that people with too much free time
write.
And sometimes, it just does
stupid things like delete files
or send spam or the like.
>> But sometimes, and increasingly,
it's more sophisticated, right?
You all know how to
dabble in encryption.
And Caesar and Vigenere
aren't super secure,
but there's other ones, certainly,
that are more sophisticated.
And so what this adversary did
was wrote a piece of malware
that somehow infected a
bunch of people's computers.
But he was kind of an idiot and
wrote a buggy version of this malware
such that when he or she
implemented the code-- oh, we're
getting a lot of-- sorry.
We're getting a lot of
hits on the microphone.
OK.
>> So what the problem was that
he or she wrote some bad code.
And so they generated
pseudorandomly an encryption key
with which to encrypt
someone's data maliciously,
and then accidentally threw
away the encryption key.
So the effect of this
malware was not as intended,
to ransom someone's data by
encrypting his or her hard drive
and then expecting $800 US in return
for the encryption key, at which point
the victim could
decrypt his or her data.
Rather, the bad guy simply
encrypted all the data
on their hard drive, accidentally
deleted the encryption key,
and got no money out of it.
But this also means that the victim is
truly a victim because now he or she
cannot recover any of the data unless
they actually have some old-school
backup of it.
>> So here too is sort of a reality
that you'll read about these days.
And how can you defend against this?
Well, this is a whole can
of worms, no pun intended,
about viruses and worms and the like.
And there is certainly software
with which you can defend yourself.
But better than that is
just to be smart about it.
>> In fact, I haven't-- this is one of
these do as I say, not as I do things,
perhaps-- I haven't really used
antivirus software in years
because if you generally know what to
look for, you can defend against most
everything on your own.
And actually, timely here at
Harvard-- there was a bug or an issue
last week where Harvard
is clearly, like,
monitoring lots of network traffic.
And all of you even
visiting CS50's website
might have gotten an alert saying
that you can't visit this website.
It's not secure.
But if you tried visiting
Google or other sites,
too, those, too, were insecure.
>> That's because Harvard, too, has
some kind of filtration system
that is keeping an eye out on
potentially malicious websites
to help protect us against us.
But even those things are clearly
imperfect, if not buggy, themselves.
>> So here-- if you're curious, I'll
leave these slides up online--
is the actual information
that the adversary gave.
And he or she was
asking for in bitcoin--
which is a virtual currency-- $800
US to actually decrypt your data.
Unfortunately, this
was completely foiled.
So now we'll look at
something more political.
And again, the goal here is
to start to think about how
you can make more informed decisions.
And this is something
happening currently in the UK.
And this was a wonderful tagline
from an article about this.
The UK is introducing, as
you'll see, a new surveillance
bill whereby the UK is
proposing to monitor everything
the Brits do for a period of one year.
And then the data is thrown out.
Quote, unquote, "It would
serve a tyranny well."
>> So let's take a look with
a friend of Mr. Colbert's.
And we begin with the UK,
Earth's least magic kingdom.
>> This week, debate has been raging over
there over a controversial new law.
>> -The British government is
unveiling new surveillance laws
that significantly extend its power
to monitor people's activities online.
>> -Theresa May there calls
it a license to operate.
Others have called it a
snooper's charter, haven't they?
>> -Well, hold on because-- snooper's
charter is not the right phrase.
That sounds like the
agreement an eight-year-old is
forced to sign promising to knock
before he enters his parents' bedroom.
Dexter, sign this snooper's charter or
we cannot be held responsible for what
you might see.
>> This bill could potentially write
into law a huge invasion of privacy.
>> -Under the plans, a list of websites
visited by every person in the UK
will be recorded for a year and could
be made available to police and security
services.
>> -This communications
data wouldn't reveal
the exact web page you looked at,
but it would show the site it was on.
-OK.
So it wouldn't store the
exact page, just the website.
But that is still a lot of information.
For instance, if someone
visited orbitz.com,
you'd know they were
thinking about taking a trip.
If they visited yahoo.com, you'd
know they just had a stroke
and forgot the word "google."
And if they visited vigvoovs.com,
you'd know they're horny
and their B key doesn't work.
>> And yet for all the sweeping
powers the bill contains,
British Home Secretary Theresa May
insists that critics have blown it out
of proportion.
>> -An internet connection record is a
record of the communication service
that a person has used, not a record
of every web page they have accessed.
It is simply the modern equivalent
of an itemized phone bill.
>> -Yeah, but that's not quite as
reassuring as she thinks it is.
And I'll tell you why.
First, I don't want the government
looking at my phone calls either.
And secondly, an
internet browsing history
is a little different from
an itemized phone bill.
No one frantically deletes their phone
bill every time they finish a call.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: A pattern's emerging
as to how I prepare for class.
It's just to watch TV for a week
and see what comes out, clearly.
So that, too, was just from last
night on "Last Week Tonight."
So let's begin to talk now
about some of the defenses.
Indeed, for something
like this, where the Brits
are proposing to keep a log of that kind
of data, where might it be coming from?
Well, recall from pset six,
pset seven, and pset eight now
that inside of those virtual
envelopes-- at least for HTTP--
are messages that look like this.
And so this message,
of course, is not only
addressed to a specific IP address,
which the government here or there
could certainly log.
But even inside of that envelope is
an explicit mention of the domain name
that's being visited.
And if it's not just
slash, it might actually
be a specific file name or
a specific image or movie
or, again, anything of
interest to you could
be certainly intercepted if
all of the network traffic
is somehow being proxied
through governmental servers,
as already happens in some
countries, or if there
are sort of unknown or
undisclosed agreements,
as has happened already in this
country between certain large players--
ISPs and phone companies and
the like-- and the government.
>> So funny story-- the last time I chose
badplace.com off the top of my head
as an example of a sketchy
website, I didn't actually
vet beforehand whether or not that
actually led to a badplace.com.
Thankfully, this domain
name is just parked,
and it doesn't actually
lead to a badplace.com.
So we'll continue to
use that one for now.
But I'm told that could've backfire
very poorly that particular day.
>> So let's begin to now talk
about certain defenses
and what holes there
might even be in those.
So passwords is kind of the go-to answer
for a lot of defense mechanisms, right?
Just password protect it, then
that will keep the adversaries out.
But what does that actually mean?
>> So recall from hacker
two, back if you tackled
that-- when you had to crack passwords
in a file-- or even in problem
set seven, when we give you a sample SQL
file of some usernames and passwords.
These were the usernames you
saw, and these were the hashes
that we distributed for the
hacker edition of problem set two.
And if you've been wondering all this
time what the actual passwords were,
this is what, in fact,
they decrypt to, which
you could have cracked in pset two, or
you could have playfully figured them
out in problem set seven.
All of them have some hopefully
cute meaning here or in New Haven.
>> But the takeaway is that
all of them, at least here,
are pretty short, pretty guessable.
I mean, based on the list here,
which are perhaps the easiest
to crack, to figure out by writing
software that just guesses and checks,
would you say?
AUDIENCE: Password.
DAVID MALAN: Password's
pretty good, right?
And it's just-- one, it's
a very common password.
In fact, every year there's a list of
the most common passwords in the world.
And quote, unquote "password"
is generally atop that list.
Two, it's in a dictionary.
And you know from problem
set five that it's not
that hard-- might be a
little time consuming--
but it's not that hard to load
a big dictionary into memory
and then use it to
sort of guess and check
all possible words in a dictionary.
>> What else might be pretty
easy to guess and check?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: The repetition of letters.
>> DAVID MALAN: The repetition
of symbols and letters.
So kind of sort of.
So, in fact-- and we won't go into great
detail here-- all of these were salted,
which you might recall from
problem set seven's documentation.
Some of them have different salts.
So you could actually avoid having
repetition of certain characters simply
by salting the passwords differently.
>> But things like 12345, that's
a pretty easy thing to guess.
And frankly, the problem
with all of these passwords
is that they're all just using 26
possible characters, or maybe 52
with some uppercase,
and then 10 letters.
I'm not using any funky characters.
I'm not using zeros for O's or ones
for I's or L's or-- if any of you
think you're being clever, though, by
having a zero for an O in your password
or-- OK, I saw someone smile.
So someone has an zero for
an O in his or her password.
>> You're not actually being as
clever as you might think, right?
Because if more than one of
us is doing this in the room--
and I've been guilty of this as well--
well, if everyone's kind of doing this,
what does the adversary have to do?
Just add zeros and ones
and a couple of other--
maybe fours for H's-- to his or her
arsenal and just substitute those
letters for the dictionary words.
And it's just an additional
loop or something like that.
>> So really, the best
defense for passwords
is something much, much more
random-seeming then these.
Now, of course, threats
against passwords
sometimes include emails like that.
So I literally just got this
in my inbox four days ago.
This is from Brittany, who
apparently works at harvard.edu.
And she wrote me as a
webmail user. "We just
noticed that your email
account was logged
onto another computer
in a different location,
and you are to verify
your personal identity."
>> So thematic in many emails like
this, which are examples of phishing
attacks-- P-H-I-S-H-I-N-G-- where
someone is trying to fish and get some
information out of you,
generally by an email like this.
But what are some of the telltale
signs that this is not, in fact,
a legitimate email from
Harvard University?
What's that?
>> So bad grammar, the
weird capitalization,
how some letters are
capitalized in certain places.
There's some odd indentation
in a couple of places.
What else?
What's that?
Well, that certainly
helps-- the big yellow box
that says this might be spam from
Google, which is certainly helpful.
>> So there's a lot of telltale signs here.
But the reality is these
emails must work, right?
It's pretty cheap, if not free, to send
out hundreds or thousands of emails.
And it's not just by sending
them out of your own ISP.
One of the things that
malware does tend to do--
so viruses and worms that accidentally
infect or computers because they've
been written by adversaries-- one of the
things they do is just churn out spam.
>> So what there does exist
in the world, in fact,
are things called botnets,
which is a fancy way of saying
that people with better coding
skills than the person who
wrote that buggy version of software,
have actually written software
that people like us unsuspectingly
install on our computers
and then start running behind
the scenes, unbeknownst to us.
And those malware
programs intercommunicate.
They form a network,
a botnet if you will.
And generally, the most
sophisticated of adversaries
has some kind of remote control over
thousands, if not tens of thousands,
of computers by just sending
out a message on the internet
that all of those bots, so to speak,
are able to hear or occasionally
request from some central site and then
can be controlled to send out spam.
>> And these spam things can be
just sold to the highest bidder.
If you're a company or
sort of a fringe company
that doesn't really care about the
sort of ethics of spamming your users
but you just want to
hit out a million people
and hope that 1% of
them-- which is still
a nontrivial number
of potential buyers--
you can actually pay these adversaries
in the sort of black market of sorts
to send out these spams
via their botnets for you.
>> So suffice it to say, this is not
a particularly compelling email.
But even Harvard and
Yale and the like often
make mistakes, in that
we know from a few weeks
back that you can make a
link say www.paypal.com.
And it looks like it goes there.
But, of course, it
doesn't actually do that.
>> And so Harvard and Yale and others have
certainly been guilty over the years
in sending out emails
that are legitimate,
but they contain hyperlinks in them.
And we, as humans, have been
trained by sort of the officials,
quite often, to actually just follow
links that we receive in an email.
But even that isn't the best practice.
So if you do ever get
an email like this--
and maybe it is from Paypal or
Harvard or Yale or Bank of America
or the like-- you still should not click
the link, even if it looks legitimate.
You should manually type
out that URL yourself.
And frankly, that's what
the system administrator
should be telling us to do so that
we're not tricked into doing this.
>> Now, how many of you, perhaps
by looking down at your seat,
have passwords written down somewhere?
Maybe in a drawer in your dorm room or
maybe under-- in a backpack somewhere?
Wallet?
No?
>> AUDIENCE: In a fireproof lockbox?
>> DAVID MALAN: In a fireproof lockbox?
OK.
So that's better than a
sticky note on your monitor.
So certainly, some of
you are insisting no.
But something tells me that's
not necessarily the case.
So how about an easier,
more likely question--
how many of you are using the
same password for multiple sites?
Oh, OK.
Now we're being honest.
>> All right.
So that's wonderful news, right?
Because if it means if just one of those
sites you all are using is compromised,
now the adversary has
access to more data
about you or more potential exploits.
So that's an easy one to avoid.
But how many of you have a
pretty guessable password?
Maybe not as bad as this, but something?
For some stupid site, right?
It's not high-risk,
doesn't have a credit card?
All of us.
Like, even I have passwords that
are probably just 12345, surely.
So now try logging into every website
you can think of with malan@harvard.edu
and 12345 and see if that works.
>> But we do this, too.
So why?
Why do so many of us have either pretty
easy passwords or the same passwords?
What's the real-world
rationale for this?
It's easier, right?
If I said instead,
academically, you guys
should really be choosing
pseudorandom passwords that
are at least 16 characters long and have
a combination of alphabetical letters,
numbers, and symbols,
who the hell is going
to be able to do that or
remember those passwords,
let alone for each and
every possible website?
>> So what's a viable solution?
Well, one of the
biggest takeaways today,
too, pragmatically, would
be, honestly, to start
using some kind of password manager.
Now, there are upsides and
downsides of these things, too.
These are two that we
tend to recommend in CS50.
One's called button 1Password.
One's called LastPass.
And some of you might use these already.
But it's generally a
piece of software that
does facilitate generating big
pseudorandom passwords that you
can't possibly remember as a human.
It stores those pseudorandom
passwords in its own database,
hopefully on your local hard
drive-- encrypted, better yet.
And all you, the human,
have to remember,
typically, is one master password, which
probably is going to be super long.
And maybe it's not random characters.
Maybe it's, like, a sentence or a
short paragraph that you can remember
and you can type once a day
to unlock your computer.
>> So you use an especially large
password to protect and to encrypt
all of your other passwords.
But now you're in the
habit of using software
like this to generate pseudorandom
passwords across all of the websites
you visit.
And indeed, I can
comfortably say now, in 2015,
I don't know most of
my passwords anymore.
I know my master password,
and I type that, unknowingly,
one or more times a day.
But the upside is that now, if any
of my one accounts is compromised,
there's no way someone is
going to use that account
to get into another because none of
my passwords are the same anymore.
>> And certainly, no one, even if he
or she writes adversarial software
to brute force things and
guess all possible passwords--
the odds that they are going to
choose my 24-character long passwords
is just so, so low I'm just not
worried about that threat anymore.
>> So what's the trade-off here?
That seems wonderful.
I'm so much more safe.
What's the trade-off?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Time.
DAVID MALAN: Time.
It's a lot easier to
type 12345 and I'm logged
in versus something that's 24
characters long or a short paragraph.
What else?
>> AUDIENCE: If someone breaks
your master password.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So you're kind of changing
the threat scenario.
If someone guesses or figures
out or reads the Post-it note
in your secure file vault,
the master password you have,
now everything is compromised
whereby previously it
was maybe just one account.
What else?
>> AUDIENCE: If you want to use any
of your accounts on another device
and you don't have LastPass [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID MALAN: Yeah, that's
kind of a catch, too.
With these tools, too, if
you don't have your computer
and you're in, like, some cafe or you're
at a friend's house or a computer lab
or wherever and you want
to log into Facebook,
you don't even know what
your Facebook password is.
Now sometimes, you can mitigate
this by having a solution
that we'll talk about in just a moment
called two-factor authentication
whereby Facebook will text you or
will send a special encrypted message
to your phone or some other
device that you carry around
on your keychain with
which you can log in.
But that's, perhaps, annoying if you're
in the basement of the science center
or elsewhere here at New Haven's campus.
You might not have signal.
And so that's not necessarily solution.
So it really is a trade-off.
But what I would encourage you to
do-- if you go to CS50's website,
we actually arranged for the first of
these companies for a site license,
so to speak, for all CS50 students
so you don't have to pay the $30
or so it normally costs.
For Macs and Windows, you can check out
1Password for free on CS50's website,
and we'll hook you up with that.
>> Realize, too, that some of
these tools-- including LastPass
in one of its forms-- is
cloud-based, as Colbert
says, which means your passwords
are encryptedly stored in the cloud.
The idea there is that you can go to
some random person or friend's computer
and log in to your Facebook
account or the like
because you first go to
lastpass.com, access your password,
and then type it in.
But what's the threat scenario there?
If you're storing things
in the cloud, and you're
accessing that website
on some unknown computer,
what could your friend be doing
to you or to your keystrokes?
OK.
I'll be manually advancing
slides here on out.
>> Keylogger, right?
Another type of malware
is a keylogger, which
is just a program that actually
logs everything you type.
So there, too, it's probably better to
have some secondary device like this.
>> So what is two-factor authentication?
As the name suggests, it's you have
not one but two factors with which
to authenticate to a website.
So rather than use just a password,
you have some other second factor.
Now, that generally is, one,
factor is something you know.
So something kind of in
your mind's eye, which is
your password which you've memorized.
But two, not something else
that you know or have memorized
but something you physically have.
The idea here being
your threat no longer
could be some random person
on the internet who can just
guess or figure out your password.
He or she has to have physical
access to something that you have,
which is still possible
and still, perhaps,
all the more physically threatening.
But it's at least a
different kind of threat.
It's not a million nameless people
out there trying to get at your data.
Now it's a very specific
person, perhaps,
that if that's an issue, that's
another problem altogether, as well.
>> So that generally exists
for phones or other devices.
And, in fact, Yale just rolled
this out mid-semester such
that this doesn't affect
folks in this room.
But those of you following
along in New Haven
know that if you'd log
into your yale.net ID,
in addition to typing your
user name and your password,
you're then prompted with this.
And, for instance, this is a
screenshot I took this morning
when I logged into my Yale account.
And it sends me the equivalent
of a text message to my phone.
But in reality, I downloaded an app
in advance that Yale now distributes,
and I have to now just type in the
code that they send to my phone.
>> But to be clear, the
upside of this is that now,
even if someone figures out
my Yale password, I'm safe.
That's not enough.
That's only one key, but I
need two to unlock my account.
But what's the downside,
perhaps, of Yale's system?
And we'll let Yale know.
What's the downside?
What's that?
If you don't have cell service or if you
don't have Wi-Fi access because you're
just in a basement or something, you
might not be able to get the message.
Thankfully, in this particular case,
this will use Wi-Fi or something else,
which works around it.
But a possible scenario.
What else?
You could lose your phone.
You just don't have it.
The battery dies.
I mean, there's a number
of annoying scenarios
but possible scenarios that could happen
that make you regret this decision.
And the worst possible
outcome, frankly, then
would be for users to
disable this altogether.
So there's always going
to be this tension.
And you have to find for yourself
as a user sort of a sweet spot.
And to do this, take a couple
of concrete suggestions.
If you use Google Gmail or Google Apps,
know that if you go to this URL here,
you can enable two-factor
authentication.
Google calls it 2-step verification.
And you click Setup, and
then you do exactly that.
That's a good thing to do, especially
these days because, thanks to cookies,
you're logged in almost all day long.
So you rarely have to
type your password anyway.
So you might do it once a
week, once a month, once a day,
and it's less of a big
deal than in the past.
>> Facebook, too, has this.
If you're a little too loose with typing
your Facebook password into friends'
computers, at least enable two-factor
authentication so that that friend,
even if he or she has
a keystroke logger,
they can't get into your account.
Well, why is that?
Couldn't they just log the
code I've typed in on my phone
that Facebook has sent to me?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
The well-designed software
will change those codes
that are sent to your phone
every few seconds or every time
and so that, yeah, even
if he or she figures out
what your code is, you're still
safe because it will have expired.
And this is what it looks
like on Facebook's website.
>> But there's another approach altogether.
So if those kinds of trade-offs
aren't particularly alluring,
a general principle in security would
be, well, just at least audit things.
Don't kind of put your head in the
sand and just never know if or when
you've been compromised or attacked.
At least set up some mechanism
that informs you instantly
if something anomalous has happened
so that you at least narrow
the window of time during
which someone can do damage.
>> And by this, I mean the following--
at Facebook, for instance,
you can turn on what
they call login alerts.
And right now, I've enabled email
login alerts but not notifications.
And what that means is
that if Facebook notices
I've logged into a new computer--
like I don't have a cookie,
it's a different IP address, it's
a different type of computer--
they will, in this scenario, send
me an email saying, hey, David.
Looks like you logged in from an
unfamiliar computer, just FYI.
>> And now my account might be
compromised, or my annoying friend
might have been logging into
my account now posting things
on my news feed or the like.
But at least the amount of time
with which I am ignorant of that
is super, super narrow.
And I can hopefully respond.
So all three of these, I would
say, are very good things to do.
What are some threats
that are a little harder
for us end users to protect against?
Does anyone know what
session hijacking is?
It's a more technical threat,
but very familiar now that we've
done pset six and seven and now eight.
So recall that when you send traffic
over the internet, a few things happen.
Let me go ahead and
log into c9 or CS50.io.
Give me just one moment to
log into my jHarvard account.
>> AUDIENCE: What's your password.
>> DAVID MALAN: 12345.
All right.
And in here, know that if I go
ahead and request a web page--
and in the meantime, let me do this.
Let me open up Chrome's Inspector
tab and my network traffic.
And let me go to
http://facebook.com and clear this.
Actually, you know what?
Let's go to a more familiar
one-- https://finance.cs50.net
and click Enter and log
the network traffic here.
>> So notice here, if I look
in my network traffic,
response headers-- let's go up here.
Response headers-- here.
So the very first request that I
sent, which was for the default page,
it responded with
these response headers.
And we've talked about
things like location.
Like, location means
redirect to login.php.
But one thing we didn't talk a huge
amount about was lines like this.
So this is inside of the
virtual envelope that's
sent from CS50 Finance--
the version you guys wrote,
too-- to a user's laptop
or desktop computer.
And this is setting a cookie.
But what is a cookie?
Think back to our discussion of PHP.
Yeah?
Yeah, it's a way of telling the
website that you're still logged in.
But how does that work?
Well, upon visiting finance.cs50.net,
it looks like that server
that we implemented is setting a cookie.
And that cookie is conventionally
call PHPSESSID session ID.
And you can think of it like a
virtual handstamp at a club or, like,
an amusement park, a little piece
of red ink that goes on your hand
so that the next time you visit the
gate, you simply show your hand,
and the bouncer at the door will let you
pass or not at all based on that stamp.
>> So the subsequent
requests that my browser
sends-- if I go to the next request
and you look at the request headers,
you'll notice more stuff.
But the most important is this
highlighted portion here--
not set cookie but cookie.
And if I flip through every one
of those subsequent HTTP requests,
every time I would see a hand
being extended with that exact same
PHPSESSID, which is to say
this is the mechanism--
this big pseudorandom number-- that a
server uses to maintain the illusion
of PHP's $_SESSION object, into which
you can store things like the user's ID
or what's in their shopping cart or
any number of other pieces of data.
>> So what's the implication?
Well, what if that
data is not encrypted?
And, in fact, we for best
practice encrypt pretty much
every one of CS50's websites these days.
But it's very common these
days for websites still
not to have HTTPS at
the start of the URL.
They're just HTTP, colon, slash slash.
So what's the implication there?
That simply means that
all of these headers
are inside of that virtual envelope.
And anyone who sniffs
the air or physically
intercepts that packet physically
can look inside and see
what that cookie is.
>> And so session hijacking
is simply a technique
that an adversary uses to sniff data
in the air or on some wired network,
look inside of this
envelope, and see, oh.
I see that your cookie
is 2kleu whatever.
Let me go ahead and make
a copy of your hand stamp
and now start visiting Facebook
or Gmail or whatever myself
and just present the
exact same handstamp.
And the reality is, browsers and
servers really are that naive.
If the server sees that same
cookie, its purpose in life
should be to say, oh,
that must be David,
who just logged in a little bit ago.
Let me show this same user,
presumably, David's inbox or Facebook
messages or anything else
into which your logged.
>> And the only defense against
that is to just encrypt
everything inside of the envelope.
And thankfully, a lot of sites like
Facebook and Google and the like
are doing that nowadays.
But any that don't leave you
perfectly, perfectly vulnerable.
And one of the things you can do--
and one of the nice features, frankly,
of 1Password, the software
I mentioned earlier,
is if you install it on your
Mac or PC, the software,
besides storing your
passwords, will also
warn you if you ever try
logging into a website that's
going to send your username
and password unencrypted
and in the clear, so to speak.
All right.
So session hijacking boils down to that.
But there's this other
way that HTTP headers
can be used to take advantage of us.
And this is still kind of an issue.
This is really just an adorable
excuse to put up Cookie Monster here.
But Verizon and AT&T and
others took a lot of flak
a few months back for injecting,
unbeknownst to users initially,
an extra HTTP header.
>> So those of you who have had
Verizon Wireless or AT&T cell
phones, and you've been visiting
websites via your phone,
unbeknownst to you, after your HTTP
requests leave Chrome or Safari
or whatever on your phone, go
to Verizon or AT&T's router,
they presumptuously
for some time have been
injecting a header that looks
like this-- a key-value pair where
the key is just X-UIDH
for unique identifier
header and then some big random value.
And they do this so
that they can uniquely
identify all of your web traffic to
people receiving your HTTP request.
>> Now, why would Verizon
and AT&T and the like
want to uniquely identify you to
all the websites you're visiting?
>> AUDIENCE: Better customer service.
>> DAVID MALAN: Better-- no.
It's a good thought, but it's
not for better customer service.
What else?
Advertising, right?
So they can build up an
advertising network, presumably,
whereby even if you
have turned off cookies,
even if you have special
software on your phone
that keeps you in incognito mode-- ha.
There is no incognito mode when the
man in the middle-- literally, Verizon
or AT&T-- is injecting
additional data over which
you have no control, thereby revealing
who you are to that resulting website
again and again.
>> So there are ways to opt out of this.
But here, too, is something
that frankly, the only way
to push back on this is to leave
the carrier altogether, disable it
if they even allow you to,
or, as happened in this case,
make quite a bit of fuss online such
that the companies actually respond.
This, too, is just another
adorable opportunity to show this.
>> And let's take a look at, let's
say, one or two final threats.
So we talked about CS50 Finance here.
So you'll notice that we have this cute
little icon on the login button here.
What does it mean if I
instead use this icon?
So before, after.
Before, after.
What does after mean?
It's secure.
That's what I'd like you to think.
But ironically, it is secure
because we do have HTTPS.
>> But that is how easy it is to change
something on a website, right?
You all know a bit of HTML and CSS now.
And in fact, it's pretty
easy to-- and if you
didn't do it-- to change the icon.
But this, too, is what
companies have taught us to do.
So here's a screenshot from Bank
of America's website this morning.
And notice, one, they're
reassuring me that's it's
a secure sign in at top left.
And they also have a
padlock icon on the button,
which means what to me, the end user?
>> Truly nothing, right?
What does matter is the fact
that there's the big green
URL up top with HTTPS.
But if we zoom in on this, is just
like me, knowing a little bit of HTML
and a bit of CSS, and saying,
hey, my website's secure.
Like, anyone can put a padlock and the
word secure sign-on onto their website.
And it truly means nothing.
What does mean something
is something like this,
where you do see https:// the fact that
Bank of America corporation has this
big green bar, whereas CS50 does not,
just means they paid several hundred
dollars more to have additional
verification done of their domain
in the US so that browsers who adhere
to this standard will also show us
a little bit more than that.
>> So we'll leave things at that,
frighten you a little more before long.
But on Wednesday,
we'll be joined by Scaz
from Yale for a look at
artificial intelligence
and what we can do with these machines.
We will see you next time.