>> DAVID J. MALAN: This is CS50 and
this is the start of week four.
And, boy, is Volkswagen in
trouble all because of software.
Let us take a look.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-Cars, the smartest characters
in the Fast and Furious movies.
This week German automaker
Volkswagen found itself
in the middle of a scandal of
potentially criminal proportions.
>> -Volkswagen is bracing for billions
in fines, possible criminal charges
for its executives, as
the company apologizes
for rigging 11 million cars to
help it beat emissions tests.
>> -Certain diesel models were
designed with sophisticated software
that used information including the
position of the steering and vehicle
speed to determine the car was
undergoing emissions testing.
Under that circumstance, the engine
would reduce toxic emissions.
But the car was rigged to bypass
that when it was being driven.
Emissions increased 10 to 40
times above acceptable EPA levels.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So let's
take a look at this
and see exactly how this
might be implemented
and how this might affect
so many cars like this.
So in my hand here are the press
release that was issued by the EPA--
the Environmental
Protection Agency which
is the US regulatory agency that
handles environmental concerns,
and then the actual
legal notice that was
send to Volkswagen just a few days ago.
>> So the EPA writes, and discloses now
publicly, a sophisticated software
algorithm on certain
Volkswagen vehicles detects
when the car is undergoing
official emissions testing
and turns full emissions
controls on only during the test.
The effectiveness of
these vehicles pollution
emissions control devices is greatly
reduced during all normal driving
situations.
This results in cars that meet the
standards in the laboratory or testing
station, but during normal operation
emit nitrogen oxides-- or NOx--
at up to 40 times the standard.
The software produced by Volkswagen
is a quote unquote, defeat device,
as defined by the Clean
Air Act in the US.
>> They go on to say that
the EPA and another agency
uncovered the defeat device
software after independent analysis
by researchers at West
Virginia University.
NOx pollution contributes to
nitrogen dioxide, ground level ozone,
and fine particulate matter.
Exposure to these
pollutants has been linked
with a wide range of
serious health effects,
including increased asthma
attacks and other respiratory
illnesses that can be serious enough
to send people to the hospital.
Exposure to ozone and
particulate matter has also
been associated with premature
death due to respiratory related
or cardiovascular related effects.
Children, the elderly, people with
preexisting respiratory disease
are particularly at risk for
health effects of these pollutants.
>> Suffice is to say, it's quite serious.
And let's go on to read
just one more excerpt
and then we'll take a look at
the underlying implications
of this in the context of a car.
Specifically, Volkswagen
manufactured and installed
software in the so-called
electronic control
module-- or ECM-- of
these vehicles that sensed
when the vehicle was being tested for
compliance with EPA emission standards.
Based on various inputs including the
position of the steering wheel, vehicle
speed, the duration of the engine's
operation, and barometric pressure,
these inputs precisely
tracked the parameters
of the federal test procedure used for
emission testing for EPA certification
purposes.
>> During EPA's emission testing,
the vehicles ECM software
ran software which produced
compliant emissions results.
At all other times, the
vehicle ECM software
ran a separate road
calibration which reduced
the effectiveness of the
overall emission control system,
specifically the selective catalytic
reduction of the Lean NOx trap--
which we'll see about in a moment.
As a result, emissions of NOx
increased by a factor of 10 to 40 times
above the EPA compliant levels
depending on the type of drive cycle.
>> So what this really means, and the
source code to the software running
on the Volkswagen's has not
yet been publicly disclosed,
is that, effectively, this
equivalent is somewhere there inside
of Volkswagen's code.
If you are being tested, and if the car
detects certain environmental factors
like the steering wheel
position or the movement
or lack thereof of the car or
any number of other factors
that are currently hypothesized
to be part of this formula,
they simply turn on
full emissions control.
In other words, they start
emitting less of the pollutants.
>> Else, in every other situation
when it's not detected as being
in the laboratory, they just don't.
And so you can simplify this into more
concrete pseudocode with something
like this.
If the wheels are turning but the
steering wheel isn't, suggestive
that the car is on some
kind of rotating cylinder
but in some kind of
warehouse being tested,
then behave as the
EPA would like you to.
Otherwise do not.
So let's take a look
at a short video that
takes a look at what the implications
are of this actually mechanically.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -Last Friday the EPA announced that some
Volkswagen Audi cars made between 2009
and this year were using
a so-called defeat device
to get around emissions laws
designed to keep the air clean.
But what does that mean exactly?
>> Well, modern cars have dozens
of computers inside them.
And some of those computers
help coordinate the functions
of the engine for optimum
performance while making sure
that there isn't too much garbage
coming out of the exhaust pipe.
They've actually been working
this way for several decades now.
Basically, every part
of a modern car's engine
has a sensor or controller
on it, and these computers
are reading in data thousands of
times per second making adjustments
like the ratio of fuel to air
that's going into the cylinders.
>> These cheating Volkswagen
and Audi models are diesels,
and diesels have one more
really important computer
controlled parameters, which is
the amount of unburned fuel going
into the exhaust.
Now that sounds bad.
Doesn't sound like you would want
unburned fuel going into the exhaust.
But in the case of a
diesel, you have something
called a NOx trap which is a device that
absorbs and traps for nitrogen oxides
that are pollutants that would
otherwise go into the atmosphere.
And the effect of that NOx trap
is enhanced with unburned fuel.
So a defeat device is a special program
inside these computers that can make it
look like the car meets emission
standards even when it doesn't.
Volkswagen had a problem on its hands.
Its diesel engines were known
for getting great fuel economy,
but the NOx trap only works well
when more fuel is being used.
So the car would detect,
using this defeat device,
when it was getting an emissions
test, it would use more fuel,
make the NOx trap work well,
emissions would be fine.
But then you get on the road, the device
turns off, you're burning less fuel
but you're putting as much as 40 times
more pollutants into the atmosphere.
But how the heck did
the car know that it was
being tested for emissions compliance?
The EPA says it was a sophisticated
system that checked things
like steering wheel position,
speed, how long the engine was on,
and even the atmospheric pressure.
In other words, there was
no way this was accidental
because the software was
designed very carefully to detect
an official emissions test.
That's some pretty serious
deception and that's
why Volkswagen is in
such serious trouble.
In fact, their CEO, Martin
Winterkorn, just stepped down.
>> So what happens next?
Well, if you're one of the half million
diesel Jettas, Beatles, Golfs, Passats,
or Audi A3s effected,
the good news is is
that your car is still safe to drive.
You don't have to put it away
until Volkswagen issues a recall.
But at some point they're
probably going to have
to update the software inside your car.
When that happens you might
get fewer miles per tank.
Lawyers are already gearing
up for class action lawsuits
so owners might get compensated
at some point in the future.
But that's not going to
happen any time soon.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: So this actually raises
an interesting bigger picture question
as to trust.
Right?
All of us have iPhones or Androids or
something in our pockets most likely
these days, or laptops
on our laps that are
running software made
by Apple and Microsoft
and bunches of other companies.
But how do we know that what
these software products are doing
is actually what these
companies say they are doing?
>> For instance, who's to
say that every time you
make a phone call on your iPhone
or Android phone or the like,
that that phone number also isn't
being uploaded to some company's server
because of some program you've
written, whether it's the operating
system itself like iOS or Android,
or because you've downloaded
some third party app
that somehow is listening
to everything you're typing in or
everything you're actually saying.
How do you know that, when
you guys are running Clang
or Make to compile your
own software in CS50, how
do you that CS50's own staff,
by way of the CS50 library,
hasn't been logging every
string you've ever gotten
or every inch you've ever gotten?
Well, you could certainly look
at the source code for something
like the CS50 library, you
could look at the source code
for Linux operating system
running on CS50 IDE.
But an amazing presentation
was given back in 1984
in receipt of the Turing Award by a
very famous computer scientist known
as-- named Ken Thompson who
received the Turing Award which
is sort of computer science's
Nobel Prize, if you will,
for his work on an
operating system called
Unix, which is very similar in
spirit to what we use which is Linux.
And the question he asked in his
acceptance speech, essentially
laying down the framework for
years and years of discussion
about trust and security, was this.
To what extent should one trust a
statement that a program-- a piece
of software-- is free of Trojan horses?
Perhaps it is more important to trust
the people who wrote the software.
>> And in fact, we've linked
to the talk that he
gave when accepting this award
in the '80s on CS50's website
under the Lectures page for today.
Because what you'll see
is that he actually gives
a fairly simple example of how even
a compiler like Clang or whatever
compilers others have used in past,
what if embedded in the compiler we
ourselves are using is a little if
condition that essentially says,
if you notice that this code is using
the GetString function or the GetInt
function, go ahead and insert
a back door or a Trojan horse
such that that program
now has some zeros
and ones that do something malicious.
Logging all of your
keystrokes, uploading that data
to some server, or really anything.
>> And what Ken Thompson
goes on to do in his talk
is to demonstrate that even if
you have access to the source
code of a compiler that
maliciously might be doing this,
it doesn't matter because
there's this chicken and the egg
reality of the past many
years whereby compilers
are used to compile themselves.
In other words, way back when someone
had to have written the first compiler.
And thereafter, any time they've updated
a compiler by changing its source code,
adding features and recompiling it
for people like us to use, well,
they're using the old
version of the compiler
to compile the new
version of the compiler.
And if you take a look
at the talk that he gave,
you'll see that because
of that circularity,
you can actually have bugs or
Trojan horses embedded in software
we're using.
And even if you look at the
source code for those programs,
it might not even be evident
because the trickery is actually
in some older version of a
compiler that ever since has been
injecting the threat into our software.
>> Which is only to say, we
really can't and should not
trust software running on our laptops
or phones or any number of places.
And in fact, later in this semester when
we start talking about web programming
and actually start building
web applications ourselves,
we'll talk about these
threats and others.
Now, you might have wondered and noticed
that there was a tiny little Darth
Vader in the clips that
The Verge was showing there
about Volkswagen. If
you've never seen, I
thought we should lighten
the mood because this is all
very depressing and frightening.
I'm going to look back
at Super Bowl 2011
when a commercial by
Volkswagen-- and this
almost makes them likable again--
aired for the first time on TV.
It's the 60 second clip
that I think you'll enjoy.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC - THEME FROM "STAR WARS"]
[DOG BARKS]
[CAR STARTS]
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
I was just checking.
That car is on the list of violations.
All right.
So we look at some
pseudocode a moment ago.
And here's a bigger
snippet of pseudocode code
that we've seen a few times thus far.
And let's use this is an opportunity
now to introduce a new programming
technique that we did
see algorithmically
last week when we looked at merge sort.
But let's formalize it and see how
we might use it in actual code,
and then we're going to use this
technique down the road most
likely to solve certain other problems.
>> So this was one of the first programs we
ever wrote, albeit in pseudocode code.
And what this program
allowed us to do course
was to find Mike Smith in a phone book.
And notice in particular lines eight
and 11 which had this Go To statement.
And in fact, certain
languages, C among them,
actually do have a
statement that is literally
go to that allows you to
jump to a specific line.
It's generally frowned upon because
it can be very easily abused
and you can start jumping your
program all over the place as opposed
to using the kind of
logic and the control flow
that we've used thus far with just
loops and conditions and the like.
>> But we can simplify this algorithm
in pseudocode code as follows.
Instead of this iterative
or looping approach
where we keep going back and
back and back to line three,
why don't we just kind of punt and more
generally say in line seven and 10,
just replace those two
pairs of lines with,
else if Smith is earlier
in the book we'll
search for Mike in the
left half of the book.
Else if Smith is later in the
book, search for Mike in the right
half the book.
And notice already the circularity.
Right?
I'm searching for Mike in
the phone book and then
I eventually hit maybe
line seven or maybe line 10
and my instruction to myself is search
for Mike in half of the phone book.
Well, how do I search for Mike?
I'm in the middle of
searching for Mike, why
are you sort of sending me in a circle?
But that's OK because what is
happening to the size of the problem,
as written in line 7 and 10?
We're not just saying search
for Mike, search for Mike.
We're specifically saying what?
Search for him in the left half of
the right half which is effectively
half the size of the problem.
So it's OK that we're kind of
engaging in this circularity,
this circular argument,
because at least we're
making the problem smaller and smaller.
And eventually we're going to reach
that so-called base case where
we have just one page left--
as our volunteer last week
did-- we had one page
left and then we don't
have to keep searching for Mike Smith
because he's either on that page
or he is not.
>> So how can we implement this idea, this
sort of circularity in actual code?
Well, we can leverage a technique
that's generally known as recursion.
And we've seen this in the
pseudocode for merge sort last week.
Recall that this was the
pseudocode for merge sort.
It's arguably even simpler than
bubble or selection or insertion sort
just in terms of the simplicity
with which you can express it.
>> But that's because
we're sort of circularly
saying, search for something
by searching for it again.
But we're searching either on
the left half or the right half
and then eventually we're
merging in this case.
But here, too, with
those two sort lines,
did we again have this
idea of recursion.
And concretely what this means,
in the context of an algorithm,
is that a algorithm is recursive
if it uses or calls itself.
>> Or in terms of C, a function is
recursive-- a function called
foo is recursive if foo,
somewhere in its source code,
calls the function foo itself.
And that's bad if all foo ever does
is call itself again and again.
It's OK if foo eventually stops, as does
merge sort, by saying, wait a minute,
if this problem is super
small, for instance,
or I found him whom I'm
looking for, just return.
Don't recursively, don't
cyclically call myself again.
>> And so let's take a look at
how this might actually work.
So I'm going to go ahead and open
up two source code examples here.
One of which is called sigma 0.
And this is not at all
recursive, but let's take
a look at what this program does.
I've stripped out all
comments from it but all
of the source code on CS50's
website has comments if you
want to read through it again later.
And let's do a couple
of sanity checks here.
>> So at the top of this code,
we have include CS50.h.
What does this do?
Why is it here?
In reasonable layman's terms.
What does it do?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: So that GetInt function works.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So that
the GetInt function works.
Because inside of this
file, CS50.h, which
we'll see before long in
terms of its source code,
has a bunch of functions
declared-- GetInt, GetString,
and a bunch of others-- and unless
we actually have that Include line,
the compiler Clang is not
going to know that it exists.
And same goes for line
two where int is defined
printf, which is a function
we keep using quite a bit.
Now, line four seems a little funky
because it's just a one liner.
It's got a semicolon, no curly
braces, no code inside of it.
But what did we call
this thing in weeks past?
Yeah.
So a prototype.
And why do we have a
prototype which seems
to be a little redundant
typically because we usually
see the function again
later in the file, right?
So why do we have-- you're just
scratching your head but I'll take it.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
function after the main.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
So that the compiler knows you
will eventually define or implement
that function after main, presumably.
So Clang and most
compilers are kind of dumb
and they'll only know
what you tell them.
And if you want to use
a function called sigma,
you better teach the compiler
that it exists in advance.
>> Now, main itself, even
though it's a bunch of lines,
is pretty familiar hopefully by now.
It's got a do while loop
whose purpose in life
here apparently is to get a
positive integer from the user.
And just keep pestering him
or her until they cooperate.
Then in line 16 I have
an interesting call.
IntAnswer.
Which on the left hand
side gives me an Int
which can store-- called Answer--
which is going to store, apparently,
the return value of sigma.
So sigma is just an
arbitrary but meaningful name
that I've given to a function
whose purpose in life
is to take one argument--
we'll call it N in this case--
and just to take the sum of that number
plus every positive number that's
smaller than it.
>> So if I pass in the number 2 to
sigma, I want to add 2 plus 1
plus 0-- not 0-- so that gives me 3.
If I pass in 3 to sigma, I want to
have 3 plus 2 plus 1, which gives me 6.
And so forth.
So it just adds up all the
numbers less than or equal to it.
>> Now, down here I'm just going
to print out the answer.
So as a quick sanity check, let's
make sigma 0-- dot slash sigma 0--
and let me type in 2.
And I indeed get 3.
Let me type in 3.
I indeed get 6.
And if anyone can do the math quickly,
if I do 50 what am I going get?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Well, no.
But 1,275 which is pretty close.
So this is the result of doing 50
plus 49 plus 48 plus 47 plus 46
all the way down to 1.
So that's all sigma does.
But let's see how we've
implemented it now.
So down here is the function itself.
And this doesn't seem to have
anything to do with recursion yet.
In fact, we're using an
old school technique.
I'm initializing a variable called sum
to zero, then I have a foreloop here,
and I'm declaring an Int called
I, setting it equal to 1--
though I could set it equal to
zero, but since I'm doing addition,
who cares if it's zero or one.
It's going to have no effect.
>> So I'm iterating so long as I is
less than or equal to m, which
is the argument that was passed in.
And then I just keep
incrementing I. And insight
of the loop all I'm doing is doing sum
plus equals I. And that's deliberate.
I don't want to do, in this
case, like sum plus plus.
I want to actually add
the current value of I
which keeps getting bigger and bigger
and bigger to the running tally.
>> And then I return sum.
And so answer gets the value sum.
And then I print it out.
So there's an opportunity here,
though, to kind of simplify
this code conceptually
and the kind of blow one's
mind in terms of the
simplicity even though it
takes a while to sort
of appreciate why this
is powerful in these small examples.
Here is sigma one-- so the
second version of this code.
Everything up top is identical so
that same story applies as before.
But now let's look at the
implementation of sigma which
I've whittled down to just these
lines-- four lines of code, really,
plus some curly braces and white space.
>> But what am I doing?
If m is less than or equal to
zero, I need to kind of handle
that super simple case.
And if you hand me zero or anything
negative which is just weird,
I'm just going to arbitrarily
but consistently return zero.
I don't want this thing to
get into some weird infinite
loop because of a negative value.
So I'm just saying, if you give me
zero or less, I'm returning zero.
>> But that's good because that's
that single page of the phone book
that's left.
I'm biting off a very specific problem
and not calling something recursively.
But in line 31, what
do I seem to be doing?
The parentheses are just keeping
things, hopefully, a little clearer.
But all I'm doing is I'm
returning m-- whatever
you hand me-- plus the
value of m-- sorry,
plus the value of sigma of m minus 1.
So what does this mean?
If you give me the number 3 as input,
the answer I want to get ultimately
is 6 because 3 plus 2 plus 1 gives me 6.
But how do I think about
how this code is running?
The first time I call sigma
and I pass in the value 3,
that's like saying on a piece
of paper, here's the value 3
and I've been passed this as sigma.
3 is obviously not less than 0 so
the IF condition doesn't apply.
The ELSE does.
So what do I do?
I want to return m, which is
3, plus sigma of m minus 1.
So let me keep track of this.
I'm going to put this
piece of paper down.
And what value, to be
clear, am I going to pass
into sigma at this point in the story?
What number?
2, right?
3 minus 1 is 2.
So I just need a little
scrap of paper here.
So now sigma is getting called again.
And I've deliberately put
this down because it's
kind of like pausing
that version of the story
because now I'm focused
on signal of m minus 1.
So m was 3, m minus 1 is 2.
So here is 2 that I've been passed.
2 is obviously not less than
0 so that case doesn't apply.
Else I return m, which is this
thing, plus sigma of what value?
So if sigma of 1-- because m is
right now 2 so 2 minus 1 is 1.
So now I have just the value 1.
I'm passing just the number
1 to the function sigma--
or myself here-- so 1 is obviously not
less than zero, still doesn't apply.
>> Else return 1 plus sigma of what?
0.
So let me just remember that.
I'll get back to that later.
Now I'm going to go ahead and jot
down the number 0 because that's
my argument or parameter.
I'm passed the number 0
and finally this process
of just repeating myself ad
nauseum does cease because what
do I immediately do once I see this 0?
I return zero.
So now you have to rewind the story.
>> If I now go backwards in time,
what was the most recent thing
I did if you were literally
rewinding a video?
I'm going to pick up the most recent
1 and that gives me 1 plus 0 is 1.
If I keep rewinding the
story, that's going to give me
2 plus this running value, which is 1.
So that's 3.
And then I'm going to keep rewinding.
When I first put down the number
3-- so 3 plus 3 gives me 6.
>> And now, if you've rewound
the video up until this point,
this was the very
first question I asked.
When passed 3, what is sigma of 3?
It's indeed 6, the sum of
all these pieces of paper.
So if that takes a little while to
wrap your mind around, that's fine.
But consider it was a little-- it
was very deliberate that I stacked
these numbers on top of each other.
It's kind of like having a
memory-- a record in time,
like a scrubber in a video,
that I can indeed rewind in.
And we're going to come back to
that metaphor in just a little bit.
>> But first, it turns out that there's
a lot of geeks and funny people,
I guess, at Google.
Would someone who's very
good at Googling mind
coming up for just a moment and
help me search for something?
Very, very low key.
Someone who's never
come up before, perhaps.
OK.
Yeah?
Come on.
Come on down.
What's your name?
>> SAM: Sam.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Sam, come on down.
This is Same.
Nice to meet you.
Hey.
Come on over.
So all I need you to do, if
you could, Sam, here's Google.
Can you search for the term recursion?
Don't spoil.
>> And now let's-- yeah.
OK Click that.
Better click that.
Ahh, get it.
No?
OK.
So let's do a couple others.
Not so much related
academically here, but have you
ever searched Google for anagram?
>> SAM: No.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Search for anagram instead of recursion.
How about askew.
You ever searched for askew?
Now, this one's a little hard to
see but hopefully everything's-- OK.
It's just you and me enjoying this.
OK.
>> So finally, this one's--
it's a little askew.
Now do a barrel roll.
Wonderful.
All right.
Big thank you to Sam.
Here you go.
Thanks.
>> So what's going on in all
of these silly examples?
So really, underneath the hood of
Google's millions of lines of code
apparently is a few silly IF
conditions that are essentially
checking if the user has
typed in this phrase,
do something that probably took
a nontrivial amount of time
to implement just to
be amusing in this way.
But that's all it boils
down to underneath the hood.
But, of course, recursion
is more of the geekier
example among those special tricks.
And surely there's others out there
as well that we perhaps haven't even
discovered just yet.
>> So take a look, or consider
now the following program,
and certainly grab any
of these on your way out.
I'm going to go ahead and
open up a program that's
going to try to swap two values.
But before we go there, let's do this.
Could we get one more
volunteer, I think?
Would you like to volunteer?
No?
Come on up.
All right.
So your name is what?
>> LAUREN: Lauren.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Lauren.
Come on up, Lauren.
So Lauren is being
challenged here as follows.
Nice to meet you.
So Lauren here has in front
of her two empty cups.
And we have some orange
juice and some milk
and we're going to go
ahead and do the following.
We're just going to fill this.
A few ounces of milk over here and let's
fill a little orange juice over here.
>> And in front of all of
these audience members,
swap the two values of these cups.
Put the orange juice in the milk cup
and the milk in the orange juice cup.
How would you do this if you were at
home and had access to other supplies?
LAUREN: Put it in another cup.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
So let's have a temporary
variable, if we will.
And go ahead now and implement
this same swapping procedure.
So, good.
We've put OJ into the temporary
variable, milk into the OJ variable,
and now the temporary variable
into the milk variable.
OK.
So very well done so far.
So it turns out-- hold that
thought for just a moment.
Here, to just geek it up a bit, this
would be the corresponding C code
that we just implemented.
We had two inputs, a and b, both of
which we'll just say for simplicity are
int's.
And notice here, if I want to swap
the values of two variables, a and b,
we indeed need a middleman, a
temporary variable, a temporary cup,
into which the pour one of the values
so that we have a placeholder for it.
But then the code is exactly
as Lauren here implemented.
>> Now, just to get a
little crazier, turns out
that you can do this without
a temporary variable.
To do this properly, though, we're going
to have to cheat with some chemistry.
We have some extra cups here.
So the closest thing that looks
like milk and water perhaps--
or milk and OJ-- is we have some
water, so we'll fill this one up
with a few ounces of clear water.
That's probably too much.
Yeah.
That's definitely too much.
Hold on one sec.
>> And now we have oil, which, as I recall
from middle school chemistry class,
hopefully it doesn't mix with water.
But it kind of sort of
looks like milk and OJ.
So now, without using
a temporary variable,
can you swap those two values?
So oils goes into the water cup,
water goes into the oil cup.
LAUREN: No other cups?
DAVID J. MALAN: No other cups.
And I've not actually
tested this before this year
so I don't know if this will
actually work chemically.
That wasn't supposed to happen.
Is it working?
All right.
So separating?
Good.
Now we got to get the
water into the other cup.
Smarter chemistry concentrators could
probably do this better than me.
>> LAUREN: The water's on the bottom.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: The water-- that was
what's key the last time we did this.
You have to do it in the right order.
Yeah.
That's-- OK.
So now we have two cups of oil.
OK.
That's OK.
But chemically if this worked than I--
>> LAUREN: This is water.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: That's mostly water.
All right.
But that's still the same cup as before.
So pour it-- try it over there.
OK.
This is a good use of class time today.
So now we-- nice.
Sort of.
All right.
So very good.
Thank you to Lauren.
Very well done.
>> So just to blow your minds,
and this is perhaps something
to play with if you like in CS50 ID,
you can, in fact, swap two variables
without using a temporary integer.
And this is the corresponding C code.
And if you recall from last
Wednesday, we introduced, if briefly,
some new operators in C. And does
anyone recall what the little carrot
symbol is, that little triangular
symbol from the keyboard represents?
What bitwise operator?
>> AUDIENCE: EXOR.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: EXOR.
Exclusive Or.
So if you want, just for fun at
home, to give a and b two arbitrary
values like any eight-- and I
would choose an eight bit value.
If you do this with 32 bits,
you'll very quickly get bored.
But just give a an eight bit
value that's whatever, one or two,
and give b a similar value.
And then using the definition
of XOR from last Wednesday,
apply that bit by bit, each of
those eight bits in each of a and b,
and then do it exactly per this code.
And it's not incorrect what
you see here on the screen.
It indeed boils down
to three XOR operations
and somehow magically a and
b will exchange positions
without losing any information.
>> So the oil and water trick is the
closest real world incarnation
I could think of to mimic that.
But it's surely easier to
use a temporary variable,
as in this case here.
And this too is an opportunity say,
too, this kind of micro optimization,
as a computer scientist
would say, while kind of fun
to brag about how you did this without
like swapping with an extra variable,
it's not all that compelling.
Because to save 32 bits, as
in the case of an actual int,
isn't all that compelling
on a system where
you might be using tens of megabytes
or even more such memory these days.
And in fact, when we get
to a later problem set
and you implement spell
checker and you'll
be challenged to do so with
this as little RAM and as little
time as possible on the
computer-- you still
have a week to implement
it-- you'll have-- you'll be
challenged to minimize those resources.
And that's really the only
occasion this semester
where you'll be encouraged to shave
off even the finest performance
costs otherwise.
>> So what-- how can we
see this in actual code?
Let me go ahead now
and open up an example
that deliberately is called
No Swap because it does not
in fact swap the variables
as you actually might expect.
So let's take a look.
Here's a program that has no CS50
library going on, just standard I/O.
Now we have a prototype
for swap up top which just
means it's got to be defined later.
And here's main.
>> I arbitrarily assigned x and y,
respectively, the values one and two
just because they're small
and easy to think about.
And then I just have a bunch of printfs
where I have a sanity check. x is 1
and y is 2 is presumably
what those printfs will say.
So no magic thus far.
>> Then I'm going to claim with
print def, swapping dot dot dot.
I'm going to call the swap
function, passing in x and y.
And let's assume for now that
swap is implemented exactly
as it was a moment ago
with a temporary variable.
And so I claim boldly, swapped.
x is now this and y is now that.
But the file, of course,
is called No Swap.
So let's actually see what happens.
If I compile no swap and then
do ./noswap , x is 1, y is 2.
Swapping swapped.
x is 1, y is 2.
So it actually seems to be flawed even
though swap-- let's scroll down now--
is implemented exactly per the
code I proposed a moment ago.
So we're not going to get fancy
with the XOR stuff for now.
This, too, should work just
like with the milk and OJ,
but it doesn't seem to be working.
>> So let's do this again.
Maybe I just wasn't running it right.
So let's run No Swap again.
Maybe I-- no.
So it's just not working.
So let's do a little sanity check.
Let me go ahead here in Swap
and just add, wait a minute,
a is %i/n and let's
plug-in the value of a.
Because I really want
to see what's going on.
And indeed, this is
a debugging technique
that you might be using in
office hours or at home already,
akin to the first half of Dan
Armendariz's video in PSET3
wherein we introduced print def as
a recommended technique, at least
for simple cases.
Let me go ahead and run make
no swap again, ./noswap.
>> Interesting.
So notice what seems to be true. x
is 1, y is 2, but a is 2 when b is 1.
So those two somehow got swapped
but x and y are not getting swapped.
So to be clear, what's happening
is, up here I have x and y
and those are variables local in the
scope of main, I'm passing in x and y
to swap.
Now, swap, as a separate function,
is free to call its arguments
or its parameters anything it wants.
Foo or bar or x or y or a or b.
Just to make clear that they're
not identical to x and y per se,
I've said a and b.
But we could call them anything we want.
>> And so it looks like
swap is being passed
x-- AKA a-- and it's
being passed y-- AKA b.
Somehow these three lines are
swapping those values exactly
as Lauren did with the milk and OJ.
But when we print out
the values, a and b
are indeed swap but x and
y have no change to them.
Recall that x and y are up here.
>> So we can see this via
another technique as well.
And this too is a technique
embedded in problem set three.
Let's go ahead and do this in
CS50 ID if you haven't already.
On the right hand side we
have this Debugger tab.
And if you open this up,
there's some arcane information
that's thrown at you initially.
But let's tease this apart real fast.
>> So one, you see local variables.
Turns out that build into CS50 IDE, and
a lot of programming environments more
generally, is a debugger.
A tool that allows you to visually see
what's going on inside of your program
without having to resort to adding
printfs and compiling and running
and adding printf's and compiling and
running, which already, in office hours
or home, is probably
getting pretty tedious.
>> So here, in just a moment, we're
going to to see in real time
the values of our local variables.
We're also going to be able to set
what are called breakpoints which
are opportunities in my program to pause
execution at a specific line of code
that I'm curious about.
Right?
These programs run in a split second.
It's kind of nice for us slower humans
to be able to pause, take a moment, see
what's going on around
a certain line of code
without the program plowing
through it and finishing entirely.
So a breakpoints going to allow us to
break and pause at a certain point.
>> Call stack is a fancy way of
saying what functions are currently
being called at the moment.
Main is always called first.
But if Main calls a
function called Swap,
we're actually going to see this
tower of functions that have been
called in reverse chronological order.
So let's see that.
>> I'm going to zoom out.
I'm going to go back to my code.
And just because I want
to be pedantic here,
I'm going to go ahead and click
just to the left of line five.
And that creates a red dot.
And notice on the right hand side
that the debugger knows, hey,
I just said a breakpoint at
noswap.c line five, specifically
at this line of code.
So the debugger knows that I
have requested that the next time
I run my program it pause
execution there rather than just
running the whole thing super fast.
>> So now I'm going to click the Debug
button at the very top of the IDE
and that's going to do the following.
It's going to open an initially somewhat
scary looking second terminal window--
remote debugging from
host such and such--
and we'll come back to what
all that means before long.
But what's important for now
is that that red dot was hit,
the debugger has deliberately
paused execution--
not on that line per se but on the first
line of actual code in that function.
And that's why line seven is
now highlighted in yellow.
>> And now let's take a look
at the right hand side.
It looks like, by default,
nicely enough, x has what value?
0.
And y has what value?
Zero.
And that's to be expected in the sense
that x and y-- that yellow line-- has
not executed yet.
So x should not have the value 1.
It might have any other value,
a so-called garbage value.
And we got lucky in that it's
zero at this point, essentially.
>> So now there's only a few
buttons we need to care
about when debugging in this way.
Notice here, we have a Play button.
And if we play or hit
resume, that's just
going to run through
the rest of the program
or until it hits another breakpoint.
But I've not set any other
breakpoints so it's just
going to run through the end.
That kind of defeats the
purpose of poking around.
>> So instead, I care about
these icons to the right.
And if I hover over
them, as you should too,
you'll see little tips-- tool tips.
This one is step over.
Now that doesn't mean skip
the following line of code.
That just means execute it and
move to the next, move to the next,
move to the next.
In other words, via
that button, can I walk
through my code one step at a time.
Line by line, literally.
Now, to the right of
that, there's another one
that we'll see in just a moment.
This is the so-called
Step Into icon that's
going to allow me dive
into another function.
But let's see this in just a moment.
So I'm going to click step over.
And now notice, as I click
this button at top right,
keep your eyes roughly under Local
Variables and see what happens to x.
x is now 1 because the
yellow line has now executed
and we've moved on to line 8.
And in just a moment y
should hopefully become 2.
>> Now, nothing that interesting
happens for a bit.
All this is is printf.
And notice, in my secondary terminal
window, I see the output of print def.
And now I have to make a
decision as the programmer.
I can step over this line of
code, executing it but not
getting curious about what's inside.
Or I can actually step into it
and go inside of Swap itself.
So let's do the latter.
>> Let me go ahead and click
not Step Over but Step Into.
Notice, all of a sudden
the window changes
to highlight the first
line of code in Swap.
That's line 21.
And now, what's kind of funky is that,
if you look over here, as expected,
a comma b is 1 and 2, respectively.
Why is temp 32,767?
Recalling that temp, much like
the empty cup a moment ago,
is declared here on line 21.
Why 32,000- I mean, why is
it just some weird value?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: It's not initialized.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It's
not been initialized.
So our computer always
has physical memory.
It always has physical RAM.
And there's always zero's
and one's in there, right?
Because we're using our
computer all day long,
you're using the CS50 IDE
or the servers all day long.
So that RAM either has some zeros or
some one's or some zeros and ones.
No matter whether or
not you're using them.
You can't just have blank
spaces where you want bits.
They're either zeros and ones.
>> So it turns out that temp, because
we've not initialized it yet,
we have those 32 bits but they've not
been initialized to any known values.
So whatever they were most
recently used for-- those 32 bits--
we're just seeing the artifacts of some
previous use of those particular 32
bits.
As soon as I click Step Over though,
phew, temp is going to get the value 1.
And if I do it again, a is
going to be given the value 2
and then b is going to
be given the value 1.
>> And so what's nice now at
this point in the story
is that the debugger is
showing me, super slowly
at my own pace, what
the state of Swap is.
But notice at the top here, notice
that the call stack actually
has two layers to it.
Now the one that's highlighted as
Swap, if I click on Main instead,
notice how the local variables change
because the developer can just hop
around and go into any different scope.
So even though we're doing all of this
work and correctly swapping a and b,
if I go back and forth between Swap
where a is 2 and b is 1 and Main,
has Main been affected at all?
No.
So what's the takeaway here?
Well, it turns out that any time
you call a function like Swap,
and you pass it arguments, what
you're passing to the Swap function
in this case is a copy
of those arguments.
So if x and y are each respectively
32 bits, what Swap is getting
is two new local
variables, or arguments,
called a and b-- but those are arbitrary
names-- but the pattern of zeros
and ones inside of a and b are
lined up to be identical to x and y
but they are not the
same thing as x and y.
>> It's as though Main has on its piece of
paper the number 1 and 2 for x and y,
and then when it hands that
piece of paper to Swap,
Swap very quickly gets
its own pen, writes down
1 and 2 on its own sheet of paper,
hands back the original xy to Main
and then does its own
thing with a and b.
And this is now super important because
this has nontrivial implications
for actually writing correct code
because it would seem we cannot swap
two variables.
>> I have written a correct Swap function.
We've implemented it with Lauren as
a correct swap function in reality,
but apparently none of that
matters if you can't actually
swap two values permanently.
So we need another way
to actually get at this,
and we need to be able to
actually solve this problem.
And it turns out-- and we'll come
back to this particular picture
before long-- this is one way that
you might draw your computer's memory.
It's just a rectangle.
You could draw it any
number of ways but it's
convenient to draw it as a
rectangle for the following reason.
>> We're going to start today and beyond
talking about the so-called stack.
And the stack is just a chunk
of RAM-- a chunk of memory--
that functions have access
to when they're called.
And so it turns out that at
the very bottom of this stack
is where all of Main's local variables
and org C and org V and all that stuff
are going to go by default. And if Main
calls some other function like Swap,
well, Swap is going to get another
layer of memory up above it.
>> And so just to give you a quick cursory
picture of this, if I go over here--
and let me mirror this on the
overhead as well-- what really I have,
if we care only about the
bottom of this picture for now,
is that when I run a program
and Main gets called,
Main is given a chunk of
RAM in my computer that is
at the bottom of this so-called stack.
And I'm going to draw it
deliberately as a square.
So it's like 32 bits or four bytes.
And if this main function has a
variable called x with a value of 1
and it has a variable called
y with the value of 2, that's
like taking this sliver of memory that
Main has been given by the operating
system and dividing it up so that
the first local variable goes here,
the second one goes here, and that's it.
>> When Main calls Swap, Swap
gets its own slice of memory
that we'll draw like this
from the operating system,
and it's going to have its
own local variables based
on our implementation earlier
with local variables a
and b that initially
get the values 1 and 2.
But then, as soon as
the Swap code executes,
and Lauren actually swaps the
OJ and milk, what's happening?
Well, this 2 is becoming a 1, this
1 is becoming a 2, and, by the way,
there is a temp variable that's being
used that whole time that eventually
goes away.
But it doesn't matter
how much work you do
in this line of-- in this memory space,
x and y are completely untouched.
>> So we need some way of giving
Swap and functions like it
secret access, if you will, to
functions like-- to memory like x and y.
So let's take a look at
an example that helps
us see exactly what's been
going on this whole time.
I'm going to go ahead
and open up Compare Zero.
And I'm going to close
our debugger, I'm going
to close this scary looking message
the just says, wait a minute,
you're in the middle debugging.
I'm going to hide this tab here
just to go back to simplicity.
So don't worry if GDB is killed.
That just means that the program has
been quit, deliberately in this case,
by me.
>> And now Compare Zero does this.
I'm using the CS50
library in standard I/O.
I've got a main function that first
says, say something, and gets a string.
Then says it again and
gets another string.
And notice that these two strings
are called s and t, respectively.
And now this program, Compare
Zero, its purpose in life,
it's supposed to tell me,
did I type the same thing?
And so I'm going back to week one.
I'm using my equal equal operator
which is the quality operator.
Not the assignment operator,
the equality operator.
I'm just comparing s and t.
>> So let's actually go ahead and do this.
And I'm going to go ahead
and make Compare Zero.
I'm going to do ./comparezero.
And I'm going to go
ahead and say something
like, let's do mom in lowercase
and how about mom in uppercase.
And of course I type different things.
All right.
That's to be expected.
>> Let's run it again.
Both times do lowercase, lowercase.
That looks super identical to me.
Enter.
OK.
Maybe it's just weird because
it's not liking my grammar.
So let's do a capital MOM,
capital MOM, identical.
Different things.
>> So why is that?
Well, what's actually going
on underneath the hood here?
So let's go back over
here for just a moment
and consider what GetString
is actually doing.
When you call GetString,
that's a function we
ourselves wrote and it somehow gets a
sequence of characters from the user.
And let's assume that the first
time I call GetString, that gives me
a chunk of memory that looks like this.
And if I typed in all lowercase
m-o-m-- and what goes after it?
Just a quick sanity check.
>> Backslash zero.
We know that.
And recall that we played
around with Zamila's name
and a bunch of other names
when Rob was here looking
at what's going on inside of memory.
So that story's exactly the same.
This is what GetString
is returning to me.
Now, my code a moment ago stored
the return value of GetString
in a variable called s.
And then the second time I called it,
it stored it in a variable called t.
>> So if I go over here, I need
to draw this local variable--
and I'm generally going to
draw a string as just-- we'll
call it s-- as a little square here.
And now, somehow-- how does mom
go inside of this variable s?
Well, we need to go back
to first principles here.
What is GetString actually returning?
>> So it turns out that M-O-M
backslash zero, and any number
of other strings in memory like
Zamila and Rob or Andy or any others,
are of course in our
computer's RAM or memory.
And your RAM has like-- you have
a gig of RAM, two gigs of RAM,
or a billion or two billion bytes,
or maybe even more these days.
So let's assume, for today's purposes,
that it doesn't matter how we number
them, but we can number each
of those billion or two billion
or four billion bytes.
>> And let's just arbitrarily say that
this is the first bite, second bite,
third, fourth.
I'm deliberately not using zero for
today but we'll come back to that.
So in other words, if this is the
very first time I'm using the program,
I'm just getting lucky and the first
bite is at location one then two
then three than four.
And if I kept drawing, box number
two billion would be way over here.
>> So what do you think, then,
GetString actually returns?
It's not returning M-O-M backslash
zero per se because that clearly
won't fit in the box that I've drawn.
So what else might GetString actually
be returning all these weeks?
The answer is on the
board here somewhere.
You can't fit M-O-M backslash zero,
so what might make sense instead?
If you had to be super clever, putting
on the so-called engineering hat,
what could you return?
What's the least amount of information
you could return that would still
let you find M-O-M in memory?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: One.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: One.
And why one?
AUDIENCE: Because it would tell
you where to go [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
I am just going to return the address
of the string that I have gotten.
The address in this
case is location one.
So what really is being stored in s--
and every string variable thus far--
has just been the
address of that string.
>> Meanwhile, if I call
GetString a second time and I
type in literally the same thing--
M-O-M with lowercase-- M-O-M
and another backslash zero,
and now maybe my program's
been running for some time so maybe this
is 10, this is location 11, this is 12,
this is 13.
The computers using some other
memory for whatever reason.
What now goes in my second
variable in my program t?
10.
Exactly.
>> And so when we look at the
source code of this program
where I'm simply trying
to compare the two values,
is s equal equal to t, what's
the obvious human answer?
Just no because 1 does not equal 10.
And so herein lies an
opportunity for us really
to just go back to, again, first
principles and think about, well,
what's going on underneath the hood?
We've been talking about
bits and bytes and memory,
but it's actually useful to understand
because when you call GetString,
even though we think of it is
returning M-O-M or string mom
or Andy or Zamila or
the like, technically
it's just returning the address
of that chunk of memory.
>> But that's OK.
Because how do I know
where the string ends?
If I'm only given the beginning?
Well, the backslash zero, right?
Just in linear time I can
print out with print def M-O-M.
And as soon as I see backslash
zero, I don't care where I started,
I already know implicitly
where I need to end.
>> And so today marks the beginning-- and
let me do this dramatically because we
went through a lot of trouble to
get these here training wheels--
so today the training wheels start
to come off and we reveal at least--
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> That was well worth the trip
to Target this morning, yes?
So now-- there is, it turns
out, no such thing as string.
String does not exist.
It's a synonym that we've had
inside of the CS50 library.
Henceforth, we're going to start calling
s and t not strings but char stars.
And the char star we'll
tease apart before long.
But this is to say,
that even if we continue
using GetString for now,
technically I should
be saying char star and char star.
>> And it turns out what that star
is going to denote is something
called a pointer or an address.
And in fact, a teaser
for what lies ahead
is this 20 second clip from our
friend Nick Parlante at Stanford
who, quite some time ago, spend
a ridiculous amount of time,
as best I can tell in his
kitchen or his basement,
making claymation
introducing to the world
a character named
Binky with whom we will
be introduced next time to pointers.
So here is a preview of what's to come.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -Hey, Binky.
Wake up.
It's time for pointer fun.
>> -What's that?
Learn about pointers?
Oh, goody.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: And on that note,
we will see you on Wednesday.
All right.
Who's dancing?
Come on.
You want me to get it started?
I'll get it started.
Woooo!
>> LAUREN: Sweet fancy Moses.