[MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50.
And this is the start of week 5.
And as you may have noticed,
some of the material
is getting a little more
complex, the little denser.
>> And it's very easy, especially if
you've been in the habit for some time,
to be trying to scribble down most
anything we do, we're saying in class.
But realize, that is not perhaps
the ideal pedagogical approach
to learning this kind of material,
and material more generally.
And so we are pleased to
announce that CS50's own Gheng
Gong has begun to prepare
a canonical set of notes
for the course, the hope of
which is that, one, these
not only serve as a
reference and a resource
for reviewing material and going
back through material that might have
escaped you the first time around, but
also so that your heads can be more
up than down, when it
comes time to lecture,
so that you might engage
more thoughtfully, as
opposed to more scribbly.
>> With that said, what you'll find on
the website is such documents as this.
And notice, at top left, there's
not only a table of contents,
but also time codes that
will immediately jump you
to the appropriate part
in the video online.
And what Chang here has done
is, essentially, documented
what happened in this
particular lecture.
And many of the lectures are
already online now with this URL.
And we'll continue to post the remainder
of those by the end of this week,
so do take advantage of that resource.
>> So without further ado,
we started to peel back
the layer that has been
string for some time.
And what did we say a string
actually is last week?
So char star.
And char star, well, what
did that really mean?
Well, all this time, if we've
been calling a function,
like getString, and storing
the so-called return
value of getString in a
variable-- it's called
s type string-- we've been writing
the line of code up there above.
And it's only when I see my
handwriting magnified here
do I realize just how atrocious this is.
>> However, let's assume that,
on the right-hand side
is, nonetheless, a reasonable
depiction of what's
been going on all this
time with getString.
getString, of course, gets a string.
But what does that really mean?
It means it gets a chunk of
memory from the operating system
by calling a function, called malloc.
But more on that later.
And then it populates
that chunk of memory
with the letters the user has
typed in, followed by, of course,
a null character, or backslash
zero at the very end.
>> Meanwhile, on the left-hand side
of this story, all this time,
we've been declaring a variable, like s.
And that variable is what now
will start calling a pointer.
It's not a box inside of which
we put the string, Daven, per se,
but rather we put in that square
box on the left what exactly?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: The address of
where it's located in memory.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
The address of where Daven
is located in memory.
And not where all of Daven is located,
per se, but specifically the address
of what?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: First character.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: The first character
in Daven, which, in this case,
I proposed was arbitrarily
and unrealistically 1, Ox1,
which just means the
hexadecimal number of 1.
But it's probably going
to be a much bigger number
that we might draw
with a 0x as a prefix,
representing a hexadecimal character.
And because we don't need to know where
the rest of the characters of Daven
are, because of what simple design
decision that was made many years ago?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Backslash 0.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
The backslash 0 allows you, albeit in
linear time, to traverse the string,
walk from left to right,
with a for loop, or a while
loop, or something like
that, and determine, oh, here
is the end of this particular string.
So with just the address at
the beginning of a string,
we can access the entirety of
it, because all this while,
a string has just been a char star.
>> So it's certainly fine to continue using
the CS50 library and this abstraction,
so to speak, but we'll
begin to see exactly
what's been going on
underneath this whole time.
So you may recall this example,
too, from last time, compare 0,
which didn't actually compare.
But we began to solve this.
>> But as perhaps a refresher,
might I interest someone
in a pink elephant today,
also made by Chang?
How about you in front? [INAUDIBLE].
Come on up.
>> And in the meantime,
as you come up, let's
consider for just a moment what
this code was actually doing.
It's declaring two variables up
top, s and t, and calling getString.
This isn't a very user-friendly program,
because it doesn't tell you what to do.
But let's just assume we're
focusing on the juicy part.
And then we do, if s equals
equals t, it should say printf,
you typed the same thing.
Hello.
What's your name?
>> JANELLE: Janelle.
DAVID J. MALAN: Janelle,
nice to meet you.
So your challenge at
hand for this elephant
is to first draw us a picture of what's
being represented in those first two
lines.
So s and t might be
represented how on the screen?
And you can just draw it with
your finger on this big screen.
>> So there's two halves to
each side of that equation.
So there's s on the left, and
then getString on the right.
And then there's t on the left,
and then getString on the right.
So how might we begin
drawing a picture that
represents what's going on
here in memory, would you say?
And let me let you explain
what you're doing as you go.
>> JANELLE: OK.
Well, first, it would be asking
you to get the input string.
And it would store-- oh, sorry.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Good.
And this is called what?
Oh, OK.
Keep going.
I didn't mean to interrupt.
JANELLE: Sorry.
So it would input it into
the address of-- not sure.
I can't exactly remember the number,
but I believe it was starting with 0.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: That's all right,
because I made the numbers up,
so there's no right answer.
>> JANELLE: Starting with the 0 arc.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so element 0.
Sure.
>> JANELLE: And then if was
like just a two-letter--
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK, back to you.
>> JANELLE: So element 0, and
then element 1 or element 2.
DAVID J. MALAN: And which piece of
the picture are you drawing right now?
The call to getString?
Or the declaration of s?
>> JANELLE: The declaration
of s, I believe.
Oh, the getString, because it would
be inputted into each [? area. ?]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
Exactly.
Even though this effectively
returns an array, recall,
when we get back a string, we can
index into that string using 01 and 2.
Technically, these are probably
represented by individual addresses,
but that's fine.
>> So suppose, if I can just fast
forward to where we left off
last time, if one of
the strings was g a b e,
backslash 0, thereby representing gabe's
input, how might we represent s now?
If this is the memory that's
been returned by getString?
>> JANELLE: Would it be
represented by an arc?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: By an arc?
Well, no.
Let's just say, pictorially,
let me just go ahead
and propose that, if this is s, this
is the return value of getString.
And you've drawn this as 0, 1, 2, which
is perfectly reasonable, because we
can index into the string, as such.
But just to be consistent with
last time, let me go ahead
and arbitrarily propose that this
is address 1, this is address 2,
this is address 3, and so forth.
And so, just to be super
clear, what's going
to go in s as a result of that
first line of code, would you say?
>> JANELLE: Address 1?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
So address 0x1.
And meanwhile, let me go ahead and
duplicate much of what you've done
and add my own t here.
If I were to type in gabe
again, a second time,
when prompted with getString, where,
of course, is gabe going to go?
Well, presumably--
>> JANELLE: Like on here?
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
JANELLE: Or it's also in the same boxes?
DAVID J. MALAN: Let me propose, yeah,
exactly, so in these additional boxes.
But what's key now is that, even
though I've drawn these pretty close
together-- 0x1, this
is 0x2-- in reality,
this now might be address 0x10,
for instance, and 0x11, and 0x12,
and so forth.
And so, if that's the case,
what's going to end up here in t?
>> JANELLE: 0x10?
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
So 0x10.
And so now, final question.
You have, by far, had to work the
hardest for an elephant thus far.
By now, if I pull up the code
again, when I do, in line three,
if s equals equals t, what am I actually
comparing that we've drawn here?
>> JANELLE: The two addresses?
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
So I'm saying is s equal equal to t?
In other words, is 1 equal equal to 10?
And of course, the
obvious answer now is, no.
And so this program is ultimately
going to print what, would you say?
>> JANELLE: Would it be,
you typed the same thing?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So if
s is 1 and t is 10?
>> JANELLE: You typed different things.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
You typed different things.
All right.
So a round of applause,
if we could, here.
[APPLAUSE]
That was painful.
I know.
Nicely done.
So now let's see if we can't
tease apart what the fix was.
And of course, when we fixed this--
which I'll now represent in green--
we did a couple of enhancements here.
First, just as a sanity
check, I'm first checking
if s equals null and t equals null.
And just to be clear, when might
s or t be null in code like this?
When might s or t be null.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
If the string that the user
typed in is way too long
to fit into memory, or some
weird corner case like that,
getString, as we'll see, literally
today, in its documentation,
says it will return null as
a special sentinel value,
or just sort of a special symbol
that means something went wrong.
So we want to check for
that, because it turns out
that null is a very dangerous value.
>> Often, if you try to do something with
null involving a function-- passing it
as input, for instance-- that function
might very will crash and, with it,
take down your whole program.
So this third line now is just a sanity
check, error checking, if you will.
That's a good habit now for
us to get into any time we
try to use a value that
could, potentially, be null.
>> Now, in the fourth line here,
"if strcmp(s, t)," well,
what's that referring to?
Well, we said this was a very succinctly
named function for string comparison.
And its purpose in life is to compare
its first argument against it second,
but not in terms of their addresses,
as we did unintentionally a moment
ago with the red code, but
rather to compare those two
strings in the humanly intuitive
way by comparing this, against this,
against this, against this, and
then stopping if and when one
or both of my fingers
hits a backslash 0.
So someone years ago implemented strcmp
to implement for us the functionality
that we hoped we would have gotten
by just comparing two simple values.
>> Now frankly, I keep drawing
all of these various numbers.
But the reality is, I've been
making these up the whole time.
And so let me just go ahead
and scribble these out
to make a point that, at the end
of the day and moving forward,
we're not really going to care about
what addresses things are actually
in memory.
So I'm not going to draw these
kinds of numbers so much anymore,
I'm just an abstract this away a
little more friendly with just arrows.
>> In other words, if s is a pointer,
well, let's just draw it, literally,
as a pointer, an arrow pointing
from itself to something else,
and not worry too much more about
the minutia of these addresses
which, again, I made up anyway.
But we'll see those addresses,
sometimes, when debugging code.
>> Now meanwhile, this program
up here fixes, of course,
that problem by comparing
those two strings.
But we ran into another problem.
This was from the copy
program last time,
whereby, I was trying to capitalize
just the first character in a string.
But what was the symptom
we saw last time when
a user typed in a value, like
gabe in lowercase, for s,
then we assigned s into t,
as in the third line there,
and then I tried to
capitalize t bracket 0?
What was the effect of
changing t bracket 0 here?
>> AUDIENCE: It changed s.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
I changed s, as well.
Because what was really going on?
Well, let me see if I can clean
up this picture, as follows.
>> If s is, again, the word g,
a, b, e, backslash, 0, and s
we'll continue drawing as a box
here, but no more addresses.
Let's stop making things up.
Let's just draw a picture
to simplify the world.
>> When I declare t with string t,
that creates that chunk of memory.
Square happens to be 32
bits in most computers.
In fact, if you've ever heard of a
computer having a 32-bit architecture,
really fancy-speak, that just
means it uses 32-bit addresses.
And as a technical aside,
if you've ever wondered
why older computers, if you actually
tried to soup them up with lots of RAM,
could only have a maximum
of four gigabytes of RAM,
well that's because, literally,
your old computer could only
count as high as 4
billion, 4 billion bytes,
because it was using 32-bit
numbers for addresses.
>> But in any case, in this
example, story's much simpler.
t is just another pointer, or
really a char star, aka string.
And how do I want to update this picture
now with that second line of code,
after the dot, dot, dot?
When I do string t equals s semicolon,
how does this picture change?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
Exactly.
I just put an arrow from the
t box to the same address,
the same first letter in gave.
Or technically, if this
guy were still at 0x1,
it's as though I had
0x1 here and 0x1 here.
But again, who cares
about the addresses?
It's just the idea that now matters.
So this is what's happening here.
So of course, if you do t bracket
0, which is array notation,
of course-- and frankly, it looks
like there's an array over here,
but now there's this weird thing.
Know that the programming language,
C, offers you this feature,
whereby, even if t is a
pointer, or s is a pointer,
you can still use that familiar,
comfortable square bracket
notation to go to the first element,
or the second element, or any element
that that pointer is pointing
to because, presumably, it
is, as in this case,
pointing at some array.
>> So how do we fix this?
Frankly, this is where it got a
little overwhelming at first glance.
But here is a new and improved version.
>> So first, I'm getting
rid of the CS50 library,
just to expose that s is indeed
a char star, just a synonym.
And t is also a char star.
But what is going on on the
right-hand side of that line
where t is assigned a value?
>> What is malloc?
What it's strlen?
What is sizeof(char)?
Why the heck does this
line look so complex?
What's it doing at a high level?
What's it storing in t?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It's allocating a
certain amount of memory space.
It's to store, I guess,
letters [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
Perfect.
It's allocating a certain
amount of memory space
to store, presumably, future letters.
And in particular, malloc
is therefore returning what?
>> AUDIENCE: Returning the [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
Returning the address of that memory,
which is a fancy way of saying,
returns the address of the
first byte of that memory.
The onus is on me to remember
how much memory I actually
allocated or asked malloc for.
>> Now how much is that?
Well, even though there's
a lot of parentheses here,
malloc takes just a single argument.
And I'm specifying strlen of s, so give
me as many bytes as there are in s,
but add one.
Why?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: The backslash 0.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
We've got to do a little housekeeping.
So because there's a backslash
0, we'd better remember that.
Otherwise, we're going
to create a string that
doesn't have that special terminator.
>> Meanwhile, just to be super
anal, I have sizeof(char),
just in case someone runs my
code not on the CS50 appliance,
but maybe a different computer
altogether where chars
are one byte, by convention, but two
bytes, or something bigger than that.
It's just to be super,
super averse to errors.
Even though, in reality, it's
most likely going to be a 1.
>> Now, meanwhile, I go ahead and copy the
string, t bracket i equals t bracket s.
And I will defer to last week's
source code to see what's going on.
But the key takeaway, and the
reason I put the code now in green,
is because that very last line,
t bracket 0 equals toupper,
has the effect of
capitalizing which string?
t and/or s?
That last line of code.
>> Just t, because what's
happened this time,
if I slightly undo that last step,
what's happened is, when I call malloc,
I essentially get a chunk of memory
that is the same size as the original,
because that's the arithmetic I did.
I'm storing in t the address
of that chunk of memory.
Even though this looks nice
and pretty, nice and blank,
the reality is there's, what we'll
keep calling, garbage values in here.
That chunk of memory might very
well have been used before,
a few seconds, a few minutes ago.
So there could absolutely be numbers
or letters there, just by accident.
But they're not valid, until I
myself populate this chunk of memory
with actual chars, as I
do in that for loop there.
All right?
>> So now, the climax of
these three examples
that were seemingly broken last time,
this Swap example, this function
worked in the sense
that it swapped a and b.
But it didn't work in what other sense?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
If I were to call this function
from another-- for instance,
from a function like main, where
I have a variable, x and y, as I
did last week, same code,
and I pass in x and y
to Swap, and then call Swap-- this,
of course, is the correct version
is what we're about to
see-- it did not work.
So what is the fix?
>> Well, so just to be
clear, let me go ahead
and-- give me one second here, and see
if I can show you the last one, which
will be in-- let's see if I can find
this real fast-- OK, [INAUDIBLE].
OK, there it is.
So ignore the commands I'm just typing.
I want it to retrieve at
the last minute an example
from last time, which
is now called no Swap.
>> So no Swap is where
we left off last time,
whereby, I initialized
x to 1 and y to 2.
I then call Swap, passing in 1 and 2.
And then this function
worked in some sense,
but it had no permanent
effect on x and y.
So the question at hand is, how now
do we actually fix this problem?
What is the solution at hand?
>> Well, in swap.c, which is new today,
notice a couple of differences.
x and y are the same.
But what is clearly
different about line 25?
What's new there, if you remember
what it looked like a second ago?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So the ampersands are a new piece
of syntax not only in this program,
but also more generally in CS50.
To date, I don't think
we've seen any examples
or really talked about them in any
detail, other than, maybe, preemptively
in section, an ampersand like this.
Well, it turns out ampersand is one
of the last pieces of new syntax
we're going to learn.
All it means is the
address of some variable.
At what address does x live?
But what address does y live?
Because if the
fundamental problem before
was that x and y were being passed
as copies, what we really want to do
is provide Swap with like a treasure
map that leads to where x and y actually
are in RAM, so that
Swap can follow that map
and go to wherever x or y marks the spot
and change the actual values 1 and 2
there.
>> So Swap needs to change slightly too.
And at first glance, this might
seem a little similar to char star.
And indeed it is.
So a is a pointer to what type of data,
based on this highlighted portion?
So it's an int.
>> So a is no longer an int,
it's the address of an int.
And similarly, b is now going
to be the address of an int.
So when I now call Swap from Main,
I'm not going to give Swap 1 and 2.
I'm going to give it like
Ox-something and Ox-something,
two addresses that will lead
Swap to their actual locations
in my computer's memory.
>> So now, my remaining implementation
needs to change a tad.
What's obviously different now
in these three lines of code?
There's these damn stars all
over the place, all right?
So what's going on here?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: It's obviously [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
So in this context-- and this was not
the best design decision, admittedly,
years ago.
In this context, where
you just have a star,
and you don't have a data type,
like int, immediately to the left,
instead you have an equal sign, clearly,
in this context, when you say star a,
that means go to the
address that's in a.
Follow the treasure map, so to speak.
>> And meanwhile, in line 37,
it means the same thing.
Go to the address a, and put what there?
Whatever is at the
location that b specifies.
In other words, go to b.
Get that value.
Go to a and, per the equal
sign, the assignment operator,
put that value there.
>> Similarly, int temp is just an int.
Nothing needs to change about temp.
It's just a spare glass from Annenberg
for some milk or orange juice.
But I do need to say, go to b.
Go to that destination and
put the value in temp there.
So what's happening then?
When I actually call Swap this time, if
this first tray here represents Main,
this second tray represents Swap, when
I pass ampersand x and ampersand y
from Main to Swap, just to be clear,
what is this stack frame receiving?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
The address of x and the address of y.
And you can think of these
like postal addresses.
33 Oxford Street and 35
Oxford Street, and you
want to move the two buildings
that are at those locations.
>> It's sort of a ridiculous idea,
but that's all we mean by address.
Where in the world can
you find those two ints?
Where in the world can you
find those two buildings?
So if finally, after all this time I
go into today's source code and compile
Swap and run ./swap, finally, for the
first time do we actually see that
my values have indeed
been swapped successfully.
And now, we can even take
note of this in, say, gdb.
>> So let me go into the same file.
Let me go ahead and run gdb of ./swap.
And now, in Swap, I'm going to go
ahead and set a break point in Main.
And now I'm going to go
ahead and run the program.
And now we see my code
paused at that line.
>> If I go ahead and print
x, what should I see here?
It's a question.
Say again?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So
random numbers, maybe.
Maybe I get lucky, and it's
nice and simple, like 0.
But maybe it's some random number.
In this case, I got lucky.
It just happens to be 0.
But it is indeed luck,
because not until I
type next and then print x has that
line of code, line 19, been executed.
>> Meanwhile, if I type next again, and
now print out y, I'm going to see 2.
Now, if I type next, it's going to
get a little confusing, because now,
the printf is going to appear on
the screen, as it did. x is 1.
>> Let's do this again.
And now, here's where
things get interesting.
Before I call Swap or even step
into it, let's take a little peek.
x is, again, 1.
Y is, of course, quick sanity
check, 2, so not hard there.
But what is ampersand x?
Answer, it's kind of funky looking.
But the int star in parentheses is just
gdp's way of saying this is an address.
It's not an int, it's a pointer to an
int, or otherwise known as an address.
>> What is this crazy thing?
We've never seen something
quite like that before.
So this is the address in my computer's
memory of where x happens to live.
It's Ox-something.
And this is, frankly, why
I've started drawing arrows,
instead of numbers,
because who really cares
that your int is at a particular
address that's that big.
But bffff0c4, these are all
indeed hexadecimal digits,
which are 0 through f.
>> So we're not going to dwell too
long on what those things are.
But if I print out y,
of course, I see 2.
But ampersand y, I see this address.
And notice, for the curious,
how far apart are x and y?
You can ignore most of the address.
Four bytes.
And that's consistent with our
earlier claim that how big is an int?
Four bytes.
So it looks like everything's lining up
nicely, as you might hope, in memory.
>> So now, let's just fast forward
to the end of this story.
Let's go ahead and type step,
to dive into the Swap function.
Now notice, if I type a, it's
identical to the address of x.
If I type b, it's identical
to the address of y.
So what should I see if I
say, go to the address a?
So print star a.
So star means go there, in this context.
Ampersand means what's the address of.
So star a means 1.
And print star b gives me 2.
>> And let me assume, for the moment,
that at least the code that
proceeds to execute now can be
reasoned through in that way.
But we'll revisit this idea before long.
So this version of Swap
is now correct and allows
us to swap this particular data type.
>> So any questions then on Swap?
On star?
On address of?
And you'll see, with
problem set 4, sort of,
but problem set 5, definitely, how these
things are useful and get much more
comfortable with them, as a result.
Anything at all?
All right.
So malloc is, again, this function
that just allocates memory, memory
allocation.
And why is this useful?
Well, all this time,
you've been using malloc.
If you consider now how
getString works, presumably, it's
been asking someone for a chunk of
memory, anytime the user types a string
in, because we certainly
didn't know, as CS50 staff,
how big those strings that humans
are going to type might be.
>> So let's, for the first time, start to
peel back how the CS50 library works,
by way of a couple of examples
that will lead us there.
So if I open up gedit
and open up scanf 0,
we're going to see the following code.
Scanf 0, available on the website for
today, has relatively few lines of code
here, 14 through 20.
And let's see what it's doing.
It declares an int, called x.
It says something like, number please.
And now it says, scanf %i, &x.
So there's a bunch of new stuff there.
>> But scanf, you can kind of think
of as the opposite of printf.
printf, of course, prints to the screen.
scanf sort of scans from the user's
keyboard something he or she has typed.
>> %i is just like printf.
This means expect the
user to type an int.
And now, why do you think I
might be passing scanf &x?
If the purpose in life of scanf
is to get something from the user,
what is the meaning of
passing it, &x, now?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
Whatever I, the human, type in, my input
is going to be saved at that location.
It's not sufficient, recall, to just
pass in x, because we've seen already,
any time you pass just a raw variable,
like an int, to some other function,
sure, it can change that
variable, but not permanently.
It can't have an effect on Main.
It can only change its own local copy.
But if, instead, you don't
give me the actual int,
but you give me directions to
that int, I now, being scanf,
surely, I can follow that
address and put a number there
so you have access to it as well.
>> So when I run this program, let's see.
Make scanf 0 dot slash, scanf 0.
And if I now type a number
like 50, thanks for the 50.
If I now type a number like
negative 1, for the negative 1.
I now type a number like 1.5, hm.
Why did my program ignore me?
Well, because simply, I told
it to expect an int only.
All right.
So that's one version of this.
Let's take things up a notch and
propose that this is not good.
And herein lies a very simple example
of how we can start writing code
that other people can exploit or
compromise by doing bad things.
So line 16, so similar
in spirit to before,
but I'm not declaring it int this time.
I'm declaring it char star, aka string.
>> But what does that really mean?
So if I don't specify an address-- and
I'm calling it arbitrarily, buffer,
but I could call it s, to be simple--
and then I do this, explain to me,
if you could, based on the previous
logic, what is scanf doing in line 18,
if pass %s and buffer,
which is an address?
What is scanf, if you apply the
exact same logic as version 0,
going to try to do here, when
the user types something in?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
Scanf, by the logic earlier,
is going to take the string
that the human typed
in-- it's now a string,
it's not a number, presumably,
if he or she cooperates--
and it's going to try to put that
string in memory at whatever address
buffer specifies.
And this is great, because buffer
is indeed meant to be an address.
>> But I claim this program is buggy in a
very serious way, because what value is
buffer by default?
What have I initialized into?
What chunk of memory?
I haven't, right?
>> So even though I've allocated a
char star that's no longer called s,
it's instead called, buffer-- so
let's draw the variable's name
now as buffer-- if I haven't
called getString or malloc here,
that effectively means that
buffer is just some garbage value.
>> Now what does that mean?
It means that I have told scanf
to expect a string from the user.
And you know what?
Whatever this thing is pointing
to-- and I draw question mark,
but in reality, it's going to be
something like Ox1, 2, 3, right?
It's some bogus value that just
happens to be there from before.
So put another way, it's
as though buffer is just
pointing to something in memory.
I have no idea what.
>> So if I type in gabe now, it's going
to try to put g-a-b-e /0 there.
But who knows what that is?
And in the past, any
time we've tried to touch
memory that doesn't belong
to us, what has happened?
Or almost every time.
Segmentation fault, right?
>> This arrow, I have no idea where it's
pointing. it's just some random value.
And of course, if you interpret
a random value as an address,
you're going to go to
some random destination.
So gabe might indeed crash
my program in this case here.
>> So what can we do that's almost as bad?
Consider this third and
final example of scanf.
This version is better in what sense?
If you are comfortable with the
previous problem, this is better.
Why?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
So this case of line 16
is better, in the sense
that we're explicitly
allocating some memory.
We're not using malloc,
we're using the week 2
approach of just declaring an array.
And we've said before that a string
is just an array of characters,
so this is totally legitimate.
But it's, of course, as
you note, fixed size, 16.
>> So this program is
totally safe, if I type
in one character strings, two character
strings, 15 character strings.
But as soon as I start typing 16,
17, 18, 1,000 character strings,
where is that string going to end up?
It's going to end up partly here.
But then who knows what else
is beyond the boundaries
of this particular array?
>> It's as though I've
declared 16 boxes here.
So rather than draw out all 16, we'll
just pretend that I've drawn 16.
But if I then try to read a string
that's much longer, like 50 characters,
I'm going to start putting
a, b, c, d, x, y, z.
And this is presumably
some other memory segment
that, again, might cause
my program to crash,
because I've not asked for
anything more than just 16 bytes.
>> So who cares?
Well, here's the CS50 library.
And most of this is just
like instructions up top.
The CS50 library, all this time,
has had this line in line 52.
We've seen typedef, or
you will see typedef
in pset 4, which just creates a
synonym whereby char star can be more
simply referred to as string.
So this is one of the
few training wheels
we've used secretly underneath the hood.
>> Meanwhile, here's the function, getchar.
Now apparently, there's no body to it.
And in fact, if I keep
scrolling, I don't actually
see any implementations
of these functions.
As a sanity check, why is that?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So this is the header file.
And header files contain prototypes,
plus some other stuff, it seems,
like typedefs.
But in CS50.c, which we've
never given you outright,
but has been in the CS50 appliance all
this time, deep inside of its folders,
notice that there's a whole
bunch of functions in here.
>> In fact, let's scroll down.
Let's ignore most of them, for now.
But scroll down to getInt
and see how getInt works.
So here is getInt.
And if you ever really cared how get
int works, here is its documentation.
And among the things
it says is it tells you
what the ranges of values it can return.
It's essentially negative 2 billion
to positive 2 billion, give or take.
>> And it turns out, all this
time, even though we've never
had you check for it,
if something goes wrong,
it turns out that all
this time, getInt has
been returning a special
constant, not null,
but rather int_max, which is
just a programmer's convention.
It means here is a special value.
Make sure to check for this, just
in case something goes wrong.
But we've never bothered
with that to date,
because again, this
is meant to simplify.
>> But how does getInt get implemented?
Well, one, it takes no arguments.
We know that.
It returns an int.
So how does it work underneath the hood?
>> So there's apparently an infinite
loop, at least the appearance of one.
Notice that we're using getString.
So that's interesting. getInt
calls our own function, getString.
And now why might this be the case?
Why am I being defensive
here in line 165?
What could happen in line
164, just to be clear?
It's the same answer as before.
Might just be out of memory.
Something goes wrong with getString,
we've got to be able to handle that.
And the reason I don't return null is
that, technically, null is a pointer.
getInt has to return an int.
So I've arbitrarily
decided, essentially,
that 2 billion, give or take, is going
to be a special value that I can never
actually get from the user.
It's just the one value I'm going
to waste to represent an error code.
>> So now, things get a little fancy.
And it's not quite the same function
as before, but it's very similar.
So notice, I declare here, in line
172, both an int n and a char c.
And then I use this funky line,
sscanf, which it turns out
doesn't scan a string from the keyboard.
It stands an existing string that
the user has already typed in.
So I already called getString, which
means I have a string in memory.
sscanf is what you'd
call a parsing function.
It looks at the string I've
typed in, character by character,
and does something useful.
That string is stored in line.
And I know that only by going
back up here and saying, oh, OK,
I called it not s this time, but line.
>> And now this is a little different.
But this effectively means, for reasons
we'll somewhat wave our hands at today,
that we are checking to
see if the user typed in
and int and maybe another character.
If the user typed in an int, it's
going to be stored in n, because I'm
passing this by address, the
new trick we've seen today.
If the user also typed
in like 123x, that x
is going to end up a
letter in character c.
>> Now it turns out that sscanf
will tell me, intelligently,
how many variables was sscanf
successfully able to fill.
So by this logic, if the function
I'm implementing is getInt,
but I'm checking,
potentially, for the user
to have typed in an int
followed by something else,
what do I want sscanf's
return value truly to be?
If the purpose is to get
just an int from the user?
>> So if sscanf returns
2, what does that mean?
The user typed in
something like, literally,
123x, which is just nonsense.
It's an error condition, and
I want to check for that.
>> So if the user types this in, by
this logic, what does sscanf return,
would you say?
So it's going to return 2, because
the 123 is going to go in here,
and the x is going to end up in here.
But I don't want the x to get filled.
I want to sscanf to only succeed in
filling the first of its variables.
And so that's why I
want sscanf to return 1.
>> And if this is a bit over the head
for the moment, that's totally fine.
Realize though, that one of the
values of getInt and getString
is that we're doing a heck of a
lot of error checking like this so
that, to date, you can pretty much
type anything at your keyboard,
and we will catch it.
And we certainly, the
staff, will definitely not
be the source of a bug in your
program, because we're defensively
checking for all of the stupid
things that a user might do,
like typing a string, when
you really wanted int.
So for now-- we'll come
back to this before long--
but all this time,
getString and getInt have
been underneath the hood using this
basic idea of addresses of memory.
>> So now, let's make things a
little more user-friendly.
As you may recall, from Binky last
time-- if my mouse will cooperate-- so
we had this code, which
frankly, is fairly nonsensical.
This code achieves nothing
useful, but it was the example
that professor Parlante
used in order to represent
what was going on in a
program involving memory.
>> So let's retell this
story super briefly.
These first two lines, in
English, do what, would you say?
Just in reasonably human, but
slightly technical terms, take a stab.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK, you're establishing
addresses for your x and y variables.
Not quite, because x and y are not
variables in the traditional sense.
x and y are addresses
or will store address.
So let's try this once more.
Not a bad start, though.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
I think that's a little cleaner.
Declaring two pointers, two integers.
And we're calling them x and y.
Or if we were to draw
this as a picture, again,
recall quite simply that all
we're doing with that first line
is drawing a box like this,
with some garbage value in it,
and calling it x, and then
another box like this,
with some garbage value
in it, calling it y.
We've declared two
pointers that ultimately
will store the address of an int.
So that's all there.
>> So when Binky did this, the
clay just looked like this.
And Nick just kind of
wrapped up the arrows,
as though they're not pointing anywhere
in particular, because they're just
garbage values.
They're not explicitly initialized
anywhere in particular.
>> Now the next line of
code, recall, was this.
So in reasonably user-friendly,
but somewhat technical English,
what is this line of code doing?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
It's allocating the chunk of the
memory that's the size of an int.
And that's half the answer.
You answered the right
half of the expression.
What is happening on the
left-hand side of the equal sign?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: And assigns
it to the variable x?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And assigns
it to the variable x.
So to recap, right-hand side allocates
enough memory to store an int.
But malloc specifically
returns the address
of that chunk of memory, which you've
just proposed gets stored in x.
>> So what Nick did last time with Binky is
he dragged that pointer out, the clay,
to point now at a white chunk of memory
that is equal to the size of an int.
And indeed, that's meant
to represent four bytes.
>> Now, the next line of code
did this, star x gets 42.
So 42 is straightforward on the
right-hand side, meaning of life.
Left-hand side, star x means what?
That too might have gone-- that's OK.
OK.
>> AUDIENCE: Basically,
go to the [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
Left-hand side means go to x.
x is address.
It's like 33 Oxford Street, or Ox1.
And star x means go to that
address and put what there?
42.
>> So indeed, that's exactly what Nick did.
He started with by,
essentially, mentally
pointing a finger at
x, following the arrow
to the white box on the right-hand
side, and putting the number 42 there.
But then things got a
little dangerous, right?
Binky's about to lose his head.
>> Star y equals 13, bad luck, means what?
So star y means go to the address in y.
But what is the address in y?
All right, it's garbage value, right?
I drew it as a question mark.
Nick drew it as a curled up arrow.
And as soon as you try to
do star y, saying go there,
but there is not a legitimate
address, it's some bogus location,
the program's going to crash.
And Binky's head is going
to fly off here, as it did.
>> So in the end, this program
was just flat out flaw.
It was a buggy program.
And it needed to be fixed.
And the only way, really, to fix it
would be, for instance, this line,
which we didn't even get to, because
the program crashed too soon.
But if we were to fix this, what
effect does doing y equal x have?
Well, it essentially points y at
whatever value x is pointing at.
>> So in Nick's story,
or Binky's story, both
x and y were pointing at
the white chunk of memory,
so that, finally, when you
do star y equals 13 again,
you end up putting 13 in
the appropriate location.
So all of these lines are perfectly
legitimate, except for this one,
when it happened before you
actually assigned y some value.
>> Now thankfully, you don't
have to reason through all
of these kinds of issues on your own.
Let me go ahead and open
up a terminal window here
and open up, for just a moment,
a super short program that
also is sort of pointless.
It's ugly.
It doesn't achieve anything useful.
But it does demonstrate issues
of memory, so let's take a look.
>> Main, super simple.
It apparently calls a function,
f, and then returns 0.
It's kind of hard to mess this up.
So Main is pretty good, so far.
>> So f is problematic.
And just didn't put much
effort into naming it
here, to keep the focus on the code.
f has two lines.
And let's see what's now going on.
So on the one hand
here-- and let me make
this consistent with the previous
example-- on the one hand,
the left-hand side is
doing what, in English?
It is--
AUDIENCE: Creating a pointer.
DAVID J. MALAN: Creating a pointer
to an int and calling it x.
So it's creating one of those boxes
I keep drawing on the touch screen.
And now, on the right-hand
side, malloc, of course,
is allocating a chunk of memory.
And just to be clear, how
much memory is it apparently
allocating, if you just
kind of do the math here?
>> So it's 40 bytes.
And I know that only because I know an
int, on the CS50 appliance, at least,
is four bytes.
So 10 times 4 is 40.
So this is storing an x, the address
of the first out of 40 ints that
have been allocated space back,
to back, to back, to back.
>> And that's what's key about malloc.
It doesn't take a little memory
here, a little here, a little here.
It gives you one chunk of memory,
contiguously, from the operating
system.
>> Now what about this,
x bracket 10 equals 0?
Arbitrary line of code.
It doesn't achieve anything useful.
But it is interesting,
because x bracket 10--?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: x bracket
10 doesn't have to be null.
The null detail only comes into play
with strings, at the end of a string.
But a good thought.
>> How big is this array, even
though I've allocated 40 bytes?
It's 0 through nine, right?
It's 10 ints, total.
40 bytes, but 10 ints,
indexed 0 through 0.
>> So what is that x bracket 10?
It's actually some
unknown garbage value.
It's memory that doesn't belong to me.
I should not be touching that
byte number 41, 42, 43, 44.
I'm going slightly too far.
>> And indeed, if I run this
program, it might very well crash.
But sometimes, we'll get lucky.
And so just to demonstrate
this-- and frankly,
you never know before you
do it-- let's run this.
It didn't actually crash.
>> But if I change this, for
instance, to be like 1,000,
to make this really
deliberate, let's see
if we can get it to crash this time.
OK, it didn't crash.
How about 100,000?
Let's remake it, and now rerun it.
OK.
Phew.
All right.
So apparently, again, these
segments of memory, so to speak,
are reasonably big, so we can
get lucky again and again.
But eventually, once you get ridiculous
and really go far out on the screen,
you touch memory that really,
really doesn't belong to you.
>> But frankly, these
kinds of bugs are going
to be harder and harder
to figure out on your own.
But thankfully, as programmers, we have
tools that allow us to do this for us.
So this is, perhaps, one
of the ugliest programs,
even uglier than gdb's output.
But it always has a line or
two that are super useful.
>> Valgrind is a program that helps
you not debug a program, per se,
but find memory-related
problems, specifically.
It will automatically run your code for
you and look for at least two things.
One, did you do something
accidental like touch memory
that didn't belong to you?
It will help you find those cases.
>> And two, it will help
you find something called
memory leaks, which we have
completely ignored, naively,
for some time and blissfully.
But it turns out, all
this time, whenever
you've called getString in
so many of our programs,
you're asking the operating
system for memory,
but you have any recollection
of ever giving it
back, doing unalloc, or
free, as it's called.
No, because we've never
asked you to do so.
>> But all this time, the programs
you've been writing in C
have been leaking memory,
asking the operating
system for more and more
memory for strings and whatnot,
but never handing it back.
And now this is a bit
of a oversimplification,
but if you've ever run your Mac or
your PC for quite some time, opening
lots of programs,
maybe closing programs,
and even though your
computer hasn't crashed,
it's getting so much slower,
as though it's really
using a lot of memory or
resources, even though,
if you're not even
touching the keyboard,
that could be-- but not always-- could
be that the programs you're running
have themselves memory leaks.
And they keep asking the OS for more and
more memory, but forgetting about it,
not actually using it, but
therefore taking memory away
from other programs that might want it.
So that's a common explanation.
Now here's where Valgrind's
output is completely
atrocious to those less
and more comfortable alike.
But the interesting
stuff is right up here.
It is telling me an invalid write of
size four happens in this program,
in particular, at line 21 of memory.c.
>> If I go to line 21, hm, there indeed
is an invalid write of size four.
Why size four?
Well, this number-- and it
could be anything-- is an int.
So it's four bytes.
So I'm putting four bytes
where they don't belong.
That's what Valgrind
is actually telling me.
Moreover, it will also
tell me, as we'll see,
as you run this in a future pset, if and
when you've leaked memory, which indeed
I have, because I've called
malloc, but I haven't actually
called, in this case, free,
which we'll eventually see
is the opposite of malloc.
>> So now, I think, a final example.
So this one's a little more
arcane, but it's perhaps
the biggest reason to
be careful with memory,
and the reason that many programs
and/or web servers, even to this day,
are taken over by bad guys somewhere
on the internet who are somehow
sending bogus packets to your server
trying to compromise your accounts,
or take your data, or just
generally take over a machine.
Buffer overflow, as the
name suggests, means
overflowing not an int, but a buffer.
And a buffer is just a fancy way
of saying it's a bunch of memory.
>> And indeed, I called a string
before buffer, instead of s.
Because if it's a buffer,
like in the YouTube sense,
or any time you're watching a video,
you might have seen the word buffering,
dot, dot, dot.
It's incredibly annoying.
And that just means
that your video player
is trying to download lots
of bytes, lots of bytes
from a video from the internet.
But it's slow, so it's trying
to download a bunch of them
to fill a buffer, a container, so that
you have enough bytes that it can then
show you the video,
without pausing constantly.
But it turns out, you can
have a buffer to this big.
But try to put this much data in
it, and very bad things can happen.
So for instance, let's look at
this final teaser of an example.
This is another program
that, at first glance,
doesn't do anything super useful.
It's got a Main function
that calls that function, f.
And that function, f, up here, has
a char array, called c, of size 12.
And then it's using this
new function called strncpy.
>> It turns out that, with this simple,
simple line of code, just two lines,
we have made my entire program,
and therefore, my entire computer,
and my user account, and my hard
drive potentially vulnerable to anyone
who knows and is good enough to run
this program with a certain command line
argument.
In other words, if this bad guy
puts inside of argvargv[1] by typing
at the keyboard a very specially crafted
string, not abc, 123, but essentially,
binary symbols that represent executable
code, a program that he or she wrote,
with this simple program, which is
representative of thousands of programs
that are similarly vulnerable, daresay,
he or she can ultimately delete all
the files on my hard drive, get a
blinking prompt so that he or she can
type commands on their own,
email all files to myself.
Anything that I can do, he
or she can do with this code.
>> We won't quite solve this yet.
And in fact, it's going to
involve a little picture
like this, which we'll soon come
to understand all the better.
But for today, let's end on
what's, hopefully, a slightly more
understandable XKCD joke,
until we resume next time.
All right.
See you on Wednesday.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> SPEAKER: And now, deep
thoughts, by Daven Farnham.
Memory is like jumping into a pile of
golden leaves on a Sunday afternoon.
Wind blowing, tossing your
hair-- oh, I miss the days when--
>> [LAUGHTER]