>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, and this
is the end of Week 2.
So today, we're going
to continue our look
at how we represent things
underneath the hood-- moving away
from numbers like integers
and floating point values
and focusing on strings and
ultimately more interesting programs.
But we'll also take a look at a
couple of domain-specific problems--
the first of which will
be involving cryptography,
the art of scrambling information,
in which you see above here
is a picture of Radio Orphan Annie's
secret decoder ring from yesteryear.
>> This is actually very primitive form
and child-friendly form of cryptopgraphy
whereby this ring has two disks--
one inside and one outside.
And by rotating one of those, you can
essentially line up letters like A
through Z with other letters
like B through A. In other words,
you can literally rotate the alphabet,
thereby coming up with a mapping from
letters to letters so that, if you
wanted to send a secret message
to someone like Annie, you could write
down your message and then rotate
the letters, whereby, if you mean
to say "A," you instead say "B,"
you mean to say "B,"
you instead say "C"--
or something a little more clever
than that-- and then, ultimately,
so long as Annie has this decoder
ring, she can decode the message.
Now, you may recall, in fact, that this
was used in a very famous film that
plays ad nauseum during
the Christmas season.
Let's take a look here.
RALPHIE PARKER: "Be it
known to all in summary
that Ralph Parker is hereby appointed
a member of Little Orphan Annie Secret
Circle and is entitled to all the
honors and benefits occurring thereto."
>> RALPHIE PARKER (NARRATING):
Signed Little Orphan Annie.
Countersigned, Pierre Andre!
In ink.
Honors and benefits,
already at the age of nine.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> [RADIO CHATTER]
RALPHIE PARKER: Come on.
Let's get on with it.
I don't need all that jazz
about smugglers and pirates.
RADIO ANNOUNCER: Listen tomorrow
night for the concluding adventure
of The Black Pirate Ship.
Now, it's time for Annie's
Secret Message for you members
of the Secret Circle.
Remember kids, only members
of Annie's Secret Circle
can decode Annie's secret message.
>> Remember, Annie is depending on you.
Set your pins to B-2.
Here is the message-- 12, 11, 2--
RALPHIE PARKER (NARRATING): I
am in my first secret meeting.
RADIO ANNOUNCER: --25, 14, 11, 18, 16--
RALPHIE PARKER (NARRATING): Oh,
Pierre was in great voice tonight.
I could tell that tonight's
message was really important.
>> RADIO ANNOUNCER: --3, 25.
That's a message from Annie herself.
Remember, don't tell anyone.
>> [PANTING]
RALPHIE PARKER (NARRATING):
Ninety seconds later, I'm
in the only room in the
house where a boy of nine
could sit in privacy and decode.
Ah.
"B."
>> [CHUCKLES]
>> RALPHIE PARKER (NARRATING):
I went to the next.
"E."
The first word is "be."
Yes!
It was coming easier now.
"U."
>> [CHUCKLES]
>> RANDY PARKER: Aw, come on, Ralphie.
I gotta go!
>> RALPHIE PARKER: I'll be right down, Ma.
Gee whiz.
"T." "O." "Be sure
to." "Be sure to" what?
What was Little Orphan Annie
trying to say? "Be sure to" what?
MOTHER: Ralphie, Randy has got to go.
Will you please come out?
>> RALPHIE PARKER: All right, Mom!
I'll be right out!
RALPHIE PARKER (NARRATING):
I was getting closer now.
The tension was terrible.
What was it?
The fate of the planet
may hang in the balance.
>> MOTHER: Ralphie, Randy's got to go!
>> RALPHIE PARKER: I'll be right
out, for crying out loud!
RALPHIE PARKER
(NARRATING): Almost there!
My fingers flew!
My mind was a steel trap.
Every pore vibrated.
It was almost clear!
Yes!
>> RALPHIE PARKER: "Be sure
to drink your Ovaltine."
Ovaltine?
A crummy commercial?
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> RALPHIE PARKER: Son of a bitch.
>> [LAUGHING]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So that then is
a glimpse at what cryptography
can be for this-- a
drink from yesteryear.
So a quick announcement.
If you are free this
Friday at 1:15 PM and would
like to join us for CS50
lunch, head to this URL here.
First come, first serve as usual.
But over time, we'll make sure that
most anyone who'd like to participate
may schedule-wise.
>> So strings.
We have Zamyla-- whom
you've now met most likely
in Problem Set 1-- whose
name is spelled thus.
And suppose you typed her name
into a computer program that's
using something like getString.
In order to retrieve
those keystrokes, how
do we go about representing a
string, a word, a paragraph,
or multiple letters like these here?
>> We talked last time about
integers and problems
that arise with integer overflow
and floating point values
and problems that
arise within precision.
With strings, we at least
have a bit more flexibility
because strings-- just
in the real world--
can be a pretty arbitrary length.
Pretty short, pretty long.
But even then, we're going to
find that computers can sometimes
run out of memory and not even
store a big enough string.
>> But for now, let's start to visualize
a string as something in these boxes
here.
So six such boxes, each of which
represents a character or "char."
So recall that "char"-- c-h-a-r-- is
one of the built-in data types in C.
And what's nice is that you can use
that sort of as a building block,
a puzzle piece, if you will, to form a
larger type of data that we'll continue
to call a "string."
>> Now, what's useful about thinking
about things like strings in this way?
Well, it turns out that we can
actually leverage this structure
to actually access individual characters
in a pretty straightforward way.
I'm going to go ahead and create
a file called "stringzero.c,"
but you can call it whatever you'd like.
And on the course's website is
already this example in advance,
so you don't need to
type everything out.
>> And I'm going to go ahead
and first do int main void.
And within a few days,
we'll start to tease apart
what void is here, why it's
int next to main, and so forth.
But for now, let's continue
to copy paste that.
>> I'm going to declare a string called s.
And I'm going to return from
GetString whatever the user types in.
This is going to be a simple
program, no instructions,
I'm just going to blindly
expect that the user knows
what to do to keep it simple.
>> And now I'm going to have a for loop.
And inside of my for loop I'm
going to have int i gets zero.
And i is, again, just a convention,
an index variable for counting,
but I could call this whatever I want.
I'm going to do i is less than-- well
Zamyla's name is six letters long.
So I'm going to hard
code that there for now.
>> And then i++.
And now inside of these curly
braces I'm going to do printf,
and I want to print one
character at a time.
So I'm going to use %c for
perhaps the first time.
And then I want to print each
character on its own line.
So I'm going to put a
little backslash n there.
Close quote.
>> And now I want to do something here.
I want to print out the
specific letter in the string,
s, as I'm iterating
from zero on up to six.
In other words, I want to
print the i'th character of s.
Now how can I do this?
>> Well much like the boxes in
this representation here,
kind of, conjure up the notion of boxing
letters in, you can similarly do that
syntactically in C by simply specifying,
I want to print out s's i'th character.
Using the square brackets
on your computer's keyboard
that on a US keyboard are
generally above your return key.
>> So this isn't quite right
yet, as you may have noticed.
But I'm going to kind of
blindly forge ahead here.
And I'm going to do make string 0.
But before I do this, let's see if we
can't anticipate some common mistakes.
Is this going to compile?
No, I'm missing a whole bunch of things.
Libraries I heard.
>> So which header files
might I want to add here?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: You need
standard I/O [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Excellent.
So I need standard I/O. For what
purpose do I want standard I/O?
For printf.
So include stdio.h.
And you also propose that I include
the CS50 library for what reason?
To have strings.
So we'll see what
CS50's library is doing
to create this notion of a string.
But for now, you can just think
of it as an actual data type.
>> So that seems to be a little cleaned up.
And now I'm going to go ahead
and indeed do make string 0.
Compiled.
So that's good.
So ./string0 let me zoom in so we can
see more closely what's happening.
Enter.
Z-A-M-Y-L-A enter.
And we've printed out to Zamyla's name.
>> So that's pretty good.
So now let's go ahead and
run this program again,
and type out Daven's full name.
Surprise, surprise.
Enter.
Hmm.
We have not printed Daven's
full first name correctly.
Now this should be obvious in
retrospect because of what,
sort of, stupid design decision?
>> Yeah, I hard coded the
six inside of my for loop.
Now I did that only because
I knew Zamyla's name
was going to be six letters.
But surely this isn't
a general solution.
So it turns out we can dynamically
figure out the length of a string
by calling a function called strlen.
>> Again, deliberately
succinctly named just
to make it more convenient to type.
But that's synonymous with
getting the length of a string.
I'm going to go back into my terminal
window and re-run the compiler.
But it's yelling at me.
Implicitly declaring library function
strlen with type unsigned int const--
I'm lost.
Completely.
>> So, especially as your
eyes start to glaze over
with error messages like this, focus
honestly on the first few words.
We know the problem is in
line 8, as indicated here.
And it's in string-0.c.
Implicitly declaring
library function strlen.
So that is generally going to
be a pattern of error messages.
Implicitly declaring something.
>> So in short, what have I seemed to
have done with respect to line 8, here.
What might be the solution be even
if you've never used strlen yourself?
>> AUDIENCE: Part of a different library?
DAVID J. MALAN: Part
of a different library.
So it is declared, so to speak.
It is mentioned in some file
other than stdio.h and CS50.h.
Now where is it defined?
To be honest, you either have to just
know this off the top of your head,
or you Google this and find out.
Or know this, I've opened up in the CS50
appliance the terminal program, which
is just the big, full screen version of
what's in the bottom of gedit's window.
>> And it turns out that there's a
similarly succinct command, called
man for manual, where if you type in
the name of a function and hit Enter,
you'll get back fairly
arcane documentation.
It's just text that generally
looks a little something like this.
It's a little overwhelming
at first glance.
But frankly I'm going to
let my eyes glaze over
and only focus on the part
I care about for the moment.
>> Which is this.
Which looks structurally like
something I'm familiar with.
Indeed the man page, so
to speak, will tell you
in what header file a function
like strlen is defined.
So I'm going to go back now to gedit.
And I'm going to go ahead and
add in here #include
and save the file.
>> I'm going to clear the screen with
Control L If you've been wondering.
And I'm going to re-run make
string.0, compiles this time.
./string.0 Zamyla.
That seemed to work Let me go
ahead and rerun it with Davenport.
Enter.
And that, too, seemed to work.
>> So we can do a little better than this,
though, we can start to tidy things
up just a little bit.
And I'm going to actually
introduce one other thing now.
I'm going to go ahead and
save this in a different file.
And I'm going to call
this file string1.c just
to be consistent with the code
you'll be able to find online.
>> And let's focus in on
exactly the same code.
It turns out that I've
been kind of taking
for granted the fact that my laptop,
and in turn, the CS50 appliance
has a lot of memory, a lot of
RAM, a lot of bytes of space
in which I can store strings.
>> But the reality if I typed long
enough, and enough keystrokes,
I could in theory type
in more characters
than my computer
physically has memory for.
And this is problematic.
Much like an int can only
count so high, in theory,
you can only cram so many characters
into your computer's RAM or Random
Access Memory.
>> So I had better anticipate
this problem, even
though it might be a rare
corner case, so to speak.
Doesn't happen that often, could happen.
And if it happens and I don't
anticipate and program for it,
my program could do who knows what.
Freeze, hang, reboot, whatever.
Something anticipated might happen.
>> So what I'm going to do
now, henceforth really,
is before I ever blindly
use a variable like s that
has been assigned the return value of
some other function like getstring,
I'm going to make sure
that its value is valid.
So I know only from having read
CS50's documentation for getstring,
which ultimately we'll point you at,
that getstring returns a special symbol
called NULL, N-U-L-L in all
caps, if something goes wrong.
>> So normally, it returns a string.
But otherwise if it returns N-U-L-L--
we'll eventually see what that really
means-- that just means
something bad happened.
Now this means, much like in Scratch,
I can check a condition here in C,
if s does not equal NULL.
So if you've not seen this before,
this just means does not equal.
>> So it's the opposite of
equal equals, which, recall,
is different from single
equals, which is assignment.
So if s does not equal
NULL, only then do
I want to execute these lines of code.
So in other words,
before I dive in blindly
and start iterating
over s, and treating it
as though it is a sequence of
characters, I'm going to first check,
wait a minute, is s definitely not
equal to this special value, NULL?
>> Because if it is, bad things can happen.
And for now, assume that bad things
happening means your program crashes,
and you can't necessarily recover.
So frankly, it looks uglier.
it's kind of confusing now to glance at.
But this will become more
familiar before long.
>> But I'm going to propose
now one other improvement.
That's an improvement to correctness.
My program is now more correct, because
in the rare case that not enough memory
exists, I will handle it,
and I'll just do nothing.
I at least won't crash.
>> But let's do a final version here.
And a file called string2.c.
I'm going to paste that
same code for just a moment,
and I'm going to highlight this
line, 11, here, for just a moment.
Now the reality is that smart compilers
like Clang could fix this for us
behind the scenes
without our ever knowing.
But let's think about this
fundamentally as a problematic design.
>> This line of code is, of course,
saying, initialize some variable i to 0.
That's pretty straightforward.
And what again is this
statement, here, i++, doing?
We've seen it before, but we
didn't really talk about it.
>> AUDIENCE: Incrementing i.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Incrementing i.
So on every iteration through
this loop, every cycle,
you're incrementing i by one.
So it gets bigger, and bigger, and
bigger until the loop terminates.
How does it terminate?
Well there's this middle
condition which we've used before.
You've seen and in
walkthroughs in the P set.
>> But what is this saying?
Do the following loop so
long as i is less than what?
AUDIENCE: The length of the string.
DAVID J. MALAN: The
length of the string.
So it translates pretty cleanly
to English in that sense.
Now the problem is that every time I
iterate through this loop in theory,
I'm asking this question.
Is i less than the string length of s?
>> Now is i changing on each iteration?
It is.
Because of the ++.
So every iteration i is getting bigger.
But is s getting bigger, or
smaller, or changing at all?
No.
So in terms of design, one of the axes
along which we try to evaluate code
in the class, this feels kind of stupid.
>> Like you are literally,
on every iteration
of this loop asking the
same damn question again,
and again, and again, and literally
it is never going to change.
At least if I'm not touching s and
trying to change the contents of s.
So I can do a little better than this.
>> And what I'm going to do is not
declare just one variable i,
but a second variable I'll arbitrarily,
but conventionally, call it n.
Assign n equal to the
string length of s.
And then over here, I'm going to
do a clever little optimization, so
to speak, that at the end of the day
is no more correct or no less correct
than before.
But it's a better design.
In the fact that I'm using
less time, fewer CPU cycles, so
to speak, to answer the same
question, but just once.
>> Any questions on that general
principle of improving,
say, a program's efficiency?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Why do you
use the [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
So why do we put the ++ on the end of
i instead of the beginning of the i?
In this case, it has
no functional impact.
And in general, I tend to
use the postfix operator
so that it's a little more clear as
to when the operation is happening.
>> For those unfamiliar, there is another
statements whereby you could do ++i.
These are functionally
equivalent in this case
because there's nothing else
around that incrementation.
But you can come up with
cases and lines of code
in which that makes a difference.
So generally, we don't
even talk about this one.
Because frankly, it makes your
code sexier, and sort of slicker,
and fewer characters.
But the reality is it's a lot harder,
I think, even for me to wrap my mind
around it sometimes,
the order of operations.
So as an aside, if you
really don't like this,
even though this is kind of sexy
looking, you can also do i+=1,
which is the uglier version of the
same idea for postfix incrementation.
>> I say this and you
should make fun of it,
but you will come to see code as
something beautiful before long.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Right?
Yeah.
Question in the middle.
>> AUDIENCE: Do you need to say int n?
DAVID J. MALAN: You do
not need to say int n.
So because we have already said int,
you do not need to say it again.
The catch is that n has to
be the same data type as i.
So that's just a convenience here.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Can you go over the
print character s bracket i again?
DAVID J. MALAN: Absolutely.
So %c, recall from last
time, is just a placeholder.
It means put a char here.
backslash n, of course, just
means put a line break here.
So that just leaves, now,
this piece of new syntax.
And this is literally saying, grab
the string called s and go get its
i'th character, so to speak.
>> And I keep saying i'th character
because on each iteration of this loop
it's as though we are printing
out, first s bracket 0,
as a programmer might say.
Then s bracket 1, then s
bracket 2, then 3, then 4.
But of course it's a variable,
so I just express it with i.
>> Key, though, is to realize,
especially if you've not
been acclimating to this world
of programming, where we all
seem to count from zero, gotta
start counting from zero now.
Because strings, first character, the
z in Zamyla is for better or for worse
going to live at location number zero.
>> All right, so let me bring
us back here to Zamyla
and see what's really going
on underneath the hood.
So there's this notion of type casting.
You might have actually
played with this already,
maybe for the hacker
edition of P set one.
But type casting just refers to the
ability in C and some other languages
to convert one data type to another.
>> Now how might we see this
pretty straightforwardly?
So this, recall, is the beginning
of the English alphabet.
And the context, recall, from
like a week ago is ASCII.
The American Standard Code
for Information Interchange.
Which is just a really long way
of saying a mapping from letters
to numbers, and from numbers to letters.
>> So A through M here, dot dot
dot, lines up with, recall,
the decimal number 65 on up.
And we didn't talk
about this explicitly,
but surely there's similar
numbers for lowercase letters.
And indeed, there are.
The world decided some years
ago that little a, lowercase a,
is going to be 97.
And little b is going
to be 98, and so forth.
>> And for any other key on
your keyboard, there's
going to be a similar pattern of bits.
Or equivalently, a decimal number.
So the question at hand,
then, is how can we
actually see this underneath the hood?
So I'm going to go over to gedit again.
And rather than type
this one from scratch,
I'm going to go ahead and
just open up something
from today's code called ASCII zero.
>> And ASCII zero looks like this.
So let's wrap our minds around this.
So first, I've commented
the code, which is nice.
Because it's literally
telling me what to expect,
display a mapping for uppercase letters.
Now I don't quite know what I
mean by that, so let's infer.
>> In English, maybe
somewhat techie English,
what does line 18 appear
to be doing for us?
Just line 18.
What's it inducing?
What's it going to kick off here?
>> AUDIENCE: A loop.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: A loop.
And how many times is
that going to iterate?
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
six times.
DAVID J. MALAN: Not six times.
AUDIENCE: 26 times.
DAVID J. MALAN: 26 times.
Yeah, sorry.
26 times.
Why?
Well, it's a little weird, but
I've started counting from 65.
Which is weird, but not wrong.
It's not bad per say.
And I'm doing that only
because, for this example,
I'm kind of anticipating
that capital A was 65.
Now this is not the most elegant
way to do this, to kind of hard code
esoteric values that no one
is ever expected to remember.
>> But for now, notice that I'm
doing this up through 65 plus 26.
Because apparently I don't even want
to do the arithmetic in my head.
So I'll let the compiler do it.
But then on each loop, each iteration
of the loop, I'm incrementing i.
>> So now this looks a little cryptic.
But we should have the basic building
blocks with which to understand this.
%c is just a placeholder for a char.
%i is a placeholder for an int.
And it turns out that by using this
new syntax, this parenthetical, so
to speak, so a data type
inside a parentheses,
I can force the compiler to treat
i not is an integer, but as a char.
>> Thereby showing me the character
equivalent of that number.
Now down here, this code
is pretty much identical.
I just wanted to make
super explicit the fact
that I'm starting at 97,
which is lowercase a.
On up through 26 more letters.
And I'm doing-- again,
casting i, so to speak.
Or type casting i, so to speak.
>> From an int to a char.
So the end result is going to be,
frankly, information we already know.
I'm going to make
ascii-0 dot-- not dot c.
Notice, you probably made that
mistake as I just did accidentally.
Make ascii-0.
Now I'm going to do ./ascii-0.
I'll zoom in, and unfortunately
it's going to scroll off the screen.
But we see an entire chart where
a maps to 97, b maps to 98,
and if we scroll up further
A, of course, maps to 65.
So this is only to say that
what we've been preaching,
there is this equivalence, is
in fact the case in reality.
So a quick modification of this.
Let me open up ascii-1.c.
And notice this clever, sort
of, clarification of this.
This is ascii-1.c, and
notice this crazy thing.
>> And this really gets to the heart
of what computers are doing.
Even though we humans would
not count in terms of letters--
I don't start thinking,
all right a then b,
and use those to count physical objects.
You can certainly say that I want to
initialize some variable called c--
but I could have called this anything--
so c is initialized to capital A.
>> Because at end of the day, the computer
doesn't care what you're storing,
it only cares how you want
to present that information.
How do you want the computer to
interpret that pattern of bits?
So this is not something I
would generally recommend doing.
It's really just an example to
convey that you can absolutely
initialize an integer to a char.
Because underneath the
hood of a char, of course,
is just a number from 0 to 255.
>> So you can certainly
put it inside of an int.
And what this also
demonstrates is that we
can convert from one
type to another, here,
ultimately printing the same thing.
And in fact, this I will fix online--
was meant to say this, again, here.
Let me clean this up online, and we'll
see in an online walkthrough as needed,
what was intended there.
>> OK.
So last example now involving
a's and b's and then we'll
take things up a notch.
So with a's and b's and
c's in the capitalization
and the equivalence thereof, let's
take a look at this example, here.
Another code example.
We'll open one that's
already made, so we
don't have to type it
all out from scratch.
>> And notice in anticipation
we're using multiple header
files, among which is
our new friend, string.h.
Now this looks, at first
glance, a little cryptic.
But let's see if we can't reason
through what's going on here.
First I get a string from the user,
and I put that string in a variable
called s.
Copy paste from before.
In line 22, I'm apparently
doing exactly what
I did a moment ago, I'm iterating
over the characters in s.
>> And the new tricks here are using
string length, the minor optimization
of storing the string length in n,
rather than calling strlen again,
and again, and again.
And just checking that i is less than n.
Now here, things get
a little interesting.
But it's just an application
of this same new idea.
What in English does
s bracket i represent?
>> AUDIENCE: Counting each
character [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Counting each character.
And even more succinctly,
s bracket i represent what?
Would you say.
Not to put you on the spot here.
>> AUDIENCE: Well--
DAVID J. MALAN: So if the word is-- if
the string is Zamyla, which starts--
AUDIENCE: --you deal with
the characters separately--
DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
Exactly.
The square bracket notation allows you
to access each character individually,
so s bracket 0 is going to be the
first character in the string.
s bracket 1 is going to be
the second, and so forth.
So the question I'm asking,
here, in this condition is what?
Is the i'th character of s greater
than or equal to lowercase a?
And what does this mean, here,
with the double ampersands?
AUDIENCE (TOGETHER): And.
DAVID J. MALAN: And.
It's just equivalent to this.
And is not a keyword in C, you have to
use, annoyingly, ampersand ampersand.
And this, conversely, is asking is
s's i'th character less than or equal
to lowercase z?
And again, here's where
understanding the underlying
implementation of a
computer makes sense.
Notice that, even though I have
the dot dot dot over there,
looks like a through z in lowercase are
all contiguous values up from 97 on up.
>> And same for uppercase starting at 65.
So the takeaway, then,
is that in English,
how would you describe
what line 24 is doing?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: On 24 it's checking to see
whether each character is a lowercase.
DAVID J. MALAN: It's checking whether
each character is a lowercase letter.
So even more succinctly, is the
i'th character of s lowercase?
That's all we're
expressing here logically,
a little cryptically, but
ultimately pretty straightforwardly.
Is s's i'th character lowercase?
>> If so, and here's where things
get a little mind bending
for just a moment, if so, go
ahead and print out a character.
So this is just a placeholder,
but what character?
Why am I doing s bracket i
minus this expression here?
>> Well notice the pattern here.
The actual numbers don't matter so much.
But notice that 97 is
how far away from 65?
>> AUDIENCE: 32.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: 32.
How far away is 98 from 66?
>> AUDIENCE: 32.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Little c from big C?
32.
So there's 32 hops from
one letter to another.
So frankly I, could
simplify this to that.
But then I'm kind of hard coding
this low level understanding
that no reader is ever
going to understand.
So I'm going to generalize it as, I
know the lowercase letters are bigger.
I know the capital letters are
smaller values, ironically.
>> But this is effectively equivalent to
saying subtract 32 from s bracket i.
So in the context of these
letters, if the letter
happens to be a, lowercase
a, and I subtract 32,
what effect does that have,
mathematically, on lowercase a?
AUDIENCE: Capitalizes--
DAVID J. MALAN: Capitalizes it.
And indeed, this is why our
program is called capitalize zero.
This program either
capitalizes a letter,
after checking if it is
indeed a lowercase letter.
Otherwise, in line 30, what do I do if
it's not a lowercase letter that I'm
looking at at a particular
iteration in the loop.
Just print it out.
>> So don't change stuff
that's not even lowercase.
Restrict yourself to
little a through little z.
Now this is fairly arcane.
But at the end of the day, this
is how we, once upon a time,
had to implement things.
If I instead open capitalize
one, oh thank god.
There's a function
called to upper that can
do everything we just did
at a fairly low level.
>> Now to upper is interesting
because it is declared in a file,
and you would only know this
by checking the documentation,
or being told, say, in class, where
it exists, in a file called ctype.h.
So this is another new friend of ours.
And to upper does exactly
what its name suggests.
>> You can pass in, as an argument, between
these parentheses, some character.
I'm going to pass in the i'th character
of s using our fancy new notation
involving square brackets.
And take a guess, what is the return
value of to upper apparently going
to be?
A capital letter.
>> So if I pass in lowercase a,
hopefully, by definition of to upper,
it's going to return an
uppercase A. Otherwise,
if it's not a lowercase letter in
the first place, I just print it out.
And indeed, notice the
second friend here.
Not just to upper exists,
but is lower, which
actually answers that question for me.
>> Now whoever wrote these things,
10s of years ago, you know what?
Implemented to upper and is
lower using code like this.
But again, consistent with
this idea of abstracting away,
sort of, lower level
implementation details.
And standing on the shoulders of people
who came before us, using functions
like to upper and is lower, which
wonderfully enough are nicely
named to say what they do, is
a wonderful paradigm to adopt.
>> Now, it turns out that if I read
the man page for, say, to upper,
I learn something else.
So man toUpper.
It's a little overwhelming.
But notice, here's that mention of
the header file that I should use.
As an aside, because this
is misleading, the function
uses ints instead of chars
for reasons of error checking.
But we'll perhaps come
back to that in the future.
>> But notice, here, to upper converts
the letter c to uppercase if possible.
So that's pretty straightforward.
And now let's be a little more specific.
Let's look at the part of the
man page under return value.
The value returned is that
of the converted letter.
Or c, if the conversion
was not possible,
where c is the original input.
Which I know from here, from
the argument to to upper.
>> So what is the takeaway of this?
The value returned is that
of the converted letter,
or c, the original letter, if
the conversion was not possible.
What improvement can I therefore
make to my code's design?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: You can remove the else.
DAVID J. MALAN: I can
remove the else statement,
and not just the else statement.
>> AUDIENCE: You can remove [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: I can
remove the whole fork
in the road, the if else altogether.
So indeed, let me open
the final version of this,
capitalize-2 and notice just how, if
you will, sexy, the code is now getting,
in that I've reduced from some
seven or so lines to just four,
the functionality that I intended
by simply calling to upper,
passing in s bracket i, and printing
out, with the placeholder %c,
that particular character.
>> Now arguably, there is a bug,
or at least the risk of a bug,
in this program.
So just to come back
to an earlier takeaway,
what should I probably also do in
this program to make it more robust,
so that there's no way it can
crash, even in rare cases?
AUDIENCE: Make sure it's not NULL.
DAVID J. MALAN: Make sure it's not NULL.
So really, to make this super
proper, I should do something like,
if s is not NULL, then
go ahead and execute
these lines of code, which
I can then indent like that,
and then put in my close brace.
So good tying together of the two ideas.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Could you use
a do while loop, instead?
DAVID J. MALAN: Could
I do a do while loop?
AUDIENCE: --you want to make sure
that you actually [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Could
you use a do while?
Short answer, no.
Because you're about to
introduce another corner case.
If the string is of zero length.
If for instance, I just hit
Enter, without ever typing Zamyla.
I'm going to hand you back an actual
string, as we'll eventually see,
that has zero characters.
It's still a string,
it's just super short.
But if you use a do while,
you're going to blindly
try to do something with
respect to that string,
and nothing's going to be there.
>> AUDIENCE: Well, if you did
do [INAUDIBLE] while s--
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh I see, keep
getting a string from the user.
So short answer, you
could, and keep pestering
them to give you a string that's
short enough to fit in memory.
Absolutely.
I just chose not to.
If they don't give me the string I
want, I'm quitting, I'm giving up.
But absolutely, for that purpose,
you could absolutely do that.
>> So the library's header files that
we're now familiar with are these, here.
Standard I/O, CS50.h, string.h,
ctype.h, and there are, indeed, others.
Some of you have discovered
the math library in math.h.
But let me introduce you, now, to
this resource that CS50 staff, Davin,
and Rob, and Gabe particular
have put together.
That will soon link on
the course's website.
It's called CS50 reference.
>> Which just to give you a quick
taste of it, works as follows.
Let me go to reference.cs50.net.
You'll see on the left hand
side an overwhelming list
of functions that come with c.
But if I care, for the moment,
about something like strlen,
I can type it there.
It filters down the list
to just what I care about.
I'm going to click it.
And now on the left,
you'll see what we hope
is a more straightforward, human
friendly explanation of how
this function works.
>> Returns the length of a string.
Here's a synopsis, here's how you
use it in terms of the header file,
and in terms of what the function
looks like in terms of its arguments.
And then here, returns
the length of a string.
But for those of you more comfortable,
you can actually click more comfy,
and the contents of this
page, now, will change
to be the default values of what
you get by using the man page.
>> In other words, CS50
reference is a simplification
of man pages by the staff, for students.
Particularly, those less comfortable
and in between, so that you
don't have to try to wrap
your mind around, frankly,
some fairly cryptic syntax
and documentation sometime.
>> So keep that in mind
in the days to come.
So here, again, is a Zamyla.
Let's now ask a question that's
a little more human accessible.
Thanks to Chang, who's been
printing more elephants
nonstop for the past few days.
We have an opportunity to give
at least one of them away.
If we could get just one volunteer
to come on up to draw on the screen.
How about here?
>> Come on up.
What is your name?
ALEX: Alex.
DAVID J. MALAN: Alex.
All right.
Alex, come on up.
We're about to see your
handwriting on the screen here.
All right, nice to meet you.
>> ALEX: Nice you meet you.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
So, super simple exercise.
Bar is not high to
get an elephant today.
You are playing the role of getstring.
And I'm going to just tell you
the string that you've gotten.
And suppose that you,
getstring, have been called.
And the human, like me, has
typed in Zamyla, Z-A-M-Y-L-A.
Just go ahead and write Zamyla on the
screen as though you have gotten it
and stored it somewhere in memory.
>> Leaving room for what will be several
other words-- that's OK, keep going.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> So Zamyla, Excellent.
So now suppose that you,
getstring, are called again.
And therefore, I provide you, at the
keyboard, with another name, Belinda.
All right.
And now the next time getstring is
called, I type in something like Gabe,
G-A-B-E. You're really taking
to heart random access memory.
Which is drawing everything
completely randomly.
OK.
>> [LAUGHTER]
ALEX: Sorry my handwriting is bad.
DAVID J. MALAN: No, that's OK.
And how about Rob, R-O-B. OK.
Good.
So I didn't anticipate you would
kind of lay things out in this way.
But we can make this work.
So how did you go about laying
out these chars in memory?
In other words, if we think of
this rectangular black screen
as representing a
computer's RAM, or memory.
>> And recall that RAM is just
a whole bunch of bytes,
and bytes are a whole bunch of bits.
And bits are somehow
implemented, generally
with some form of
electricity in hardware.
So that's sort of the
layering we've talked about
and can now take for granted.
How did you go about
deciding where to write
Rob versus Gabe versus
Belinda versus Zamyla?
>> ALEX: I just did it in the
order that you told me.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And that is true.
But what governed where you put
Belinda's name and Gabe's name?
>> ALEX: Nothing?
DAVID J. MALAN: [LAUGHS]
So that works, that's fine.
So computers are little
more orderly than that.
And so when we implement-- stay there
for just a moment-- when we actually
implement something like
getstring in a computer,
Zamyla might be laid out pretty much
like you did on the screen, there.
>> And what is key to notice
here, what Alex did,
is there is kind of a demarcation
among each of these words, right?
You didn't write
Z-A-M-Y-L-A-B-E-L-I-N-D-A-G-A-B--
in other words, there's some kind
of demarcation which seems to be,
sort of, random spacing
between these various words.
But that's good, because
we humans can now
visualize that these are
four different strings.
It's not just one sequence
of lots of characters.
So a computer, then, meanwhile,
might take a string like Zamyla,
put each of those letters
inside of a byte of memory.
But that number is much bigger,
of course, than six characters.
>> There's a whole bunch of RAM.
And so henceforth, this
grid of boxes is going
to represent what Alex just
did here on the screen.
And now, Alex, we can offer you a
blue or an orange elephant from Chang.
ALEX: I'll take a blue elephant.
DAVID J. MALAN: A blue elephant.
So a big round of applause,
if we could, for Alex here.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> ALEX: Thank you.
DAVID J. MALAN: Thank you.
So the takeaway is that, even though the
pattern kind of changed over time, here
on the board, there was this
demarcation among the various strings
that Alex got for us.
Now computers, frankly,
could do the same thing.
They could kind of plop
strings anywhere in RAM.
Up here, over here,
down here, down here.
>> They could do exactly that.
But, of course, that's
probably not the best planning.
Right?
If I kept asking Alex to
get names, probably he'd
put some more down here, maybe up
here, over here, over here, eventually
over here.
But with a bit more planning, certainly,
we could lay things out more cleanly.
And indeed, that's what a computer does.
>> But the catch is that
if the next string I get
after Zamyla is something
like the Belinda,
propose where we might write the
letter b with respect to this grid?
Where would you go?
To the right of the a,
below the z, below the a?
What would your first instincts be?
AUDIENCE: Below the z.
DAVID J. MALAN: So below the z.
And that's pretty
straightforward, right?
It's kind of neat, it's what we do
on a keyboard when we hit Enter,
or an email when making a
bulleted list of things.
But the reality is that computers
try to be more efficient,
and cram certainly as much
data into RAM as possible,
so that you don't waste any bytes.
So that you don't waste
any screen real estate.
And the problem, though, is that
if we literally put the letter
b after a, how are we going to
know where Zamyla's name ends
and the Belinda's name begins?
So you humans just proposed, well,
hit the Enter key, essentially.
Put it down below.
Or even as Alex did, just start writing
the next name below the previous one,
and below that one, and
then below that one.
That's a visual cue.
>> Computers have another visual cue,
but it's a little more succinct.
It's this funky character.
Backslash 0, which is perhaps
reminiscent of backslash n,
and so forth, now.
The special escape sequences.
Backslash 0 is the way of
representing eight zero bits in a row.
0000 0000.
>> The way you express that is not to
hit the number zero on your keyboard,
because in fact that is an ASCII char.
It looks like a number, but
is actually a decimal number
that represents the circular
glyph, the circular typeface.
Meanwhile, backslash
zero means, literally
put eight zero bytes here for me.
>> So this is somewhat arbitrary.
We could've used any pattern
of bits, but the world
decided some years
ago, that to represent
the end of a string in memory,
just put a whole bunch of zeros.
Because we can detect that.
Now that means that no letter of the
alphabet can be represented with zeros.
>> But that's OK, we've already seen
that we're using 65 on up in 97 on up.
We didn't get anywhere
close to all zeros.
So Belinda in a computer's memory
is actually going to go here.
I've drawn it in yellow just
to draw our attention to it.
And notice, too, this
is completely arbitrary.
I've drawn it as a grid.
Like, RAM is just some physical object.
It doesn't necessarily have
rows and columns, per se.
It's just got a whole bunch of bytes
implemented in hardware somehow.
But if after Belinda I
typed in Gabe's name,
he's going to end up here in memory,
and if I typed in Daven's name,
for instance, he's going to end up here.
And I can continue to
write even more names.
>> Unfortunately, if I try to
write a super long name,
I might eventually run out of memory.
In which case, getstring is
going to return NULL, as we said.
But thankfully, at least in this visual
here, we didn't get quite that far.
>> Now what's nice is that this
general idea of treating things
as being in boxes is
representative of a feature of C
and a lot of languages,
known as an array.
An array is another type of data.
It's a data structure, if you will.
Structure in the sense of it really,
kind of, looking like a box, at least
in your mind's eye.
An array is a contiguous
sequence of identical data types,
back to back to back to back.
>> So a string, in other
words, is an array of chars.
An array of characters.
But it turns out you can have
arrays of bunches of things.
In fact, we can put even
numbers in an array.
So the form in which
we're going to start
declaring this data
structure known as an array
is also going to use square brackets.
But these square brackets are going to
have different meaning in this context.
>> And let's see it as follows.
Suppose that I opened
up a new file here.
And I save this as ages.c.
And I'll save this in my folder here.
And now I'm going to go ahead
and start typing something
like include CS50.h, include
stdio.h, int main void.
And then inside of here, I want
to first have an int called age.
>> And I'm going to use that to get an
int from the user for his or her age.
But this program is meant to be used by
multiple people, for whatever context.
I've got a line of people.
All of them have to type in their
age for maybe some, I don't know,
competition, or event
that they've arrived for.
So the next person, I
need another variable.
>> Because if I just do
age gets getInt, that's
going to clobber, or overwrite
the previous person's age.
So that's no good.
So my first instinct
might be, oh, all right,
if I want to get multiple people's
ages-- let's call this age1,
int age2 gets int, int age3 gets getInt.
And now I'm going to use
some pseudocode code here.
>> Do something with those numbers.
We'll leave for another day what
we're doing there, because we only
care for the moment
about age1, age2, age3.
Unfortunately, once I
compile this program
and put it in front of actual users,
what's the fundamentally poor design
decision I seem to have made?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
I haven't even tried
to figure out how many ages
do I actually care about?
If I have fewer than three people here,
and therefore fewer than three ages,
I'm still blindly expecting three.
God forbid four people show up.
My program just won't even support them.
>> And so this, long story
short, is not a good habit.
Right?
I was essentially copying and
pasting code and just tweaking
the variable names.
And, my god, if you had, not three
ages, but 10, or 100, or even 6,500
undergraduates, for instance.
This is not going to be particularly
elegant code, or sustainable.
You're going to have to
rewrite the program every time
your number of people changes.
>> So thankfully, in our actual
ages.c file for today,
we have a more clever solution.
First, I'm going to borrow the
construct we've used a few times,
this do while loop, in order to get
the number of people in the room.
I'm just going to pester the user, again
and again, until he or she gives me
a value of n that's a positive integer.
>> I could have used, last
time's get positive int.
But we don't have that
for real, so I went ahead
and re implemented this idea.
Now down here, this is the new trick.
In line 27, as the comments
in line 26 suggests,
declare an array in which
to store everyone's age.
>> So if you want to get, not one int, not
two ints, but a whole bunch of ints.
Specifically n integers, were n might
be three, might be 100, might be 1,000.
The syntax, quite simply, is to
say, what data type do you want?
What do you want to call
that chunk of memory?
What do you want to call the grid
that looks like this pictorially?
>> And in brackets here, you say
how big you want the array to be.
And so earlier, when I said the
syntax is a little different here,
we're still using square brackets,
but when I'm declaring an array,
the number inside of the
square brackets means
how big do you want the array to be.
>> By contrast, when we were using s
bracket i a moment ago, s, a string,
is indeed an array of chars, but
when you're not declaring a variable,
as with this keyword here,
you're simply getting
a specific index, a specific
element from that array.
Once we know that, the rest
of this is straightforward.
If new I'm first going to print out
what's the age of person number i.
Where I just say person number one,
person number two, person number three.
>> And I'm just doing arithmetic,
so that like normal people,
we count from one for this
program, and not from zero.
Then I call getint, but I store
the answer in ages bracket i.
Which is the i'th age in the array.
So whereas last time we were treating
these boxes as chars for Zamyla's name,
and others.
Now, these boxes represent
32 bits, or four bytes
in which we can store
an int, an int, an int.
All of which, again,
are the same data type.
>> Now I do something silly,
like time passes, just
to justify writing this program.
And then down here, I again iterate
over the array saying a year from now,
person number one will
be something years old.
And to figure out that
math-- I mean, this
is not very complicated arithmetic--
I just add one to their age.
Just to demonstrate, again, this.
>> Just as I can index into a string, s,
so can I index into an array of ages,
like that there.
So where is this going to be taking us?
So we will see, ultimately, a
few things in the days to come.
One, all this time, when
writing your own programs,
like Mario, greedy, credit.
You've been typing the name of
the program and hitting Enter.
And then getting the user's input.
>> With getString, getInt,
getLongLong, or the like.
But it turns out that C supports
something called command line
arguments, which is going to let us
actually get at words that you type,
at the blinking prompt,
after your program's name.
>> So in the days to come, you
might type something like Caesar,
or ./caesar number 13, thereafter.
We'll see how that works.
Because indeed, in
problem set two, we're
going to introduce you
to a little something
reminiscent of Ralphie's
challenge earlier of cartography.
The art of scrambling information.
This, in fact, is very
reminiscent of what Ralphie did.
>> This is an example of an encryption
algorithm called rot13, R-O-T 13.
Which simply means rotate the
letters in the alphabet 13 places.
And if you do that, you'll see now
what is, perhaps, a familiar phrase.
But the way we're going to use
this, ultimately, is more generally.
>> In P set two, in the standard edition,
you'll implement a couple of ciphers,
one called Caesar, one called Vigenere.
Both of them are rotational
ciphers, in that somehow you
turn one letter into a different letter.
And Caesar is super simple.
You add one, you add 13,
or some number up to 26.
Vigenere does that on
a per letter basis.
So Vigenere, as you'll see
in the spec, is more secure.
>> But at the end of the day what
you'll be implementing and P set two,
is that key that you use both
for encryption and decryption.
Referring to the process of turning
plain text, some original message,
into cypher text, which
is something encrypted.
And then decrypting it again.
>> In the hacker edition,
meanwhile, you'll be
tasked with something similar
in spirit, where we'll give you
a file, from a typical Linux, or
Mac, or Unix computer called etsy
password, which contains a whole
bunch of usernames and passwords.
And those passwords have all
been encrypted, or hashed,
so to speak, more properly
as you'll see in the spec.
>> And the hacker edition will challenge
you with taking an input like this,
and cracking the password.
That is, figuring out what the
human's password actually was.
Because, indeed, passwords are
generally not stored in the clear,
and generally passwords
should be hard to guess.
That's not often the case.
>> And what I thought we'd do is
conclude with a couple minutes
glance at a particularly
poor choice of passwords
from a film you might recall fondly.
And if not, you should rent.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -Helmet, you fiend, what's going on?
What are you doing to my daughter?
>> -Permit me to introduce the
brilliant young plastic surgeon,
Doctor Phillip Schlotkin.
The greatest nose job man in the
entire universe and Beverly Hills.
>> -Your Highness.
>> -Nose job?
I don't understand.
She's already had a nose job.
It was her sweet 16 present.
>> -No, it's not what you think.
It's much, much worse.
If you do not give me the
combination to the air shield,
doctor Schlotkin will give your
daughter back her old nose.
-[GASPS] Nooooooooooooo.
Where did you get that?
>> -All right.
I'll tell, I'll tell.
>> -No, Daddy, no.
You mustn't.
>> -You're right my dear.
I'll miss your new nose.
But I will not tell them the
combination no matter what.
>> -Very well.
Doctor Schlotkin, do your worst.
>> -My pleasure.
>> -No!
Wait, wait.
I'll tell.
>> -I knew it would work.
All right, give it to me.
>> -The combination is one.
>> -One.
-Two.
-Three.
-Four.
-Five.
-So the combination is one,
two, three, four, five.
That's the stupidest combination
I ever hear in my life.
That's the kind of thing an
idiot would have on his luggage.
>> -Thank you, your highness.
>> [REMOTE CLICKS]
>> -What did you do?
>> -I turned off the wall.
>> -No, you didn't, you
turned off the whole movie.
>> -I must've pressed the wrong button.
>> -Well, put it back on!
Put the movie back on!
>> -Yes, sir!
Yes, sir.
-Let's go, Arnold.
Come, Gretchen.
Of course you know I'll
have to bill you for this.
-Well?
Did it work?
Where's the king?
>> -It worked, sir, we
have the combination.
-Great.
Now we can take every last breath
of fresh air from planet Druidia.
What's the combination?
>> -One, two, three, four, five.
>> -One, two, three, four, five?
-Yes.
-That's amazing.
I've got the same
combination on my luggage.
Prepare Spaceball 1 for
immediate departure.
>> -Yes, sir.
>> -And change the
combination on my luggage.
[DOOR CLOSING SOUND]
[CLINK OF DOORS HITTING HELMET]
-Ahh.
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: That's it for
CS50, we'll see you next week.
NARRATOR: And now, Deep
Thoughts, by Daven Farnham.
>> DAVEN FARNHAM: Coding in C is
so much harder than Scratch.
printf, Scratch was a lie.
>> [LAUGHTER SOUNDBITE]