>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, and this
is the end of Week Four.
And one of the topics today
is that of digital forensics,
the art of recovering information.
And indeed, even though
you're in the midst
right now of Peace at Three
and Breakout, next week,
the focus will be on
precisely this domain.
>> So one of the coolest jobs I ever
had was back in graduate school,
when I was working for the local
Middlesex County District Attorney's
office, doing forensics work.
So essentially, the Massachusetts
State Police, on occasion,
when working on cases would
bring in things like hard drives
and floppy disks and
memory cards and the like.
And they would hand them
to me and my mentor,
and our goal was to find evidence,
if there was any, on these media.
Now, you might have seen glimpses
of this world of forensics
in the media, TV and movies.
But the job I had, and
daresay that world,
is not quite like you would see it.
Let's take a look at what
you've probably seen.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-OK.
Now, let's get a good look at you.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> -Hold it.
Run that back.
>> -Wait a minute.
Go right.
-There.
Freeze that.
-Full-screen.
>> -OK.
Freeze that.
-Tighten up on that, will you?
>> -Vector in on that
guy by the back wheel.
>> -Zoom in right here on this spot.
>> -With the right equipment, the
image can be enlarged and sharpened.
>> -What's that?
>> -It's an enhancement program.
>> -Can you clear that up any?
>> -I don't know.
Let's enhance it.
>> -Enhance Section A6.
I enhanced the detail, and--
-I think there's enough to enhance.
Release it to my screen.
>> -I enhanced the reflection in her eye.
-Let's run this through
video enhancement.
>> -Edgar, can you enhance this?
>> -Hang on.
>> -I've been working on this reflection.
>> -There's someone's reflection.
>> -Reflection.
-There's a reflection of the man's face.
>> -The reflection!
-There's a reflection.
-Zoom in on the mirror.
You can see a reflection.
>> -Can you enhance the image from here?
-Can you enhance it?
-Can we enhance this?
-Hold on a second.
I'll enhance.
-Zoom in on the door.
-Times 10.
-Zoom.
-Move in.
-More.
-Wait, stop.
-Stop.
-Pause it.
-Rotate us 75 degrees
around the vertical, please.
>> -Stop.
Go back to the part
about the door again.
>> -Got an image enhancer that can bitmap?
>> -Maybe we can use the Pradeep Singh
method to see into the windows.
>> -The software is state of the art.
>> -The eigenvalue is off.
>> -With the right
combination of algorithms--
>> -He's taken illumination
algorithms to the next level,
and I can use them to
enhance this photograph.
>> -Lock on and enlarge the z-axis.
>> -Enhance.
Enhance.
-Enhance.
-Freeze and enhance.
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: So those are
all words, but they were not
used in sentences correctly.
And indeed in the future, any time,
please, you hear someone say the word,
"enhance," chuckle just a little bit.
Because when you try to enhance,
for instance, this is what happens.
>> So here's a gorgeous photo.
This is CS50's own Daven.
And suppose that we wanted to
focus in on the twinkle in his eye,
or the reflection of the
bad guy that was clearly
captured by the security camera.
This is what happens when
you zoom in on an image that
has only a finite number
of bits associated with it.
>> That is what you would get.
And indeed, in Daven's eye
is but four, maybe six pixels
that compose exactly what
was glimmering there.
So Problem Set Four will ultimately have
you explore this world, particularly
by nature of something
we call file i/o, where
i/o is just a fancy way of
saying input and output.
>> So thus far, all of the interactions
we've had with a computer
have been largely with your
keyboard and the screen,
but not so much with the hard disk,
or saving of files beyond the ones you
yourself write.
Your programs thus far have
not been creating, and saving,
and updating their own files.
>> Well, what's a file?
Well, something like a JPEG.
This is an image you might
have or upload to Facebook,
or see anywhere on the web.
Indeed, that photo we just
saw of Daven was a JPEG.
And what's interesting
about files like JPEGs
is that they can be identified,
typically, by certain patterns of bits.
>> In other words, what is it that
distinguishes a JPEG from a GIF
from a PING from a Word
document from an Excel file?
Well, it's just different
patterns of bits.
And those different patterns are
usually at the start of those files.
>> So that when your computer opens a Word
doc, or when a computer opens a JPEG,
it looks typically at the
first several bits in the file.
And if it recognizes a pattern,
it says, oh, this is an image.
Let me display it to
the user as a graphic.
Or, oh, this looks like a Word doc.
Let me show it to the user as an essay.
>> So for instance, JPEGs,
it turns out, are
fairly sophisticated
underneath the hood.
But the first three bytes in most every
JPEG start with these three numbers.
So byte zero, one, and two are, in
most every JPEG, 255, then the number
216, then the number 255.
>> And what you'll be able
to start doing next week
is actually poking underneath
the hood of files like JPEGs
and like bitmap files, and seeing
what's always been there for as long
as you've been using a computer.
>> But what's there is not typically
written like decimal numbers like this.
Computer scientists don't
tend to speak in decimal.
They don't really speak in binary.
Typically, when we want
to express numbers,
we actually use hexadecimal,
which you may recall
from, say, Problem Set
One, which challenged
you to think about a different system.
>> We, of course, are familiar
with decimal, zero through nine.
We talked about binary.
And we don't really have
to use that much here
on out, because computers will use that.
But programmers will very
often, but not always,
use hexadecimal, which just means
you have 16 letters in your alphabet,
as opposed to two or 10.
>> So how do you count to higher
than nine in hexadecimal?
You go 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
a, b, c, d, e, f, just by convention.
But what's key is that each
of these is a single symbol.
There is no 10.
There is no 11, per se, because each
of your digits, just like in decimal
and just like in binary, should just
be a single character, by convention.
>> So that then is the alphabet we have
at our disposal for hexadecimal.
So what does a JPEG look like if you
were to write out those first three
bytes not as decimal but,
for instance, as hexadecimal?
And why is hex even all that useful?
>> Well, a quick look at an example.
So if I write out the bits that
represent these decimal numbers--
this might be a little rusty
now from a few weeks back,
but the left one and the
right one are pretty easy.
255 was the biggest number we
could represent with eight bits.
It was all ones.
So the only one that's mildly
interesting is the middle one.
And if you kind of do out the
math, you will deduce that, indeed,
that pattern of one and
zeros represents 216.
So let's just stipulate for
now that these are correct.
But why is this interesting?
>> Well, a byte, of course, is eight bits.
And it turns out that if you think
of a byte as two chunks of four bits,
like this.
Let me just add some space.
So before, after.
I've just added some white space
for visualization's sake here.
How might we now represent in,
say, hexadecimal each quad of bits,
each set of four bits?
>> So for instance, on the left
now, we have 1111 in binary.
What is that number in decimal,
if you do out the math?
You have the ones place, the twos place,
the fours place, and the eights place.
>> AUDIENCE: 15.
DAVID J. MALAN: It's 15.
So if we do eight plus four
plus two plus one, we get 15.
So I could write down 15 below
1111, but the whole point here
is hexadecimal, not decimal.
So instead of writing down 15, 1-5,
I'm going to write that in hex,
which if you think back, if you have
zero through f, what is 15 going to be?
AUDIENCE: f.
DAVID J. MALAN: So it turns out it's f.
And you can work that out by saying,
well, if a is 10, then OK, f is 15.
So indeed, we could rewrite
this same set of numbers as f f.
And then if we do a bit of math,
we'll deduce that that's d.
Eight is pretty easy, because we
have a one in the eights place.
And then, we have a couple more f f's.
>> So what humans tend to do by convention
when they use hexadecimal is they just
write this a little more succinctly,
get rid of most of that white space.
And just to be super clear to
readers that this is hexadecimal,
the simple convention among
humans is you write zero
x, which has no meaning other
than a visual identifier of,
here comes a hex number.
>> And then, you put the two digits, f
f in this case, then d a, then f f.
So long story short,
hexadecimal just tends
to be useful because each of its
digits, zero through f, perfectly lines
up with a pattern of four bits.
>> So if you have two hexadecimal digits,
zero through F, again and again,
that gives you perfectly
eight bits or one byte.
So that's why it tends to
be conventionally useful.
There's no intellectual
content really beyond that,
other than its actual utility.
>> Now JPEGs aren't the only
file formats for graphics.
You might recall that there are
files like this in the world,
at least from a few years back.
>> So this was actually
installed in Windows XP
on millions of PCs around the world.
And this was a bitmap file, BMP.
And a bitmap file, as you'll see next
week, just means a pattern of dots,
pixels as they're called,
a map on bits, really.
>> So what's interesting, though,
about this file format, BMP, is
that underneath the hood, it
has more than just three bytes
that compose its header, so
to speak, the first few bites.
It actually looks a little
complicated at first glance.
And you'll see this in the P set.
And getting something
particular out of this now
isn't so important, as just the fact
that at the beginning of every bitmap
file, a graphical format,
there's a whole bunch of numbers.
>> Now Microsoft, the
author of this format,
tends to call those
things not ints and chars
and floats but words and d
words and longs and bytes.
So they're just different data types.
They're different names
for the same thing.
But you'll see that in P Set Four.
>> But this is only to say that if a human
double-clicks some .BMP file on his
or her hard drive, and a window opens
up showing him or her that image,
that happened because the operating
system presumably noticed not only
the .BMP file extension
in the file name,
but also the fact that there's some
convention to the pattern of bits
at the very beginning
of that bitmap file.
>> But let's now focus on
such a complicated file,
but instead on something like this.
Suppose here in GEdit, I
just have the beginnings
of a program that's pretty simple.
I've got some includes up top.
Now I've got #include "structs.h" but
I'll come back to that in a moment.
But this is useful for now.
So this is a program
that's going to implement
like the registrar's database.
So a database of students,
and every student in the world
has a name and a house and probably some
other stuff, but we'll keep it simple.
Every student has a name and a house.
>> So if I wanted to write a
program whose purpose in life
was just to iterate from
zero on up to three,
if there's three students
at Harvard University.
And I just want to get, using GetString,
each student's name and house,
and then just print those out.
>> This is sort of like Week
One, Week Two stuff now,
where I just want a for
loop or something like that.
And I want to call GetString a few
times, and then print f a few times.
So how might I do this, though,
when both a name and a house
are involved for each student?
>> So my first instinct might
be to do something like this.
I might first say, well, give me,
say, an array of strings called names.
And I don't want a hardcode three here.
What do I want to put there?
So STUDENTS, because that's just
a constant declared at the top,
just so I don't have to hardcode
three in multiple places.
This way, I can change it one place,
and it affects a change everywhere.
And then, I might do
string houses STUDENTS.
>> And now, I might do something like
for (int i = 0; i < STUDENTS; i++.
So I'm typing fast, but this is
probably familiar syntax now.
>> And now, this was more recent.
If I want to put in the i-th
student's name, I think I do this.
And then, not names
but houses bracket i.
I do this, GetString, and let
me go back and fix this line.
Agree?
Disagree?
It's not very user-friendly.
I haven't told the user what to do.
>> But now, if I also
wanted to later, let's
say, print these things
out-- so TODO later.
I'm going to do more with
this-- this arguably is
a correct implementation of
getting names and houses, three
of them total of each, from a user.
>> But this is not very good design, right?
What if a student has not just a name
and a house, but also an ID number,
and a telephone number,
and an email address,
and maybe a home page, and
maybe a Twitter handle,
and any number of other details
associated with a student or a person,
more generally.
How would we begin to add
functionality to this program?
>> Well, I feel like the simplest way might
be to do something like, let's say,
int ids STUDENTS.
So I can put all their IDs in there.
And then, for something
like phone numbers,
I'm not sure how to
represent that just yet.
So let's go ahead and just call
this twitters STUDENTS, which
is a little strange, but--
and a bunch more fields.
>> I've started to effectively
copy and paste here.
And this is going to grow pretty
unwieldy pretty quickly, right?
Wouldn't it be nice if there were
in the world a data structure known
not as an int or a string, but something
higher level, an abstraction, so
to speak, known as a student?
C did not come with built-in
functionality for students,
but what if I wanted to give it such?
>> Well, it turns out, I'm going to
open a file called structs.h here,
and you can do exactly that.
And we're going to start doing this now.
And underneath the hood of P Set Three,
you've already been doing this now.
There is no such thing as a g rect or
a g oval in the programming language C.
>> Folks at Stanford implemented those
data types by using this approach here,
declaring their own new data
types using a new keyword
called struct and another
one called typedef.
And indeed, even though the syntax
looks a little different from stuff
we've seen before, in
principle, it's super simple.
>> This just means "define a type."
That's going to be a
structure, and a structure
is just like a container
for multiple things.
And that structure is going
to have a string called name,
and a string called house.
And let's call, just for convenience,
this whole data structure student.
>> So the moment you get to
the semicolon, you have now
created your own data
type called student
that now stands alongside int,
and float, and char, and string,
and g rect, and g oval, and any number
of other things people have invented.
>> So what's useful about this
now is that if I go back
to struct 0 and finish this
implementation, which I wrote
in advance here, notice that all
of the inevitable messiness that
was about to start happening as I added
phone numbers and twitters and all
these other things to
a student's definition,
now it's succinctly wrapped up
as just one array of students.
>> And each of those students now
has multiple things inside of it.
So that just leaves one question.
How do you get at the name,
and the house, and the ID,
and whatever else is
inside of the student?
Super simple, as well.
New syntax, but a simple idea.
>> You simply index into the array,
as we did last week and this.
And what's clearly the
new piece of syntax?
Just ., which means "go inside the
structure and get the field called
name, get the field called house,
get the field called student."
>> So in P Set Three, if you're
still working on that,
and most folks still
are, realize that as you
start using things like
g rects and g ovals
and other things that don't seem to
come from Week Zero, One, or Two,
realize that that's because Stanford
declared some new data types.
>> And indeed, that's exactly what we'll
do, as well, in P Set Four, when
we start to deal with things
like images, bitmaps, and more.
So that's just a teaser and a
mental model for what is to come.
Now, I procrastinated
a bit this morning.
I was kind of curious to see what
the Microsoft wallpaper actually
looks like today.
And it turns out someone in 2006
actually went to almost precisely
the same spot to photograph in reality
what looks like that these days.
The field is now a little overgrown.
>> So speaking now of images,
let's bring back Daven here
on the screen and Nicholas,
and just remind you
that if you'd like to join us for lunch
this Friday, head to our usual URL
here.
>> So where did we leave off on Monday?
We introduced this problem, right?
This was seemingly a correct
implementation of swap,
whereby you taking two ints,
one called a, one called b,
swap them, just like Laura did here
on stage with the milk and the water,
by using a temporary
variable, or an empty cup,
so that we could put b in a and a in
b without making a mess of things.
We used a variable.
It's called temp.
>> But what was the fundamental
problem with this code on Monday?
What was the problem here?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: It takes up more space.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Takes up more
space, because I'm using a variable,
and that's OK.
That is true, but I'm
going to say that's OK.
It's only 32 bits in the grand
scheme of things, so not a big deal.
Other thoughts?
AUDIENCE: It only swaps
the variables locally.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
It only swaps the variables locally.
Because any time you call a function--
when I had the trays from Annenberg
last time, you have main on the bottom.
As soon as you call a function called
swap, swap does not get x and y,
the original values.
What does swap get, did we claim?
AUDIENCE: Copies.
DAVID J. MALAN: So copies of them.
So it gets one and two, if you
recall the example from last time,
but a copy of one and two
that are successfully swapped.
But unfortunately in the end,
those values are still the same.
So we can see this with our
new friend, hopefully GDB,
that you or the TFs and Ca's have
been guiding you toward as follows.
>> So no swap recall looks like-- let's
open up this-- looks like this.
We initialized x to one, y to two.
Had a bunch of print f's.
But then, the key call
here was to swap, which
is exactly the code we
just saw a moment ago.
Which is correct at first
glance, but functionally,
this program does not work, because
it doesn't permanently swap x and y.
>> So let's see this, a quick warm
up here with GDB, a ./noswap.
A bunch of overwhelming information that
I'll get rid of with Control L for now.
And now, I'm going to
go ahead and run it.
And unfortunately, that
was not that useful.
It ran the program inside of this
program called GDB, a debugger,
but it didn't let me poke around.
>> So how can I actually pause
execution inside this program?
So break.
And I could break on any
line number, one, 10, 15.
But I can also break symbolically
by saying break main.
And that's going to set a break
point, apparently at line 16 in main.
And where is line 16?
Let's go up to the code
and go up to noswap.
And indeed, line 16 is the
very first in the program.
>> So now, if I go ahead and type
run this time, Enter, it paused.
So let's poke around.
Print x-- why is x zero?
And ignore the dollar sign.
That's just for fancier
usage of the program.
Why is x zero at the moment?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: It paused right before
line 16, not actually on line 16.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
GDB, by default, has paused
execution just before line 16.
So it hasn't executed, which
means x is of some unknown value.
And we got lucky that it's
something clean like zero.
So now if I type next,
now it executed 16.
It's waiting for me to execute 17.
Let me go ahead and print x.
It's one.
Let me go ahead and print y.
What should I see now?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: A little louder.
DAVID J. MALAN: Not quite a consensus.
So yes, we see some garbage value.
Now, y is 134514064 there.
Well, it's just some garbage value.
My program uses RAM
for different purposes.
There's other functions.
Other people wrote inside my computer.
So those bits have been used for
other values, and what I'm seeing
is the remnants of some
prior use of that memory.
>> So no big deal, because as soon
as I type next and then print y,
it's initialized to
the value that I want.
So now, let's go ahead a little faster.
N for next.
Let's do it again.
But I don't want to hit
it here, because if I
want to see what's going on inside
of swap, what's the command?
>> AUDIENCE: steps.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: steps.
So this steps me into a
function, rather than over it.
And now, it's a little cryptic
honestly, but this is just
telling me I'm in line 33 now.
And let's do this again.
Print temp.
Garbage value, negative this time,
but that's just still a garbage value.
So let's do next, print temp.
It's initialized to 1, which
was the value of x, aka a.
>> Now, where are our a and x coming from?
Well, notice in main, we
called these values x and y.
We then passed them to swap as follows.
X came first, comma y.
And then, swap could call them x and y.
But for clarity, it's
calling them a and b.
But a and b are now going to be
copies of x and y, respectively.
>> So if I go back to GDB, temp
is now one and a is now one.
But if I do next and now do print
a, a has already been moved over.
The milk has been poured into the former
orange juice's glass, or vice versa.
>> And if I do next again, and now
if I print out as a sanity check,
a is still two, but b is now one.
Frankly, it's still there.
I don't care what temp is.
But as soon as I now type, let's say,
continue to go back, now I'm at the end
the program.
And unfortunately, x is
still one and y is still two.
>> So what was the utility of GDB there?
It didn't help me fix
the problem per se,
but it hopefully help me
understand it by realizing
that yes, my logic is right, but
my code is not ultimately having
a permanent impact.
So that's a problem we're
going to now solve today.
>> But let's get there by way of this.
String is a lie.
It, too, not a data type
that exists in C. It's
been a synonym for some
time for something else,
and we can reveal that as follows.
>> Let me go ahead and open up
a program called compare-0.
And rather than type this one out,
we'll start to walk through the code
I already wrote, but
it's only a few lines.
So this is compare-0.
And the first thing I'm doing
is getting a line of text.
>> But notice what I'm
doing for the first time.
What is different clearly about line 21?
Actually, wait a minute.
This is copy two.
That is not even the right program.
All right, spoiler alert.
All right, so never mind that.
That's the answer to a future question.
>> Here is compare-0, and I'm
about to get a line of text.
Program's much simpler.
So this is straightforward.
This is like Week One, Week Two stuff
at the moment. string s = GetString.
Now, I say it again down here.
string t = GetString.
And then, the last thing in this
program, as its name suggests,
is I'm going to try to compare them.
>> So if s, the first string,
equals = t, then I'm
going to say you type the same thing.
Else, I'm going to say
you type different things.
So let's compile and run this program.
So make compare zero.
Looks good.
No compilation errors.
>> Let me go ahead now
and type ./compare-0.
Let me go ahead and say something
:Daven and something :Rob.
And I type different things.
So far, so good.
Program seems to be correct.
>> But let's run it again.
Say something: Gabe.
All right.
Maybe I hit space bar
or something funky.
Let's do it again.
So Zamyla.
Zamyla.
Different things.
So what is going on?
>> So we have these two lines of
code, GetString being called twice.
And then, I'm simply
trying to compare s and t.
But what really then is going on?
Well, my handwriting's about to
butcher this example somewhat.
And let's actually throw
this up over here, as well.
>> So we have a line like
string s = GetString.
So that's simply the first
interesting line from that program.
But what all this time has been
going on underneath the hood?
Well, on the left-hand side is string,
which is some type of variable,
and it's called s.
So I know that this is using memory,
or RAM, in my computer somehow.
So I'm going to abstractly
draw that as a square.
32 bits, it turns out, but
more on that in the future.
And then, what's going on over here?
>> Well, GetString obviously
gets a string from the user.
And GetString got
Zamyla or Gabe or Daven.
So let's choose the first
of those, which was Daven.
So effectively, what GetString got
me in that first case was D-a-v-e-n.
And then, what else did
it give me secretly?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
the /0 or null character.
So it effectively gave me a string.
But we already know from previous
looks that a string is just an array
of characters, and it's terminated by
this special sentinel character, /0.
>> But if this is true
and this is a square,
this is clearly a much bigger rectangle.
And indeed, this is,
I claim, only 32 bits.
And this is clearly more than 32
bits, because this is probably
eight plus eight plus eight
plus eight plus eight,
just because of bytes in ASCII.
How the heck are we going to fit
Daven into this little box here?
>> Well, what is GetString actually doing?
Well, this grid here represents
my computer's memory or RAM.
So let's arbitrarily say that if
each of these represents a byte,
then we can think of each
byte as having an address,
like 33 Oxford Street, or 34
Oxford Street, or 35 Oxford Street.
>> So just like homes have addresses
and buildings have addresses,
so do individual bytes of
memory have addresses or numbers
that uniquely identify them.
Now, this is arbitrary.
But to keep it simple, I'm going to
use hexadecimal just by convention,
but the 0x means nothing other
than "this is hexadecimal."
and I'm going to claim that the
"D" ends up at Byte One in memory.
>> I got nothing else going on in
memory, so Daven got the first spot
at Byte One.
This, then, is going to be 0x2.
This is going to 0x3.
This is going to be 0x4.
This is going to 0x5.
This is going to be 0x6.
>> But once you start thinking
about what the computer's doing
underneath the hood,
you can start to infer
how you, some years ago, would
have implemented C itself.
What is GetString probably
returning-- because it
feels like it's not
returning Daven, per se,
because he's surely not going
to fit in this little box--
so what is GetString probably returning?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: The location of Daven.
And it's been doing this
ever since Week One.
What GetString is really
returning is not a string, per se.
That's one of the little white lies.
It's returning the address of the
string in memory, the unique address.
Daven lives at 33 Oxford Street.
But more succinctly, Gavin lives
at 0x1, Address Number One.
>> So what gets put in this
little box then, to be clear,
is just the address of that string.
So all this time, this
has been going on.
But what this hints at
now is that if all s has
is a number inside of it, who's
to stop you, the programmer,
from putting any number in
any variable and just jumping
to that chunk of memory?
And indeed, we'll see
that's a threat next time.
>> But for now, this feels insufficient.
If I say, get me a
string, you give me Daven.
But you don't really give me Daven.
All you give me is Daven's address.
How do I then know for sure
where Daven begins and ends--
the story's getting weird--
where Daven begins and ends,
and then, the next
string in memory starts?
>> Well, if you're handing
me the beginning of Daven,
essentially, how do I know
where the end of his name is?
That special null character, which
is all the more important now
if strings underneath the
hood are simply identified
uniquely by their location in memory.
So all this time, that's
what's been going on.
>> So when we look now at
the code here, explain
if you would the bug in line 26.
Why is Zamyla and Zamyla different?
Why is Gabe and Gabe different?
Yeah, in back.
>> AUDIENCE: They have different addresses.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Simply because
they have different addresses.
Because when you call GetString
again, which I'll do quickly here,
if this is the second line, string
t, as I did in that program,
equals another call to GetString.
The next time I call
GetString, I'm going
to get a different chunk of memory.
>> GetString is allowed
to ask the operating
system for more and more memory.
It's not going to reuse the same
six bytes every single time.
It's going to get a new
chunk of memory, which
means t is going to get
some other value over here.
>> So when I do s equals =
t, you're not comparing
D against this and A against
this and V against this.
You're comparing this
against this, which
frankly is pretty useful-- useless--
is pretty useless, because who really
cares where the strings are in memory?
>> And indeed, we haven't.
And we're not going to
start particularly caring.
Only to the extent that bugs can arise
and security threats can arise will
we actually start to care about this.
So let's fix this problem.
Turns out, you fix it super simply.
>> And let's actually, before I
reveal that again, what would
you do if in a CS50 class,
and you had to implement
a comparison against two strings.
You clearly can't just use s equals = t.
But just logically, how
would you compare this string
against this string using C code?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Just do the
for loop [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
Just use a for loop or a
while loop or whatever.
But just apply the basic idea that if
this is a chunk of memory or an array
and this is, iterate over
both at the same time.
And just compare the letters.
>> And you've got to be a
little careful, because you
don't want one finger
to go past the other
because one string is
longer than the other.
So you're going to want to check for
this special value at the end, null.
But it really is, in the
end, as simple as that.
And frankly, we don't need
to reinvent that wheel.
Here is Version Two.
And what I'm going to say here is that
instead of comparing s equals = t,
I'm instead going to say, if string
comparison of s comma t equals = 0.
Now, what is string compare?
>> It turns out, it's a function that
comes with C, whose purpose in life
is to compare two strings.
And stir compare, if we read its
man page or documentation or CS50
reference, it will
simply tell you that stir
compare returns either a negative
number or a positive number or zero,
where zero means they're equal.
>> So just conjecture.
What might it mean if
stir compare returns
negative value or positive value?
AUDIENCE: Greater than or less than.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
greater than or less than.
So if you wanted to sort a whole
bunch of strings in a dictionary--
as we will eventually down the road--
perfect function to use potentially,
because it's going to do that
comparison of strings for you, and tell
you does a comes before b, or does
b come before a alphabetically.
We can do exactly that.
>> And notice I did one other
thing in this example.
What else has changed higher
up in this main function?
Char*.
And this is that other white lie.
All this time, when you've
been writing string,
we have been secretly rewriting
string as char* so that clang actually
understands you.
>> In other words, in CS50.h
and as we'll eventually see,
we made a synonym called string
that's the same thing as char*.
And for now, know only that the
*, in this context, at least,
means the address.
>> The address of what?
Well, the fact that I said
char*, and not int* or float*,
means that char* is
the address of a char.
So this little box here, aka
string, is really of type char*,
which is simply a fancy way of saying,
in this box will go an address.
And what does that address refer to?
Apparently, a char.
>> But we could absolutely
have int* and other things.
But for now, char* is really the most
straightforward and one of interest.
So this problem is going
to rise, though, again.
>> Suppose I open up this program.
Let's see if now we can predict
what's wrong with this code.
So in this program, copy-0, I'm
going to go ahead and again call
GetString and store the value in s.
>> And then, why am I doing this,
just as a reminder from weeks past?
We did say that GetString
sometimes returns null.
What does it mean if
GetString returns null?
Something went wrong.
It probably means the string is too
big, the computer's out of memory.
It happens super, super, super
rarely, but it could happen.
We want to check for it,
and that's all we're doing.
>> Because we'll see now, if you don't
start checking habitually for things
like null, you might
actually start to go
to addresses in memory that are invalid.
And you're going to start inducing
more and more segmentation faults.
Or in a Mac or a PC, just
causing a computer to hang
or a program to freeze, potentially.
>> So now, I claim in copy-0.c, that I
am going to copy these strings by way
of line 28.
And then, I'm going
to claim at the bottom
here that I'm going
to change one of them.
>> So notice this.
I'm calling our old friend strlen.
And just explain in English
what this line 34 is doing?
What does t bracket 0
represent on the left.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: First character of t?
DAVID J. MALAN: First character of t.
That's it.
First character of t, I want
to assign the uppercase version
of the first character in t.
So this is capitalizing
the first letter.
And then, the very last thing I do
in this program is I claim here's
the original, s, and here's the copy, t.
>> But based on the story we just
told about what strings really are,
what is line 28 really
doing, and what is
the resulting bug going
to be on the screen?
>> So first, the first question, 28.
What is string t = s really doing?
If we have on the left-hand
side here string t = s;
that gives me one box
here and one box here.
And suppose this address is 0x,
let's say, 50 this time, arbitrarily.
What does string t = s
do underneath the hood?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It stores the memory
address there, so 0x50 goes there.
So if now, I go to the first
character in t and uppercase it,
what am I effectively doing to s?
I'm really doing the same thing, right?
Because if Address 0x50-- and just, I
don't have much room on the board here,
but assume that this is 0x50 down here,
somewhere in my computer's memory.
>> And I have, for instance, gabe
in lowercase here, like this.
And I have said t bracket
0 gets capitalized.
Well, t bracket 0 is
the first letter in t.
So little g is going to
become big G. But the problem
is, what does s also point to?
>> AUDIENCE: The same.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: The same exact thing.
So a simple explanation perhaps,
even if the syntax is a little weird.
So let's do this.
Make copy-0 and then ./copy-0.
Say something: Gabe.
And unfortunately, both of
them have now been capitalized,
but for that underlying
reason that we're simply
now dealing with addresses.
>> So how do we begin to
address-- no pun intended--
how do we begin to address
this particular problem?
Well, in copy1.c, things are going
to get a little more complicated.
But I would claim a
conceptually simple solution.
>> So hard to get at first glance.
Not going to be easy for the first
time you type it out, perhaps,
but if the problem is that
simply doing t = s just
copies the address, what,
again if I can pick on you,
is going to be the solution
for actually copying a string?
>> AUDIENCE: We'll probably
use a loop again.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So we're going to need a loop again.
And because if we want to copy
a string s into another string,
we probably want to do it
character by character.
But the problem is, if
this is originally s,
now we need to start explicitly
allocating memory for t.
>> In other words, let's
redraw this one last time.
If this is string s = GetString.
And let's put this up here, as well.
This is GetString.
And then, the picture for something
like that is going to be as before,
g-a-b-e-/0.
That looks a little something like this.
And s therefore, we call this 0x50,
and that's going to be 51, 52.
>> So this is 0x50.
And then, I do string t.
In memory, that's just going to
give me a little square like this.
So what's the key step now?
If I want to copy s into t, what
blank do we need to fill in here?
Or what do we need to
do at a high level?
Yeah?
Someone?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: We need to [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, we
need to fill in this blank.
I can't copy and then
capitalize Gabe's name
until I ask the operating system
for another chunk of memory
that's at least as big as the original.
So that leaves us with a question.
>> How do I ask the operating system not
just for a simple little pointer--
as this is called, an
address, a pointer-- not
for a simple little box
like this called a string?
How do I ask the operating
system for a big chunk of memory?
Thus far, I've only gotten that back
indirectly by calling GetString.
So how is GetString
even getting its memory?
>> Well, it turns out that there's
this other function here
that we'll now start to use.
Now, this looks way more cryptic than--
and I am the only one who can see it--
this line looks way more cryptic
then it should at first glance.
But let's tease it apart.
>> On the left-hand side, I have char* t.
So in English, let's start to formulate
proper sentences in technical jargon.
So this is allocating a
variable of type char* called t.
Now, what does that really mean?
>> Well, that means, what am I going
to put in this variable called t?
An address of a char.
So that's just the simpler,
more reasonable way
of describing the left-hand side.
So that creates this box here only.
So the right-hand side,
presumably, is going
to allocate that bigger
chunk of memory how?
So let's tease this apart.
>> It's overwhelming at first glance,
but what's going on inside here?
First, there's malloc, which
is apparently our new friend,
"memory allocate."
So this is the argument being passed
into it, so it's a pretty big argument.
So let's tease this apart.
>> strlen of s, of course, represents the--
AUDIENCE: The number of characters.
DAVID J. MALAN: Just the
number of characters in s.
So the length of s, the original string.
So G-a-b-e.
So it's probably four in this case.
Why am I doing +1 after
calling strlen of s?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: For that
special null character.
If you ask me what's the length of
Gabe's name, I am going to say four.
Underneath the hood, though, I need
that fifth byte for the null character.
So that's why I'm doing the +1.
>> Now just in case you are running this
program on a computer other than, say,
the CS50 appliance,
where the size of a char
might be different
from my own computer--
turns out that I can call this
operator sizeof, just ask the computer,
what is the size of a
char on this computer?
>> And by multiplying five in this
example by the size of a char, which
on most computers will
just be one, malloc
is going to allocate for me this big
chunk of memory over here on the right.
And it's going to return--
it is a function-- so it's
going to return to me what?
AUDIENCE: The address?
DAVID J. MALAN: The address of what?
AUDIENCE: Of the memory it allocated?
DAVID J. MALAN: Of the
memory it allocated.
So I have no idea, frankly,
where this is going to end up.
I'm going to propose that
it's going to end up at 0x88.
Completely arbitrary, but
somewhere other than 0x50,
because the operating system, what
Windows and Mac OS do for me, is
make sure that it's giving
me different chunks of RAM.
>> So this is the value where this
chunk of memory might end up.
So this is what ends up in here, 0x88.
So now clearly, I can understand
that this is not the same as this,
because they're pointing at
different chunks of memory.
So if I now actually want to copy this
in, let's do your proposed solution.
>> Let's just go, create a for loop,
and do t bracket i gets s bracket i.
Because now I can use
this array-like notation,
because even though malloc very
generically allocates me memory,
memory is just contiguous bytes.
Byte, byte, byte, back to back to back.
>> I can surely as a programmer
treat it as an array, which
means I can use this finally familiar
notation of just some square brackets.
>> So let me pause there, because
this is a lot all at once, even
though the basic idea to recap
is that string, all this time,
is not a new data type per se.
It's just a so-called pointer,
an address of a character,
which just means it's a number
that by human convention
we tend to write as 0x something.
>> But it's just a number,
like 33 Oxford Street,
which happens to be the
CS building's address.
Any questions on these details?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Why do we check
for t equal to null?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Why do we
check for t equal to null?
If we read the documentation--
great question-- for malloc,
it's going to say in fine print,
sometimes malloc might return null,
just like GetString.
And indeed, GetString returns null
if, in turn, malloc returns null,
because GetString uses malloc.
>> And that might happen if the OS,
Mac OS, Windows, whatever, is simply
out of memory for you.
So that's what happened there.
>> And let me reveal one other thing
that might just blow your mind
or completely be too far over the line.
But let me pull up the
same for loop for copying,
which a moment ago, recall was
this. t bracket i gets s bracket i.
>> Nice and user-friendly.
Feels like Week Two again.
But this version actually can be
rewritten as this, which looks cryptic.
It's a technique called pointer
arithmetic, address arithmetic.
But why does this work?
>> Now annoyingly, the
authors of C decided to use
the * symbol for different purposes.
We've seen it used once already,
char*, which means "give me a variable
that's going to contain
the address of a char."
So char* in that context
means "give me a variable."
>> Unfortunately, if you use the * without
a word in front of it, like char,
it's now called the
dereference operator.
And we'll see more of this before long.
But it just means "go there."
It's like saying, if someone handed me
on a piece of paper "33 Oxford Street,"
if I do "*33 Oxford Street," that means
"go down the road to the CS building."
>> So * just means go there if
there's no word in front of it.
So what is t, to be clear?
t is the address of the chunk of
memory that was given back to me.
s is the address of what, to be clear,
in the example we've been discussing,
of lowercase gabe?
s is the address of--
AUDIENCE: The string.
DAVID J. MALAN: Of Gabe's original name.
So it's the address of
this chunk of memory.
So if I say t + i-- i, notice,
is just our old friend.
It's just an index variable
that's iterating from zero on up
to the length of the string s.
So it's going to be zero, then one,
then two, then three, then four.
So let's assemble these new
Scratch-like puzzle pieces, if you will,
even though, again, the syntax
is far more arcane than Scratch.
So t is an address +
i is going to give me
a number, because these are all
numbers that we've been drawing as hex.
But they're just numbers.
>> So if the address of t we said
was 0x88, what's 0x88 plus zero.
Even if you're not comfortable
with hex yet, take a guess.
>> AUDIENCE: The original.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Still 0x88.
So what does * 0x88 mean?
It means, "go there" which means
effectively, "put your finger here."
And now on the right-hand side of
this expression, * and then in parens,
s + i means s, which is the
address up here of the little g.
s + 0 is, of course, s, whatever s is.
>> So now, it's *s, which just like *33
Oxford Street means go to the address
s.
So here's this finger, right hand.
So what am I going to copy into what?
The thing on the right, which is
gabe, little g here, into here.
>> And so the effect of that
first iteration of the loop,
as you proposed, even though it looks
crazy more complicated than anything
we've seen before, is simply saying
go here and copy that character here.
It's giving you a map to both locations.
>> And we'll see far more of this.
But for now, the hope is just to
introduce some of these basic ideas.
And indeed, let's look at
one final program here,
and then the promised claymation,
which will make everything all right.
All right.
So let me open up-- there we go.
So let me-- we'll come back
to this picture before long.
Let me open up this final example here.
>> So here is a super, super
program that accomplishes
nothing in life that does the following.
It first declares two variables, x
and y, that are not numbers this time,
per se.
They're not integers, per se.
They are apparently int*.
So just anyone, what does it mean
if your data type, your variable,
is of type int* star?
That's the address of an int.
>> So I've no idea where it is yet.
It just means "put, eventually,
the address of an int here."
0x50, 0x88, wherever it is in
memory, an address is going there.
And that's what y is
going to be, as well.
>> If I now say x = malloc(sizeof(int)),
this is a fancy way of saying,
hey operating system, via malloc,
give me enough memory for the size
of an int, which is probably
going to be 32 bits or four bytes.
>> So what does malloc return?
Malloc returns an address.
So what's going to get stored in x?
The address of the chunk of
memory, the four bytes, that malloc
just found for me by asking
the operating system.
>> Now meanwhile, line
four here, the *x = 42.
Just to be clear,
what's going down there?
On the left-hand side, *x.
that's like *33 Oxford Street.
So *x means what?
>> AUDIENCE: Go to.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Go to that address.
Wherever that chunk of
memory is, go to it.
And put what there, obviously?
AUDIENCE: 42.
DAVID J. MALAN: 42.
All right, *y, same idea.
Go to the address in y.
Put the number 13 there,
but what is y at the moment?
AUDIENCE: There is no memory for y.
DAVID J. MALAN: There
is no memory for y.
So what does y probably
contain, as we've been saying?
>> AUDIENCE: Garbage.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Some garbage value.
Now, garbage value is still a number.
It can still be mistaken for an address.
It's as though someone
scribbled something down,
and I misinterpreted it as meaning
some building down the street.
And if you just try to go into
some building you don't own,
or some chunk of memory you haven't
been given, bad things might happen.
Computer might crash, or some other
undetermined behavior might happen.
>> So the intro, then, to Binky is this.
I still remember, 20
some odd years later,
where I was when I finally
understood pointers.
>> Which is to say, if you
leave here in three minutes
and think I don't
understand pointers, realize
I have remembered for 20
years for some crazy reason
when and why it finally sunk
in, sitting with my teaching
fellow, Nishat Mehta in the
back of Eliot Dining Hall.
Now, I've remembered
this because this was
one of the topics I, in
particular, struggled with.
And then, it finally clicked,
like I dare say a lot of topics
eventually will.
And now, to make that feel all the
happier and all the more convincing,
let's take a final look in our
last three minutes here at Binky,
from our friend, Nick
Parlante from Stanford.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -Hey, Binky.
Wake up!
It's time for pointer fun.
>> -What's that?
Learn about pointers?
Oh, goody!
>> -Well, to get started, I guess we're
going to need a couple pointers.
>> -OK.
This code allocates two pointers,
which can point to integers.
-OK.
Well, I see the two pointers, but they
don't seem to be pointing to anything.
>> -That's right.
Initially, pointers
don't point to anything.
The things they point to are called
pointees, and setting them up's
a separate step.
>> -Oh, right, right.
I knew that.
The pointees are separate.
Er, so how do you allocate a pointee?
>> -OK.
Well, this code allocates
a new integer pointee,
and this part sets x to point to it.
>> -Hey, that looks better.
So make it do something.
>> -OK.
I'll dereference the pointer x to
store the number 42 into its pointee.
For this trick, I'll need my
Magic Wand of Dereferencing.
>> -Your Magic Wand of Dereferencing?
That-- that's great.
>> -This is what the code looks like.
I'll just set up the number, and [POP]
>> -Hey, look.
There it goes.
>> -So doing a dereference on x follows
the arrow to access its pointee.
In this case, a store 42 in there.
Hey try using it to store the number
13 through the other pointer, y.
>> -OK.
I'll just go over here to y,
and get the number 13 set up.
And then, take the Wand of
Dereferencing and just [BUZZ]
>> -Oh!
>> -Oh, hey!
That didn't work.
Say, Binky, I don't think dereferencing
y is a good idea, because you know,
setting up the pointee
is a separate step.
And I don't think we ever did it.
>> -Good point.
-Yeah.
We allocated the pointer y, but we
never set it to point to a pointee.
>> -Very observant.
-Hey, you're looking good there, Binky.
Can you fix it so that y points
to the same pointee as x?
>> -Sure.
I'll use my Magic Wand
of Pointer Assignment.
>> -Is that going to be
a problem like before?
-No.
This doesn't touch the pointees.
It just changes one pointer to
point to the same thing as another.
>> -Oh, I see.
Now y points to the same place as x.
So wait.
Now, y is fixed.
It has a pointee.
So you can try the Wand of
Dereferencing again to send the 13 over.
>> -Uh, OK.
Here it goes. [POP]
>> -Hey, look at that.
Now dereferencing works on y.
And because the pointers are sharing
that one pointee, they both see the 13.
-Yeah.
Sharing, whatever.
So are we going to switch places now?
>> Oh, look.
We're out of time.
>> -But--
>> -Just remember the three pointer rules.
Number One, the basic structure
is that you have a pointer,
and it points over to a pointee.
But the pointer and
pointee are separate,
and the common error
is to set up a pointer,
but to forget to give it a pointee.
>> Number Two, pointer dereferencing
starts at the pointer
and follows its arrow over
to access its pointee.
As we all know, this
only works if there is
a pointee, which kind of
gets back to Rule Number One.
>> Number Three, pointer
assignment takes one pointer
and changes it to point to the
same pointee as another pointer.
So after the assignment,
the two pointers
will point to the same pointee.
Sometimes, that's called sharing.
And that's all there is to it, really.
Bye-bye now.
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: That's it for CS50.
We will see you next week.