[MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID MALAN: This is CS50.
And this is both the start and the
end-- like literally-- almost the end
of week six.
>> I thought I'd share a
little bit of a fun fact.
I've pulled this up from a
past semester's data set.
You may recall that we ask you on every
p set form if you've watched online
or if you've attended in person.
And here is the data.
So today was very much predictable.
But we wanted to spend a bit
of time with you nonetheless.
Would anyone like to conjecture why this
graph is so jaggy, up down, up down,
so consistently?
What do each of the peaks
and troughs represent?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
And more amusingly, god forbid,
we hold one lecture on a Friday
at the beginning of the semester,
that's what we see happen.
So today, we partake in a bit
more about data structures.
And to give you more of a solid
mental model for problems at five,
which is now out.
Misspellings, wherein, we'll
hand you a text file some 100,000
plus English words, and
you're going to have
to figure out how to cleverly load them
into memory, into RAM, using some data
structure of your choice.
>> Now one such data structure could
be, but probably shouldn't be,
the fairly simplistic linked list,
which we introduced last time.
And a linked list had at least
one advantage over an array.
What's one advantage of
a linked list arguably?
>> AUDIENCE: Insertion.
>> DAVID MALAN: Insertion.
What do you mean by that?
>> AUDIENCE: Anywhere along
the list [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID MALAN: Good.
So you can insert an element wherever
you want in the middle of the list
without having to shuffle anything,
which we concluded, in our sorting
discussions, isn't
necessarily a good thing,
because it takes time to actually move
all of those humans left or right.
And so with a linked list, you can
just allocate with malloc, a new node,
and then update a couple of
pointers-- two, three operations max--
and we're able to slot someone
in anywhere into a list.
>> What else was advantageous
about a linked list?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
Perfect.
It's really dynamic.
And that you're not committing,
in advance, to some fixed size
chunk of memory, like you would have
to with an array, the upside of which
is that you can allocate nodes only on
demand thereby using only as much space
as you actually need.
By contrast with an array, you might
accidentally allocate too little.
And then it's just going
to be a pain in the neck
to reallocate a new bigger array, copy
everything over, free the old array,
and then move about your business.
Or worse, you might allocate way
more memory than you actually need,
and so you're going to have a very
sparsely-populated array, so to speak.
>> So a linked list gives you these
advantages of dynamism and flexibility
with insertions and deletions.
But surely there must be a price paid.
In fact, one of the themes
explored on quiz zero
was a couple of the trade-offs
we've seen thus far.
So what's a price paid or a
downside of a linked list?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: No random access.
>> DAVID MALAN: No random access.
But who cares?
Random access doesn't sound compelling.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
If you want to have
a certain algorithm--
and let me actually propose
binary search in particular, which
is one we've used quite a bit--
if you don't have random access,
you can't do that simple arithmetic
of finding like the middle element
and jumping right to it.
You instead have to start at the first
element and linearly search from left
to right if you want to find
the middle or any other element.
>> AUDIENCE: It probably takes more memory.
>> DAVID MALAN: Takes more memory.
Where is that additional
cost coming from in memory?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
In this case here, we had
a linked list for integers,
and yet we're doubling
the amount of memory
we need by also storing these pointers.
Now less of a big deal as
your structs get larger
and you're storing not a number but
maybe a student or some other object.
But the point certainly remains.
And so a number of the operations
on linked lists were called
were big O of n-- linear.
Things like insertion or search
or deletion in case an element
happened to be at the very end of
the list whether it's sorted or not.
>> Sometimes you might get lucky and in
so lower bounds on these operations
might also be constant time if you're
always looking at the first element,
for instance.
But ultimately, we promised
to achieve the holy grail
of data structures, or
some approximation thereof,
by way of constant time.
Can we find elements or add elements
or remove elements from a list?
We shall see quite soon.
And it turns out that one
of the mechanisms we're
going to start to use today,
annual use in p set five,
is actually pretty familiar.
For instance, if this is a bunch
of exam books, each of which
has a student's first
name and last name on it,
and I pick them up from
at the end of an exam,
and they're all pretty
much in a random order,
and we want to go about sorting
these exams so that once graded
it's just a lot easier and
faster to hand them back out
to students alphabetically.
What would your instincts be
for a pile of exams like this?
>> Well, if you're like me, you
might see that this is m,
so I'm going to sort of put this into,
if this is my table or my floor where
I'm spreading things
out-- or my array really--
I might put all of the Ms in there.
Oh.
Here's an A. So I might
put the As over here.
Oh.
Here's another A. I'm going
to put that over here.
Here's a Z. Here is another M. And so
I might start making piles like this.
And then maybe I'd go in later
and sort of very nitpicky-ly sort
the individual piles.
But the point is I would look
at the input that I'm handed
and I would make some calculated
decision based on that input.
If it starts with A, put it over there.
If it starts with Z, put it over
there, and everything in between.
>> So this is a technique that's
generally known as hashing-- H-A-S-H--
which generally means taking as
input and using that input to compute
a value, generally a number, and that
number is the index into a storage
container, like an array.
So in other words, I might have a
hash function, as I do in my head,
that if I see someone's
name who starts with A,
I'm going to map that
to zero in my head.
And if I see someone with Z, I'm
going to map that to 25 in my head
and then put that into
the last most pile.
>> Now, if you think about not my brain
but a C program, what numbers could
you rely on to achieve that same result?
In other words, if you
had the ASCII character A,
how do you determine
what bucket to put it in?
You probably don't want to
put it into bucket 65, which
would be like over there
for no good reason.
Where do you want to put A
in terms of its ASCII value?
Where do you want to do to its ASCII
value to come up with a smarter bucket
to put it in?
>> AUDIENCE: Minus A.
>> DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So minus A or minus
specifically 65 if it's
a capital A. Or 98 if
it's a lowercase a.
And so that would allow us to, very
simply and very arithmetically,
put something into a bucket like that.
So it turns out we actually do
this as well even with the quizzes.
>> So you might recall you circled your
teaching fellow's name on the cover.
And the TF's names were organized
into these columns alphabetically,
well, believe it or not,
when all 80 plus of us
got together the other night to grade,
the last step in our grading process
is to hash the quizzes into a big
space of floor at the [INAUDIBLE]
and to lay everyone's quizzes out
in exactly the order of their TF's
names on the cover, because
then it's a lot easier for us
to search through that using linear
search or some kind of cleverness
for a TF to find his or
her students' quizzes.
>> So this idea of hashing
that you'll see is
quite powerful is actually pretty
commonplace and very intuitive,
much like perhaps divide and
conquer was in week zero.
I fast forward to the hackathon
a couple of years ago.
This was Zamyla and a couple of
other staff greeting students
as they came in.
And we had a whole bunch of folding
tables there with name tags.
And we had the name tags organized
with like the As over there
and the Zs over there.
And so one of the TFs very cleverly
wrote this as the instructions
for the day.
And in week 12 of the semester this
all made perfect sense and everyone
knew what to do.
But anytime you've
queued in the same way,
you're implementing the
same notion of a hash.
So let's formalize it a little bit.
Here is an array.
It's drawn to be a little
wide just to depict, visually,
that we might put strings
in something like this.
And this array is
clearly of size 26 total.
And the thing is called
table arbitrarily.
But this is just an artist's rendition
of what a hash table might be.
>> So a hash table now is going to
be a higher level data structure.
At the end of the day
we're about to see that you
can implement a hash table, which
is much like the check-in line
at a hackathon much like this
table used for sorting exam books.
But a hash table is
sort of this high level
concept that could use an array
underneath the hood to implement it,
or it could use a length list, or even
perhaps some other data structures.
And now that's the theme-- taking
some of these fundamental ingredients
like an array and this building
block now of a length list
and seeing what else we can build
on top of those, like ingredients
into a recipe, making more and more
interesting and useful final results.
>> So with the hash table
we might implement it
in memory pictorially like this, but
how might it actually be coded up?
Well, maybe as simply is this.
If CAPACITY in all caps, is just
some constant-- for instance 26,
for 26 letters of the alphabet--
I might call my variable table,
and I might claim that I'm going to
put char stars in there, or string.
So it's as simple as this if you
want to implement a hash table.
And yet, this is really just an array.
But again, a hash
table is now what we'll
call an abstract data type that's just
sort of a conceptual layering on top
of something more mundane
now like an array.
>> Now, how do we go
about solving problems?
Well, earlier I had the luxury
of having enough table space here
so that I could put the
quizzes anywhere I wanted.
So As might go here.
Zs might go here.
Ms might go here.
And then I had some extra space.
But this is a bit of a cheat right
now because this table, if I really
thought of it as an array, is just
going to be of some fixed size.
>> So technically, if I pull
up another student's quiz
and see, oh, this person's
name starts with an A too,
I kind of want to put it there.
But as soon as I put it there, if
this table indeed represents an array,
I'm going to be overriding or clobbering
whoever this student's quiz is.
Right?
If this is an array, only one thing can
go in each of these cells or elements.
And so I kind of have
to pick and choose.
>> Now earlier I kind of
cheated and did this or I
just kind of stacked
them above each other.
But that's not going to fly in code.
So where could I put the
second student whose name
is A if all I had is this
available table space?
And I've used three slots and it
looks like there's just a few others.
What could you do?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Maybe let's just keep it simple.
Right?
It doesn't fit where I want to put it.
So I'm going to put it
technically where a B would go.
Now, of course, I'm starting
to paint myself into a corner.
If I get to a student
whose name is actually B,
now B is going to be moved a little
forward, as might happen, yep,
if this is a B, now it has to go here.
>> And so this very quickly
could become problematic,
but it's a technique that actually
is referred to as linear probing,
whereby you just consider your
array to be along the line.
And you just kind of probe or
inspect each available element
looking for an available spot.
And as soon as you find
one, you drop it in there.
>> Now, the price being paid now
for this solution is what?
We have a fixed size array,
and when I insert names
into it, at least initially, what's
the running time of insertion
for putting the students'
quizzes in the right buckets?
Big O of what?
>> AUDIENCE: n.
DAVID MALAN: I heard big O of n.
Not true.
But we'll tease apart
why in just a moment.
What else might it be?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: And let me do it visually.
So suppose this is the letter S.
>> AUDIENCE: It's one.
DAVID MALAN: It's one.
Right?
This is an array, which
means we have random access.
And if we think of this
as zero and this as 25,
and we realize that,
oh, here's my input S,
I can certainly convert
S, an ASCII character,
to a corresponding number
between zero and 25
and then immediately
put it where it belongs.
>> But of course, as soon as I get to the
second person who's name is A or B or C
eventually, if I've used the
linear probing as my solution,
the running time of
insertion in the worst case
is actually going to devolve into what?
And I did hear it here
correctly early on.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So it is n indeed once
you have a sufficiently large data set.
So, on the one hand, if
your array is big enough
and your data is sparse enough, you
get this beautiful constant time.
But as soon as you start
getting more and more elements,
and just statistically you get
more people with the letter
A as their name or the letter
B, it could potentially
devolve into something more linear.
So not quite perfect.
So could we do better?
>> Well, what was our
solution before when we
want to have more dynamism than
something like an array allowed?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: What did we introduce?
Yeah.
So a linked list.
Well, let's see what a linked
list might do for us instead.
Well, let me propose that we
draw the picture as follows.
Now this is a different
picture from an example
from a different text, actually, that
is actually using an array of size 31.
And this author simply
decided to hash strings
not based on the person's names,
but based on their birthdates.
Irrespective of the month, they figured
if you're born on the first of a month
or the 31st of a month, the author
will hash based on that value,
so as to spread the names out a bit
more than just 26 spots might allow.
And perhaps it's a little more uniform
than going with alphabetical letters,
because of course there's probably
more people in the world with names
that start with A than certainly
some other letters of the alphabet.
So maybe this is a little
more uniform, assuming
a uniform distribution
of babies across a month.
>> But, of course, this is still imperfect.
Right?
We're having collisions.
Multiple people in this
data structure are still
having the same birthdate at least
you're irrespective of month.
But what has the author done?
Well, it looks like we have an array
on the left-hand side drawn vertically,
but that's just an artist's rendition.
It doesn't matter what direction you
draw an array, it's still an array.
What is this an array of apparently?
>> AUDIENCE: Linked list.
>> DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
It looks like it's an
array of linked list.
So again, to this point of sort
of using these data structures now
as ingredients to more
interesting solutions,
you can absolutely take a
fundamental, like an array,
and then take something more
interesting like a linked list
and even combine them into an even
more interesting data structure.
And indeed, this too would
be called a hash table,
whereby the array is
really the hash table,
but that hash table has
chains, so to speak,
that can grow or shrink based on the
number of elements you want to insert.
>> Now, accordingly, what's
the running time now?
If I want to insert someone
whose birthday is October 31,
where does he or she go?
All right.
At the very bottom where it says 31.
And that's perfect.
That was constant time.
But what if we find someone else
whose birthday is, let's see,
October, November, December 31?
Where is he or she going to go?
Same thing.
Two step though.
That's constant though isn't it?
All right.
At the moment it is.
But in the general case,
the more people we add,
probabilistically, we're going
to get more and more collisions.
>> Now this is a little
better because technically
now my chains could be in
the worst case how long?
If I insert n people into this more
sophisticated data structure, n people,
in the worst case it's going to be n.
Why?
>> AUDIENCE: Because if everybody
has the same birthday,
they're going to be one line.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
It might be a little contrived,
but truly in the worst case,
if everyone has the same birthday,
given the inputs you have,
you're going to have a
massively long chain.
And so, you could call it a
hash table, but really it's
just a massive linked list with
a whole lot of wasted space.
But in general, if we assume that
at least birthdays are uniform--
and it probably isn't.
I'm making that up.
But if we assume, for
the sake of discussion
that they are, then in theory, if
this is the vertical representation
of the array, well then hopefully you're
going to get chains that are, you know,
roughly the same length where each of
these represents a day of the month.
>> Now if there's 31 days in the month,
that means my running time really
is big O of n over 31, which
feels better than linear.
But what was one of our
commitments a couple of weeks
ago whenever it came to expressing
the running time of an algorithm?
Just only look at the high order term.
Right?
31 is definitely helpful.
But this is still big O of n.
But one of the themes
of problem set five
is going to be to
acknowledge that absolutely,
asymptotically, theoretically
this data structure
is no better than just
one massive linked list.
And indeed, in the worst case, this
hash table might devolve into that.
>> But in the real world, with us humans
that own Macs or PCs or whatever
and are running real world
software on real world data,
which algorithm are you going to prefer?
The one that takes end steps or the
one that takes n divided by 31 steps
to find some piece of data or
to look up some information?
I mean, absolutely the 31 makes
a difference in the real world.
It is 31 times faster.
And we humans are certainly
going to appreciate that.
>> So realize the dichotomy
there between actually
talking about things theoretically
and asymptotically which definitely
has value as we've seen,
but in the real world,
if you care about just making the
human happy for general inputs,
you might very well want to accept
the fact that, yes, this is linear,
but it's 31 times faster
than linear might be.
And better yet, we don't just have to
do something arbitrary like a birthdate,
we could spend a little
more time and cleverness
and think about what we might do,
given a person's name and maybe
their birthdate to combine those
ingredients to figure out something
that is truly more
uniform and less jaggy,
so to speak than this picture
currently suggests it might be.
How could we implement this in code?
Well, let me propose that we
just borrow some syntax we've
used a couple times thus far.
And I'm going to define
a node, which again
is a generic term for just some
container for some data structure.
I'm going to propose that
a string is going in there.
But we're going to start taking
those training wheels off now.
>> No more CS50 library
really, unless you want
to use it for your final
project, which is fine,
but now we're going to pull back the
curtain and say it's just a char star.
So the word there is going to be
the person's name in question.
And now I have a link
here to the next node
so that these represent
each of the nodes
in the chain, potentially,
of a linked list.
>> And now how do I declare
the hash table itself?
How do I declare this whole structure?
Well, really, much like I used a pointer
to just the first element of a list
before, similarly can I just say
I just need a bunch of pointers
to implement this whole hash table.
I'm going to have an array
called table for hash table.
It's going to be of size capacity.
That's how many elements can fit in it.
And each of those elements in this
array is going to be a node star.
Why?
Well, per this picture, what I'm
implementing the hash table as
effectively in the beginning is just
this array that we've drawn vertically,
each of whose squares
represents a pointer.
That ones that have slashes
through them are just null.
And the ones that have
arrows going to the right
are actual pointers to actual nodes,
ergo the start of a linked list.
>> So here, then, is how we might
implement a hash table that
implements separate chaining.
Now can we do better?
All right I promised last time that
we could achieve constant time.
And I kind of gave you
constant time here,
but then said not really
constant time because it's still
dependent on the total
number of elements
you're inputting into
the data structure.
But suppose we did this.
Let me go back to the screen over here.
Let me also project this up here, clear
the screen, and suppose I did this.
Suppose I wanted to insert the name
Daven in into my data structure.
>> So I want to insert a string
Daven into the data structure.
What if I don't use a
hash table, but I use
something that's more tree-like
like a family tree, where
you have some root at the
top and then nodes and leaves
that go downward and outward.
Suppose then, that I
want to insert Daven's
into what's currently an empty list.
I'm going to do the following: I'm
going to create a node in this family
tree-like data structure that looks
a little like this, each of which
rectangles has, let's say,
for now 26 elements in it.
And each of the cells
in this array is going
to represent the letter of an alphabet.
>> Specifically, I'm going to treat
this is A, then B, then C, then D,
this one here.
So this is going to effectively
represent the letter D.
But to insert all of Daven's
name I need to do a bit more.
So I'm first going to hash, so to speak.
I'm going to look at the first letter
in Daven's which is obviously a D,
and I'm going to allocate
a node that looks
like this-- a big rectangle big
enough to fit the whole alphabet.
>> Now D is done.
Now A. D-A-V-E-N is the goal.
So now what I'm going to do is this.
As soon as I started D notice
there's no pointer there.
It's garbage values at the moment,
or I might initialize it to null.
But let me keep going with
this idea of building a tree.
Let me allocate another one of these
nodes that has 26 elements in it.
>> And you know what?
If this is just a node in memory that
I created with malloc, using a struct
as we'll soon see,
I'm going to do this--
I'm going to draw an arrow from
the thing that represented D down
to this new node.
And now, first the next
letter in Daven's name,
V-- D-A-V-- I'm going to go ahead
and draw another node like this,
whereby, the V elements here, which
we'll draw for instance-- whoops.
We won't draw there.
It's going to go here.
>> Then we're going to
consider this to be V.
And then down here we're going to index
down from V into what we'll consider E.
And then from here we're going to
go have one of these nodes here.
And now we have a question to answer.
I need to somehow indicate that
we're at the end of the string Daven.
So I could just leave it null.
>> But what if we have Daven's
full name also, which
is, as we've said, Davenport?
So what if Daven is
actually a substring,
a prefix of a much longer string?
We can't just permanently
say nothing is going
to go there, because we could
never insert a word like Davenport
into this data Structure
>> So what we could do instead is
treat each of these elements
as maybe having two
elements inside of them.
One is a pointer, indeed,
as I've been doing.
So each of these boxes
is not just one cell.
But what if the top
one-- the bottom one's
going to be null, because
there is no Davenport just yet.
What if the top one
is some special value?
And it's going to be a little
hard to draw it this size.
But suppose it's just a check mark.
Check.
D-A-V-E-N is a string
in this data structure.
>> Meanwhile, if I had more space
here, I could do P-O-R-T,
and I could put check in the node
that has the letter T at the very end.
So this is a massively
complex-looking data structure.
And my handwriting
certainly doesn't help.
But if I wanted to insert something
else, consider what we would do.
If we wanted to put David in,
we'd follow the same logic, D-A-V,
but now I would point in the next
element not from E, but from I to D.
So there's going to be
more nodes in this tree.
We're going to have call malloc more.
But I don't want to make a
complete mess of this picture.
So let's instead look at one
that's been pre-formulated
like this with not dot, dot,
dots, but just abbreviated arrays.
But each of the nodes
in this tree up here
represents the same thing--
an array Ray of size 26.
>> Or if we want to be
really proper now, what
if someone's name as
an apostrophe, let's
assume that each node actually has
like 27 indexes in it, not just 26.
So this now is going to be a data
structure called a trie-- T-R-I-E.
A trie, which is supposedly
historically a clever name for a tree
that's optimized for
retrieval, which of course,
is spelled with an I-E so it's trie.
But that is the history of the trie.
>> So a trie is this tree-like data
structure like a family tree
that ultimately behaves like that.
And here is just another example of a
whole bunch of other people's names.
But the question now
at hand is what have
we gained by introducing arguably a more
complicated data structure, and one,
frankly, that uses a lot of memory.
>> Because even though,
at the moment, I'm only
using D's pointer and
A and V and Es and Ns,
I'm wasting a heck of lot of memory.
But where I spend one resource,
I tend to do gain back another.
So if I'm spending more space,
what's probably the hope?
That I'm spending less what?
AUDIENCE: Less time.
DAVID MALAN: Time.
Now why might that be?
Well, what is the insertion
time, in terms of big O now,
of a name like Daven
or Davenport or David?
Well, Daven was five steps.
Davenport would be nine steps,
so it would be a few more steps.
David would be five steps as well.
So those are concrete
numbers, but surely there's
an upper bound on the
length of someone's name.
And indeed, in the problem
sets of five specification,
we're going to propose
that it's something
that's 40-some-odd characters.
>> Realistically, no one has
an infinitely long name,
which is to say that the length of a
name or the length of a string we might
have certain the state of
structure is arguably what?
It's constant.
Right?
It might be a big constant like
40-something, but it is constant.
And it has no dependency on how many
other names are in this data structure.
In other words, if I
wanted to now insert
Colton or Gabriel or Rob or Zamyla or
Alison or Belinda or any other names
from the staff into this data
structure, is the running time
of inserting other names
going to be at all impacted
by how many other elements are
in the data structure already?
It's not.
Right?
Because we're effectively using
this multi-layer hash table.
And the running time of
any of these operations
is dependent not on the number of
elements that are in the data structure
or that are eventually going
to be in the data structure,
but on the length of what specifically?
>> The string being
inserted, which does make
this asymptotically constant
time-- big O of one.
And frankly, just in
the real world, this
means inserting Daven's name takes
like five steps, or Davenport nine
steps, or David five steps.
That's pretty darn small running times.
And, indeed, that's a very
good thing, especially when
it's not dependent on the total
number of elements in there.
So how might we implement this
kind of structure in code?
It's a little more
complex, but still it's
just an application of
basic building blocks.
I'm going to redefine
us node as follows:
bool called word-- and this
could be called anything.
But the bool represents
what I drew as a check mark.
Yes.
This is the end of a string
in this data structure.
>> And, of course, the node star
there is referring to children.
And, indeed, just like
a family tree, you
would consider the nodes
that are hanging off
of the bottom of some parent
element to be children.
And so the children is going to
be an array of 27, the 27th one
just being for apostrophe.
We're going to sort
of special case that.
So you can have certain
names with apostrophes.
Maybe even hyphen should
go in there, but you'll
see in p set 5 we only care
about letters and apostrophes.
>> And then how do you represent
the data structure itself?
How do you represent the root
of this trie, so to speak?
Well, just like with a linked list, you
need a pointer to the first element.
With a trie you just need one
pointer to the root of this trie.
And from there you can hash
your way down deeper and deeper
to every other node in the structure.
So simply with this can
we represent that struct.
>> Now Meanwhile-- Oh, question.
>> AUDIENCE: What's bool word?
>> DAVID MALAN: Bool word is
just this C incarnation
of what I described
in this box here, when
I started splitting each of the
array's elements into two pieces.
One is a pointer to the next node.
The other has to be
something like a check box
to say yes, there's a
word Daven that ends here,
because we don't want,
at the moment, Dave.
>> Even though Dave is going to be a
legitimate word, he's not in the trie
yet.
And D is not a word.
And D-A is not a word or a name.
So the check mark
indicates only once you
hit this node is the
previous path of characters
actually a string that you've inserted.
So that's all the bool
there is doing for us.
>> Any other questions on tries?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: What is the overlap?
What if you have a Dave and a Daven?
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
So if we insert, say a nickname,
for David-- Dave-- D-A-V-E?
This is actually super simple.
So we're only going to take four steps.
D-A-V-E. And what do I have to
do once I hit that fourth node?
Just going to check.
We're already good to go.
Done.
Four steps.
Constant time asymptotically.
And now we've indicated that both Dave
and Daven are strings in the structure.
So not a problem.
And notice how the presence
of Daven did not make it
take any more time or less
time for Dave and vice versa.
>> So what else can we now do?
We've used this metaphor before
of trays representing something.
But it turns out that a
stack of trays is actually
demonstrative of another abstract data
type-- a higher level data structure
that at the end the day is just
like an array or a linked list
or something more mundane.
But it's a more interesting
conceptual concept.
A stack, like these
trays here in Mather,
are generally called
just that-- a stack.
>> And in this type of data structure
you have two operations--
you have one called push for
adding something to the stack,
like putting another tray
back on the top of the stack.
And then pop, which means you
take the topmost tray off.
But what's key about a stack is that
it's got this curious characteristic.
As the dining hall staff are
rearranging the trays for the next meal,
what's going to be
true about how students
interact with this data structure?
AUDIENCE: They're going to pop one off.
DAVID MALAN: They're going to
pop one off, hopefully the top.
Otherwise it's just kind of stupid
to go all the way to the bottom.
Right?
The data structure doesn't really allow
you to grab the bottom tray at least
easily.
So there's this curious
property to a stack
that the last item in is
going to be the first one out.
And computer scientists call
this LIFO-- last in, first out.
And it actually does have
interesting applications.
It's not necessarily as obvious as some
others, but it can, indeed, be useful,
and it can, indeed, be implemented
in a couple of different ways.
>> So one, and actually, let
me not to dive into that.
Let's do this instead.
Let's look at one that's almost the
same idea, but it's a little fairer.
Right?
If you're one of these fan boys or
girls that really likes Apple products
and you woke up at 3:00 AM
to line up at some store
to get the very latest iPhone, you
might have queued up like this.
>> Now a queue is very deliberately named.
It's a line because there's
some fairness to it.
Right?
It would kind of sucked if you've
got there first at the Apple Store
but you are effectively the bottommost
tray because the Apple employees then
pop the last person who
actually got in line.
So stacks and queues, even though
functionally they're kind of the same--
it's just this collection
of resources that's
going to grow and shrink-- there's
this fairness aspect to it,
at least in the real world,
where the operations you exercise
are fundamentally different.
A stack-- a queue
rather-- is said to have
two operations: n queue and d queue.
Or you can call them
any number of things.
But you just want to capture
the notion that one is adding
and one is ultimately subtracting.
>> Now underneath the hood, both the stack
and a queue could be implemented how?
We won't go into the code of
it because the higher level
idea is sort of more obvious.
I mean, what do humans do?
If I'm the first person at the Apple
Store and this is the front door,
you know, I'm going to stand here.
And the next person's
going to stand here.
So what data structure
lends itself to a queue?
>> AUDIENCE: A queue.
DAVID MALAN: Well, a queue.
Sure.
What else?
>> AUDIENCE: A linked list.
>> DAVID MALAN: A linked
list you could implement.
And a linked list is nice because then
it can grow arbitrarily long as opposed
to having some fixed number
of people in the store.
But maybe a fixed number
of places is legitimate.
Because if they only have like 20
iPhones on the first day, maybe
they only need an array of size
20 to represent that queue, which
is only to say now once we start talking
about these higher level problems,
you can implement it
in any number of ways.
And there's probably just going to
be a trade off in space and time
or just in your own code complexity.
>> What about a stack?
Well, a stack, we've seen too
could just be these trays.
And you could implement this an array.
But at some point if you use an array,
what's going to happen to the trays
you're trying to put down?
All right.
You're only going to
be able to go so high.
And I think in Mather they're
actually recessed in that opening.
So indeed, it's almost
like Mather is using
an array of fixed size,
because you can only
fit so many trays in that opening in
the wall down below people's knees.
And so that might be
said to be an array,
but we could certainly implement that
more generally with a linked list.
>> Well, what about another data structure?
Let me pull up one other visual here.
Something like how about this one here?
Why might it be useful to have not
something as fancy as a trie, which
we saw had these very wide nodes,
each of which is in an array?
But what if we do something more
simply, like an old school family tree,
each of whose nodes here
is just storing a number.
Instead of a name or a descendant
is just storing a number like this.
>> Well, the jargon we use in
data structures is both tries
and trees, where a trie, again, is
just one whose nodes are arrays,
is still what you might
use from grade school
when you made a family
tree-- leaves and the root
of the tree and children of the
parent and siblings thereof.
And we might implement a tree,
for instance, as simply as this.
A tree, if it as a node, one of
these circles that has a number,
it's not going to have
one pointer, but two.
And as soon as you add
a second pointer, you
can actually now make sort
of two-dimensional data
structures in memory.
Much like a two-dimensional
array, you can
have kind of two-dimensional
linked lists but ones
that follow a pattern
where there's no cycles.
It's truly a tree with one
grandparent way up here and then
some parents and children and
grandchildren and great-grandchildren.
and so forth.
>> But what's really neat about this too,
just to tease you with a bit of code,
recall recursion from
awhile back, whereby
you write a function that calls itself.
This is a beautiful opportunity
to implement something
like recursion, because consider this.
>> This is a tree.
And I've been a little anal with how
I put the integers into the street.
So much so that it has a special
name-- a binary search tree.
Now we've heard of binary
search, but can you
work backwards from this thing's name?
What is the pattern of how I
inserted the integers into this tree?
It's not arbitrary.
There's some pattern.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Smaller ones on the left.
>> DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Smaller ones are on the left.
Bigger ones are on the right.
Such that a true statement is a
parent is greater than its left child,
but less than its right child.
And that alone is even a
recursive verbal definition
because you can apply that
same logic to every node
and it only bottoms
out, a base case if you
will, when you hit one of
the leaves, so to speak,
where a leave has no children further.
>> Now how might you find the number 44?
You would start at the root and say, hm.
55 is not 44 So do I want to go
right or do I want to go left?
Well, obviously you want to go left.
And so it's just like the phone
book example in binary search
more generally.
But we're implementing it
now a little more dynamically
than an array might allow.
And in fact, if you want to look
at the code, at first glance sure.
It looks like a whole bunch of lines.
But it's beautifully simple.
If you want to implement a function
called search whose purpose in life
is to search for a value
like n, an integer,
and you're passed in a one pointer--
a pointer to the node of the roots,
rather, of that tree from which
you can access everything else,
notice how straightforwardly
you can implement the logic.
If tree is null,
obviously it's not there.
Let's just return false.
Right?
If you hand it nothing,
there's nothing there.
>> Else, if n is less than
tree arrow n-- now arrow n,
recall we introduced super
briefly the other day,
and that just means de-reference the
pointer and look at the field called n.
So it means go there and
look at the field called n.
So if n, the value you're given, is less
than the value in the trees integer,
where do you want to go?
To the left.
>> So notice the recursion.
I'm returning-- not true.
Not false.
I'm returning whatever the answer
is from a call to myself, passing
an n again, which is redundant,
but what's slightly different now?
How am I making the problem smaller?
I'm passing in as the second
argument, not the root of the tree,
but the left child in this case.
So I'm passing in the left child.
>> Meanwhile, if n is bigger than
the node I'm currently looking at,
I search the right hand side.
Else, if the tree is not null, and
if the element's not to the left
and it's not to the right,
what is wonderfully the case?
We've actually found the node in
question, and so we return true.
>> So we've just scratched the surface
now some of these data structures.
In problem set five you'll
explore these yet further,
and you'll be given your design
choice of how to go about this.
What I'd like to conclude on
is just a 30 second teaser
of what awaits next week and beyond.
>> As we begin-- thankfully you might
think-- our transition slowly
from the world of C and lower
level implementation details,
to a world in which we can take for
granted that someone else has finally
implemented these data
structures for us,
and we'll start to understand the
real world means of implementing
web-based programs and
websites more generally
and also the very security
implications that we've only
begun to scratch the surface of.
Here is what awaits us
in the days to come.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -He came with a message,
with a protocol all his own.
He came to a world of cruel
firewalls, uncaring routers,
and dangers far worse than death.
He's fast.
He's strong.
He's TCP/IP, and he's got your address.
"Warriors of the Net."
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: Coming next week.
We will see you then.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-And now, "Deep Thoughts"
by Daven Farnham.
-David always starts
lectures with, "All right."
Why not, "Here's the solution
to this week's problem set"
or "We're giving all of you an A?"
[LAUGHING]
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]