>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID MALAN: All right this is CS50
and this is the end of week one.
So I'd like to introduce my former
advisee, Andel Duff, who not only makes
iPhone 5 stands, as well as this
lectern, he also makes cars.
ANSEL DUFF: How's it going, everybody?
I just want to tell you a little
bit about Formula SAE, of which I
am the captain.
It's an MIT team.
I just want to tell you
guys a little bit about it
and hopefully generate some interest.
>> So let me just run through a
couple things about our team.
So we're completely
student run, wherein all
of the members design, simulate,
test, and manufacturer a subsystem
of the car.
We have our own machine shop
and garages, and N52-- or sorry,
N51-- which is the same building
as the MIT Science Museum.
And we are the people
that drive the car.
There's a national competition
in the beginning of the summer,
and then there are smaller shootout
competitions throughout the year.
And then we do driver training
days to get new members acquainted.
>> Our build days are on
Saturdays from 11 AM to 8 PM.
Lunch and dinner are taking care
of, from Bertucci's and Beantown
respectively.
We have a weekly meeting and
seminar, which is for course credit.
Which is new as of this semester, and
it will also be for next semester,
so you can cross-reg for that.
And then we have designing, shop,
and CAD days during the week,
whereas members will independently
CAD parts, order stock et cetera.
>> So for electrical
engineering at the team
we have our tractive,
high voltage system,
which runs at a nominal
300 volts, which includes
motors, motor controllers,
and battery packs.
Then we have a low
voltage system, which runs
at 12 volts, which includes
controls, CAN nodes, the brain
box, and the dashboard.
As far CS goes, we do
have website maintenance
that we need done for events, membership
changes, new pictures, and PR material.
And then we have code that controls the
car for our traction control, launch
control, dash control, torque vectoring,
and regenerative braking systems, which
run typically in MATLAB,
Simulink, and LabView.
>> Tell you a little bit about the car.
So it's about 500 pounds.
It's rules limited to 85 kilowatts.
It has 2 EMRAX 207 motors in the
back, one for each rear wheel.
It has custom-built battery packs
from Prismatic A123 pouch cells,
totaling 300 volts and
5.6 kilowatt hours.
And it's direct drive with
a 2.64 to 1 drive ratio.
Here are some pictures we
took of it at competition.
Here's the back, nose cone,
and here are the motors,
those big black disks
underneath the et mens manus.
Here's a slide that I pulled
out of our competition scheme.
And this is just comparing our car to a
couple of commercially available cars,
like the KTM XBOW, Ariel
Atom, and Caterha M 7-280.
If you're familiar with price, power
pull weight, dollars per horsepower,
dollars per torque, and our car
blows them all out of the water.
If you have any questions,
jot down this email address.
Shoot us an email at fsae@mit.edu.
>> We're happy to talk about
anything you'd like.
Harvard students are kind
of the minority on the team.
If you have any questions about
that please do shoot us an email,
happy to talk, and I'm going
to head back over to David.
Thanks.
I appreciate it, guys.
[APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID MALAN: Ansel spent the summer
working with us here on campus in CS50
this summer.
And in addition to working on
things like the binary bulbs,
he actually really opened our
eyes-- and mine in particular--
to what really the intersection of
not of hardware and software can be.
In fact a lot of the things he just
toured you through are ultimately
created first in software,
and then ultimately fabricated
in the real world in hardware.
So if you're interested in
exploring that intersection,
perhaps take up that group.
>> Now meanwhile, those of you
who are fans of technology,
and Apple products in
particular know that there
were a couple of
announcements yesterday.
But we thought we'd show
you one that came out
a few days prior that
you might not have seen.
>> JORGEN EGHAMMER: You know,
once in awhile something
comes along that
changes the way we live.
A device so simple and intuitive
using it feels almost familiar.
Introducing 2015 IKEA catalogue.
It's not a digital book or
an e-book, it's a book-book.
>> The first thing to note is no
cables, not even a power cable.
The 2015 IKEA catalogue
comes fully charged,
and the battery life is eternal.
The interface is 7.5 by 8 inches,
but can expand to 15 by 8 inches.
The navigation is based on tactile touch
technology that you can actually feel.
>> Content comes pre-installed
via 328 high-definition pages
of inspiring home furnishing ideas.
To start browsing,
simply touch and drag.
Right to left to move forward,
left to right to move backwards.
>> Notice something else?
That's right.
No lag.
Each crystal clear page
loads instantaneously,
no matter how fast you scroll.
If you want to get a quick overview,
just hold it in the palm of your hand,
and using just your thumb,
speed browse the content.
>> If you find something you want to save
for later, you can simply bookmark it.
And even if you close the application,
you can easily find the bookmark again.
Amazing.
>> [LAUGHTER]
[APPLAUSE]
So that brings us to
the end of week one.
A few announcements now.
So sectioning is now in progress.
Go to this URL here sometime
between now and Friday at noon
to actually specify whether you are
among those less comfortable, more
comfortable, or somewhere in between.
>> This is typically one of those
things that you just kind of know.
And in fact those of you who are less
comfortable probably know as much,
those of you who are more
comfortable know as much,
and again if you aren't quite sure which
of those buckets you fall into you're
probably somewhere in between.
But rest assured you can swap
after a couple of weeks if need be.
>> Meanwhile, for the coming week
we don't start sections per se,
but super sections, which
are open to all students.
This coming Sunday at a location to
be announced on the course website
we will have one for
those less comfortable,
as well as one for
those more comfortable.
And those somewhere in between
can choose which of those two,
or both if you'd like, to sit-in on.
And the focus of those
will be ultimately on C,
which we'll continue our
conversation of today.
>> Problem set 0 meanwhile is
hopefully in your hands.
Officially due tomorrow,
Thursday, at noon.
Unless you cash in one
of your 5 late days,
which would bring it
until Friday at noon.
Problem set 1 meanwhile will be
posted on the course's website.
And this will be our first
foray as a class into C.
And that problem set spec will walk you
through a lot of the mechanics of what
we started talking about on Monday,
and we'll continue talking about today.
C, Linux, the CS50
appliance, all of that
will await you in the specification.
>> Office hours meanwhile are in progress,
in the undergraduate dining hall.
Head to this URL here to see the
schedule for tonight and tomorrow,
if you would like to partake.
Questions meanwhile, so that you
have opportunities to ask questions
asynchronously, 24/7, realize you're
not limited to sections and office
hours, but rather this tool
here, CS50 Discuss at that URL
will be the course's online
bulletin board software, via which
you can ask questions of
classmates and also staff.
So keep in mind that resource as well.
Meanwhile a tradition
starts this Friday.
As you may have glimpsed from
last Wednesday's teaser video,
we have a tradition most
every Friday during term
of taking some 50 students and
staff to a local restaurant called
Fire and Ice, at which we're
typically joined by some alumni
or friends from industry
to generally aspire
to make a large class feel smaller.
So it's a completely casual lunch.
A bunch of us, the staff
especially, will play musical chairs
and chat with students about
50, life outside of 50,
life in the future, the real world,
I'm talking about job opportunities
with friends in industry.
>> So if you would like to join us
this Friday, head to this URL here.
Space is limited, but we'll do this
recurringly throughout the term.
Head there to cs50.harvard.edu/rsvp.
And if you don't get in
this time, not to worry.
We will do it again in
the coming weeks as well.
>> So this is the picture
we painted last week,
and you've probably been
dabbling in thus far.
But let's try to connect this now
to what we're going to do today
and onward.
Could I have one volunteer?
All right, or several.
How about here on the
end, in the blue shirt.
Come on up, what's your name?
ALANA: Alana.
DAVID MALAN: Alana.
So Alana, for just a
moment-- nice to meet you--
is going to play the role
of this function here.
The purple block we've
called thus far a function.
So what I'm going to go
ahead here and offer Alana
is a little name tag, to make
clear what role you're playing.
>> So you shall be the say block.
If you want to go ahead and put that on.
And we're going to
keep this super simple.
If the goal at hand is simply
now to implement with Alana,
this so-called say block,
here's how it's going to work.
I have-- let's call it
an argument or parameter,
it's really just a blank sheet of paper.
And it's white to kind of be reminiscent
of the white box into which you
can write words.
>> Meanwhile I'm going to go here.
I'm going to go ahead and
write H-E-L-L-O comma world.
And now I, as say the programmer, don't
actually know how to say something.
I can come up with the words,
but I don't necessarily
know how to express myself
verbally or on the screen.
And so what I'm going
to do is take this piece
of functionality, whose input--
or argument, as we'll call it,
I've written on this piece of paper--
and I'm going to outsource it.
>> And indeed that's the role that
functions in a programming language
can play.
Something like the say
block can be outsourced
to someone who really knows
what she or he is talking about.
So if you'll step over
here for just a moment,
I am going to pass this input to
Alana, and ask that you say this input.
>> ALANA: Hello, world.
DAVID MALAN: That's it.
So that there is a function.
Now we can take it a little more,
we can take a step forward here.
Because that was clearly underwhelming.
So let's now convert this to
something a little more sophisticated.
>> So this of course is our C version.
So now if you want to take that
one off, that name tag off,
and let's have you put on a new name.
But fundamentally you're
playing the same role,
it just so happens to
be called printf now.
>> The story is, of course,
going to be-- probably
just as underwhelming-- is
going to be the following.
You are now the function printf.
I am the caller, or the
programmer, who wants
to stand on the shoulders of
people in the past like you,
who've already figured out how
to actually write something down.
And so this time,
rather than say it let's
actually use our screen over here.
So if you'd like to step
over here, I'm going
to pass again this as
input to my printf friend.
If you could go ahead and
print that on the screen,
simply by drawing with your
finger on the black screen.
Excellent.
All right, so lots of suspense for
how that was going to play out.
>> So now let's take things up one
final notch, if we could, as follows.
So this is a C program
as we said last time.
And this just does what you did, it
prints out to the screen, hello, world.
Even though there's clearly a lot
of distracting stuff up there.
But let's take things up a notch and
introduce this version, which recall
was the third version that
we ended up with last time.
>> And now there's clearly
two uses of printf.
There's 2 calls to Alana
in this case for printf,
but there's also a call
to another function.
What's that function clearly?
Getstring.
>> Can we get one more volunteer?
OK, come on up.
What's your name?
>> JAVIER: Javier.
>> DAVID MALAN: Javier, come on up.
So Javier's role is on
this piece of paper.
Which I'm going to call generically s.
Now this is a variable, it's
of type string, as implied
by that second line in the middle there.
And I'd like you to go get me a string.
Specifically head down to the orchestra
section and get me the name of someone,
and come back with a variable
containing that value.
It can be anyone you want.
>> Here we go.
All right, Javier is
writing down the name.
All right.
We can all probably guess how
this is going to play out.
We're perhaps belaboring
the point of what
a function is doing, but
nonetheless thank you very much.
>> So Javier has returned this string
here, which, can't quite see,
Jonathan is the string
that we've gotten.
So now what I'm actually going
to provide to Alana though
is something a little different.
Because in this version of the
program, first there's state your name.
So the very first argument
I need to provide Alana
with is going to be
literally state your name.
All right, so simple as that
I would hand this to you.
And as I write up the
next argument, if you
want to go ahead and write this
on the board, let's go ahead
and do the final example here to make
clear what's ultimately got to happen.
So state your name,
write it toward the top
if you don't mind, just so that
we have room for one second line.
Because the last thing I'm going
to now provide you with is not one,
but two pieces of paper.
>> All right.
H-E-L-L-O comma and then a blank line.
So what I'm about to hand Alana now
is something a little different.
Not only is she getting this,
where fill in the blank represents
that percent-- what was the
placeholder we've been using?
Yeah, so percent s.
Meanwhile I'm going to pass
her in a second argument, which
is precisely what Javier
retrieved from Jonathan.
>> So let me give you these two.
If you'd like to, go ahead
and print that effect.
What's ultimately happening
now is, Alana again
is playing the role of printf.
Javier was playing
the role of GetString.
So that will be your souvenir.
And ultimately what's happening, despite
this hello-- yep go ahead and comma.
ALANA: Did I receive this yet or no?
DAVID MALAN: Yep, you
received them both at once.
So the idea is that you
can now flip the page
to handle the second
of those two inputs.
So this is only to hammer home the
point that whereas Alana executed
this green line here, and then
Javier did this one for us
and return to me something
we'll call s, but it was really
just that piece of paper of his own.
And now Alana has done this third line.
>> And even though all of this looks
so incredibly cryptic perhaps
at first glance, it really
is as simple as that.
Passing inputs around,
getting outputs, either
being physically handed back something,
or seeing a side effect like this.
Something visually
written on the screen.
So let's go ahead and
thank Alana and Javier,
who was down here, for
joining us up here.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> So now let's take for granted just how
straightforward all of that might be.
And let's proceed to actually
do something in actual code.
So up on the screen here is a screenshot
of the so-called CS50 appliance.
And if you had to at, as a
2:00 PM on Wednesday afternoon,
explain to some friend
what the CS50 appliance is,
how would you define it in a sentence?
Any one sentence?
Yeah?
STUDENT: It's like a program
that makes everyone's computer
run with the same system.
DAVID MALAN: Good!
It's a program that enables everyone's
computer to run with the same system.
It's sort of your own
copy of an operating
system that happens to
be called Ubuntu Linux.
And it runs effectively inside of
a window on your own Mac or PC,
so that this way right out of the gate
in week 1, everyone here in the class
has access to the same tools,
the same configuration,
and there's no learning curve specific
to a Mac or a PC in particular.
>> Now we opened up, inside of the CS50
appliance on Monday, this program here.
It happens to be called gedit.
But that's really just
a graphical editor.
It's something like Notepad or Text
Edit on Windows or Mac OS respectively.
And I proposed that there were really
three important parts to this screen.
The top side is where you
would write your code.
And that's where we spent much of our
three examples in Monday's lecture.
The bottom we called what,
this black window, yeah?
>> STUDENT: Compiler?
>> DAVID MALAN: Compiler we
accessed by way of that window.
But more generally.
Yeah, it was just a terminal window.
This is an age old term that just
describes essentially a blinking
prompt, that years ago used to be on
one of those big CRT style monitors.
But nowadays it's sort
of virtual in software.
And the terminal windows
let's us type commands.
It sort of the simplified version
of the user interface or UI.
It's not a graphical
user interface or GUI,
it's a text-based interface
or a command line interface.
>> And indeed that's where ultimately
I was able to write some code.
Once I had written some code though,
recall that I used this command.
And as it the name
kind of suggests, this
allows me to make a
program called Hello.
But what was it really doing?
Well make was taking my
input, my source code,
and converting it to what, ultimately?
>> Object code.
And object code is just a fancy
way of saying zeros and ones.
And then once I wanted
to run that object code,
once I wanted to pass as input those
zeros and ones into my computer's
brain, the so-called CPU
or central processing unit,
I had to run the program.
But it wasn't quite a simple on Monday
as just double clicking some icon.
What instead did I have to
do in order to run a program?
>> What was that second command?
I'm hearing a little slashes?
Yes, yeah?
>> STUDENT: Dot slash and
the program's name.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Dot slash and the program's name.
Now what did this mean?
Well dot is just an arcane way
of saying current directory.
Whatever folder you are in is
referenced as, is represented as dot.
The slash is just what you've seen
in Mac OS and Windows for years,
it's a separator between a directory
or folder and the rest of some name.
In Windows it happens to go
backwards, in Linux and Mac
OS it happens to go forwards.
But it's just the separator, so it's
just an uninteresting syntactic detail.
>> The juicy part of course is
the name of the program, Hello.
And that's what make created for us.
It outputted that file for us.
But how did we get to that point?
Let's now ask the
question, what was really
going on here, at least with
regard to some of this syntax?
>> So in an sentence or so,
how did we explain away
this first line that's
highlighted in green?
What was that first line doing,
with respect to my program?
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Say it again?
STUDENT: Including and downloading
past functions [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Good.
Including, I won't say
downloading, but let's say
including functions that people
have written in the past.
And those functions are implemented
somewhere in my computer.
Someone wrote a file
years ago, and that file
is somewhere inside of the CS50
appliance, or on my hard drive
more generally.
And so this line is essentially saying,
go find that file, standard I/O dot
h, and copy and paste its contents
right here on the top of my file
so that I don't have to
do that manually myself.
>> And among the juiciest pieces inside of
that file we claimed was what function?
What function did we say was declared
or mentioned in standard I/O dot h
most likely?
Printf, right?
We did not write printf on
Monday, it just existed.
Much like Alana just came
up on stage and she just
existed and knew how to draw
something on the screen,
so does printf exist for many years.
And so this is how we access it.
Now if we move on here,
main was analogous we
said to the puzzle piece
called when green flag clicked
in the world of Scratch.
It's just sort of the
default name that humans
decided would represent the
default entry point to a program.
The chunk of programming code
that gets executed first.
>> Meanwhile these curly braces are
kind of like the curved shape
of a lot of those yellow scratch pieces.
They kind of encapsulate a whole
bunch of instructions together.
So it just kind of binds together
some related functionality.
printf of course is a function that
prints the screen, as we just did.
>> What about these parentheses?
How would you define-- even if you've
never programmed before, but just based
now on an increasing
hopefully intuition, what
are the parentheses doing for us here?
Or what are they surrounding?
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: They're saying what
you're going to print with printf.
>> DAVID MALAN: Yeah, they're saying what
Or more generally, they are
surrounding the inputs to the function.
So you can almost think
of those parentheses
as being like the metal
clip on this clipboard.
It's what's holding, it's what's
going to be used to provide arguments
into the function, which in
this case is called printf.
>> So in general almost any
time we call a function,
we are going to see a pair parentheses.
Maybe with something in it,
like now, maybe nothing in it.
But that's where you would put
the inputs or so-called arguments
to a function.
>> Here's one such argument.
I've highlighted everything
between the quotes,
because it turns out
in this language called
C, when you want to represent a
string-- that is a word or a phrase
or even a paragraph-- you have to
surround it with double quotes.
Not single quotes, double quotes.
And that's exactly what I've done here.
>> Meanwhile there's a funky
symbol toward the end there.
The backslash n.
What did we say that represented?
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: A new line.
>> DAVID MALAN: New line.
Right, you don't
generally hit Enter when
you want the program
to spit out a new line.
Rather you tell it explicitly
with this admittedly arcane piece
of syntax, backslash n, that
you want a new line to go there.
Finally the semicolon.
We didn't really talk
too much about this,
and by far this will be the bane of some
of your existence for the first problem
set, when you just failed to realize
you've forgotten something as stupid
as a semicolon.
And generally putting it
there will fix that problem.
But what's it doing
for us, would you say?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID MALAN: Sorry?
DAVID MALAN: Finishing a statement.
It's sort of like the period at
the end of an English sentence,
whereas in this language
C it's ending a statement.
An instruction of programming
code that you just want to say,
I'm done with this.
Now notice that's the only one here.
So you don't want to get in
a habit of putting semicolons
after every closed parenthesis.
For instance there's none
next to void, and we'll
come back in the future
to what void means.
But in this case your printf is a
function, or a statement being used,
and so we want to have that
terminus at the very end of it.
>> And I'm intentionally picking on C. And
frankly a lot of languages like C, C++,
Java, JavaScript, and any number of
other languages have a lot of these
sort of syntactic details.
That certainly if you're new to
programming can genuinely trip you up.
And you will, mark my
words, some of you will
have this experience
in office hours or late
at night working on some p-set, where
your damn program just doesn't compile,
it doesn't run, you have
no idea what's wrong,
it seems completely
logically correct to you.
And it's because you forgot
something like hitting
a semicolon at the end of some line.
>> But these are the kinds of things you're
going to immediately learn to see.
And indeed these are the things
that the CA's and TF's have
been sort of trained to see
much more quickly than you.
And so this is only to say, as you
dive into problem set 1 especially,
don't get frustrated by this stuff.
Once you sort of acclimate
to the world, you
begin to see things that you might not
see at first glance this first week.
>> So source code is something like that.
We want to pass it into
the so-called compiler.
And that compiler as
we said provides output
known as object code, the
so-called zeros and ones.
But from there, what does that give us?
Well it gives us these patterns.
And again your computer,
your Intel inside,
understands these patterns
of zeros and ones.
And sometimes the pattern
represents an actual decimal number
as we saw last week, sometimes
it represents a letter
like we saw last week, sometimes
it represents an instruction,
like printing something to the screen.
>> So printf for instance--
but rather, let me rewind.
We've been taking for granted
that those zeros and ones are
produced by this command make.
But make is not a compiler.
Make is not the thing in the middle
that's producing the zeros and ones.
Rather make is just a very conveniently
named program whose purpose in life
is essentially to figure out
how to compile your program.
And we use it in these
first weeks because it just
saves us a lot of trouble.
>> But what make is really
doing when you compile hello,
is, as we said last time, it's
looking on your hard drive
or in the current folder, for
file called what, apparently?
Hello.c, right?
That's just kind of a convention.
It's arbitrary, but
that's the way things are.
Make, if you just specify the name
of a program that doesn't yet exist,
it's going to look for the source code
in a file, by default means hello.c.
And if it finds it, great.
It's going to convert that source
code into object code for you.
>> But every time I've hit Enter
after running make hello,
do you recall seeing last time a
fairly long and cryptic sequence
of other white letters and
characters on the screen?
Well that was the actual command, the
actual compiler, that was running.
So the actual compiler we'll use most of
the semester is something called clang.
Some of you might have used
Visual Studio before, or GCC,
or any number of other compilers.
We'll use clang.
>> And clang allows us to actually convert
that source code to object code.
What does this actually
mean in practice?
Well let me go into one of
my folders from last time.
Inside of the CS50 appliance.
And let me go ahead and create this
same file, include standard I/O dot h.
Int main void.
And we'll come back in the future as
to what int means and what void means.
But for now let's do
hello world backslash n,
just like we did on the board.
>> Let me save this file called hello.c.
And now if I want to compile this
I could-- let me zoom in-- run
make hello enter.
And this again was
that very cryptic line.
But now at least one word
probably jumps out at you.
Clang is that line we saw before.
Now there's a lot of other stuff frankly
that we'll wave our hands at for today.
But there's a few subsets,
a few characters in here
that are of interest.
But I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to first run
hello, just to prove
that this is working as it was Monday.
But now I'm going to delete the program.
And much like we had these
short names last time,
the command for removing
something is rm, remove, enter.
You're going to get some
fairly cryptic questions.
Hard to believe that you can make
even this question hard to understand.
But remove regular file hello just
means do you want to delete hello.
>> And I can go ahead and type y for
yes, Enter, and now it's gone.
What this means now,
if I clear my screen,
is that instead of
doing make hello-- you
know what, I'm getting good at this.
I'm going to run the compiler myself.
I don't need some program to
figure out what my file is called.
I wrote hello.c, I
know what it's called,
I'm clearly capable of typing that.
So I'm going to go ahead
and do clang hello.c Enter.
>> Seems to work.
And there's no additional output,
because clang is the compiler.
It's what's converting the
source code to zeros and ones.
So if I now do dot
slash hello Enter, hm.
New error message today.
So bash is just the name of the
blinking prompt that we're using.
That's a gross oversimplification,
but for now that's all that is,
it's the blinking prompt.
And that's why it's yelling at us.
>> No such file or directory is
a little more straightforward.
But surely I made that object code.
But the catch is, that
if I type the command
to list the contents of this
directory, which is what?
ls for list.
There's a bunch of stuff in here,
some of which came with the appliance,
like my Desktop folder, Downloads
folder, Dropbox folder, and all
that stuff.
But what is interesting
is hello.c, which
I created a moment ago with gedit.
And what's the weirdest
looking name in here,
perhaps that we didn't
see last time at all?
>> a.out, right?
So back in the day, it
was just decided that when
you compile a program
for the first time,
and you don't specify the name
of a file, let's call it a.
And a.out just means this was
the output of the compiler.
So it's a horrible name for a program.
But by that logic, dot slash for
current directory, slash a.out,
should mean there's in fact
my hello world program.
Now a little warm up exercise, too.
If I want to rename this
file, turns out that you
move a file from one name to another.
So mv a.out, and then I
can call it hello Enter.
So this is a Linux command.
DOS had this years ago,
Windows has a terminal window
of some sort that looks
like this, Linux and Mac
computers have this blinking prompt.
Even though most of us probably
rarely, if ever, use it.
>> But what I've done is run a
program, whose name is mv,
and I've provided it with
two arguments, so to speak.
Two inputs.
a.out is the original name.
Hello is the new name.
So if I now do dot slash
hello, Enter, that exists.
And if I do dot slash a.out,
what do you expect I should see?
>> Bash, no such file or directory.
Because I just renamed it.
So this takes a bit of getting used to.
But the problem set 1
specification will truly
hold your hand through
some of this minutae.
Because this is a complete
intellectual distraction
from the more interesting
ideas at hand, which
is actually creating
something out of code.
But let's do one modification
now to this program.
>> Recall that last time I did something
like this, printf state your name.
And indeed we just did this
on the big screen over there.
And then I did string s gets
GetString open paren, close paren.
And paren just shorthand
notation for parenthesis.
So does GetString take any arguments?
No inputs no, but it
needs the parentheses,
because that's what demarcates
the calling of a function.
>> So I'm going to go ahead and try to
run the compiler on this program now.
Clang hello.c, because I
didn't change its name for now.
And I got a bunch of errors.
Let's zoom out here.
If I scroll up again,
like I said last time,
to the first, same error
that I got last time.
On line 6 of hello.c I had an
undeclared identifier string,
did I mean standard in?
I didn't.
Because what mistake have I made in this
program, if you recall from last time?
Yeah, we need the
so-called training wheels
that we'll just use for a few weeks.
But I need to specify that also,
somewhere inside of the appliance,
is a file that we wrote
just a few years ago.
Inside of which are functions
like apparently GetString.
So now if I go back down here,
zoom in, and re-run clang hello.c.
Damn, another error.
But we haven't seen this one before.
>> This one's a little more
esoteric to figure out.
But this is deliberately on the screen,
because we wanted to tell this story.
When you compile hello.c, just as
the picture from before suggested,
you're only converting that
source code to zeros and ones.
Now CS50 staff a few years ago wrote
CS50.h, and a corresponding file,
CS50.c.
And we, a few years ago,
compiled those files
into a file that happens
to be called CS50.o.
>> Or it can be renamed a
few different things.
But that's a simple way
of thinking about it.
So we compiled CS50's
library into zeros and ones.
But nowhere have I specified
that I want to combine my zeroes
and ones for my hello world
program with the zeros and ones
that CS50 staff created a few years
ago into one complete program.
All I've specified by writing
clang hello.c is compile hello.c.
>> I've not told clang to
link in the zeros and ones
that CS50 staff created
for you some time ago.
So it's an easy fix,
dash l for link, CS50.
And we'll again see this
before long again and again.
But notice now there was no complaints.
So now if I run dot slash
hello, now it's working.
Although that's a bit misleading
since I just recreated what file?
a.out.
>> So let me rewind for just a moment.
The program we just compiled
has the three lines of code.
When I ran hello world, hello a moment
ago, I didn't see state your name.
And that's because I ran the
old version of the program.
But if I do indeed run dot slash a.out
Enter, state your name, Rob, hello,
world.
Hm.
That's kind of a bug.
Probably meant to say Rob, right?
So what's the fix here in code.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So I just need to make that final tweak
so that I'm passing in a placeholder,
like a fill in the blank,
like we did a moment ago.
But percent s is now
that fill in the blank.
So lastly let's reveal one last
detail so that there's no magic.
I'm going to go ahead
and get rid of hellow.
and get rid of a.out.
So now I have no programs,
just my source code.
And I'm going to run a
slightly longer command, clang
dash o hello hello.c dash LCS50.
>> Now this is starting to sort of go
in one ear and out the other perhaps.
But just tease apart what this is doing.
Clang is the compiler, dash LCS50
deliberately at the very end
does what in a sentence?
Links to the CS50 library.
Grabs the zeros and
ones that the staff made
and crams them into my own program.
So the last question at hand is,
what is dash o hello probably
doing, even if you've never
seen this syntax before?
>> Outputting a program that's
not named the default a.out.
Rather it's named hello.
So now there is no a.out.
No such file or directory,
because I explicitly said
call this program hello, so that
I can now type in a name like that
and have it behave.
>> Now frankly, boy is that
uninteresting to have
to remember all of that
little minutia, right?
So let's go ahead and
get rid of hello again.
And let's now return to a world in
which it suffices to say make hello.
But that's the magic that
make is doing for you,
that's the tedium that
it's doing for you.
And as our programs and
problems get more complex,
make will truly be your friend.
Because not too long
from now we're going
to have programs that are written
not with one file, but several files,
and make will automate the process of
compiling all of that for us together.
>> So now print.
printf is inside of this file, standard
I/O dot h, that we've seen before,
but there's more to printf than that.
There's backslash n, but there's also
a bunch of other escape sequences.
And escape sequence is just a
fancy way of saying something
that starts with a backslash,
not a forward slash, a backslash,
and does some special thing.
And we won't dwell on most of these,
but why is there backslash double quote,
do you think?
Why is there this weird sequence of
characters, backslash double quote,
why might that be useful?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Exactly, right?
Think back to our hello world program
that we've seen quite a few times now,
every time we've seen that hello world
program we've had double quotes inside
of which is hello comma
world backslash n.
But think to yourself,
what if you actually
wanted to print out a quotation mark?
Your first instinct might be, I don't
know why I might want to do-- here,
we can be a little passive
aggressive, hello friend.
We might want to do something like that.
>> But why is this now problematic?
Ignoring the curly quotes aside that
keynote made for us automatically.
Why is this problematic?
>> Exactly.
Because we have like 4 quotation marks.
Well the first one probably
goes with the second one,
and maybe the fourth one
goes with the third one,
or, I mean I'm not even sure,
nor is the computer going to be.
Computers again, compilers
again, are fairly dumb.
They'll only do what
you tell them to do.
And if you're not unambiguous they
are probably going to throw an error.
>> If you're not unambiguous as to how to
make a peanut butter and jelly sandwich
strange things might arrive.
It's the same idea.
Now suffice it to say there's
some other escape sequences,
but we'll come to those before long.
Essentially these escape
sequences represent something
that you might not be able
too easily at the keyboard,
without confusing the computer.
>> Now meanwhile we have
placeholders in printf.
Percent d, which can also be written
in almost all cases as percent i,
is a placeholder for what type of data?
What type of value?
A decimal number.
So actually we'll start
using percent i because it's
a little simpler, like an integer.
Percent i.
An integer that happens to be decimal.
>> Percent s we already said was
a placeholder for a string.
Which is just a word, a phrase,
a paragraph, an essay, whatever.
It's a sequence of
characters of some length.
And we'll see before long
some of these others.
But percent c is for a single character.
Percent f is for a
floating point number,
like a real number that has
a decimal point in it, which
is of course not an integer.
And there's a whole
bunch of others as well.
>> Meanwhile in C, and
in a lot of languages,
we have different data types.
Different types of
glass bowls if you will.
The bowl I used last time
was for ping pong balls,
but we can also store different
values like chars and strings
and integers in a container,
like a variable, and C has these.
Char is the type of data,
the type of variable,
in which you can store a character.
Float is a type of variable in
which you can store a real number.
>> Int is of course for an int.
And rather ridiculously
named a long long
is where you can store essentially
a really long number, with even
more digits then a
typical int might store.
But we'll come back to that before long.
>> In CS50 dot h meanwhile
the other header file
that we've seen a couple
times in use, there's
two other data types that
don't exist in C typically.
One is string, and we'll see in
a few weeks what strings really
are underneath the hood.
And one is bool.
And a bool is a variable that
can only take on certain values.
And just based on last week's
explanation of Scratch,
and more recently C,
what would you guess
are the two possible values for
some container that is of type bool?
>> Yes and no.
One and zero.
True or false.
And indeed it's the last that tends
to be conventional in a programming
language, saying something
like true or false.
>> Meanwhile the CS50 library comes
with a bunch of functionality
that the staff wrote for you,
besides just getting a string.
We wrote in advance functions that
can get an integer from the user,
get a single character,
get a float, that
is just a number with the decimal point.
Get a long long, a really
big value from the user.
So we've only seen this in
action in the form of GetString.
But via these functions
will soon be able to write
programs that get input from the user.
>> Meanwhile consider this
program, and consider
how we might now start to add
to it with new constructs.
A quick whirlwind tour
and then we'll look
at some writing some
programs manually ourselves.
Henceforth if we want to
implement a condition,
it's not going to look like a
nice little pretty puzzle piece.
It's going to look a little more arcane.
But this is the canonical
structure of a condition in C.
>> The word if, two
parentheses, inside of which
is going to be some kind
of Boolean expression.
Now the slash slash
in the middle, this is
at the moment sort of like
pseudocode code placeholder.
But more properly, any line of code
in C that starts with slash slash
is a comment.
>> It's like a sticky note that you might
put on an essay, printed on paper.
It's a note to yourself.
It has no functional
impact on the program.
It's sort of a reminder, it's your own
documentation as to what's going on.
So do this at the moment
is sort of a placeholder
for whatever's inside
of those curly braces
eventually is going to do something.
>> Meanwhile you have two forks in the
road, an if else construct like this.
You can if, elseif, else.
Now it's worth noting, especially
if you've been Googling around
online for resources out of
curiosity, or if you pick up
one of the course's
recommended books on C,
you will see that humans have lots
of different preferences for how
to express themselves in code.
Some people like to put the
curly braces as I've done here.
Some people like to put the curly
braces for instance up here.
>> Some people like to put the elses
up here and then this over here.
There's any number of ways to
write code, and none of them
are right per se.
Although there's a few
that are pretty wrong.
But there are no-- if this is
ultimately a very religious debate.
In fact, one of the most annoying
things about computer science
is how opinionated
computer scientists can be.
And you will find over time that
even you develop personal preferences
as to how your code should look.
>> Not just behave, not just create output,
but how it should look aesthetically.
So what we will do is guide you along
the way toward, for now at least,
a standard CS50 style that at least
keeps things uniform and easy to read.
But more on those
distinctions before long.
>> A Boolean expression in C, if you
wanted to say if this condition is true
and this other condition is
true, you don't write the word
and, as you would in English.
You instead use ampersand ampersand,
for reasons we'll come back to.
If you want to say or you use two
vertical bars, which on a US keyboard
is generally above the Enter
key next to the backslash.
And this just means if this condition
or this other condition is true do this.
>> Meanwhile there's this
crazy thing, which
you'll have occasion
to use once in awhile.
But it's just an alternative
way to express yourself.
This, for now, let's
stipulate, it's just
another funky way of expressing
if, elseif, elseif, elseif, elseif.
It's just formatted in terms
of cases, where you literally
enumerate the values that
you might want to check for.
>> Meanwhile loops.
We saw a comparison of
Scratch with a loop.
And I'm going to wave my hand at
what each of these things means.
But notice that a loop will very
often start with the keyword for.
Or it will start with the keyword while.
Or it will start with the keyword
do, and end with the keyword while.
>> But what we're about to see
is things more like this.
Here is, in general in C, how you might
declare a variable and give it a value.
In C it doesn't suffice,
like in Scratch, you just
say give me a variable called something.
You have to tell C, and tell
your compiler, more specifically,
what type of value do you
want to put in the glass bowl.
>> Is it an integer?
If so, you have to
literally say int and then
the name of the variable,
then a semicolon.
If you instead wanted string and called
it s like I did my code here today,
you would say string s semicolon.
Once you want to give it a value
you can then use the equal sign,
otherwise known as the
assignment operator.
And notice how each
of these lines of code
has the semicolon at the end of it.
>> But frankly this just
looks a little ugly.
Why can't I say to the computer, give
me a variable and initialize it to zero.
That is, give me an empty glass bowl.
While you can.
And so one of the judgment calls you'll
have to make stylistically over time
is, do you write your code like this, or
do you kind of clean it up and impress
people by writing two lines as just one.
And this would be considered
generally a more elegant way
of writing your code stylistically.
>> Functions we're of course seen.
They're going to take this format.
The name of a function, some
parentheses, and then maybe some
stuff inside.
Or you might see uses of
multiple functions side
by side, like something like this.
Now as a tangent, does
this joke now make sense?
>> [LAUGHTER]
It doesn't mean it's funny, but it
does perhaps make a little more sense.
So now let's go into the
CS50 appliance for a moment.
And let me open up one teaser here.
>> And indeed one of the reasons
for introducing IKEA catalog
and flashing the picture
of the iPhone a bit ago
was to actually tie in together the
fact that just a few years ago, in 2007,
this piece of code was
released, which was
one of the very first implementation
of a piece of software
that does what's called jailbreaking.
For those unfamiliar, jailbreaking
something like a phone or an iPhone
means essentially figuring
out how to do things
with it that the company
who made it didn't intend.
Like you want to install certain
software that's not in the app store,
jailbreaking your phone which
you do things like that and more.
But what was fun in
2007-- and there's been
dozens of different versions
of these things since then,
in all sorts of languages-- is that
this program here, called iUnlock,
was actually written in C. And so I
pulled up the source code for this,
just to kind of show you some of
the similarities with the constructs
we've been discussing thus far.
Now there's way more complexity here
than we've seen already in class.
Let me scroll up just a little bit here.
>> But notice these-- well we notice a few
things-- but notice these lines here,
including standard I/O dot h.
And all-- line 24, please--
notice standard I/O
dot h and a whole bunch of other
files that apparently other people
have written.
And if we scroll down through
this, little arbitrarily,
notice I don't know how to write
all of this myself necessarily yet,
but there's if.
So apparently this has a branch.
>> And if I scroll down a little
further there's another if.
If I scroll up, I think
around line 100 I saw for.
So I'm not quite sure
how this works yet,
but this is a for loop that's going to
let me iterate some number of times.
And if I scroll all
the way to the bottom
I see that there's a
function down here called
main, and some additional credits
for your reading pleasure.
>> So this is only to say-- and we'll put
this online among the course's source
code today-- that even some of these
devices that we take for granted,
at the end of the day you're still
using these basic constructs that we've
been introducing already thus far.
That's enough of that one.
All right, so now let's
actually build something.
>> Let's go beyond something like
hello.c, and open up this,
let's write this program here.
I'm going to go ahead and
write a program called adder.c,
whose purpose in life is going to be
like my first super simple calculator
that just adds a couple of numbers.
Not because that's a hard
problem, but because it
allows me to now tie
together a few things.
So I'm going to go ahead and include
standard I/O dot h and CS50 dot h.
I'm going to say int main void.
And again in the future
we'll come back to it
into in this context and void means.
>> And now I'm going to say something
like printf, give me an integer.
And now on my second line,
how do I express myself such
that I want to declare a variable
that's going to store an int?
Literally what do I type if I want to
create a variable that stores an int
would you say?
int a equals getint.
Sure, so that works.
And just for consistency
with the code you'll
see online, let me change
this to x, just because x
is a common variable name
to use, at least in algebra.
Now let me go ahead and do printf again.
Give me another integer.
And now I'm going to kind
of learn from that pattern,
I'm going to say int y gets to GetInt.
>> And we've not used
GetInt before, but just
like GetString goes and gets a string,
like Javier did from the audience,
similarly does GetInt
start blinking the prompt.
And effectively waiting for the user
to give it an integer, by typing it in
and hitting Enter.
Now lastly I'm going to do
this, printf the sum of--
and let me get fancy now--
percent i and percent i is present
i exclamation point backslash n.
And what do you think I'm going to
put in now as the additional inputs
to printf?
>> I don't want to say
literally quote unquote x.
I want to class in x and
then, and now let's get fancy
and let's just assume
we can do what we want.
What you want to say next?
x plus y.
And indeed that will work.
It's minimally programming languages
do understand basic arithmetic,
and so this should in fact work.
>> So let me go ahead and do make
adder in my black and white window
down here, Enter.
Cryptic line but no error
message, so that's good.
Dot slash adder, give me an integer, 1.
Give me another integer, 2.
The sum of 1 and 2 is 3.
>> All right, so a pretty trivial
program, but what's it done?
It's allowed me to use a function
call here, call another function here,
two calls to GetInt, a
third call to printf,
and then using these placeholders.
So it's a little more
sophisticated than last time.
But what if I want to
get a little fancier?
>> Let me go ahead and now do this.
Let me go ahead and create a
new file called conditions zero.
And I'm going to save
some time for classes sake
and just paste in that
code as a starting point.
And now I'm just going to put
something new here in the middle.
So printf I'd like an integer please.
And all this code is available
on the course's website,
you needn't type it all out
in class if you'd rather not.
int, and now I'm going to
use, instead of x and y,
I'm going to use n, which is
probably the most common name
for an integer in a computer program.
And now I want to do a
little judgment here.
I'm going to see if n
is greater than 0, then
I'm going to say printf-- whoops,
printf-- you picked a positive number,
exclamation point backslash n.
Close that.
Else I'm going to print out printf
you picked a negative number.
>> Now before you yell at me,
let's run this program.
Let me go down here.
And how do I compile a program
called conditions dash 0?
Make conditions dash 0.
Kind of a stupid name, but-- dammit.
OK, good teaching moment.
Why did that break?
>> What did I accidentally call this file?
You can kind of infer
from the tab up here.
So it's not bad that I
did this, because this
will happen perhaps to some of you.
So I accidentally named my
source code condition 0.
But my source code by convention should
be in a file called condition 0 dash c,
or whatever dot c.
>> So let me fix this.
Just like Microsoft Word I can go up
to Save As and do condition 0 dot c.
Now just to be tidy I'm
going to go ahead and remove
condition 0, which was my old version.
And now let's do make
condition 0, Enter.
OK, seems good.
>> Condition 0, Enter.
I'd like an integer please, 50,
you picked a positive number.
Now how about negative 50?
You picked a negative number.
How about now, 0.
Pretty sure 0's not negative.
>> So this is kind of a logical bug.
How do I fix this?
Else if n is less than 0, do this, else
we can have a three way branch here,
printf you picked 0.
So now if I rerun this
program, after compiling it
again with make, and now rerun
condition 0, what I'll see here
is 0 gives me that output.
So where are we going with this?
>> Well it's very easy to lose sight
of the forest for the trees.
And so allow us to conclude
with this 2 and 1/2 minute video
that ultimately is a bit
of an ad from Google,
but that really is testament to
what even using these basic building
blocks we can ultimately do once
we have a bit of programming
savvy under our belts.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> SAROO BRIERLEY (VOICEOVER):
It was 26 years ago,
and I was just about to turn 5.
We got to the train station and
we boarded our train together.
My brother just said I'll
stay here, and I'll come back.
And I just thought, well you know,
I might as well just go to sleep
and he'll just wake me up.
And when I woke up the next
day, the whole carriage
was empty on a runaway train, a ghost
train taking me I don't know where.
>> I was adopted out to Australia,
to an Australian family.
And mom had decorated my
room with the map of India,
which she put next to my bedside.
I woke up every morning
seeing that map, and hence
it sort of kept the memories alive.
People would say, you're
trying to find a needle
in a haystack, Saroo
you'll never find it.
>> I'd have flashed of the places that I
used to go, the flashes of my family
faces.
There was the image of my mother,
sitting down with her legs crossed,
just watching her cry.
Life is just so hard.
That was my treasure.
And I was looking at Google Map and
realized there's Google Earth as well.
In a world where you could zoom into,
I started to have all of these thoughts
and what possibilities
that this could do for me.
I said to myself, you know, you've
got all those photographic memories
and landmarks where you're from, and
you know what the town looks like.
This could be an application that
you can use to find your way back.
>> I thought, well I'll put a
dot on Calcutta train station,
and a radius line, you know, that you
should be searching around this area.
I sort of came across
these train tracks.
And I started following it, and
I came to a train station which
reflected the same image
that was in my memories.
Everything matched.
I just thought yep, I
know where I'm going.
I'm just going to let the
map that I have in my head
lead me and take me back to my hometown.
>> I came to the doorstep of
the house that I was born.
And walked around about 15
meters around the corner,
there was three ladies standing
outside, adjacent to each other.
And the middle one stepped forward, and
I just thought, this is your mother.
She came forward, she hugged me, and
we were there for about five minutes.
>> She grabbed my hand and
she took me to the house
and got on the phone, where she
rang my sister and my brother
to say that, you know,
your brother has just
all of sudden appeared like a ghost.
And then the family was reunited again.
Everything's all good,
I helped my mother out,
she doesn't have to be slaving away.
She can live the rest
of her life in peace.
>> It was a needle in a haystack,
but the needle was there.
Everything's there.
Everything we have in the world
is at the tap of a button.
But you've got to have the will and
the determination to wanting it.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: Wonderfully
sweet testimonial
to just what you can
now do with technology.
We will see you next week.