>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: This is CS50,
Harvard University's introduction
to the intellectual
enterprises of computer science
and the art of programming.
Now if you are among those that
every year are sitting here
with a bit of nerves in your mind, such
that you don't think you belong here,
you think that most
anyone sitting around you
knows far more than you, is indeed
more comfortable than you at computer
science or computers
more generally, realize
that 78% of the students who now
take CS50 have no prior experience.
>> Indeed, there's 100 dots there
on the display, 78 of which
are solid green, which means you,
if you're among that demographic,
are in very good company here on out.
And if you are instead among the
22% of CS50 students who do indeed
have prior experience, whether in
high school or some other program,
realize that you, too, will
be challenged in the course.
>> Not only do we have different tracks
for students less comfortable and more
comfortable alike in sections, we
also have so-called hacker editions
of most problem sets that
will challenge those students
with that additional experience
to explore similar material
but from a more
sophisticated perspective.
>> But what is computer science?
Well, ultimately, what's going to
matter as you explore this field is not
so much where you end up
relative to your classmates,
but where you yourself end up in
week 12 versus where you begin here
in week zero.
Now computer science-- well, let's
call it the science of computation--
where computation is really just a
fancy way of saying, taking some input,
producing some output, and
doing so by running algorithms,
sets of instructions for solving
some problem on those inputs
in order to produce some output or
solution in which you are interested.
>> So we recently had
occasion to travel out
to California to meet with an alumna.
Her name is Susan Wojcicki.
And she'd like to speak
to you here on video
to testify to just how applicable
even just a taste of computer
science at the
introductory level can be.
Even if you don't go on to pursue
computer science as a field,
or even engineering,
or STEM more generally,
you'll see, in fact, how a certain
course so influenced her life.
And she only just took it when she
was a senior here at Harvard College.
>> If we could dim the lights for Susan.
SUSAN WOJCICKI: Hello, world.
I'm Susan Wojcicki.
I'm the CEO of YouTube.
And I took CS50 when I was
a senior at Harvard in 1990.
I was actually a history
and literature major.
>> And my junior summer,
I realized that maybe I
wanted to learn something
about computers.
And so, I came back.
I took CS50.
It was hard, but it was the
most amazing class I took.
>> It changed how I think about everything.
And when I graduated from Harvard
in 1990, I went to Silicon Valley.
And I got a job.
And I've been working
in tech ever since.
DAVID J. MALAN: Now what Susan
didn't mention in this video,
that it was actually in her
garage that Google itself was
founded by Larry and Sergey.
>> Now we also reached out to our friends
at code.org, an organization that
over the past year has been
getting people particularly
excited about computer science
and programming, in particular.
But it's worth noting that programming
is not computer science per se.
Computer science is not programming.
Rather programming is just a
tool-- with which all of you
will be all too well
familiar by semester's end--
such that you can apply not
just to future courses in CS
but to whatever fields from whence
you're coming, in humanities,
social sciences, natural
science, or the like.
>> Indeed, allow a few other
alumni and their colleagues
to speak to the applicability
of the field that awaits.
>> BILL GATES: I was 13 when I
first got access to a computer.
>> JACK DORSEY: My parents
bought me a Macintosh in 1984
when I was eight-years-old.
>> MARK ZUCKERBERG: I was
in the sixth grade.
>> SPEAKER 1: I learned to code in college.
>> RUCHI SANGHVI: Freshman year, first
semester, Intro to Computer Science.
>> BILL GATES: I wrote a program
that played tic-tac-toe.
>> DREW HOUSTON: I think it was
pretty humble beginnings.
I think the first program
I wrote asked things like,
what's your favorite color?
Or how old are you?
ELENA SILENOK: I first learned
how to make a green circle
and a red square appear on the screen.
GABE NEWELL: The first
time I actually had
something come up and say, hello, world.
And I made a computer do that.
It was just astonishing.
>> MARK ZUCKERBERG: Learning how
to program didn't start off
as wanting to learn
all of computer science
or trying to master this
discipline or anything like that.
It just started off because I
wanted to do this one simple thing.
I wanted to make something that
was fun for myself and my sisters.
>> And I wrote this little program.
And then basically just
added a little bit to it.
And then when I needed
to learn something new,
I looked it up, either in
a book or on the internet,
and then added a little bit to it.
>> DREW HOUSTON: It's really not unlike
playing an instrument or something
or playing a sport.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
So let us now actually
dive in a little deeper.
What are these inputs and outputs
that we're talking about here?
>> So how about something simple?
You probably know, even if you have
no familiarity with computer science
whatsoever, that computers somehow use
and understands only zeros and ones.
But how can that possibly be given how
much today's desktops and laptops alike
can do?
>> The DNA of the day, the only
alphabet that they understand
is a zero or a one.
Well, consider this.
We, humans, tend to use the
decimal system. "Dec" meaning 10.
And that's 10 because we have
10 digits, 0 through nine.
>> Now computers, by contrast,
tend to use binary.
"Bi" meaning two.
So they tend to use only zero and one.
But it turns out, that even
just with zeros and ones, that
is a sufficiently large alphabet
with which to represent most
any piece of data you want,
whether it's a number,
whether it's a letter, whether it's
a graphic or video on the screen.
>> Consider, for instance, how we humans
typically interpret this number here.
This is just three
digits, one, two, three.
But we know this number
innately now as 123.
But why is that?
>> Well, if you think back
to perhaps grade school,
you probably were taught to think of
these numbers as being in columns,
where the one is in the hundreds
place, the two is in the tens place,
and the three is in the ones place.
Why is that actually useful?
Well, think about the
super simple arithmetic
that we all have been
doing for years now.
Effectively, if you've got
a one in the hundreds place,
you do the quick math 100
times 1 plus 10 times 2--
because two is in the tens
place-- plus 1 times 3--
because three is in the ones place.
So, of course, if we
actually multiply this out,
what we're really representing
with this pattern-- one
two three-- is 100 plus 20 plus
3, which, of course, is 123.
>> Now binary, and computers really,
fundamentally speak the same language
that we do.
They just have a smaller alphabet.
So computers only have zeros
and ones at their disposal.
So whereas we humans have essentially
powers of 10 in each of these places--
10 to the zero, 10 to the one, ten
to the two, giving you 110 and 100
respectively.
>> Because computers only have two values
they can understand, zero and one,
they have to use different values
in these columns, one, two, four.
And if we kept going, eight,
16, 32, 64, and so forth.
But the pattern and the
mentality is exactly the same.
>> So by this logic, anyone, how would
I go about representing the number
one in binary?
If you've never even thought about
this before, what's your gut say?
>> AUDIENCE: One.
DAVID J. MALAN: One.
Exactly.
We just need a one in the
ones place because the zeros
suffice to give us
neither a four nor a two.
So one times one equals one.
Now things get a little interesting.
If I want to represent in
binary the number two-- but,
again, even if you've never
spoken this language before,
how do we represent in binary
the value we humans know as two?
Zero one zero.
Just put the one in the
column that you want it.
>> Now it's getting pretty
easy probably now.
So if I want to represent three--
there is no three's column.
So, again, I can now add these values
together by putting a one here.
So 2 times 1 plus 1
times 1 is, of course, 3.
>> Now things get a little fun in
that the ones now become zeros.
And to represent four, I get this.
And if we increment slowly
here-- that would be five.
This would be six.
This would be seven.
>> But now I seem to have
run into a problem.
How might I go about representing
eight-- would be the next value.
Yeah, so we need a new bits.
And, indeed, if you've
heard this phrase before,
bits, that's just short for
binary digit, zero or one.
>> And so I happen to be representing
only three such bits here.
But if I had a way of storing not
three different bits, but four,
surely I could represent
eight, and then nine, and then
10, and even higher and higher.
>> But that then calls
into question how we can
go about representing these
things in the first place.
It's one thing to draw
them up here on a slide,
but how do you represent them
if you're a mechanical device?
What is a computer doing to
represent the inputs and outputs that
fundamentally define computation
at the end of the day?
>> Well, what about something
super simple like this?
It's just a light bulb.
And I can trigger this
light bulb to go on
by turning some electricity
on and allowing electrons
to flow through, which changes its
state or its value, so to speak.
For instance, this is
an old school desk lamp
here with one such
light bulb inside of it.
And right now it's not
really doing anything useful.
But as soon as I plug it
into an electrical socket
and then use this switch-- or
we can even call it a transistor
or think of it as such--
I can now represent either
this value, where the light bulb's
obviously off, or this value.
This value or this value.
This value and so forth.
>> So inside of a computer, presumably,
are much smaller pieces of hardware,
but that at the end
of the day simply have
to use electricity--
perhaps capture it--
and then either keep something
on or keep something off.
Of course, this isn't
particularly interesting to do
with just a single light bulb.
>> In fact, how high can I count in
binary with this desk lamp here?
>> AUDIENCE: One.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: One, right?
I need more desk lamps if I
actually want to count higher.
But we can do better than that.
Because the light bulbs that
we've put in these things
are actually fancier light bulbs
than yesteryear would allow.
And they're actually
networked light bulbs.
And bunches of companies
make these things these days.
>> But it turns out that
this one in particular
comes with a feature whereby
you can change its colors.
So for instance, if you
adorned your dorm room
with a few of these light
bulbs, depending on your mood,
depending on who comes in,
depending on the weather,
depending on the time
of day, you can actually
change the colors of
the bulbs in your room.
And that's because these light
bulbs and others like it have what's
called an API, an application
programming interface, which
is a topic with which you'll be well
familiar with by semester's end.
>> And this is just a fancy,
cryptic way of saying,
you can program these light
bulbs to do your bidding.
You can send them messages
just like you, a human,
can send a message to a web server
saying, give me today's news
or give me my email.
>> You can send more arcane
messages to these light bulbs
to say, turn on and turn off.
But that's not all that interesting.
You can say, turn on red,
turn on green, turn on blue,
all with the same light bulb.
And you can even, with a bit more
savvy, say, turn yourself to blue
when it's a gloomy day
outside, for instance.
It can actually patch into
a weather API and find out
what the weather is, or the time
of day, or other such triggers.
>> So, in fact, two of
CS50's own staff members,
Dan Bradley and Ansel
Duff here, kindly procured
us a whole bunch of these light bulbs.
And they built CS50's
first ever binary bulbs,
where we've represented here--
with these playful little magnets--
the various placeholders we
alluded to just a bit ago.
>> So way over here is the
ones place, two, four.
And we didn't see higher than that.
But, of course, they're powers of two.
Eight, 16, 32, 64, and 128.
So if I now want to be a little fancier
than using this old school switch,
I have here on this iPad
a super simple interface
that Dan Bradley, a former
student and now teaching fellow,
programed using some HTML
and JavaScript, which
are markup and programming
languages respectively.
And you can probably
see-- even in the back--
there's a big plus and a big minus,
plus one button for each of these bulbs.
And what this is going to allow me to
do is, for instance, click the plus
and now represent, of
course, what number?
One.
And I can hit it again.
Two.
Three.
Four.
Five.
Six.
Seven.
>> And here now we get that rollover,
but we have a fourth bit this time,
so now we have eight.
So we could do this for quite some time.
In fact, as an aside,
how high could we count?
Anyone?
>> AUDIENCE: 255.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: 255, right?
Don't worry too much about the math for
now, but that's a pretty decent number.
But it actually does bound just
how many pieces of information,
like a letter, or a graphic
that we could represent.
>> But no matter for now.
I'm going to go ahead
and turn them all off.
And if I could, I'd like to ask for
a volunteer, our first volunteer--
oh, hello-- on stage.
The catch is you have to be
comfortable appearing, as you clearly
are in front of all your classmates,
as well as on the internet.
And let me look a little beyond the--
how about here in the white shirt?
And hand up.
Come on up.
What is your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Jackie.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Jackie.
Jackie, come on up.
So what there is also on this
iPad is a button called Game Mode.
And this Game Mode is
going to allow me to input
in advance a particular decimal
number, the numbers we humans are
familiar with.
And then you will be challenged
here to use the buttons
on the top-- one for
each of these bulbs--
to actually figure out
the pattern of light bulbs
that represents the number in question.
>> And I'm sorry, what was your name again?
>> AUDIENCE: Jackie.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Jackie.
All right.
Good to meet you.
>> So let me go ahead and program in
for the world to see the number 15.
We'll keep it small at first here.
And I'm going to go into Game Mode.
And I'm going to specify,
give us the number 15.
>> OK.
And now with everyone watching-- if
you want to maybe stand this way,
because it will line up-- go ahead and
toggle the eight buttons along the top
to turn the bulbs on
or off as you see fit.
>> AUDIENCE: OK.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And no cheating
by hitting plus 15 times.
Oh, we are going to do that.
>> AUDIENCE: Oh, wait.
I'm so sorry.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: You can also turn
the light bulbs on individually
with each of these buttons on top.
AUDIENCE: Oh, OK.
So it would be like--
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
So now we have eight.
So let's pause for the
audience to engage here.
What number is Jackie
currently representing?
11.
So we're almost there.
And excellent.
So we have our first winner.
Congratulations.
>> And we thought we'd have
some fabulous giveaways.
If you'd like to be one such
dorm room here on campus,
you can yourself have a final project
using now this API, thanks to Jackie.
So now--
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> --if we could, one more
such around of this.
Oh, now everyone wants some light bulbs.
For the so-called hacker edition,
we're going to ramp it up a-- oh,
yeah, noncommittal.
I think you're coming up now
if your hand's going down.
What is your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Alex.
DAVID J. MALAN: Alex, come on over here.
So for Alex, we are going to
program in a slightly larger number.
Perhaps in order.
The number 50.
>> AUDIENCE: OK.
DAVID J. MALAN: But, as
I said-- and you might
want to stand here so
that the buttons line up
as you would expect-- but I did
call this the hacker edition.
So-- good luck!
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> You will be able to turn
them off if you-- OK.
Excellent.
Wonderful.
Congratulations.
>> [APPLAUSE]
I suppose I should pay up.
Congratulations to Alex as well.
OK.
>> So the ultimate takeaway
here is hopefully, frankly,
the simplicity-- the
simplicity with which
you can get some nice light
bulbs, apparently in [INAUDIBLE].
But they represent,
ultimately, the same ideas
with which we humans are
already all too familiar.
So what might the next
step be in the progression
of trying to do something
interesting with data
and representing inputs that aren't just
numbers but are maybe letters or more?
>> Well, it turns out that the
computer world, for many years,
simply adopted an arbitrary but a
consistent standard that maps numbers
to letters of the alphabet.
For instance, here is an
excerpt from that mapping.
It's called Ascii.
A-S-C-I-I. And that is simply a
table that maps uppercase letters--
in this case-- to decimal numbers.
>> But what's the implication?
Well, if you actually want to represent
something like an email or some text
on a web page, you
obviously want to show
the human letters of the
alphabet, not numbers.
So depending on the
context of the program
that a user is using, if it's
a web browser or email client,
numbers can certainly be
interpreted as letters.
That is to say, patterns of bits can
easily be interpreted as letters.
>> And so what we can have
is the letter A being
represented as 65, B
being represented as 66.
So if we have a super
short word, like hi,
what a computer would ultimately
store in decimal but really in binary,
using some sequence of bits, leveraging
a bit of electricity in some way,
would be the two numbers 72 and 73.
>> But the pattern of bits that
represents those values.
So these then are how we can
represent our inputs and outputs.
And suffice it to say, we can
do more complex representations
ultimately with things like
graphics, videos, music, and more
as we'll see later this term.
>> So that just leaves then
algorithms, these sets
of instructions with which
we're solving actual problems.
We're passing in inputs to algorithms.
And those algorithms are producing
outputs, hopefully correct outputs
and hopefully, too,
efficiently gathered outputs.
In other words, it's one thing
to implement something correctly.
It's another thing to implement
something well or efficiently.
>> For instance, one demonstration
that we're fond of in the course
is this one.
But these things are getting
increasingly hard to find.
But this is indeed an old school
phone book, inside of which
are 1,000 plus pages of
names and telephone numbers.
And if I wanted to look up
someone in this phone book,
I could simply do a
very naive algorithm.
I could open up to the first page, and
I could start to look for, say, someone
named Mike Smith.
And if he's not on the first
page, I progress to the second,
and then to the third, and then
to the fourth, and so forth,
until I finally find Mike Smith.
>> Now is that algorithm correct?
>> AUDIENCE: Yes.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
If he's in there, I'll
eventually find him.
But it's arguably not very
efficient, certainly not fast,
because, my god, why am I
wasting my time flipping
through all of these pages when I could
certainly do this physically faster?
>> Well, a slight optimization, so to
speak, might be not one page at a time,
but two, four, six, eight, 10.
Still correct?
>> AUDIENCE: No.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So no if I for
instance skip over Mike Smith.
But so long as I back pedal
one page, if I overshoot him,
maybe we could correct what
might otherwise be a gotcha.
>> But is it better?
Is it faster?
I mean, yeah.
It's literally twice as fast
if I do two pages at a time.
So if I originally had 1,000 pages,
now I only have to flip 500 times,
not fully 1,000 pages to get
potentially in the worst case
to the end of the phone
book, where someone
like Mike Smith or someone with
a later name might actually be.
>> But, of course, we
humans certainly aren't
going to be doing that, certainly
not at this point in our lives.
What is a reasonable
human likely going to do?
AUDIENCE: Go straight to the9 S's.
DAVID J. MALAN: Go straight to the S's?
How do I go straight to the S's?
>> AUDIENCE: Rip it in half.
DAVID J. MALAN: Well,
there's no marking.
So, yes, if there were indeed
a label or a sticky tab for S,
we should jump right there.
But it's pretty innocuous.
So the best I can do is roughly
to the S section or maybe roughly
into the middle.
But the key takeaway
now-- and the intuition
that you've taken for
granted for years probably--
is that what do you now
know about this problem?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Mike Smith is surely
not in this half of the problem
because Smith comes after the middle
which is roughly the M section,
it seems to be.
So as you might have seen at
Visitas, we can now literally
tear this problem in half.
AUDIENCE: Woo!
DAVID J. MALAN: It's
getting easier and easier.
[APPLAUSE]
There you go.
[LAUGHTER]
And now I fundamentally
have the same problem,
but it's literally half as big.
I'm still looking for Mike Smith.
And I daresay, I can still
look for him in the same way,
splitting the problem in half
again, tearing the problem again
in half, which now leaves me with
a problem a quarter of the size,
dramatically throw that half away, and
repeat this process again and again
and again, glancing down
at each point to see
if Mike Smith is on
the page in question.
>> Now if I do this right,
ultimately I'll find myself
with just one page on which Mike Smith
is if he's indeed in the phone book.
Of course, I could
never call Mike again.
But the point here is that if we started
with 1,000 pages, my first algorithm,
flip the page, maybe 1,000 times--
definitely less because it's
an S name and not a Z name, but as
many as 1,000 pages potentially.
>> Second algorithm, better.
500 pages.
Third algorithm, though,
how many steps would it
take to divide a 1,000 page
phone book in half like that?
10, give or take.
So only by flipping through that
phone book, diving and conquering,
so to speak, 10 times, will I make
my way down to just one single page.
>> And so we can capture this intuition
now a little bit graphically
if you just consider
this super simple graph.
We're on the x-axis, or horizontal
axis, is the size of my problem,
the number of pages in the phone book.
And computer scientists
generally like to call
the size of a problem n, where
n is just some variable that
represents-- in this
case-- number of pages.
>> The vertical, or y-axis, here is
going to be the time to solve,
maybe the number of page turns,
maybe the number of seconds
or minutes, whatever
your unit of measure is.
And so this red line
represents the first algorithm,
because there's a one to one
relationship between number
of pages and amount of time it takes.
>> If Verizon doubles the number of
pages in the phone book next year,
my running time-- the
time required to execute
that first algorithm--
doubles in the worst case.
But the second algorithm,
where I'm flipping by two,
requires less time for
a given size problem.
So if I have this many
pages here-- notice
that the yellow line
suggests less time to solve.
And indeed, it represents,
we'll say, n over two.
>> But what's the shape of the third
and final curve going to look like?
Yeah, it's indeed going to look-- I
don't know what you were going to say.
But let's see what
you were going to say.
>> AUDIENCE: Like that.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It's going to look like
this, a logarithmic slope-- exactly--
whereby you have this curious slope.
It's no longer a straight line.
And what's compelling about that is that
even though the graph is now cut off,
you can extrapolate in your
mind that that green line's not
going to increase in
height all that much
as you proceed further
down that horizontal axis.
>> Indeed, Verizon, for
instance, could double
the number of pages in the phone
book between this year and next year
from 1,000 to 2000
pages, but no big deal.
With this third and final,
there's a intuitive algorithm
of dividing and conquering.
It's going to take me how many more
steps next year to find someone
like Mike Smith?
>> AUDIENCE: One.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: There's just one.
And they can quadruple it, it's
going to take me just two more steps
and so forth.
And so this is testament to
just how some careful design
and some appreciation for what
your inputs are can do even better.
Now we're cheating a
little bit in the sense
that we're leveraging an assumption.
What is my assumption
about our phone book
that allowed me to divide and conquer
in this intuitive and still correct way?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So it was ordered.
It was alphabetized by
the phone book company.
If it were in random order, that
would be a hell of a phone book,
but it certainly wouldn't
lend itself to the algorithm
I used, because you would never
just happen across Mike Smith
if you kept dividing in
half in that way by chance.
>> So let's now formalize
what's clearly intuitive.
So something called
pseudocode is where we'll
begin some of our initial problems.
And this is a generic way of describing
an algorithm or a computer program,
not using C, or C++, or Java,
or any specific language,
but just using English, with
which any human might be familiar.
>> And we might write the pseudocode
for this problem as follows.
Step one, pick up the phone book.
Step two, open to middle of phone book.
Step three, look at the names.
Step four, if Smith is among names--
>> And now this is an
interesting construct.
It's a decision point.
It's a fork in the road, if you
will, a branch, so to speak.
So I'm going to indent
just by convention step--
not five-- which is to
say, I'll call Mike.
So this indentation, totally
arbitrary human convention, but it's
simply meant to convey semantically
that if Smith is among names,
then I should call Mike.
>> Meanwhile in step six, notice
that the indentation's gone.
So else is the other fork in the
road, the other road I might travel.
So else if Smith is
earlier in the book, what's
my next step probably going to be here?
AUDIENCE: You go to the left side.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so go to
the left half of the phone book.
Throw away the right half if
Smith is earlier in the book.
So open to the middle of
the left half of the book.
>> And then step eight, go to line three.
And this is a curious loop I'm
inducing, a recursion so to speak.
But more on that in the future.
>> I'm using my same algorithm,
my same pseudocode,
to solve the same problem again
because the only thing that's changed
is the size of the problem, not
my objective, and not the person
I'm looking for.
So I can reuse the algorithm
that I've already defined.
>> Else if Smith is later
in book-- you might
guess-- open to the middle of
the right half of the book.
And again, go to line three.
Else-- what's the final line
in this program going to be?
If he's not among the
names on the page I'm
on, if he's not earlier in
the book, and he's not later
in the book, what do I know
is true about Mike Smith now?
AUDIENCE: He's not in the book.
DAVID J. MALAN: He's not in the book.
So the best I can do is just
give up and stop this program.
All right.
So at this point, let's take a
quick tour of some of what awaits.
And in fact, I'm joined here
by a number of CS50 staff.
If these folks could all
join me up here on stage.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Mind you, this is only
a subset of CS50 staff,
since each year we have nearly 100 staff
members in roles of course assistants,
teaching fellows, and more.
Come on up.
So they will join us here
awkwardly for just a moment
as we give a whirlwind tour of what
you should expect here in the course.
>> So first and foremost, we have SAT/UNS
as the grading option in the course.
This is meant deliberately
to be an option whereby
if you are a bit uneasy
at being in the course,
and you do fear failure-- even if
frankly failure means hurting your GPA,
getting a B and not an A-- that is
precisely what, certainly for a gateway
course like CS50 and other
introductory courses,
this grading option is meant to allow.
>> I wholeheartedly encourage
students-- especially
if on the fence-- to start the
course SAT/UNS, even remain SAT/UNS.
But you can certainly switch to a letter
grade by the fifth Monday in the term.
>> Frankly, back when I
was a freshman in 1995,
I myself didn't even take CS50
because I didn't get up the nerve
to actually step foot in the classroom.
It seemed a domain far too
unfamiliar to me and really only
for those friends of mine,
frankly, who had been programming
since they were six-
or maybe 10-years-old.
And it was only because I was
able to take CS50 in my day
in the equivalent version of
SAT/UNS-- pass/fail back in the day--
that even I took 50.
And somehow or other, I'm
here again with you today.
>> Now meanwhile what else you
should keep in mind about 50
is simultaneous enrollment.
Contrary to rumors that
you might have heard,
you can, in fact, simultaneously
enroll in CS50 and another class that
meets at the same or some overlapping
time as CS50's lectures right here.
See the syllabus for the particulars
of the implementation thereof.
>> Lectures, meanwhile, contrary to
what's officially in the catalog,
will generally only
meet for just an hour.
On occasion we may run a little long.
But keep in mind that the
goal in CS50's lectures
is to provide you with
a conceptual overview,
hopefully some demonstrations,
maybe even some giveaways,
of what awaits for
the week that follows.
>> And so in lectures, we'll explore
those topics and examples together,
bringing students up on stage, and
staff up on stage as often as we can,
for just a couple of hours each week.
Sections, meanwhile, will be
offered by these folks here-- many
of them teaching fellows, some
of them course assistants-- will
be happening weekly.
>> And what's key to keep
in mind is that we
do have-- not unlike First
Nights, the music class--
different tracks of sections for
students less comfortable, more
comfortable, and somewhere in between.
And frankly, you know if
you're less comfortable.
And you probably know if
you're more comfortable.
And if you're not really sure, you are
by definition somewhere in between.
So when it comes time to section
in a week or so, per the syllabus,
we'll ask you that question.
And you can self-select based
on your own comfort level
and be with students-- be with green
dots-- similar in comfort level to you.
>> Meanwhile, we have problem
sets, which will ultimately
define your experience in this course.
They're offered typically
in multiple editions.
A standard edition that we expect most
every student in the course to tackle
but also a so-called hacker edition
that offers no form of extra credit
outright but really the bragging rights
to say that you tried and tackled
the course's hacker editions that
approach the similar material
but from a more sophisticated angle.
>> What we offer for the
standard edition, for,
again, a super majority
of students, are not
only walk-throughs, which are
videos led by the course's staff
that truly walk you through the
course's problems and possible design
implementations.
And we also, after the
fact, offer postmortems,
whereby if you're wondering
how you could have
or should have solved some
problem, the teaching staff
will walk you through
those on video as well.
>> Meanwhile, what awaits too are
five late days and the fact
that we will drop your
lowest problem set score.
We certainly appreciate that in exchange
for the workload that 50 expects
of you, life gets in the way
sometimes, if not five times.
And so this will offer
you a bit of flexibility,
extending your deadline from, say, a
Thursday at noon to a Friday at noon.
See the syllabus for the
implementation details thereof.
>> Now what now awaits?
And it's only occurring
to me now just how long
I'm having you guys stand here on stage.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: But we'll get to
the climactic finish before long.
So what awaits in terms
of the problem sets?
Well, perhaps a teaser of what we all
did last year with your predecessors.
In the first problem set
last year, we introduced
Scratch, a graphical
programming language that
lets you program literally by
dragging and dropping puzzle pieces,
like these, that are
reminiscent of the constructs
will see just one week
hence, when we switch
to a more traditional
language, known as C.
>> Last year we proceeded
to this problem set,
involving for cryptography,
the scrambling of information
to keep it from governmental or friends'
eyes that you don't want to see it.
Encoded in here is a
message that soon you
will be able to decrypt or de-scramble.
>> Breakout was a problem
set last year, wherein
you use these new found programming
skills to actually implement
a game wherein-- as you
may recall from childhood--
the goal was to bash the
bricks that are atop the screen
here, accumulating a
score along the way,
and implementing your own algorithms
with which this solution ultimately
lets you play the game.
Meanwhile, later in the
semester, we will give you
a dictionary of 143,091 English words.
And you will be challenged
to write a program that
spell checks, documents, by
loading that many words into memory
as efficiently as possible.
Generally pitting you
against your classmates
if you opt into a bit of a
challenge in leader board
to see who can use the fewest
seconds of running time,
and the fewest number
of megabytes of memory,
and actually fine-tuning your programs
to be incredibly resource efficient not
just time.
>> Last year, too, we looked at the end
of the semester at web programming.
And indeed, we'll do that again this
year with multiple problem sets,
introducing you to the techniques and
the mindset with which you can apply
these programming skills to
websites, dynamic websites,
websites that actually solve
problems and behave differently
and are not simply static
sites with static information.
>> The final project ultimately
will define, though,
the climax of the course
for students, wherein
you'll be challenged to implement
most anything of interest
to you, so long as it somehow
draws upon the course's lessons.
>> And as you saw in the
video at the start,
we will conclude the semester with the
CS50 Hackathon, which if, unfamiliar,
will begin at 7:00 PM one night and
end at 7:00 AM the next morning.
Around 9:00 PM, we'll
order in first dinner.
Around 1:00 AM, we'll
order in second dinner.
And if you're still
standing at 5:00 AM, we
will shuttle bus you
to IHOP for breakfast.
>> The CS50 Fair, meanwhile, is an event
to which 2,000 plus faculty, students,
and staff from across campus will
come to see your accomplishments
in the course and the final
projects and creations
that you create on your laptops,
desktops, or perhaps even light bulbs.
>> Meanwhile, office hours
and the support structure.
And now it would've been a
better time to bring you all up.
>> Office hours will take place four nights
a week for multiple hours each night
with generally 20 to 30 of the
course's staff on duty at once
to provide you with intimate
one-on-one opportunities for support
with the course's problem sets.
Tutoring too will be
available, particularly
for students less comfortable-- or
dare say least comfortable-- for whom
office hours are not the
most nurturing environment
and are certainly not
the most stress-free.
Especially when deadlines are pressing,
we will proactively pair you ourselves
with a member of the staff to work with
on some regular schedule as your needs
and their schedule allows.
>> And staff.
Allow me to introduce Davon, Rob,
and Gabriel, this year's heads.
If you would each like to say--
>> [APPLAUSE]
--a word.
[APPLAUSE]
Davon over here is the
course's manager, which
means in his full-time role
he helps with the execution
and logistics of CS50.
DAVON: Yeah, hi, guys.
You'll see a lot to me at office hours.
I'll be teaching sections.
And if you shoot emails ahead,
I'll probably be responding.
So I'll see lots of you all semester.
And welcome to CS50.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And now Gabriel, who
himself was just a freshman last year,
but for the past couple of years has
been operating his own version of CS50
in Brazil, whereby he downloaded
all of the course's content--
which is clearly being
filmed and placed online--
so that he could translate it to
Portuguese and then teach more than 100
of his classmates over the
course of a couple of years,
teaching in his native tongue
the course's curriculum.
>> GABRIEL: Hello.
>> [APPLAUSE]
GABRIEL: Hi, I'm Gabriel.
I'm the head TF of the course.
And I hope you'll love CS50.
This is CS50.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Now for Rob.
Oh, you want introduction?
>> ROB: No, I don't know.
[LAUGHTER]
DAVID J. MALAN: And Rob Boden.
ROB: Hi, I'm Rob.
This is my fifth year
involved with the course.
Every year, it's just a
better and better class,
so you guys are clearly
going to be awesome.
I hope you all have fun with it.
I'm going to have fun with it.
So see you around.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And
time won't permit us--
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Time won't permit us
to introduce everyone
on the stage and all of their colleagues
who are shopping classes today.
But allow me to introduce
Belinda and CS50 Puzzle
Day, which awaits this
coming Saturday, which
is the first of the
course's large scale events.
>> This one in particular meant
to hammer home the point
that computer science is ultimately
not about programming, but rather
about problem solving more generally.
And Puzzle Day, as you'll
see, will bring you
and your classmates together--
we hope this Saturday.
>> BELINDA: OK.
Hi, guys.
So thanks.
So as our illustrious captain
said, my name's Belinda.
I am a sophomore at Quincy House.
>> I, just like you guys, took
CS50 last year, really loved it.
I have a soft spot for
you guys in the third row.
And I'm proud to say, I'm now
in a committed relationship
with CS50 [INAUDIBLE].
OK.
That was my lame version of a joke.
>> Anyway, so moving on,
just wanted to invite
you guys all to the i-lab, or HBS hives.
We're going to be having
Puzzle Day from 12:00 to 3:00.
And it's a great opportunity for you
guys to meet your fellow CS friends,
solve some non-CS puzzles, like Captain
mentioned, and also eat some free food,
earn some awesome prizes, like
gift cards, $75 per person,
and also-- what was it?
Wii U or something?
Wii U?
Yes.
For our raffle.
Awesome.
So I'll stick around after class.
And if you guys have any
questions, let me know.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And you'll see, beyond
this there's nothing to do today.
The first problem set
will go out Friday.
But to bring us home today, I'd like to
introduce you to specifically one more
member of the staff, Colton
Ogden here, whose hands are now
protected above you with
this MIDI controller
to hammer home the point further
that computer science, too,
has applicability far beyond engineering
and STEM and computer science itself,
extending even to such domains as music.
>> Colton has kindly offered-- I thought
one of them was going to fix the focus.
Andrew, if we could summon focus
over here for just a moment.
>> What Colton has done
in advance is program
this device, this pad of buttons
that you see pictured up here,
as a MIDI controller,
whereby each of those buttons
is wired to a particular musical note
or a sound, more generally a recording,
such that by playing patterns of these
buttons, much like patterns of bits,
can represent other
higher level concepts.
Will he be able ultimately
to take us home here today?
Without further ado, if
we could dim the lights,
and turn on the screen behind Colton.
>> AUDIENCE: Woo!
>> DAVID J. MALAN: This is CS50.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> That's it for CS50.
We will see you Friday.
Some cake awaits you in the Transept.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]