>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50.
This is the start of week eight.
And you may recall that we left off
last time looking at a new language
altogether.
In fact, one that's fairly
lightweight and it's not even
a programming language.
It's a markup language that lets us
actually structure and make web pages.
And when you something else
in conjunction with this--
or you soon will, if
you haven't already.
We're going to use Cascading
Style Sheets, or CSS, which
is another type of language
with properties and values
that's going to let us do
things like change the color
and change the position
and these kinds of tweaks.
But today and onward, we start to
focus on more powerful languages,
actual programming languages like PHP.
>> So PHP has been around for some time.
And as you'll see, it
was designed primarily
early on for actual
use in web development
and actually generating web pages.
So what kinds of
features does a language
need in order to make web
pages dynamically with it?
>> In other words, if you want to generate
content dynamically-- like Facebook's
Newsfeed, which changes constantly, or
instant messages that pop up from time
to time-- like what's the
key piece of functionality
you need in a programming language
that would let you dynamically
print new information to the screen?
>> STUDENT: Code.
DAVID J. MALAN: Code.
OK.
We'll take that.
A little more precise.
I mean, we could do
this with C, frankly.
It would be a pain in the neck.
But-- is this commitment?
>> STUDENT: Yeah.
Variables, maybe?
DAVID J. MALAN: Variables.
OK, sure.
Variables can certainly help us out.
And even something simpler.
We used it in the very first
program of the very first day
when we actually said "hello world."
>> STUDENT: Print.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Print, right?
Print, or printf in the
world of C. So all this time,
we've had at our
disposal a language-- C,
in particular-- and even
Scratch for that matter that
can generate strings of text.
>> Well, if HTML, as we saw last week, is
just a whole bunch of strings of text
albeit with open brackets and closed
brackets and some kind of rhyme
and reason behind it,
well then we could really
start generating web pages either
manually by typing them out in gedit
or in Microsoft Word, for that
matter-- we just need a text editor.
>> Or we could write code,
to your suggestion
earlier, that would let us
dynamically generate HTML,
and that's what we're going
to start doing with PHP
and ultimately even with a
language called JavaScript,
is use one language to generate another.
And indeed, this is what Facebook
and many, many other sites
do to actually dynamically
display new information to you.
>> So let's begin with this-- a
cryptic looking line, but one
that's actually pretty powerful.
Thus far, we've been using C,
which is a compiled language.
And just a quick recap-- a compiled
language has what characteristic?
You obviously need to compile
it, but what does that mean?
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: It needs to be
assembled into machine code.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
It needs to be assembled
into machine code.
So you take your source code,
which is sort of English-like.
You convert that to
something lower level,
which is ultimately called
object code-- 0's and 1's.
And it's those 0's and 1's that
a CPU, like those made by Intel,
actually understand.
>> Now, PHP and Python and Ruby and
JavaScript and bunches of other
languages are not compiled
languages but interpreted languages,
which means you just type them and then
you don't turn them into 0's and 1's.
You instead just provide then as
input to someone else's program,
called an interpreter.
And that person's
program has been designed
to understand what each and
every symbol in Python or PHP
or Ruby or any number of
other languages means.
>> And so all we need is
something like this.
So in fact, I'm going to
go over to the appliance
here, just into any
old window, and we're
going to go ahead and open
a file called, say, hello.
Now previously, I might have saved
this even with a file extension,
but I'm going to do
something even simpler here.
I'm going to go ahead and start
this file with this cryptic syntax.
So "user, bin, env,
for environment, php."
>> This is simply one line of code that's
going to tell my operating system,
go find in your local
environment whatever that is,
wherever PHP is-- the interpreter--
and go ahead and use that interpreter
to interpret the following code.
Now, this is kind of
an ugly feature of PHP.
But in this language, any
time you write PHP code,
you need to have one of these ugly
PHP tags demarcating the beginning
of your code-- <?php.
>> But below here, I can now do something
quite simple, like printf hello comma
world backslash n close
quote, close parenthesis.
And then just for good
measure, I'm going
to go ahead and close
my php tag over here
so that everything looks
nicely pretty printed.
>> And as soon as I click Save,
gedit is actually smart enough
to look at that very first line and
realize, oh, you're writing PHP code.
Let me syntax highlight
it with the colors
here so that it stands
out a little more.
But now I'm going to go
down to my terminal window.
I'll zoom in.
>> This program was called "hello,"
so I'm going to do dot slash hello,
but permission denied.
And bash.
We actually heard of that
thing a couple weeks ago
in the context of Shellshock,
one of those bugs.
>> But permission denied we've seen
before, maybe in a different context.
Does anyone recall how
you might fix something
where permission is denied like this?
What's the command, at least?
>> STUDENT: Chmod.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, chmod,
for changing the mode of a file.
And you'll get all the more used to
this next week with a subsequent problem
set.
But for now, I'm going to change
the mode not to be readable,
but to give everyone executeability
privileges, the ability
to run this file.
And I'm going to assign
that to the file hello.
>> If I now do dot slash hello enter, you
see, in fact, my program, hello world.
And what step did I
clearly skip altogether?
Compiling.
So I just ran this program quite simply.
>> And it turns out you can do this with
a lot of syntax reminiscent of C.
Let me go in to today's code,
which I put into my vhost directory
here, for real reasons
we'll come back to.
And I'm going to go into,
let's say, conditions 1.
>> And you'll see here, first and
foremost, a whole bunch of comments.
But this is actually
a re-creation in PHP
of a program we did in week
one called conditions 1.c
where the purpose in
life of this program
is apparently to ask
the user for an integer
and then do some fluffy
analysis on it whereby
you say if it's positive or
negative or equal to zero.
And I bring this up only because,
except for maybe one little detail,
it's indistinguishable so far from C.
>> What's the one characteristic
here that maybe jumps out
at you as a little different?
Maybe two things.
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: Dollar sign n?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So dollar sign n is present.
And dollar signs, as
we'll see, are going
to be a fix to the beginning
of any variable in PHP.
It's both good and bad-- good in
that it's sort of obvious what's
a variable, bad in that it's
yet another thing to type.
And there's one other
thing we haven't quite
seen, at least by this spelling. yeah?
>> STUDENT: Readline.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Readline.
Readline we didn't see, per se, in
C, even though there exists something
similar, but we've used getstring,
and this is its counterpart.
So if I go into this
directory, which happens to be,
as I'll explain in a bit in my vhost
directory and my source A directory,
and I go ahead and do dot slash
conditions-- whoops-- dot slash
conditions 1, you'll see, again,
the same issue-- permission denied.
>> So let me zoom in and do chmod a plus
x on conditions, dot slash conditions.
I'd like an integer, please, 50.
And we could play this
game all day long.
It's going to behave exactly
as it did in week one.
>> OK so not all that different, except
not just that slight bit of syntax,
but at the top, I again
had this line which
allowed me to create something that
looks like a C program called hello,
called conditions 1.
But it's not 0's and ones
I'm executing directly.
It's instead running this
interpreter whose name
happens to be identical to the language.
The program is called PHP, and my code
below line one is being passed into it.
>> We can do another fairly simple
example reminiscent of something
we did weeks ago.
Again, this is a sort of
arbitrary chunk of code
that apparently does
what when you run it?
What's this going to print, presumably?
>> So initially on line 16, it's
going to say x is now 2, probably.
%d is the same as $i for printf.
So then it's cubing, dot,
dot, dot, in line 17.
And then line 18 appears
to call a function Cubed.
And where is Cubed defined?
>> Well, it looks like in line 25,
so that's not all that different.
I've got some comments above
it, but for the most part,
it's a fairly straightforward
porting or conversion
from the C program to the PHP version.
But there are now a couple of
differences that maybe should jump out.
What else is different about how you
might write this same program in C?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: There's
no prototype up top.
So PHP-- and frankly, a
lot of modern languages--
are a lot smarter and more helpful
than C compilers in that you
can put the function up here,
you can put a function down here,
and the interpreter is going
to do you the favor of reading
the whole file before it decides
that some function doesn't exist.
So nice improvements years later.
But there's also something
else different or absent here.
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: We don't have to
declare the types of variables,
so we'll see before long that
there are different types in PHP,
but you don't need to specify them,
which also is both good and bad.
And there's one other thing missing.
>> STUDENT: There's no libraries.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: There is no libraries.
OK, so that's nice.
We get a lot more out of the box.
So there's actually a lot more
things than I thought were different.
How about way in back?
What's that?
Say it once more?
>> STUDENT: Pointer.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: No pointers.
OK, at least in this example, no.
That's fair.
So there are not pointers
in PHP actually in general.
There are something called references,
but we won't spend too much time there.
And what else?
>> STUDENT: Main.
DAVID J. MALAN: Main.
So this was the biggie
I was thinking of.
Notice there's no main entry point.
You simply start writing your code.
And this is actually
going to be advantageous
when we transition
momentarily to actually using
this same language for web-based
programming, for which we
don't want to have just one entry point.
We might want to have a bunch of
URLs, a bunch of different files
all taking in user input
and producing output.
>> But here is the very disheartening
example that I promised last time,
namely in this folder
here, misspellings.
So in this file speller, which we
won't spend too much time on, there is
essentially a porting-- P-O-R-T.
It's just the word given when, say,
you convert from one language
to another manually usually.
>> This is a porting of PC
version of speller from PSET 5.
And I essentially tried to convert
it line by line as closely as I can.
So if you like this kind of thing,
it actually is worth at some point
pulling them both up side by
side and seeing what's the same
and what's different.
But they're pretty darn similar.
If you remember what
speller even looked like,
even though you didn't
have to change this file,
it's pretty similar
structurally with just a couple
of changes here and there.
>> So this is only to say that it's pretty
straightforward to convert speller
from C to PHP.
But in dictionary, there's
something even more compelling.
Let me go ahead and create
my own dictionary.php file.
So slightly different in that
we'll call it .php instead of .c.
Because this is a PHP file, I
do-- slightly annoyingly-- have
to start the file with
a php tag like that.
And I'm going to go ahead
and define a few functions.
Function called check, which is
going to take in a word like before.
But this argument's
going to have a dollar
sign because we're, again, using PHP.
Another function from
dictionary.c was load
and it took in the name of a dictionary,
so I'll get that function ready to go.
>> Another one in dictionary.c was what?
Size was one of the nicest ones, at
least if you kept some variable around.
so size just has to return a variable.
And then there was unload.
>> So there were these four
functions in problem set 5
that you needed to implement with
some data structure or structures.
So I promised that in
PHP, we can declare
a hash table, for instance,
all that more easily.
In fact, if I want a hash table,
I'm just going to go like that
and there's my hash table.
And that's the note, disheartening,
that we left off on last time.
And you know what, if I wanted
a variable for size, well,
this one's not all
that different from C,
but I'm going to go ahead and do that.
And notice no data type.
And I'll go back later and
actually add some comments here.
But what about load?
>> If dollar sign dictionary
is the name of my file
and I actually want to load
words into this table now,
I can actually do
something fairly simple.
One-- and this is minorly
annoying-- in PHP,
you have to specify inside
of a function if you
want to access some global
variable that's defined outside.
>> But that's not particularly
interesting right now.
What's more interesting is this for each
construct that I mentioned last time.
And it turns out that PHP has a function
called file whose purpose in life
is to open a file and read in
all of its lines into an array
and hand them back to.
>> Which is to say I can do dictionary so
that now effectively when I call file,
this is going to hand me back
an array of words from the file.
It's not all that good.
It's still going to be a line
of words, something linear.
But I can go ahead and iterate
over each of these words using
that syntax we saw briefly last time.
And you'll see it more
in the upcoming PSET.
>> But now I have a loop iterating
over each word in the dictionary.
And on each iteration, recall I'm
calling the current word "word."
And all it's going to take to
put a word into the dictionary is
going to be word guess "true."
That's my insert function.
That's my load function
for my dictionary.
Now it's a bit of a cheat because,
you know what, there's actually
backslash n's at the end of the words
that I should probably get rid of,
but that's not a problem because PHP has
a function called chop which literally
chops off one character at the very end.
So no problem there.
We've gone ahead and actually
shortened that to just this.
And now I should probably keep track
of size, so let's at least do this--
size++.
I can do that as before.
And then this is probably going to
work just fine, so that's return true.
Done.
PSET 5.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
We're going to do that again
with the next PSET, too.
So what about size?
Well, this one hopefully is about
as you would expect last time,
although I have to do
this stupid global thing.
It's just an artifact from
the language's design.
>> But check is a little more interesting.
So if I passed in dollar
sign word, I first
want to have access to
that global variable table.
And now if I want to
check if a word is there,
I can simply say if it is true that
the following is set in the table,
then go ahead and return
true; else, return false.
Done.
The other half of PSET 5.
>> All right, so again, I'm
cutting a few corners.
In fairness, I should probably
spend a few more seconds
on this implementation.
And I probably shouldn't mock all the
hours you put on the PSET so much.
So strtolower is a function.
Something similar existentialist
in C, at least for characters,
but PHP's got a whole string version.
>> That's going to force everything
to lowercase, which some of you
might have done to canonicalize what
you were putting in your dictionary.
And now you can do this in C, too.
This has nothing to do with PHP.
>> But any time you have
a Boolean condition,
like something on line
10 there, which is only
going to evaluate to true or
false, and your if else clearly
is returning true or false, I could
simply really make this sexier
and just do something like this.
So that there's my check function.
Right, if the Boolean
returns a true or a false,
let's just return it straight away.
>> And there's a few other tweaks
I could make here and there.
Load-- unload, by the way, that's done.
Nothing to do there.
Since all of the memory in
PHP and many other languages
is actually managed for you.
So whereas in C, as
you've learned painfully,
anything you malloc or calloc or
realloc, you have to free yourself.
Anything you fopen, you have to fclose,
so that resources are ultimately freed
and tools like Valgrind don't
notice and don't complain,
which is a good thing to run on them.
>> But surely, there must
be some catch, right?
Otherwise, we kind of wasted
a whole bunch of weeks.
So there's any number of reasons
why we sort of take this trajectory,
but there is a trade-off.
Right, this has been thematic.
>> So what might a trade-off
here moving, from C to PHP?
Feels like all win so far other than
a bit of ugliness here or there.
Yeah.
What's that?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] memory.
DAVID J. MALAN: Speed.
OK.
Well, my speed was pretty fast.
Right?
But speed of execution of the program?
OK, so that's a fair point.
>> So as it would happen, I in advance
cued up both my try solution, the one
I had on the big board
was a try-based solution,
and I have that in this directory here.
So I in a moment, I can go ahead and
run this on the King James Bible,
hitting Enter.
And this is hopefully correct
implementation at the end,
gives me time in total
of 0.38 seconds for that
one somewhat arbitrary example.
>> And if I now go into this
second terminal window
here where I first opened gedit, let
me go into today's code-- which, again,
is in this directory here-- and
let me go ahead and run speller.
So just to be clear,
this is the PHP version.
I'm just showing the top of it here.
>> So if I do speller of tilde CS50
PSET 5 texts, King James, enter.
It's still faster than writing
it in C, but the total time
is, notice, 0.93, whereas my
C-based implementation was 0.38.
So it's a non-trivial difference.
>> And this is just on one file.
If you were to run the two
programs versus the big board
and have a whole bunch of inputs
tested, this would surely add up.
And if we had even larger data sets,
this, too, would add up all the more.
So yes, paying some price
of speed is indeed the case.
What else?
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: Amount of RAM use.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Amount of RAM use.
So I didn't give one second
thought when writing this PHP
version as to how much
memory I was using.
I'm completely deferring that to PHP
itself and whoever wrote that program.
And that might be OK,
but if I actually really
care about squeezing as much performance
out of my program or out of my website
or out of whatever tool
I'm building, maybe
PHP, indeed, is not the right language.
>> And in fact, that is why, for
instance, many web servers--
the actual programs that
serve up web content--
are not written in PHP
or in Python or Ruby.
They are written, like
you'll now do with PSEt 6,
in C so that you can squeeze
every bit of performance out of it
and really exercise
fine-grain control over what's
going on underneath the
hood and not just take it
for granted some higher
level data structure.
>> Consider, after all,
whoever in PHP implemented
that notion of a hash
table-- it's actually more
properly called an associative array--
does he or she have any idea what kind
of inputs you are going to be
putting into the structure?
So obviously not, right?
It's a generic tool
in the toolkit that's
provided to anyone who wants
to use it, and so surely it
can't be optimized ultimately
for exactly what you want to do.
>> So trade-offs-- development time might
differ, performance might differ,
complexity or memory usage might differ.
And so what you'll find
increasingly is that there's
going to be different
tools for the trade.
And in fact for a super majority of
people's final projects in this class,
believe it or not, C is not going
to be the right language to use.
>> And in fact, one of the takeaways
ultimately for any class like this
is to get you thinking about,
well, what should you pull off
the shelf when you want
to solve some problem.
And indeed, we'll cross this bridge
even more as we look at more languages
even beyond today.
>> So let's transition now to
perhaps a more familiar context
for using a language like PHP.
It's somewhat common to use at
the command line, writing scripts
like I did, but it's
much, much more common.
And it was intended to be used in
the form of files that typically end
in .php-- but that's
not a prerequisite--
that themselves generate web content.
>> So let me go ahead and open a few
examples I prepared in advance.
And these are actually sort of true
stories in that one of the first things
I ever did myself after finishing
CS50 and maybe, I think,
CS51 years ago is my
roommate and I were helping
to run the freshman intramural
sports program, which, at the time,
had freshman registering for various
sports by filling out a piece of paper,
as it was called, walking
across the yard to Wigglesworth,
and dropping it in some
proctor's door drop.
And then he or she would go through
them and then actually email us manually
that we were registered for some sport.
>> So clearly, an opportunity
for improvement.
These days, you might turn to just
Google Forms, but back in the day,
we had to actually reach for-- this
wasn't even that long ago-- reach
for a programming
language that wasn't PHP.
At the time, it was
something called Perl,
which has gone out of vogue since.
But the idea is the same.
>> And I essentially sat down to try
to port goes Perl versions to PHP,
but in full disclaimer, did not give
any thought to the aesthetics just yet.
So here is a web page.
This is a file.
If I zoom in, its apparently
called froshim0.php
just because it's our first
example in this series.
And notice that it has what appears
to be a very ugly HTML form,
but a form is interesting
because it allows
me to provide user input to the browser.
>> Now last time when we had a form, to
whom did we submit our query parameter,
the queue parameter as it was called?
So to Google, right?
We totally punted on the idea of
doing anything with that input.
>> But today, we start producing output.
And the behavior I'm going to see
here initially is pretty trivial.
David, I'll check off gender
here, say Matthews here.
I won't be captain.
I'm going to click Register.
And notice that the URL has
changed to register-0.php,
and then there's this ugly text here.
I gave no thought to
the formatting of this.
>> But what is interesting is that three
values were apparently passed in.
This is PHP's sort of
equivalent to printf--
we'll see what it's really called
in a bit-- that just prints out
what you passed into it.
So this suggests that that form
had at least three fields to it,
and you saw me type them in.
One was my name, one was
gender, one was dormitory.
And captain didn't even get sent to
the server because I didn't check it.
>> So this is to say apparently,
when you submit things on the web,
not only does the URL sometimes
change-- sometimes it doesn't.
In fact, the file name changed,
but what is absent from the URL
that we did see last time with Google.
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: No query string
>> DAVID J. MALAN: There's no query string.
There's no question mark something.
There's no question mark q
equals cats, as we did last time.
And there's certainly no
question mark name equals
David or dorm equals Matthews,
so where is that all going?
>> Well, let me go back to gedit here
and open up the first of those files
in my vhost, local host, public
directory here and go into froshim0.
So it turns out that almost
all of this page is just HTML.
And this might be unfamiliar to you,
but it soon will be more so with PSET 6
and PSET 7 and PSET 8.
But this is just an HTML page.
>> And the interesting stuff
seems to be over here.
A form tag whose action attribute
has a value of register 0.
That's why when I submit
this, it goes to that file.
But method is different today-- post.
So it turns out there's at least
two methods on the web used
to send information
from browser to server.
Get puts it in the URL.
Post puts it elsewhere.
And when and why might you
actually want a website
to use post then instead
of get, just intuitively?
Any website.
What kind of data should be passed just
by inference now via post as opposed
to get, if we've seen
the two differences?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] secure.
DAVID J. MALAN: If you want
something to be secure.
So you might type a password
into a website, a credit card
into a website would
kind of these suboptimal
if the browser put that
value inside of the URL.
Why?
You see it, which doesn't
seem to be such a big deal,
but odds are you pretty frequently walk
away from your computer or use computer
labs, and so someone
else or even a roommate
could easily walk up and see
that private information.
When you send an email
via the web, you probably
don't want that data ending
up in the URL as well.
And so there's any number of reasons
why we might want to put it here.
And photos-- right, I can't even quite
imagine how you would take a graphic,
like a JPEG, and put it into a URL.
You could do it.
There's ways of encoding it, but it's
just not straightforward like that.
>> So register 0 is actually
very underwhelming.
All it says literally is this.
It prints out inside of some
HTML tags the following.
I've got a PHP tag here
nested inside of a pre tag.
"Pre" just means pre-formatted text,
mono-spaced, like a typewriter.
>> Printr is a print recursive function.
And then there's this
interesting thing here.
And we'll come back to this
because there's others,
but dollar sign underscore
post appears to be
a variable in PHP in which anything
you send from browser to server
gets stored for you.
And we'll see how to get at
that information before long.
>> But first, let's go back to
a slightly different example.
Going into register-- or
rather, froshims1.php,
which looks a little different.
I took a little more
effort with formatting,
even though it's still pretty ugly.
But I'm going to go ahead
and type in "David" now.
Male.
We'll check "captain" this time.
We'll do Matthews.
And register.
>> And this time it says, hm, not really.
All right, so what's register 1?
Let me go into open register 1 and-- hm.
All right, so this is
interesting, and this
is a stepping stone now toward
more interesting programs.
>> Notice the top of this file has a
PHP tag as well as some comments.
And these are, for now, a distraction
so let's just get rid of those comments
just like they're in C. And I claim
with this chunk of code with a comment
that this code is
validating the submission.
>> Well, it turns out that
variables like dollar sign
underscore post are
called super globals.
They're like these
special global variables
that are just omni-presently
available within your program.
And you can use square bracket notation
to index into them not using numbers
like 0, 1, 2, 3, but actual words.
>> So you can think of dollar sign
underscore post as sort of a hash table
that you could pass a key into, a lookup
word in-between the square brackets,
and it's going to give you back the
value that the user actually provided.
PHP has a function
called empty that just
says yes or no, this
variable is empty or not.
We have these double bars,
which just means or, like in C.
>> So in effect, this line 4 is just
saying if the user didn't give a name
or didn't give a gender or didn't
give a dorm, go ahead and redirect him
or her via this line here.
So this is a little cryptic,
but this just means literally
go back to this location,
so it punts the user
back to wherever he or she came from.
But it's a little inelegant
in that I hard coded it.
>> But what if this if condition
does not evaluate to true?
What if the user did give me his
or her name and dorm and gender?
That if condition's not
going to evaluate to true,
so I don't hit the exit in line 7.
So what happens?
And this is what's
interesting about PHP.
>> You can drop into and out
of PHP mode, so to speak.
If you want some code to execute,
you can open and close a PHP tag
and put code there like I've done here.
As soon as you close
the PHP tag, the server
is just going to spit out
whatever you put there.
And indeed, this was part of
the original design of PHP,
for better for worse, was this
commingling of code and markup
language.
And we'll see that this very
quickly devolves into a mess.
And so we'll do better than
this ultimately, but just
notice the ease with which I'm
actually able to execute some logic.
>> But still a bit underwhelming.
Let's open up version
two of Frosh IMs, which
apparently submits to register2.php.
So this file's actually going
to look almost the same.
I'm going to go to Frosh IMs 2 .
But in Frosh IMs 2,
let's see what happens.
>> David, click the radio button, as
it's called; Matthews, no captain.
Register.
You are registered.
Not really.
Oh wait, we just did
that example, didn't we?
All right, stand by.
We'll do the three.
Clearly something's about
to happen with Gmail.
We'll get there.
>> So Frosh IMs 3 looks like this.
No different.
But when I do David, male, Matthews, and
register, this third and final version
claims, quite simply, you
are registered really.
That's sort of immaterial.
But I claim with this
third and final version
I have now recreated exactly what my
roommate and I built for the Frosh IMs
program years ago.
And it was simple.
There was no database,
no Excel spreadsheet.
But more importantly,
there was no more paper
because what we did with this program
was to actually email the proctor, who
was previously receiving
these things via forms.
>> And apparently we've programmed this in
such a way that when someone registers,
John Harvard's account emails the
proctor-- or himself in this case,
John Harvard-- with the following
text-- "This person just registered."
Name is David, captain is blank;
gender, male; and dorm, Matthews.
>> So what happened there?
Well, the file in question here
is apparently register3.php.
And if I open this, you'll see
both the power of code like this
and also, frankly, the insecurity
of a system like email.
I have just effectively pretended to
be John Harvard in the following way.
>> I have the open php tag up top, which
just says here comes some PHP code.
Down here, turns out there
are libraries in PHP.
You just don't need to
include header files as much.
You get more with the
kitchen sink, so to speak.
>> But this time in line 4, I do
want to special library called
PHP mailer, which is something you
can install for free in many systems.
Down here I'm validating
the submission just
by checking did the user give
me a name, a gender, and a dorm.
And if so, go ahead and
instantiate a mailer.
>> You can think of this as being a
line of code that just allocates.
It's like malloc, but
it's a little sexier
in that you mention not just
malloc and some generic number.
You say give me one of these,
give me a new one of these.
>> And if you've programmed in
Java or C++ or other languages,
you might have seen this.
But the short of it, if
unfamiliar, this line
puts into dollar sign mail
a special struct called
an object that has built-in
email functionality.
And in fact, notice and similar syntax.
>> This is not a pointer, per se.
PHP just uses the same syntax.
This line is saying use
SMTP-- Simple Mail Transfer
Protocol, which is just the
protocol used to send mail.
This is specifying use
Harvard's SMTP server, which
is somewhere here on campus.
>> This is saying what TCP
port number to talk to,
and I just figured that out by
googling or by asking the help desk.
And then because Harvard uses some
system security on the mail server--
at least to encrypt
traffic between you and it,
even though anyone can send to it--
I'm going to turn on the TLS protocol
for keeping this secure.
>> But this is where things
get a little scary.
I can just arbitrarily
say that I am jharvard,
and I can just arbitrarily
email myself here.
And then I can specify a
subject with this line here.
>> And this just looks ugly, but it's
just a bunch of concatenation.
Turns out PHP has a super useful symbol,
like some languages, the dot operator,
which just literally concatenates
string after string after string,
and you don't have to malloc or figure
out the total length of the string.
You just do it.
And indeed, because I'm concatenating
in all of these things with these dots,
that's why the email I
sent looked as it did.
>> And then lastly here, I'm sending mail.
So if this is false,
I'm just going to die,
which is a function that just prints
to the screen some error message.
But it is, in fact,
calling the send function.
Otherwise, if all of this fails,
it redirects me back here.
>> And why did I see that
I'm registered really?
Well, it happened right here.
So I bring this up for
a couple of reasons.
>> One, this is exactly how if you build
some website for a final project
or for the real world, this is
how you send email reminders
to your customers or your subscribers.
This is how you send password reminders.
This is how you send people messages
that they have a new Facebook
message pending or something like that.
>> But it also speaks to
the fact that this could
have been very well from
Davin or anyone else.
And I say this kind of
with a smile because I'm
quite sure what's going through
several of your minds at this point.
But this is one of those do as I
say, not as I do kind of things,
because it is trivial to
forge emails like this.
But as you may have seen
or read in the Crimson,
of late it's also pretty
trivial for people
to trace them back to some origin.
And ask me some time, perhaps
at CS50 lunch, how I first
got acquainted very closely
almost to the ed board many years
ago when I discovered
how the internet worked.
So in any case-- slightly
after the ed board did.
>> So in any case, there is a
whole bunch of super globals,
as they're called here, one of which
we saw-- dollar sign underscore post.
There's a counterpart called get,
which is where stuff from a URL
ends up going.
And there's a whole bunch of others,
too-- session and server and cookie.
We'll come back to
cookie some other time,
but session is kind of cool
because right now-- up until now--
everything we've done with a web browser
is sort of stateless, so to speak.
I can click around, access
files on the server, something
happens on the screen, but
then the connection closes.
The Internet Explorer or the
Firefox icon stops spinning
and you just see what
that web page contains.
>> So HTTP is stateless in that
once it makes a connection,
gets some data, that's it.
No more connection, unlike Skype,
unlike Facetime, unlike GChat, which
maintains a constant
connection to the server.
The web is fundamentally
disconnected, though we'll
see before long how
we can simulate things
like Facebook chat and GChat,
which maintain the illusion--
or actually do maintain a
constant connection using
more modern technology.
>> But if I go to, say, counter.php,
this is another simple example,
as we'll see, that currently thinks
I visited the site zero time.
But if I simply reload the page,
it somehow knows I was here before.
If I reload again, it
knows I was here before.
And again and again and again and again.
>> So there's some plus-plussing
going on, but notice
the little thing spins ever so
briefly up top and then disconnects,
so it's not like I have a constant
connection to my appliance.
Well, if I go into counter.php,
notice how simple it is.
I first call this special
function that we'll soon
start taking for granted
called session start.
Start a session.
>> And a session henceforth is just
going to be a bucket, like a shopping
cart in which you can put values
and kind of trust as a programmer
that they're going to be here when
that user comes back-- a second
later, an hour later, even a year later,
so long as he or she doesn't clear
their cookies, as we'll eventually see.
And now I just have
an if condition here.
So if the following key,
called counter, is set inside
of this super global-- this hash
table, if you will-- called session,
then go ahead and grab the
value from the session-- think
of this as a shopping
cart-- and store it
in a temporary variable called counter.
>> Otherwise, if that value counter was
not set in the so-called shopping cart,
just initialize it to 0.
Lastly, down here, go and put back
into the shopping carts or the session
the value of counter +1.
So it turns out that this
special container here--
which, again, is one of these associated
arrays, an array that you can index
into words instead of numbers--
persists even after the user goes away.
Again, I'll go back to the page now.
It's been a minute or so.
But it remembers that I've
been here 19 times before.
This is my 20th visit.
>> And so this is going to be key to
implementing any website that remembers
that you're logged in, that you put
something literal in your shopping cart
to buy or that you have some
number of messages pending.
Anytime you want to
remember information,
we'll see that PHP, like
several other languages,
provides us with this illusion of state
even though, as you'll see in PSET 6,
as you're making HTTP requests
from client to server, that's it.
Once you get back that
response, there's nothing more
coming back from the server by default.
But we'll see how to work around that.
>> Well now, let's try to
clean this up a little bit.
We've seen a few
different examples there.
Oh, and as an aside, for
those familiar or unfamiliar,
the reason that the
Frosh IMs example went
from looking really
ugly to slightly-- well,
still ugly-- to slightly
less ugly though still ugly
is because if we look
at the source code here,
it turns out that I have this
at the very top of the file.
>> Turns out that bootstrap is one of many
freely available libraries out there
that exist not for programming languages
always, but for CSS or for JavaScript
or HTML or any number of languages.
>> And these folks here--
originally came out
of Twitter-- just have
a whole bunch of styles.
It's a massive file
here that someone wrote,
or someone's wrote, over time that
specifies colors and formatting
and whatnot so that I can
kind of borrow their syntax
and not have to figure out
how to lay out my form.
This is also minified
so that a computer can
understand it but not
necessarily a human.
So that's just why the
stylization there changed.
>> But let's now do better
in terms of design,
because if we stay down
this road too long,
our code's going to
get messy and messier.
So let's focus on these examples here.
The last for today.
>> So here is a super simple
version 1.0 of CS50's website.
It only has links to
lectures and syllabus,
and it's using that unordered list
tag-- the UL tag that we used last time.
And if in fact, if I
open up View Page Source,
you'll see that this is
really, really simple HTML.
And in fact, even though this is
a PHP file underneath the hood,
it's still just spitting
out only HTML for now.
>> So if I click on Lectures,
we see this happen.
And if I click on week
zero, we see this.
And if I click on
Wednesday, we see this.
And this apparently was the PDF
of the slides from that day.
All I've done is link with an
anchor tag to this URL here.
>> So this is only to say this is a pretty
simple version of CS50's website.
Let's see how it's implemented.
If I go into the mvc0 directory,
we'll see a few files.
One is a README, so if
some of this is too fast,
you can just poke around
more leisurely later.
And notice in here is an index.php file.
It turns out that if
you yourself, the human,
don't specify a final name in
a URL, the web server usually
infers some default name for you.
An index dot something
is generally the default.
>> So that's why a moment ago
when I visited this URL here,
no file name, no file
extension, no period in the URL.
It just knew somehow magically
to look for index.php.
It's just a convention.
Could be called anything.
>> So if I now go into
index.php, you'll see
that, indeed-- let's
get rid of the comments
here because there's really
nothing interesting to it--
this is just hard coded HTML.
So that's consistent,
though, with my claim
that you can commingle HTML and PHP.
There's no actual
programming logic in here.
>> And the other files are pretty
much just as uninteresting.
It's just hard-coded week one
here to week one m and week one w,
for Monday and Wednesday.
And then if I open up week zero,
notice it's almost identical.
>> And that's kind of a key takeaway.
Notice just how redundant this is.
These files barely change, and yet I
pulled one of these copy/paste jobs
where I took one file-- presumably
in week zero-- copied it
when week one came around,
and tweaked a few values.
We should probably be able
to do better than this.
>> So let's go back up to mvc
and go into version one.
And notice I've got a
few files, because what
was common to all of those files just a
moment ago-- if I go back to version 0,
let's go back into index,
and just postulate--
once I get rid of the comments--
what part of this page
is presumably in every one of my files?
Just call it out.
Which lines are duplicated
probably across all of these pages?
Yeah?
>> STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: 1 through 9.
Yeah, absolutely.
1 through 9, except maybe 8
changes a little bit because CS50
becomes lectures or
week zero or something.
But almost identical.
So all this stuff is just
kind of copied and pasted.
And there's a couple
other lines I can think
of that are probably identical
across all the files.
>> STUDENT: 12 and 13.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
Sure, 12, 13, and 14 probably,
just because the interesting stuff
is happening on lines 11
and 10, so it would seem.
So let's look at version 1,
which tries to improve on this.
In version 1 of this mvc example-- we'll
explain what mvc means in a moment--
if I go into index, it kind of
looks a little confusing now.
It's not quite as simple as before.
>> But once you start to
read it carefully, it's
pretty straightforward what it's doing.
Apparently line 1 and
line 8 have replaced
all of the stuff you just identified--
though just for good measure,
I left the ULs there just in case some
days didn't have a list of things.
And so require is kind of like pound
include in C. It copies and pastes
the contents effectively
right here into this file.
>> So in header.php, as you
might infer from its name,
is going to be the header of the page.
It's kind of orphaned here.
It only has the top to it, but
there's no more content below.
>> And if I look at footer meanwhile,
which was the other file mentioned--
this one's even less interesting,
but again, it's common to everything.
So this is the footer.
This is the header.
This is the file that's
changing, so why not
try to factor out the commonality
with these two lines here?
>> But we can clean this
up a little further.
I'm going to go ahead and
open up version two where
we'll see that there's
a new file, helpers.php.
We'll see what that is in a moment.
Let's go to index, as the
entry point as before.
>> And now notice I'm requiring
helpers.php, not header or footer.
But helpers is kind of like
helpers.c and helpers.h from PSET 2
or PSET 3 long ago when you actually
did search and find for that PSET,
and you had all of your code for sorting
and searching in a separate file.
That's what's going on here.
>> And now line 3 looks a little different.
And it's just one line.
To make this even more
clear, I could just
do this to be stylistically consistent
with everything else we've done.
But that's not really
changing the functionality.
It's just one line of real code.
>> Apparently, there's a function
somewhere called render header,
and this is where things
get pretty powerful.
Notice that inside of its parentheses
is what other piece of syntax?
It's probably a little hard to say, but
notice there's-- I'll put some white
space.
There's square brackets.
>> And square brackets we saw a bit ago
in the context of associative arrays,
which are, again, like hash tables.
And if you think now to C, the
order of arguments into a function
has to always be the same.
You have to remember what the
order is-- x, y, z or z, y, x--
and you have to always provide them
in the same order or look them up
if you've forgotten.
>> But this seems to be a clever way
of passing an arbitrary key value
pairs whereby title is the name
of an argument in this case
and CS50 is its value.
And the fact that I have
these square brackets
here means that I could
also pass in something
like a week is 1 or 0 or 2 or 3.
So we've parameterized
this function in such a way
that it can take multiple inputs,
but for now it's just the one.
>> If I now go into helpers.php,
notice what it's doing.
This is a little bit
of new functionality,
but for now just take
on faith that this is
the syntax with which you
define a function in PHP.
You literally say function.
You don't specify a return
type, and that's consistent
with the variable detail earlier
where you don't really strongly type.
>> This just specifies
that, by default, this
takes an associative
array as an argument.
And you know what?
If the user doesn't pass one
in, assume a default value.
>> This is a feature that C doesn't have
for us, which is nice, because now
data, even if you
don't give it anything,
is going to be an
array but an empty one.
And as an aside, extract
just does something funky
where it takes all of the keys from this
associative array, all of the things
you could put in square brackets,
and creates variables out of them
so that we can ultimately have access
to them in footet.php and header.php.
That's a little abstract,
so let me point this out.
>> In index.php, notice that I'm
passing in a key value pair of title
with a value of CS50.
If I now look at helpers.php,
notice that RenderHeader
is extracting that data that I'm passing
in, and then requiring header.php.
What I've done is sort of a poor man's
implementation now of the following.
>> If I open up header.php,
notice that I've no longer hard
coded the word CS50 in this header file.
I've put this admittedly atrociously
named function, HTML special chars,
in there.
But notice what I've done.
I've got open HTML.
I then have open head and open title.
>> And then inside of the title's open and
close tags, I have a bit of PHP code.
And this is a nice but of syntax,
which just means echo out.
It literally means this--
echo the following--
but this is sexier to write.
Echo out the title
that's been passed in.
>> But what do you think HTML
special char is all about,
especially if you have
some prior HTML experience?
What characters might be
dangerous to pass in to a page
where you're dynamically generating
the web page with code like this?
Let me go to this file, version
two, and see if I can't induce this.
>> Version two is this.
And notice everything
is fine, working well.
But suppose I go into index.php and
I specified that the title of my page
is not CS50.
It is open bracket script alert
hello world, close single quote,
close parenthesis, semicolon,
open bracket, slash script.
>> Script, as we'll
eventually see, is a tag
that you can use to use of another
programming language called
JavaScript inside of a web page.
And now notice the logic here.
Here is a key called title.
Here is it's crazy long value now.
>> But if I go to the helpers page-
or rather, the header page,
I'm calling this function
on that title first.
So if I now reload this page, I
see this, which looks ridiculous,
but it's safe.
It just looks stupid.
>> But suppose instead
I had forgotten this.
And mark my words, a nonzero number
of you will forget to do this
and you'll get some industrious
student or friend coming up
to you at the CS50 fair or anonymously
at night poking around on your website
and essentially injecting code
unbeknownst to you into your site
somehow.
>> Because if I simply spit
out title here and title
there-- well, if title literally
looks like this and PHP
as a language that can spit
out other languages text,
this is literally going
to replace this tag with,
of course, what I put elsewhere.
>> So if I now go here and reload after
undoing those safety mechanisms,
now I have hello world here.
Now that's not all that big of a
deal, but you could do something
a little more malicious
here, like there's
other tags-- as we'll see once we spend
more time in JavaScript-- like location
dot href gets, quote, unquote, HTTP
business.com, but the opposite of that
from the other day.
And now you can induce a web
page to actually go immediately
to this web page here.
>> And actually, I don't want
to even go to business.com
because I don't want
to know what that is.
But this, too, will trigger code
to be injected into this page.
So this is only to say that even though
we're introducing super early on some
of these more complex structures,
it's all toward an end of making sure
that your code is not exploitable.
>> So now a third version here.
It's getting a little fancier.
I didn't really like--
the anal side of me
was getting a little annoyed by the
fact that I had a function called
RenderHeader and RenderFooter
that were almost identical.
So it occurred to me, why don't
I parameterize these functions
into just one called render,
have it take a second argument
like the name of the template, the final
to render-- either header or footer?
And then optionally, if I want
to pass in some key value pairs
like I do for the title for the
header but not for the footer,
I could do that.
>> And so now if I go into helpers.php,
it's a little more complex.
And I'll wave my hands at the
details, but it's just one function.
So that's a step toward a better design.
>> We can take this one step further.
If I go into my fourth
version of this, notice now
that I'm doing something
even more kind of cryptic.
And I know this is a
lot to absorb at once,
but we're just kind
of cleaning things up.
Now I'm putting my helpers
file into a folder called
includes-- just an arbitrary
name where I want to put stuff
that I want to include-- and then
the rest of this is the same.
>> But if I look now in gedit,
notice that I've gotten rid
of all of those other files and I've
moved them, for instance, into here.
And then in templates,
I have this here, too.
And so this is all now toward a step
of using a much better design pattern.
And we're very quickly
going to move away
from PHP's default functionality,
which we started here with,
where you just commingle PHP,
and your HTML, and your CSS,
and you just spit it out
and you go about your way.
It's not going to be very maintainable.
Just like in C, we started using
multiple files and multiple functions
and factoring things that out.
We'll do the same here.
And in fact, in the fifth and final
version here, I did one other thing.
You can even use dot dot, which,
again, is just the parent directory.
To be even more security conscious,
because if I look at the listening
here for fifth and final version, notice
that I have one directory here called
public, and then on the
same level, so to speak,
I've got includes and templates
and then that text file readme.
>> And the reason I've structured
it like this-- and so many web
hosts, especially those $5 a
month ones or $10 month ones,
if you've ever had one of these
services-- what so many of them do
is they just expect you to dump all
of your files into one directory,
like we did already with
this very first example.
>> But as soon as you start building more
sophisticated sites that just store
data you care about and files you
care about, actually organizing things
correctly and with more security
consciousness in mind can
we start to defend
against all of the friends
that you have either in or
outside of this class who,
as soon as you start making
programs yourself on the web,
are going to start picking
on you and on them.
>> And so we'll look
ultimately at this design.
This is just a picture
that depicts the following.
We're going to put all of our
programming logic in one or more files,
and we're going to just start
calling those controllers.
It's where the brains of
our websites actually are.
Then we're going to
have views, and views
are as simple as just separate
files-- called templates, often.
They just have the
aesthetics of my page,
what I want the page to look
like-- the colors and the layout
and the positions of
all of the variables.
>> And then more interesting
that we'll eventually get to
is the model, which is going to be just
the word we slap on other technologies
that we bring into the
picture, like actual databases,
so that when you want
to save information,
you don't just send an email
to your proctor or to yourself,
you actually store it in a database
using another language known as SQL.
And so we'll leave here today and
pick up with this on Wednesday
and introduce databases then.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]