>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> [AUDIENCE CHEERING AND APPLAUDING]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: This is CS50,
Harvard University's introduction
to the intellectual
enterprises of computer science
and the art of programming.
We are so excited to have an
amazing alum here with us today.
He was a member of the
Harvard class of 1977.
He concentrated in
applied math economics.
And he was a resident of Currier House.
>> [AUDIENCE CHEERING]
>> He was manager of the
Harvard football team,
advertising manager of the Crimson,
and publisher of the Harvard Advocate.
And upon graduation, he headed off
for a to Stanford's business school,
but didn't stay long, as he was
quickly recruited by a friend of his
to a little company we all know now
as Microsoft, where he served first
as business manager, later as CEO, and
is now the owner of the LA Clippers.
>> [AUDIENCE CHEERING]
>> CS50, this is Steve Ballmer.
>> [CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
>> STEVE BALLMER: Well, thanks.
I'm honored to have a chance
to be here with you today.
When I first talked to
David about this, he said,
I'd really like you to come on
in and give an advanced lecture
in machine learning and
computational thinking.
We didn't dwell on that idea very long.
>> So I thought I'd give
you a little talk--
if I can figure out which
space bar I'm hitting--
what do we need to do to change?
I won't touch that one.
This one I won't touch.
There we go.
OK.
>> I thought I'd give you a little-- you've
got to be a competitor in business.
Anyway, I thought we'd
talk a little bit today,
just a few thoughts, on
most of what I learned
I learned at Harvard University.
I thought I'd try to summarize that
in about nine easy steps and then four
things I learned after
I got out of this place,
and hopefully get all through
that in about 25 minutes-- just
to give you a little
bit of food for thought.
And then we'll do Q&A.
>> I am 99.999999999% sure that
nothing we talk about today
will matter for your grade
or will appear on the final.
I think you're as safe
as rain on that today.
But hopefully, get you thinking about
a couple things as we go through.
First thing that's probably
important for you to register-- this
is sort of academically dangerous--
of all those many important things
I learned at Harvard, it
wasn't in the classroom.
As I listened to David do the
introduction, I thought to myself,
it sounds like I majored in
extracurriculars when I was here.
That's actually true.
I attended all of one
class session senior year.
Junior year was a little bit better.
>> With modern technology, I don't
know what the possibilities are,
but they would seem to
be even greater today
for mischief outside the classroom.
But I will tell you it was really
very, very formative and seminal.
I arrived here in 1973.
And I was hell bent and determined
that I was going to get my Ph.D.
in either math or physics.
And about the only
thing to figure out was
whether it was going
to be math or physics.
That was it.
That's all that needed
to be figured out.
>> Freshman year, the big
decision was whether to take
Physics 55-- I don't know if that
course still exists-- or Math 55.
I thought I'd take both, and the kindly
adviser said, young Steve, big mistake.
I won't allow you to do that.
So I took one of them and did an
independent study in the other.
And thank god I did.
>> First lesson, I learned
very, very early.
Freshman year, I took my first exam.
I took my first exam.
I walked out of it.
I called my parents and said, I
think I just flunked out of school.
I was already involved with the
Harvard football team doing statistics.
I was supposed to go down to Penn, so it
must have been about this time of year,
since the schedule for football
hasn't changed in 50 years.
>> We were supposed to go down Penn.
I didn't go, because I was crest fallen
that I had flunked out of school.
I got my exam back the next
week, and sure enough, I
had gotten a 33, which was about
fifth or sixth in the class.
The guy who got 75 is Ph.D. in
physics, is a professor of physics,
and is a genius.
So it took me about two months
to learn I wasn't a physicist
and I wasn't a genius.
And everything good started right there
with my first big failure, so to speak.
>> I just finished giving a class,
actually, at the business school
at Stanford.
And I worked with a lady who had been a
professor here at Harvard in economics
and now is at Stanford Business School.
And I took the opportunity to look
back and reflect on, let me say,
important lessons that I've
learned over the time of my life,
but particularly that mattered
to me as I was running Microsoft.
>> And I'm not going to try to
go through the detail of each,
but I summarise them in short form.
And when I stopped and looked
back and I said, how many of those
relate to something concretely that I
got out of my experience at Harvard,
the answer turns out to be very high.
>> Small show of hands-- how many
freshman do we have in the class?
Sophomores?
Juniors?
Seniors trying to get that
last CS in before you leave?
OK, good.
>> I will tell you that in reflection, the
amount you can get out of this place
is stunning.
My best friends, many of them I
met to this day while I was here.
The formative experiences, I got here.
And everybody tells
you, but it's amazing
what you can get out of the place.
>> Number one for me, life
lesson, is ideas matter.
Now, people say, of course ideas matter.
What kind of stupid life
lesson is it that ideas matter?
The truth of the matter is this is
both under and over appreciated.
Most people think every idea is a
good idea as long as they had it.
The truth of the matter is
not every idea is a good idea.
Not every idea matters.
And not every idea should be pursued.
>> And if you're in a field like
I am or was of innovation,
not every idea is a good idea, even if
it strikes you that way on first blush.
In fact, most people are
lucky to have one idea that
really matters in their whole life.
That's not a criticism.
But earth shattering,
life changing ideas
are very few and far between--
research insights, investment insights,
innovations.
A good idea needs to be
cherished and nurtured.
And in some senses, you could say I
learned that here at Microsoft-- here
at Microsoft-- here at Harvard.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> I actually know what's
on the slide, though.
I learned it here.
Microsoft was started here by Bill
Gates and Paul Allen when I was here.
When I finally joined the
company, it was five years
after Microsoft got started.
Some people would say it got started up
at the Currier House, but it really got
started up at the housing
project up at Ringe,
which is where Paul Allen was living.
>> But this notion, which
Microsoft started,
was the idea that software represented
a form of free intelligence,
and that if you coupled it with this
new essentially free intelligence
in the form of the microprocessor,
unbelievable things would happen.
And that basic idea that
software was a mobilizing force
for this new microprocessor, which was
free-- that obviously was a big idea.
>> And that was the idea
that Paul Allen and Bill
Gates had when they started the company.
And ideas do matter.
And it is worth considering
and not falling in love
with every idea you have, whether
you're trying to solve a problem set
or you're trying to do something else.
>> Second thing I learned
is there is an advantage
to being what I like
to call now hardcore.
Hardcore-- I don't know
quite how to describe it.
It's a combination of tenacious
and dedicated and passionate and
committed-- something
like that, hardcore.
>> I learned about being hardcore
from math concentrators at Harvard.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> I'm not going to ask whether we
have any math concentrators here.
But I would say that's
where I got my lesson.
People could just go crazy-- focused.
And it wasn't just that
people were genius,
but working and working
and working and working.
I'd sit in my room working on a
problem set, and after three hours--
I'm a little ADD-- I
just couldn't take it.
The most hardcore people could
just power through anything.
>> And the advantage of being
that tenacious and dedicated
and committed-- I claim
it helped us at Microsoft.
It was fundamental at Microsoft.
But I learned it here at Harvard.
>> Passion-- I think it's probably fair
for me to say at this stage in my life
that basketball is a passion.
I started keeping track
of rebounds and assists.
$12 a game I used to get paid.
I went to every Harvard basketball
game, which I would have gone to anyway.
But I got paid $12 to keep
track of rebounds and assists.
>> And I will say that finding
your passion is something
you get to do almost in
a unique way in college.
And finding the things that
you are passionate about
is probably the most
important thing that you
get to really start doing
when you get to college.
Before college, everything's
about getting to college.
It's unfortunate, but I know it's true.
>> Here, take the time to
explore your passion.
I now this year will probably go
to about 200 basketball games.
I think it's fair to
say it is a passion.
But sitting there in the old IAB, which
I think is called the Malkin Center,
marking down-- there's
a guy named Lou Silver
who played on the Harvard
basketball team in 1975.
I gave him the benefit of the
doubt on every rebound ever.
I think I was part of
his All Ivy success.
And who was one of the first guys to
email me when I bought the LA Clippers?
Lou Silver-- passion
built early in life.
>> Own the results.
This is actually, I think, one of the
hardest things for college kids to get,
especially kids at Harvard,
which is at the end of the day,
it's not just about whether
you have a good idea
and whether you're really
talented and really smart.
That's enough to get you into a lot
of good colleges, including this one.
>> But all of those things are
not really measures of success.
You have to do something other than
make grades and get measured on them
in life.
That's generally how the world works.
And really being
accountable for outcomes
makes you better at everything you do.
I comped for the Crimson and had to
go sell $1,000 worth of advertising.
That was a lot of money.
I don't know what the numbers would be
these days-- but $1,000 of ad revenue,
and then took on ad sales.
>> And feeling the pressure,
particularly at an institution
that basically has no
money-- at least that's
where the Crimson was 35
years ago-- it's good for you.
It's good for the soul.
And it actually makes you better at
everything you do to own outcomes.
>> Time-- how many people in the
room would say they are too busy?
Not busy enough?
That's a politically unpopular
place to put your hand,
but God bless you for putting
your hand up over there.
The truth of the matter is,
thinking about time as something
to be managed, whether it's how long--
for those of you who are seniors,
I'm sure you'll ask the question,
how long will I do my first job?
How long?
Will I stay in my job six
months, a year, five years?
>> How long before I decide
whether I really like my career?
How long before I really like my major?
How am I really managing my time?
>> I got involved in a lot
of extracurriculars.
The one that broke the bank for me was
becoming publisher of the Advocate.
I'm not even sure why I did.
Really, I'm not sure why I did it.
It was another resume build.
I was already busy with
football and the Crimson.
>> But I did it.
And then time management
really got into my vocabulary.
I really did have to manage--
and I don't even measure it.
I started skipping class.
I already confessed to that.
But managing time even
amongst the extracurriculars
got to be a big, big deal.
>> Today, I actually keep a
spreadsheet, a bunch of them.
These are all the things
I'm going to do in my life.
Here's how much time is budgeted
to them, and allocate it.
I record everything into Outlook.
I have a macro that
spits it out in Excel.
And I do budget versus
actual comparisons.
>> It's a little different since
I've, quote, retired, unquote.
But at Microsoft, I could tell you I was
going to have 12 one on ones with Harry
this year.
And then I would track them.
How many did I have?
I was going to spend 10 hours a year
talking to customers over the telephone
versus in person.
And I just measure everything,
because I think time is so important.
>> Storytelling-- I think in
whatever you choose to do in life,
even if you're going to be the most
hardcore, dedicated computer engineer,
learning to tell a story, whether you
do it with my-- I can't write a lick,
but I'm not bad at a
speech, but my speech style
is very different than
people standing at podiums.
It's very different.
>> Being able to tell a story through
your work, through your speech,
through your writing is so important.
You want a grant application?
You better tell your story.
You want your start up idea funded?
You want to be the top
engineer on the team who's
compelling vision about
where the product should go?
You better be able to tell a story.
>> And in general, I don't
think people come out
of school well versed in storytelling.
On the other hand, as
Harvard football manager,
I had to get up every team meal-- listen
up, everbody-- and make announcement
for the coaches.
And I got to tell you, being a manager
is not a lofty, revered position.
At least, it wasn't 40 years ago.
I'm sure now it's very different,
because the whole system has changed.
But you'd get up there and you'd
say, how do I tell this story?
What am I really going to announce?
What am I going to do?
Even learning to give speeches--
I was very shy as a kid.
And being a Harvard
football manager for me
was like this huge,
transformative experience.
>> The last lesson I learned at
Harvard is-- not literally,
but figuratively-- it's
get in the weight room.
The weight room in sports
is where you get in shape.
You build new muscles.
You build new flexibility.
You learn to do new things
because you have new capabilities.
>> In life, you have to
stay in the weight room.
You have to keep evolving, building
new skills, learning new things.
And that's easy to say, but
a lot of people don't do it.
You could say, OK, well, people
who go into the tech industry
all do-- not true.
>> I'll just give you
one big transformation
that's happening in the world today.
Most people who are my age
learned a form of computer science
where you wrote a program
that took inputs and gave
you outputs that were
correct or incorrect.
Most modern programming says,
give me a bunch of inputs
and I'm going to statistically guess
about what might be interesting here.
>> That's a very new skill.
And if you find people who are, let's
say, 10 or 15 years out of college,
they don't think that way
technologically, even to this day.
And so the need-- whether it's in
your career or in your life-- for me
at Harvard, I taught Math A?
Does Math A still exist as a course?
It was pre-calculus.
>> Suffice it to say, because I thought
of myself as some super math guy,
I had to learn to take concepts
and explain them simply.
I was teaching pre-calc, something
I had done five years earlier.
And the ability to build
new skills-- I point
to the experience of
doing that at Harvard.
>> Beyond Harvard-- yeah, there
were still a few things to learn.
I know this is the best institution,
absolutely, in the world.
I was at the Boston Globe
today talking about Harvard,
number one in everything.
I bleed Harvard.
But I actually learned a couple
things after I got out of Harvard.
>> The first message I
would say is in life,
you want to be your own quarterback.
See the playing field.
Many people like to get
myopically tied into one thing,
and they have a hard time stepping back.
Being CO of Microsoft is this
amazing, wonderful opportunity.
It turns out, everybody in the
world wants to tell you what to do.
And they'll educate you.
>> You want to learn about
any field of technology?
As long as you don't act like a know
it all, somebody will educate you.
And you have a unique ability to see
broadly across the technology field.
Right now, I'm spending a lot of my time
studying government and the economy.
>> It turns out the number
of places you can actually
read about the totality of government
in the United States is almost zero.
What is the total spent in
government in this country,
and what does it get spent on?
There's no government
report on that topic.
>> The best site happens to come from
some random blogger who I met,
who I think it's great, by the way.
But I found him through our Bing
search engine, not surprisingly.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> That's my only plug for today.
I'm still a shareholder--
but seeing the field.
In life, it's always good to be the
first person to achieve something.
It turns out the guy who wins is
the guy who was doing it last.
So it's always best to invent a new
idea, be the first to do something.
But ultimately, it's about committing to
be successful and to stay at something.
It's sort of a corollary
of being hardcore.
>> And certainly, there are
fields of Microsoft's success,
like selling to large enterprises, where
when we started on that in the '80s,
people said, you'll never do it.
That's all IBM's purview.
And today, that would be 70%
or 83% of Microsoft profits
come because we failed at something
for 20 years but we kept at it.
>> Corollary to ideas matter--
it's hard to have a second idea.
If you really study the tech industry,
most tech companies have one idea,
and as long as the idea is hot, they
stay hot and then they fade to black.
If you look at all the companies
that were important in technology
when I got to Microsoft in
1980, only IBM is still around.
And I might argue it's not
a tech company anymore.
>> And my great dream for Microsoft
is that it is, so to speak,
a two, three, or four trick pony.
I said someplace that I thought
Apple and Microsoft were amazing
because they were two trick ponies, and
somebody thought I was bashing Apple.
No, that's my ultimate compliment.
>> Anybody who can have two good-- if you
have one idea, I think you're amazing.
If you have two ideas, you're
lionized in history for your success.
It's really interesting.
>> Optimim-- Colin Powell came to speak
one year at our executive retreat
after he had been Head of
the Joint Chiefs of Staff.
And he has this quote
that I have come to love.
"Optimism is a force multiplier."
And particularly amongst technical
people and really smart people,
the chic, chic, cool thing to do
is to be cynical and skeptical
and pick things apart.
>> I know that would never happen
in CS50, but you see that
amongst certain kind of
high IQ technical people.
And yet, optimism is a force multiplier.
So how are you brutally
realistic and be optimistic?
It's very, very important.
>> I figured this out after
a while at Microsoft.
Salespeople at Microsoft are naturally
optimistic, probably everywhere.
Just tell us where to
go and we're gonna run!
And I know we're gonna succeed!
Because people want to believe.
Engineers, you say, here's
where we're going to go,
and the first thing they
say is, oh, come on.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> That's not right.
That's not the right way to go.
But I have found-- and this might
belie my fundamental optimism--
that the engineer's
optimist is sometimes
a little different than the salesman.
While the salesman just says, where to
go, charge, the engineer likes to say,
the world is all screwed
up, but I can fix it.
That's an engineer's optimism to me.
Everything's-- but I can fix it.
>> Luck-- this is the one
that really doesn't always
play well amongst Harvard guys.
It turns out that as smart as
you are, as privileged as you
are to be at a place like
this, and as hard as you work,
luck is still going to
be a factor in your life.
Whether you're Bill Gates, Mark
Zuckerberg, or the man in the moon,
luck is important.
It really is.
>> Why is that important to know?
Because it means you better
like what you're doing.
You better not be doing things just
because it will make you successful,
because you're going to need some luck
to make yourself as successful as you
want to be anyway.
So find something where
your passion wins out,
where you're really satisfied.
And then understand-- I know this.
>> I think I'm really talented guy.
I think Bill's a genius.
I think Paul Allen is
amazing, insightful guy.
And I say, boy, how lucky we were.
Apple-- I've seen
their success, and yet,
how lucky they were in many dimensions.
We're a company that
gave them $500 million
when they were almost bankrupt
in '97-- confluence of factors.
And then they did great things with it.
But luck always factors in.
>> And then last, but not least, because
I think I'm about out of time,
everything in the world-- and this
comes from a guy with a real bias--
everything is a technology problem.
Innovation and technology
is the heartbeat
that leads to progress in the world.
>> I read this book in the last six months.
It's called Inequality,
Capital in the 21st Century
by a French economist named Piketty.
It was kind of controversial.
It turns out, if you look
at the Amazon statistics,
hardly anybody finished the book.
It sort of reads like a
socialist diatribe in the end.
But it's got all this great
analysis in the beginning.
>> But a fundamental point
he makes, looking back
over thousands of years
of history, is GDP growth
is only a function of three things.
So the improvements
in life are a function
of population growth and innovation.
That's it-- population
growth and innovation.
>> Today, the hot technology, the
operating system of all innovation,
is computer science.
And as I guess David likes
to say, I'm Steve Ballmer.
This is CS50, the most important
class you'll take at Harvard.
Thank you.
>> [APPLAUSE]
DAVID J. MALAN: So Steve has kindly
left an enormous amount of time
here to take questions.
We have two microphones here.
We have two microphones in the balcony.
So you are encouraged to meet
Gabe and Davin and others here
if you would like to be the first
and second to ask these questions.
STEVE BALLMER: Or you can shout out.
I've heard that's standard
protocol in this class.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: All the better.
>> STEVE BALLMER: That also works.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Our first
question over by Gabe here.
>> AUDIENCE: What was it like
for you making that decision
to drop out and go to Microsoft?
Because obviously, there
was a lot of uncertainty.
>> STEVE BALLMER: OK.
It's 1980.
I'm at Stanford Business School
finishing up my first year.
Bill Gates calls as I'm trying to
decide what to do for a summer job.
He says, hey, look, how are things?
Yeah.
Yeah, oh, you're not finished yet.
Too bad you don't have a twin.
We could kind of use a
business person around here.
That was the pitch.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> I thought about it, and
I said, well, shoot.
I guess I could tell him.
So I called him back the next day
and said, well, maybe we talk.
We should talk.
And my instincts were actually right.
The most risk-free
decision you'll ever make
is the decision to drop out of college.
No, why?
I say it for a reason.
>> Colleges let you drop back in.
All my friends, professors--
oh, you're not gonna do that.
You're gonna go to work for McKinney
or blah blah blah-- I can't remember
who I had offers from--
Brownstone Consulting Group.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> And I said, I might go join this friend
of mine who's got this small start up.
Well, what do you know about that place?
And I said, it's the world leader
in something called software.
And I had written a couple programs, but
it's not like I-- I did not take CS50.
The only programs I had written was
for AM115 or something like that.
It was a mathematical modeling class.
>> And they looked at me kind of funny.
And I told my mom and dad.
My dad was an immigrant.
My dad did not go to college.
My mom did not go to college.
My dad was an immigrant
from Switzerland.
The only college he really grew
up hearing about was Harvard.
Even when I went to
Stanford to Business School,
he was afraid I was making
a mistake, because it
was some place unheard of to him.
And I said, I'm going to drop out.
And this company is the world leader
in software for personal computers.
And my dad said to me, what's software?
Well, that was not an
ignorant question in 1980.
It would seem funny now.
>> And my mom asked me an even
more prescient question,
which is why would a person
ever need a computer?
Because remember, we're in a
time of room-sized computers.
But I said, look.
I made a deal with Bill that said
if it didn't work, he could fire me
or I could drop back into
Stanford at the end of the summer.
>> After a month, I decided I'd made
a mistake going to Microsoft.
I was basically the bookkeeper
for a 30-person company.
I told Bill we were 30 people.
We needed to add 18.
He said, you're gonna
bankrupt this place, Steve.
I didn't ask you to drop out of
Stanford to bankrupt Microsoft.
>> And we had a huge fight.
We were good at that.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> And then he said, come on.
We're going out to dinner with my dad.
Bill's dad's sort of a scary looking
dude-- not really, but he's 6'7".
6'7" doesn't look that
tall anymore either to me,
but that's a Clipper thing.
>> But anyway, I went through my
shtick for Bill and his dad.
And that's where Bill invented what I
think was the theme for the company.
He said, you don't get it, Steve.
We're going to put a computer
on every desk and in every home.
>> And I settled down.
I stayed.
Stanford would still take me back.
It turns out, to this day,
I could go finish my MBA.
It just isn't that risky a proposition,
because these great schools
let you take time off as opposed
to drop out of their memory banks.
It turns out, I'm still a Stanford alum,
too, when it comes to alumni giving.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Another question
from Ian at the mic here.
>> AUDIENCE: So you've made a series
of comments about net neutrality,
particularly speaking against
it, most recently in a tweet.
And that's a particularly
unpopular opinion
amongst a lot of young
people and tech people,
so I was wondering if
you could elaborate that
in maybe more than 180 characters.
>> STEVE BALLMER: Yeah.
Well, first, I haven't
made a lot of comments.
I made one little tweet
yesterday, because I
was kind of annoying on the
plane and had nothing to do.
So I tweeted.
And boy, did that tweet get more
attention than I ever expected.
>> But look, I can explain.
What is net neutrality about?
I'm not quite sure.
But it's not necessarily about keeping
down the price of internet access.
Competition keeps down the
price of internet access.
Net neutrality is merely
deciding who's going to pay.
If the providers who are making
money on the internet-- the Googles,
the Netflixes-- the
Clippers, for example,
if we were to go over the top
with the Clippers broadcast,
we too would be a
broadband content provider.
We're looking at that at the Clippers.
>> But by saying you can't differentially
charge for the traffic, what it says
is all consumers should
pay a higher price
for the people who need the
services that actually cost more.
So if you watch Netflix,
there's two approaches.
You can tell your neighbor who
doesn't watch Netflix, ha, ha, ha, ha.
You pay more, even though you
don't watch Netflix, than I do.
Or you can let the market
compete in differentially priced.
>> I think we're going to get
better service, more pricing
options, and a better overall
deal by having competition
between broadband providers
than by regulating the price.
So this, to me, is not about
low prices versus high prices.
It's about letting free enterprise
solve the problem versus thinking
a few thinkers in DC can invent
complicated pricing and tariffing
schemes that are superior in
creating opportunity than the market.
>> Ultimately, what we really want is more
investment in broadband infrastructure
that leads to better
service at lower prices.
I'm with you on that.
I'm 100% in on that.
I'm making a statement in terms of how I
think the world will best achieve that.
And I feel clear in my
thinking about that.
DAVID J. MALAN: Up next,
our microphone by Anton.
STEVE BALLMER: And I'll say that
even though I know we probably
will wind up-- if we go over the
top with our Clippers TV broadcast,
we will wind up paying more
and our customers will pay more
and we will make a little less
profit, but everybody else
will get lower prices for
fundamental broadband access.
AUDIENCE: Thanks for your time.
What do you love most
about owning the Clippers?
Who's-- wave your hand so--
>> AUDIENCE: Up here.
STEVE BALLMER: Oh, hi.
AUDIENCE: What's up, Steve?
STEVE BALLMER: It seemed like God.
Go ahead.
>> AUDIENCE: Voice of a deity.
>> STEVE BALLMER: What do I like
best about owning the Clippers?
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah, exactly.
>> STEVE BALLMER: I don't know.
Three months in, I can find the
bathrooms now in the stadium.
That's my level of sophistication.
There's a lot of things
that have been fun.
It turns out it's even more fun
to think about the team dynamics
and hear about those from
the coach than I thought.
>> Worrying about the fan
experience in the arena--
I didn't-- the song you were
playing before this started,
I don't know the name, but I
need to get the name from you.
I was thinking, that's a great song.
We could really use that song for
pump ups coming out at time outs.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> No, seriously.
You could say it's my-- I still am
I a "We Will Rock You" kind of guy.
But we have 150 possessions
in a basketball game.
And let's say at least
on half of them, we
want to do something to
keep the crowd engaged.
How do you do that?
How do you orchestrate that
kind of busy environment?
What do you want to do on the Jumbotron?
>> The technology in
basketball-- unbelievable.
Every MBA arena now has
six cameras in the ceiling
that are taking pictures of the action.
And there actually are start ups that
have machine learning technology that
looks at the video and
characterizes the action
so it uses computers to decide that
was a pick and roll versus a pick
and pop with Chris
Paul and Blake Griffin.
That was a blitz by Jamal Crawford.
And every arena is equipped
with this technology.
>> And literally-- it's a company
called Second Spectrum.
And one of the key guys is a 6'9" hooper
out of MIT who never played basketball
after college, but he's doing machine
learning algorithms across vision
recognition on basketball stuff.
That's been kind of fun.
The in arena, thinking about
going over the top and what
do the economics look
like-- it turns out
there's a lot of pretty cool things.
>> It's much more complicated
business than it is large.
Microsoft, we have 100,000 people.
We got about 130 at the Clippers.
And yet, the breadth of problems we
get to think about is actually-- well,
it's not 1,000 times less complicated.
It's probably 500 times less
complicated than Microsoft.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Next question
from Gabe's mic here.
AUDIENCE: Oh, hi.
My name is Larson Ishii.
I write for Clips Nation, so I was
going to continue with the Clippers
questions.
But I was going to ask about how you're
incorporating the rest of technology.
I've seen that you guys have an
increased proportion of statistics
within games, such as
showing the four factors that
produce the probability of victory
within the game, which I don't think
any other teams are doing in the league
currently, which is really awesome.
>> So I just want to know how,
from your math background,
you're incorporating more of the
technology and statistical side
into the game of basketball in what
is scene as more than emerging field,
and if that can help solve the Clippers'
small forward problem right now.
STEVE BALLMER: With a little edge
in the end of that question--
[LAUGHTER]
What we're doing right noq--
and the tech is just not quite
there-- is for every
game, we produce a couple
of plays that actually take some
key play from last time we played
an opponent, and it shows
statistically what the probability was
of success and the
expected points, depending
upon the decisions the player makes.
So you see the guys on the court.
Chris is with the ball.
If he throws it to Blake
Griffin, 30% chance.
On this one, he'd have a 40% chance of
making a basket with an expected two
point or three shot point shot.
And we're using that to demonstrate.
>> What you want to do, of course,
is get it so comes back real time.
So we can take a play that just
happened and have the visualization
based upon the data that's coming out
of the sensors happen in real time
so fans can really track just how
amazing the speed and the decision
making at that speed is.
>> But we're working our way up to that.
The thing that we've done that
actually gets a lot interest
is the thing we call our
Clipper Tron application.
You just go to www.clippertron.com
while you're sitting in the arena,
and you can pick your favorite player.
You can pick a kind of a play-- a pick
and roll, a blitz, a this and this.
And we'll go throw the
highlight up on the Jumbotron.
We're adding, now, Twitter
and Facebook integration.
So we put your name.
We'll put your picture.
And we'll put the plays
that you picked and we can--
people love seeing themselves
on the Jumbo-- kiss
cam, all that kind of stuff.
>> At least, now, we're letting
people throw up basketball action.
Eventually, I want to be able
to do it in people's homes.
So with your phone,
you go to Clipper Tron,
and we'll throw it up live
in the broadcast to you
on TV-- so some of the
stuff we're playing with.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Another
mic up by Dan Bradley.
>> AUDIENCE: Steve, after his
contract with the Lakers is up,
would you consider signing Jeremy
Lin as a backup for Chris Paul?
>> STEVE BALLMER: I support Doc
Rivers 100% in his decision
making about our basketball team.
My job is to support, ask a
lot of questions, and support.
How's that for not
answering your question?
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> I did go to the Laker-Clipper game
in LA last week, week before last.
I'm pleased to report two things.
One, Jeremy Lin played well.
And two, we kicked them.
>> AUDIENCE: So I'm Bobby.
I'm from LA, just in case you
guys need interns this summer.
No, I'm just kidding.
[LAUGHTER]
>> But seriously--
>> STEVE BALLMER: Bobby,
sballmer@clippers.com,
in case you need an
internship this summer.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> Luck, opportunity, take advantage of it.
You got to feed the aggressive instinct.
Go ahead, Bobby.
Run with it, though, babe.
>> AUDIENCE: So you mentioned your
33 on your first exam or whatever.
But can you tell us more about other
examples of failure in your career
at Microsoft or in your life
and what you've learned from it
and how you responded, et cetera?
STEVE BALLMER: Yeah.
I'm funny.
I don't actually-- it turns out, I
got a B plus on the test with the 33,
because it was the fifth
highest grade in the class.
Although I do to play golf with a guy in
LA who reminds me he got 50 on the test
and beat me.
He remembers that to this day.
>> So everything's relative.
I'm a guy who's so optimistic,
in a way, I never think I fail.
I just haven't succeeded yet.
I say be first, but commit to be last.
OK.
Well, that's not going well.
And you can see it in
Microsoft behavior.
People used to say we don't get
things right till version three.
I don't know whether to take
that as a criticism or praise.
Get it right early is good, but
commit to getting things right.
>> So I've certainly had setbacks,
whether it was at school.
Certainly, when we and
IBM split ways, I thought
our company would probably
go out of business.
That was about 1990.
Certainly, I've been told
many times that we'd never
succeed in the enterprise business.
I was told that you can't
do a start up video game.
>> I was told no search engine
will ever succeed versus Google.
There's still more of an element
of truth to that one than I'd like.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> I was told that the mobile device market
is locked up, which I don't believe.
It's partly because I believe in the
power of innovation and the power
not only for people to change
and improve themselves,
but that things do change over time.
And as long as you're prepared,
as I said in my talk--
if you've been in the weight room
and you have the capabilities
and skills to do something
and you stay in the game,
then you're prepared to take
and seize on the next idea.
>> It's kind of like saying, hey, look,
we don't know how to beat the-- I
won't take basketball.
I'll take football.
People don't know how to beat
the Patriots or the Seahawks.
But that doesn't mean you don't stop
training, working out, building skills.
You keep working on your
game plan, but you're always
building your skills and capabilities.
Then you can be optimistic that failure
will lead to success the next time.
DAVID J. MALAN: Why don't we
take a couple more questions
and leave some time
for hellos at the end?
Belinda?
AUDIENCE: Hey, thanks
so much for coming.
So I really appreciated a
lot of the things you said,
and I think three things in
specific really resonated with me.
One, treasure your time.
Two, see the field.
And three, also explore your passions.
>> So the way I see it, the problem
is that time is so finite
and that we have such limited time.
And explore your passions
seems to me more depth-based,
whereas seeing the field
is very breadth-based.
So taken in the context of
also acquiring new skills,
how do you prioritize your time?
And specifically for you, when you said
you created a budget for your time,
how did you decide what was important
and what would be worth your time,
basically?
>> STEVE BALLMER: OK.
Let Two stories-- let me start
as an undergraduate at Harvard.
I beg every senior I know do what I did,
because I thought it really worked out.
When I was a senior, I interviewed
with 35 different companies on campus.
>> I'm trying to get my son to do that.
He's a senior.
I've tried to get friends
of mine whose kids went
to Harvard-- people don't do that.
But why was that good?
And then I got a chance to
sniff 35 different companies, 35
different cultures.
I went back and visited.
I can tell you what it felt like to run
a check processing room at Mellon Bank.
I can tell you what it
would have felt like
to go to Minot, North Dakota
and trade grain for Cargill.
I can tell you what it
would have felt like
to run a small start
up insurance company
in Cleveland-- Progressive
Insurance, which is now,
of course, a major player.
I remember all these visits.
And I just think if you
want to see the field,
you have opportunities
to get what I would
call rapid little experiences that
are really helpful before you get down
to your passions.
>> What I would say as a CEO I did
is I blocked two kinds of time.
One was time that I would do whatever
our people in a given country
wanted me to do or our engineers in a
given product group wanted me to do.
That means they're
telling me about things
I'm not necessarily interested in.
But I can always help the
sales rep with a sale.
Hey, the boss is here, blah blah blah.
But I'm learning, learning,
learning, learning.
>> And then I also blocked explicitly
about call it a total of 20% of my time
where people couldn't schedule it.
And then I could use it
for reading, exploring.
But even time to explore
needs to be blocked.
And time to let others educate
you needs to be blocked.
>> And I think that's part of how
you can continue to see the field
and then develop the kind of
passion-- so just a few thoughts.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Last
question from Davin's mic.
>> AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm J. Paul Meyer.
Over your years at Microsoft,
what product or hire
or whatever it is have you been most
excited about or you most excited
about?
>> STEVE BALLMER: It's kind of like asking
which of your kids you like the best.
And it's kind of situational, timewise.
You look at Windows 1.0 when it came
out-- I can't write a line of code,
but I was the development
manager for Windows 1.0.
Of course that's my favorite
product, and at the end of the day,
it's the backbone of Microsoft.
>> On the other hand, when you
say slick and interesting,
I'd probably point to Excel.
Life changing for me, I'd
probably point to Surface Pro
3 and the pen and One Note.
I finally have the thing I
really want to get my work done.
I really can be paperless.
I really have my life in the cloud.
>> For me, inking is very
important, because if you're
the guy somebody's presenting
to, you can't sit there and type.
If you want to draw and
annotate, markup, you can't type.
So I might say Surface Pro 3.
If I was home with my family, because I
have three boys of about the right age,
I'd say, well, of course, it
was Xbox 360 and the Halo game.
My 15-year-old still believes that's
the only worthwhile piece of work
I did in my working career.
>> [LAUGHTER]
Three weeks ago, he says to
me, Dad, I'm very disappointed
in you leaving Microsoft.
I was worried about this.
Aaron.
I don't know whether you can still get
me the new Halos when they come out.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> So beauty's a little in
the eye of the beholder,
but I'd probably point to the
Surface Pro 3 in modern days
and Windows 1.0 in historic days.
DAVID J. MALAN: Well, let me
wrap up with a little something
we've never done before.
But we, on behalf of
CS50 TFs and TAs would
like to make you an honorary member
of CS50's staff if you'll have us.
>> STEVE BALLMER: OK, absolutely.
>> [CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
Nice!
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And for everyone
here, you are all cordially
invited to a special event that
President Drew Faust, Dean Cherry
Murray, and Steve Ballmer
will be hosting tomorrow
at the I-Lab at 12:00 PM, for which
there will be a puzzle hunt which
is inside of this packet which
you'll be handed on the way
out, for which there's fabulous
prizes, including several Xboxes
and also a pair of Clipper tickets.
>> STEVE BALLMER: Clipper/Celtic tickets
for the game here on March 29,
visiting owners seats.
Do compete.
[CHEERING]
STEVE BALLMER: Thanks, everybody.
DAVID J. MALAN: CS50,
this was Steve Ballmer.
>> STEVE BALLMER: This is CS50!