>> DAVID J. MALAN: This is CS50,
and this is the start of week 10.
You may recall that we've shown
on the screen a 3D printer, which
is this device that
takes spools of plastic
and then extrudes it by heating it
up and melting it so that we can then
form Chang's army of
elephants, for instance.
>> So at Leverett House,
though, recently, I
was chatting with one of your
classmates and a friend of Chang's
named Michelle, who actually interned at
this other company this past year that
has a different technique for actually
creating three-dimensional objects,
like this tiny little elephant here.
In particular, the way this works
is that it's an example of something
called stereolithography, whereby
there's this basin of resin or liquid,
and then a laser strikes that
liquid, and gradually, the device
lifts and lifts and lifts the thing
that you're printing, like an elephant,
as that liquid becomes solid.
And the result, actually,
is something that's
much more robust than some of
the plastic giveaways some of you
might have had.
>> And what Chang kindly
did for us here was
did a time-lapse using photographs
over the course of an hour or more,
probably, to produce this guy here.
Would someone who's never come up before
like to come hit Start on this video?
Let me go with, how about there.
Come on up.
All right.
And you are?
LUKE: My name's Luke [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Hi, Luke.
Nice to meet you.
>> LUKE: Nice to meet you.
AUDIENCE: He's running for UC.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: I know,
we're trying not to promote.
All right, so Luke, all
you have to do here in CS50
is hit the space bar
to print this elephant.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-[MACHINE WHIRRING]
-[CRASH]
-[BOOM]
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: So that is exactly
what it's like to 3D print.
And here is your elephant.
Thanks for volunteering.
All right.
So again, per the specification for
the final project, this hardware that's
available to you guys
is, for some reason,
your project has some intersection
of software and hardware,
realize that these are now resources.
>> I wanted to take one moment to touch
upon a Crimson article that came out
late last night, which was to
announce that this fellow here, David
Johnson, who's been the senior
preceptor for Ec 10 for quite some time,
is leaving Harvard at the
end of the academic year.
And I just wanted to
take a moment, honestly,
to thank David in front of CS50.
He's been a mentor of
sorts to us over the years.
>> And I feel like we, CS50, have
rather grown up with Ec 10
in here, since they are right before us.
And he and the whole team in Ec 10 has
been wonderfully gracious, frankly,
as we lug in all of our equipment
each and every week, and years ago,
provided a great deal
of counsel as we were
curious as to how they operate Ec 10.
So our thanks and
admiration to David Johnson.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Now, unrelatedly, so
the end is indeed near.
We are here in week 10.
And we only have just a
couple of formal weeks
here in class left, followed
by a couple of events.
So to give you a sense of what's
on the horizon, here we are today.
>> This Wednesday, recall,
we'll have a guest lecture
by none other than
Microsoft's own Steve Ballmer.
If you've not yet gone to
cs50.harvard.edu/register,
do so, since space will be limited.
And they will be checking
IDs at the door this day.
If you weren't here
last week, I thought I'd
tease you with a different look
at Steve and the excitement that
awaits us on Wednesday.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -Passion.
>> -We're going to be hardcore-- hardcore.
>> -Innovator.
>> -Bill said, you don't get it.
We're going to put a
computer on every desk
and in every home, which became
the motto for the company.
I swear, Bill invented it
that night to really give me
some of the vision of
why I should say yes.
I've never looked back,
really, after that.
>> -Fresh out of college, he
joined a fledgling startup
and helped it grow into one of America's
most successful businesses ever.
The life of and business
lessons learned along the way
let him back to his
childhood passion and love.
And those experiences have prepared
him for his next challenge in life.
>> -Nothing gets in our way-- boom!
Keep coming hardcore!
Go Clippers!
>> -This is Steve Ballmer,
"In My Own Words."
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: --this
Wednesday to CS50.
Head again to this URL here.
As for what else is on the horizon,
next week, no lecture on Monday.
But we will be following that
by quiz one on Wednesday.
Go to CS50's homepage for details
on people, places, and times
for all of the various proctoring
logistics and the like,
as well as about review
sessions that are forthcoming.
And then, lastly, on Monday, the day
before the week of Thanksgiving break,
realize it will be our final lecture.
We will serve cake and a great
deal of excitement, we hope.
>> Now, a couple of other updates.
Keep in mind that the status
report, which is really just
meant to be a casual interaction
with your TF to proudly state just
how far along with your
final project you are,
or at least as a sanity
check that you should
be approaching that
point shortly thereafter.
The Hackathon then follows that.
Realize the Hackathon
is not an opportunity
to start your final project, but
is meant to be an opportunity
to be in the middle of or toward
the end of your final project,
with the implementation due a few
days later, followed by the CS50 fair.
>> Now, CS50's production
team, a couple years ago,
put together a teaser
for the CS50 fair that we
thought we'd show you today,
because they've been hard at work
on a prequel for that, a new video
that we'll conclude today with.
But here's what awaits you
for this year's CS50 fair.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-[CELL PHONE RINGING]
[MUSIC "THEME FROM MISSION: IMPOSSIBLE"]
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: So that is exactly how
we close final project submissions.
A couple of now teasers-- if
you'd like to join Nick here
for lunch, as usual, this
Friday, head to this URL here.
Moreover, if you would like
to join Nick or this Nick
or this Allison or any
members of CS50's team,
do realize that, shortly
after term's end,
CS50 will already be recruiting
for next year's team,
for CAs, TFs, designers, producers,
researchers, and other positions
that here operate CS50 both in
front of and behind the scenes.
So if this might be of interest
to you, head to this URL here.
And students more comfortable,
less comfortable, and somewhere in
between alike are all welcome
and encouraged to apply.
>> So it was perfect timing that, no
joke, this morning, when I woke up,
I had this here spam in my inbox.
It actually slipped
through Gmail's spam filter
somehow and ended up in my actual inbox.
And it says, "Dear mailbox
user, you're currently
upgraded to 4 gigabytes of space.
Please log into your account
in order to validate E-space."
>> And then there's this nice blue
enticing link there to click on
for faculty and staff, which then led me
to a wonderfully legitimate page, which
asked me to give them my name
and email address and, of course,
password to validate
who I am and so forth.
But of course, as is always the case,
you arrive at this landing page,
and of course, there's
at least one typo,
which seems to be the nail in
the coffin of any of these scams.
And we'll post, perhaps, some other
links to these kinds of screen shots
in the future.
But hopefully, most people in
this room have not clicked--
or even if you've clicked
such links as this,
you haven't gone so far as to
fill out those forms and so forth.
In fact, it's OK if you have.
We'll try to fix that today, because,
indeed, today's conversation is
about security.
>> And indeed, one of the
goals of CS50 is not
so much to teach you CE or
PHP or JavaScript or SQL
or any of these underlying
implementation details.
But it's to empower you as humans
to just make smarter decisions as it
relates to technology down the
road so that, whether you're
an engineer or humanist or
scientist or any other role,
you are making informed decisions
about your own computing usage,
or if you're in a
decision-making position,
in politics, in particular,
you're making much,
much better decisions than a
lot of humans today have been.
And we'll do this by
way of a few examples.
>> First, I was rather surprised
recently to discover the following.
So passwords, of course,
are what most of us
use to protect our data-- email, chat,
and all kinds of resources like that.
And just by an awkward-- not show of
hands, but embarrassed looks of shame,
how many of you use the same password
in a lot of different websites?
>> Oh, OK, so we'll do the hands.
OK, so a lot of you do.
Anyone who does this, just why?
And what?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It's easy to remember, because
you don't have to remember [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
it's easy to remember.
It's a perfectly reasonable,
rational behavior,
even though the risk
you're putting yourself
at in these cases is just
one or more of those websites
is vulnerable to hacking or to
insecure or your password's just
so darn guessable,
anyone can figure it out.
Not only is one account
compromised, but in theory, any
accounts you have on the internet.
So I know I might say today, don't
use the same password everywhere,
but that's a lot easier said than done.
But there are techniques for
mitigating that particular concern.
>> Now, I happen, for instance, to
use a program called 1Password.
Another popular one is called LastPass.
And a bunch of CS50 staff use one
or more of these kinds of tools.
And long story short,
one takeaway for today
should be, yes, you might have
the same password everywhere,
but it's very easy to no longer do that.
For instance, these days, I know
maybe one of my dozens or hundreds
of passwords.
All of my other passwords
are pseudo-randomly
generated by one of these programs here.
And in a nutshell, and even
though most of these programs
tend to come with a bit of a cost,
you would install a program like this,
you would then store all of
your usernames and passwords
inside of this program on
your own Mac or PC or whatnot,
and then it would be
encrypted on your computer
with what's hopefully a
particularly long password.
So I have a whole bunch of
passwords for individual websites,
and then I have a really
long password that I
use to unlock all of
those other passwords.
And what's nice about
software like this is
that, when you visit a website that's
asking for your username and password,
these days, I don't type in
my username and password,
because, again, I don't even know
what most of my passwords are.
I instead hit a keyboard
shortcut, the result of which
is to trigger this software to
prompt me for my master password.
I then type that one big
password in, and then the browser
automatically fills in
what my password is.
So truly, if you take nothing else
away from today in terms of passwords,
these are software that are worth
downloading or investing in so
that you can at least break
that particular habit.
And if you're the type that's
using Post-It notes or the like--
and odds are at least one of you is--
that habit, too, suffice it to say,
should be broken.
>> Now, I happened to discover, as a result
of using the software, the following.
I was ordering an Edible Arrangement,
this basket of fruit, recently.
And I hit my special keyboard
shortcut to log in to the website.
And the software triggered a
pop-up that said, are you sure
you want me to automatically
submit this username and password?
Because the connection is insecure.
>> The connection's not
using HTTPS, for secure,
using that protocol known as
SSL, Secure Sockets Layer.
And indeed, if you look at
the top left of this website,
it's just www.ediblearrangements.com,
no HTTPS, which isn't so good.
>> Now, I was curious-- maybe this
is just a bug in the software.
Surely, some website like
this that a lot of us know of
is at least using encryption
or HTTPS URLs to log you in.
So I got a little curious this morning.
And I got out my CS50 skills,
I opened up Chrome Inspector.
It's not even much of a skill.
It's just hit the right keyboard
shortcut to open this up.
And here's a big window
of Chrome's Inspector.
>> But what was actually a
little tragic and ridiculous
were these two lines here.
Up at the top, notice the URL to
which my username and password
were submitted.
Let me zoom in.
It was this here.
And all of that is
sort of uninteresting,
except for the thing all the way at
the left, which starts with http://.
And so then, OK, maybe
they're just sending
my username, which is
not such a big deal.
Maybe my password gets sent later.
That would be kind of an
interesting design decision.
>> But nope.
If you then look at the request
payload, the username and password
I sent-- and I mocked
these up for the slide--
were actually sent in the clear.
So you go to this particular website and
order an Edible Arrangement like this,
and indeed, apparently, for all this
time I've been ordering from them,
your username and password
is going across in the clear.
So honestly, this is
completely unacceptable.
And it's so trivial to avoid things
like this as the designer of a website
and as the programmer of a website.
>> But the takeaway here for
us as users of websites
is just to appreciate that all
it takes is for one stupid design
decision, unjustifiable design decision,
so that now, if you know my password is
"crimson" on this
website, you've probably
just got into a whole bunch of
other websites that I now have.
And there's not much of
a defense against that
other than what Chang did this morning.
He went to Edible Arrangements, which
is located down the street in Cambridge,
and physically bought this for us.
That was much more secure than
using the website in this case.
>> But the detail to keep an eye out for
is actually what's in the browser up top
there.
But even that can be a little deceptive.
So another interesting
example and way of defending
against this-- and actually, let's
do that first-- the way of defending
against this is a technique
that security people would
call two-factor authentication.
>> Does anyone know what the solution
to problems like this means?
What is two-factor authentication?
Or put another way, how
many of you are using it?
OK, so a couple of shy people.
But yeah.
I saw your hand go up.
What is two-factor authentication?
>> AUDIENCE: Basically, in addition
to typing in your password,
you also have a secondary [INAUDIBLE]
sent via text message to your phone
at the [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
In addition to some primary form
of authentication, like a password,
you're asked for a secondary
factor, which is typically
something you have
physically on you, though it
can be something else altogether.
And that thing is typically a
cellphone these days to which you get
sent a temporary text message that says
"your temporary pass code is 12345."
>> So in addition to my
password "crimson," I also
have to type in whatever
the website has texted me.
Or if you have this with a
bank or an investment account,
you sometimes have these
little dongles that
actually have a pseudo-random
number generator built into them,
but both the device and the bank
know what your initial seed is
so that they know, even as the
little code on your little key fob
marches ahead every minute
or two, changing values,
so does that value change
on the bank's server
so that they can similarly authenticate
you, not only with your password,
but with that temporary code.
Now, you can actually do this in Google.
And frankly, this is a
good habit to get into,
especially if you're using
Gmail all the time on a browser.
If you go to this URL here, which is in
the slides online for today, and then
click on 2-Step Verification,
same actual thing there.
You'll be prompted to give
them your cell phone number.
And then, any time you log into
Gmail, you'll be not only asked
for your password, but also for a
little code that gets sent to your phone
temporarily.
And so long as you have cookies enabled,
and so long as you don't explicitly
log out, you'll only have
to do that once in awhile,
like when you sit down
at a new computer.
>> And the upside here, too, is, if you
sit down at some internet cafe style
computer or just a
friend's computer, even
if that friend
maliciously or unknowingly
has some keyboard logger
installed on his or her computer,
such that everything you
type is being logged,
at least that second factor, that
temporary code, is ephemeral.
So he or she or whoever's
compromised the computer
can't log into you subsequently,
even if everything else
was vulnerable or even
unencrypted altogether.
Facebook has this, too,
with that URL here,
where you can click on Login Approvals.
So here, too, if you don't
want friends to poke people,
you don't want to be poking on Facebook
or posting status updates for you,
two-factor authentication
here is probably a good thing.
And then there's this
other technique altogether,
just auditing, which is even
a good thing for us humans,
if two-factor proves annoying, which,
admittedly, it can, or it's just not
available on some website, minimally
keeping an eye on if and when
you're logging into sites, if they
allow you, is a good technique, too.
So Facebook also gives you this
login notifications feature, whereby
anytime Facebook realizes, hm, David has
logged in from some computer or phone
that we've never seen before from
an IP address that looks unfamiliar,
they'll at least send you an
email to whatever email address
you have on file, saying,
does this look suspicious?
If so, change your password immediately.
And so there, too,
just auditing behavior
even after you've been
compromised, can at least
narrow the window during
which you are vulnerable.
>> All right, any questions
on that stuff thus far?
Today is the day to get all of
your paranoia confirmed or denied.
That's mostly confirmed, sadly.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] phone,
what if your phone breaks,
and then it's always
difficult to verify--
>> DAVID J. MALAN: True.
>> AUDIENCE: Or if you're in a different
country, and they don't let you
log in because [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Absolutely.
And so these are the additional
costs that you incur.
There's always this theme
of a trade-off, after all.
And then, if you lose your phone,
if it breaks, if you're abroad,
or you just don't have a
signal, like a 3G or LTE signal,
you might not actually
be able to authenticate.
>> So again, these two are trade-offs.
And sometimes, it can create a
lot of work for you as a result.
But it really depends, then, on
what the expected price to you
is of something being
compromised altogether.
>> So SSL, then, is this technique that
we all generally take for granted
or assume is there, even though
that's clearly not the case.
And you can still mislead
people, though, even with this.
So here's an example of a bank.
>> This is Bank of America.
There's a whole bunch of these
in Harvard Square and beyond.
And notice that, at the very top of
the screen, there's an, indeed, HTTPS.
And it's even green
and highlighted for us
to indicate that this is indeed
a legitimately secure website,
or so we've been trained to believe.
>> Now, besides that, though,
notice that, if we zoom in,
there's this thing here, where
you're prompted to log in.
What does this padlock mean right
there, next to my username prompt?
This is pretty common on websites, too.
What does this padlock mean?
You seem like you know.
>> AUDIENCE: It doesn't mean anything.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It
doesn't mean anything.
It means that Bank of America knows how
to write HTML with image tags, right?
It truly means nothing, because even
we, using the first day of our look
at HTML, can code up a page with
a red background and an image,
like a GIF or whatnot, that
happens to look like a padlock.
And yet, this is super
common in websites,
because we've been trained to assume
that, oh, padlock means secure,
when it really just means you know HTML.
>> For instance, back in the day, I could
have just put this on my website,
claiming it's secure,
and asking, effectively,
for people's usernames and passwords.
So looking in the URL is
at least a better clue,
because that's built into Chrome
or whatever browser you're using.
But even then, sometimes
things can go wrong.
And in fact, you might not always
see HTTPS, let alone in green.
>> Have any of you ever
seen a screen like this?
You might have, actually,
earlier in October,
when I forgot to pay for our
SSL certificate, as it's called,
and we were looking like
this for an hour or two.
So you've probably seen things
like this, with a strike-through,
like a red line, through
the protocol in the URL
or some kind of screen that's
at least admonishing you
for trying to proceed further.
And Google here is inviting
you to go back to safety.
>> Now, in this case, this just meant that
the SSL certificate that we were using,
the big, mathematically useful numbers
that are associated with CS50's server,
were no longer valid.
And in fact, we can simulate
this, as you can on your laptop.
If I go into Chrome here,
and let's go to facebook.com,
and it looks like this is secure.
But let me go ahead now and
click on the padlock here.
>> And let me go to Connection,
Certificate Information.
And indeed, what you'll
see here is a bunch
of lower-level details about
who facebook.com really is.
It seems that they have paid money to
a company called maybe DigiCert High
Assurance that has promised
to tell the rest of the world
that, if a browser ever sees
a certificate-- you can think
of it literally as a certificate that
looks like that cheesy thing at top
left-- then facebook.com is who they say
they are, because all this time, when
you visit a website, like
cs50.harvard.edu or facebook.com
or gmail.com that use HTTPS
URLs, behind the scenes,
there's this sort of transaction
happening automatically
for you, whereby
facebook.com, in this case,
is sending to your browser its
so-called SSL certificate, or rather,
its public key,
and then your browser
is using that public key
to subsequently send encrypted
traffic to and from it.
>> But there's this whole hierarchy
in the world of companies
that you pay money to who will
then testify, in a digital sense,
that you are indeed facebook.com or
your server is indeed cs50.harvard.edu.
And built into browsers, like
Chrome and IE and Firefox,
is a list of all of those
so-called certificate authorities
that are authorized by
Microsoft and Google and Mozilla
to confirm or deny that
facebook.com is who it says it is.
But the catch is that
these things do expire.
In fact, Facebook's looks like
it expires next October, in 2015.
>> So we can actually simulate this if I
go in my Mac to my System Preferences,
and I go into Date and Time, and
I go into Date and Time here,
and I unlock this here-- thankfully,
we didn't reveal a password this time--
and now I go down to uncheck this.
And let's actually-- oops, that's
not as interesting as doing this.
We are literally in the future now,
which means this is what 2020 is like.
If I now reload the page--
let's do it in Ingognito mode--
if I reload the page, there we go.
>> So now, my computer thinks
it's 2020, but my browser
knows that this certificate from
Facebook expires, of course, in 2015.
So it's giving me this red message.
Now, thankfully, browsers
like Chrome have actually
made it pretty hard to
proceed nonetheless.
They indeed want me
to go back to safety.
>> If I click here on Advance, it's
going to tell me some more details.
And if I really want
to proceed, they'll let
me go to facebook.com, which is,
again, unsafe, at which point
I'll see Facebook's homepage, like this.
But then other things
seem to be breaking.
What's probably breaking at this point?
AUDIENCE: JavaScript.
DAVID J. MALAN: Like the
JavaScripts and/or CSS
files are similarly
encountering that error.
So this is just a bad situation overall.
But the point here is that at least
Facebook does indeed have SSL enabled
for their servers, as many websites,
do, but not necessarily all.
>> But that's not alone the takeaway here.
Turns out that even SSL
has been demonstrated
to be insecure in some way.
So I'm sort of hinting that SSL, good.
Look for HTTPS URLs, and life is
good, because all of your HTTP traffic
and headers and content is encrypted.
>> No one can intercept it in the
middle, except for a so-called man
in the middle.
This is a general technique
in the world of security known
as a man-in-the-middle attack.
Suppose that you're this little
laptop over here on the left,
and suppose you're trying to visit
a server over there on the right,
like facebook.com.
>> But suppose that, in
between you and Facebook,
is a whole bunch of other servers and
equipment, like switches and routers,
DNS servers, DHCP servers,
none of which we control.
It might be controlled by Starbucks
or Harvard or Comcast or the like.
Well, suppose that someone
maliciously, on your network,
in between you and Facebook,
is able to tell you
that, you know what, the IP address of
Facebook is not what you think it is.
It's this IP instead.
>> And so your browser's
tricked into requesting
traffic from another
computer altogether.
Well, suppose that computer
simply looks at all
of the traffic you're requesting from
Facebook and all of the web pages
that you're requesting from Facebook.
And any time it sees in your traffic
a URL that starts with HTTPS,
it dynamically, on the
fly, rewrites it as HTTP.
And any time it sees a location
header, location colon,
like we use to redirect
the user, those, too,
can be changed by this man in
the middle from HTTPS to HTTP.
>> So even though you yourself might
think you're at the real Facebook,
it is not that hard for an
adversary with physical access
to your network to simply
return pages to you that
look like Gmail, that
look like Facebook,
and indeed the URL is
identical, because they're
pretending to have that same host name
because of some exploitation of DNS
or some other system like that.
And the result, then, is
that we humans might only
realize that, OK, this looks like
Gmail or at least the older version,
as is this slide from
an older presentation.
But it looks like this--
http://www.google.com.
>> So here, too, the reality
is that how many of you,
when you go to Facebook or Gmail or any
website and you know a little something
about SSL, how many of you physically
type https:// and then the website
name, Enter.
Most of us just type, like, CS50,
hit Enter, or F-A for Facebook
and hit Enter, and let it auto-complete.
But behind the scenes, if
you watch your HTTP traffic,
there's probably a whole bunch
of those location headers
that are sending you from
Facebook to www.facebook.com
to https://www.facebook.com.
>> So that's one or more HTTP transactions
where your information is completely
sent in the clear, no
encryption whatsoever.
Now, that might not be such a big
deal if all you're trying to do
is access the homepage, you're not
sending your username and password.
But what is it underneath
the hood, especially
for PHP-based websites that's also
being sent back and forth when
you visit some webpage if
that website uses, say, PHP
and implements functionality like pset7?
What was being sent back and forth
in your HTTP headers that gave you
access to this pretty
useful super global in PHP?
>> AUDIENCE: Cookies.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Cookies,
specifically the PHP sess ID cookie.
So recall, if we go to,
say, cs50.harvard.edu again,
but this time, let's open up the
Network tab, and now, up here,
let's literally just go
to http://cs50.harvard.edu
and then hit Enter.
And then look at the screen down here.
Notice that we indeed got
back a 301 moved permanently
message, which means that
there's a location header here,
which is now redirecting me to HTTPS.
>> But the catch is that, if I already had
a cookie stamped on my hand virtually,
as we've discussed before, and
I the human sort of unknowingly
just visit the insecure
version, and my browser takes it
upon itself to show that hand stamp for
the first request, which is via HTTP,
any man in the middle, any
adversary in the middle,
can theoretically just see
those HTTP headers, just
like we're looking at them here.
It's only once you're
talking to an HTTPS
URL does that hand stamp itself get
encrypted, a la Caesar or Vigenere,
but with a fancier algorithm altogether.
So here, too, even if
websites use HTTPS,
we humans have been conditioned, thanks
to auto-complete and other techniques,
to not even think about
the potential implications.
Now, there are ways around this.
For instance, many
websites can be configured
so that, once you have this hand
stamp, you can tell the browser,
this hand stamp is only
for SSL connections.
The browser should not present
it to me unless it's over SSL.
But many websites
don't bother with that.
And many websites apparently
don't even bother with SSL at all.
>> So for more on that, there's actually
even more dirt in this presentation
that a fellow gave at a so-called black
hat conference a couple of years ago,
where there's even other
malicious tricks people have used.
You might recall this
notion of a favicon, which
is like a little logo that's
often in the browser's window.
Well, what's been
common among bad guys is
to make fab icons that look like what?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Say again?
AUDIENCE: The websites.
DAVID J. MALAN: Not a website.
So favicon, tiny little icon.
What would be the most
malicious, manipulative thing
you could make your website's
default icon look like?
AUDIENCE: A green lock.
DAVID J. MALAN: What's that?
AUDIENCE: A little green lock.
DAVID J. MALAN: Like
a green lock, exactly.
So you can have this aesthetic
of a little green padlock,
hinting to the world, oh, we're
secure, when, again, all it means
is that you know some HTML.
So session hijacking
refers to exactly that.
If you have someone who's kind of
sniffing the airwaves in this room here
or has physical access to a
network and can see your cookies,
he or she can grab that
PHP sess ID cookie.
And then, if they're
savvy enough to know
how to send that cookie as their own
hand stamp just by copying that value
and sending the HTTP headers,
someone could very easily
log into any of the Facebook
accounts or Gmail accounts
or Twitter accounts that are here, open
in the room, if you're not using SSL
and if the website is
not using SSL correctly.
>> So let's transition to another one.
So another true story.
And this just broke in the
news a week or two ago.
Verizon has been doing
a very evil thing,
and as best people can tell,
since at least 2012, whereby,
when you access websites via a Verizon
cellphone, whatever manufacturer it is,
they have been presumptuously,
as the story goes,
injecting into all of your HTTP
traffic their own HTTP header.
And that header looks
like this-- X-UIDH.
UID is like a unique
identifier or user ID.
And X just means this is a custom
header that's not standard.
>> But what this means
is that, if I pull up,
for instance, any website
on my phone here--
and I'm using Verizon as my carrier--
even though my browser might not
be sending this HTTP
header, Verizon, as soon
as the signal reaches their
cellphone tower somewhere,
has been for some time injecting this
header into all of our HTTP traffic.
Why do they do this?
Presumably for tracking reasons,
for advertising reasons.
>> But the moronic design decision
here is that an HTTP header,
as you guys know from pset6,
is received by any web server
that you're requesting traffic of.
So all this time, if
you've been visiting
Facebook or Gmail or any website
that doesn't use SSL all the time--
and actually, those
two thankfully now do--
but other websites that
don't use SSL all the time,
Verizon has essentially
been planting, forcibly,
a hand stamp on all of our
hands that even we don't see,
but rather, the end websites do.
And so it hasn't been that
hard for anyone on the internet
running a web server to
realize, ooh, this is David,
or, ooh, this is Davin, even if we're
rigorous about clearing our cookies,
because it's not coming from us.
It's coming from the carrier.
>> They do a lookup on your phone number
and then say, oh, this is David.
Let me inject a unique identifier so
that our advertisers or whoever can
keep track of this.
So this is actually very,
very, very bad and horrifying.
And I would encourage you to
take a look, for instance,
at this URL, which I should disclaim
I actually tried this this morning.
I wrote a little script,
put it at this URL,
visited it with my own Verizon
cellphone after turning Wi-Fi off.
So you have to turn Wi-Fi off so that
you're using 3G or LTE or the like.
And then, if you visit
this URL, all this script
does for you guys, if
you'd like to play,
is it spits out what HTTP headers
your phone is sending to our server.
And I actually, in fairness, did
not see this this morning, which
makes me think either the local
cellphone tower I was connected to
or whatnot is not doing it, or they've
backed off of doing this temporarily.
But for more information,
to head to this URL here.
>> And now to this-- this
comic might make sense.
No?
OK.
All right.
That died.
>> So let's take a look at a couple of more
attacks, if only to raise awareness of
and then offer a couple
potential solutions
so that you're all the more mindful.
This one we talked about the other
day, but didn't give a name to it.
It's a cross-site request forgery, which
is an excessively fancy way of saying
you trick a user into clicking on
a URL like this, which tricks them
into some behavior that
they didn't intend.
>> In this case, this seems
to be trying to trick me
into selling my shares of Google.
And this will succeed if
I, the programmer of pset7,
have not done what?
Or rather, more generally, in what
cases am I vulnerable to an attack
if someone tricks another user
into clicking a URL like this?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: You don't distinguish
between GET and POST.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
If we don't distinguish
between GET and POST,
and indeed, if we allow
GET for selling things,
we're inviting this kind of attack.
But we could still mitigate it somewhat.
And I commented, I think,
last week that Amazon at least
tries to mitigate this with a technique
that's pretty straightforward.
What would a smart thing
to do be on your server,
rather than just blindly selling
whatever symbol the user types in?
AUDIENCE: Confirmation of sorts?
DAVID J. MALAN: A confirmation screen,
something involving human interaction
so that I am forced to
make the judgment call,
even if I've naively clicked
a link that looks like this
and led me to the cell screen, at
least asked me to confirm or deny.
But not an uncommon attack, especially
in so-called phishing or spam-like
attacks.
>> Now, this one's a little more subtle.
This is a cross-site scripting attack.
And this happens if your
website is not using
the equivalent of htmlspecialchars.
And it's taking user input and just
blindly injecting it into a web page,
as with print or echo, with--
again-- out calling something
like htmlspecialchars.
>> So suppose the website in
question is vulnerable.com.
And suppose it accepts
a parameter called q.
Look at what might happen
if I actually, a bad guy,
type in or trick a user into
visiting a URL that looks like this--
q= open script tag, closed script tag.
And again, I'm assuming
that vulnerable.com is not
going to turn dangerous
characters like open brackets
into HTML entities, the
ampersand, L-T, semicolon thing
that you might have seen before.
>> But what is the script
or JavaScript code
I'm trying to trick a
user into executing?
Well, document.location refers
to my browser's current address.
So if I do document.location=,
this allows me to redirect the user
in JavaScript to another website.
It's like our PHP function
redirect, but done in JavaScript.
>> Where am I trying to send the user?
Well, apparently, badguy.com/log.php,
which is some script, apparently,
the bad guy wrote, that takes
a parameter called cookie.
>> And notice, what do I
appear to be concatenating
onto the end of that equal sign?
Well, something that
says document.cookie.
We haven't talked about this.
But it turns out, in
JavaScript, just like in PHP,
you can access all of the cookies
that your browser is actually using.
>> So the effect of this one
line of code, if a user
is tricked into clicking on this link
and the website vulnerable.com does not
escape it with htmlspecialchars,
is that you have just effectively
uploaded to log.php all of your cookies.
And that's not always that problematic,
except if one of those cookies
is your session ID, your
so-called hand stamp, which
means badguy.com can make his or her own
HTTP requests, sending that same hand
stamp, that same cookie header,
and log into whatever website
you were visiting, which in
this case is vulnerable.com.
It's a cross-site scripting
attack in the sense
that you're sort of tricking
one site into telling
another website about some information
it should not, in fact, have access to.
>> All right, ready for one
other worrisome detail?
All right, the world is a
scary place, legitimately so.
Here's a simple
JavaScript example that's
in today's source code
called geolocation 0 and 1.
And there's a couple
walkthroughs online for this.
>> And it does the following if I
open this web page in Chrome.
It first does nothing.
OK, we'll try this again.
Oh.
No, it should do something.
OK, stand by.
>> Let's try this once more.
[INAUDIBLE]
Ah, OK, not sure why
the-- oh, the appliance
probably lost internet
access for some reason.
All right, so happens to me, too.
>> All right, so notice
what's going on here.
This cryptic-looking URL, which
is just one of CS50 server,
wants to use my computer's
location, like physically it means.
And if, indeed, I click on
Allow, let's see what happens.
Apparently, this is my current latitude
and longitudinal coordinates down
to a pretty darn good resolution.
>> So how did I get at this?
How does this website, like CS50 server,
know physically where in the world
I am, let alone with that precision.
Well, turns out-- let's just
look at the page's source--
that in here is a bunch of HTML at
the bottom that first has this--
body onload="geolocate"--
just a function I wrote.
>> And I'm saying, on loading
the page, call geolocate.
And then there's nothing
in the body, because
in the head of the page,
notice what I have here.
Here's my geolocate function.
And this is just some error checking--
if the type of navigator.geolocation
is not undefined.
So JavaScript has this
mechanism where you
can say, what is the
type of this variable?
And if it's not undefined--
that means it is some value--
I'm going to call
navigator.geolocation.getCurrentPosition
and then callback.
>> What's this?
So in general, what is a
callback, just to be clear?
You might have encountered
this already in pset8.
Callback's a generic
term for doing what?
Feels like just me today.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly,
a function that should
be called only when we have data.
This call to the browser, get my current
position, might take one millisecond,
it might take a minute.
What this means is we are telling
the get getCurrentPosition method,
call this callback function,
which I literally named callback
for simplicity, which
apparently is this one here.
>> And the way getCurrentPosition works,
simply by reading the documentation
for some JavaScript code online, is
that it calls that so-called callback
function, passes it into
it a JavaScript object,
inside of which is .coords.latitude
and .coords.longitude,
which is exactly how, then,
when I reloaded this page,
I was able to see my location here.
Now, at least there was a defense here.
Before I visited this page,
when it actually worked,
what was I at least prompted for?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yes or no-- do
you want to allow or deny this?
But think, too, about the habits
you guys have probably adopted,
both on your phones and your browsers.
Many of us, myself
included, are probably
pretty predisposed these days-- you
see a pop-up, just Enter, OK, Approve,
Allow.
And increasingly, you can put
yourself at risk for those reasons.
>> So in fact, there was this wonderful bug
a few years ago-- or lack of feature--
that iTunes had a few years ago,
whereby, if you had a cell phone,
and it was an iPhone,
and you left your home
and therefore traveled around the world
or the neighborhood, all this time,
your phone was logging
where you are via GPS.
And this is actually disclosed,
and people kind of expect this now.
Your phone knows where you are.
But the problem was that,
when you were backing up
your phone to iTunes-- this was before
the days of iCloud, which is for better
or for worse-- the data was being stored
in iTunes, completely unencrypted.
So if you have a family or roommates
or a malicious neighbor who's
curious about literally every GPS
coordinate you have ever been to,
he or she could just
sit down at iTunes, run
some software that was freely
available, and produce maps like this.
>> In fact, this is what I
produced of my own phone.
I plugged it in.
And it looks like, based
on the blue dots there,
that's where most of
the GPS coordinates were
logged by iTunes that I
was in the Northeast there.
But I apparently traveled around
a bit, even within Massachusetts.
>> So that's Boston Harbor
there on the right.
That's kind of Cambridge and
Boston, where it's darkest.
And occasionally, I would run
errands to a larger geography.
>> But iTunes, for years, had, as best
I could tell, all of this data on me.
You could tell that,
that year, I was actually
traveling a lot between Boston
and New York, going back and forth
and back and forth.
And indeed, this is me on Amtrak, back
and forth, back and forth, quite a bit.
All of that was being logged and
stored encrypted on my computer
for anyone who might have
access to my computer.
>> This was worrisome.
I did not know why I was
in Pennsylvania or why
my phone was in Pennsylvania,
apparently fairly densely.
And then, finally, I looked
at my Gcal, and, oh, I
visited CMU, Carnegie
Mellon, at the time.
And phew, that kind of
explained that blip.
And then, if you zoom
out further, you can
see I visited San Francisco
one or more times then,
and I even had a layover in what
I think is Vegas, down there.
So all of this-- just a
layover, at the airport.
>> AUDIENCE: [LAUGHTER]
>> So this is only to say that these
problems, honestly, are omnipresent.
And it only feels
increasingly like there's
more and more of this being disclosed,
which is probably a good thing.
I daresay, the world isn't
getting worse at writing software.
We're getting better,
hopefully, at noticing
how bad certain software
is that we're using.
And thankfully, some
companies are beginning
to be held accountable for this.
>> But what kinds of defenses
can you have in mind?
So besides password managers, like
1Password and LastPass and others,
besides just changing your passwords
and coming up with random ones
using software like
that, you can also try
as best you can to encrypt
all of your traffic
to at least narrow the zone of a threat.
So for instance, as Harvard affiliates,
you can all go to vpn.harvard.edu
and log in with your Harvard ID and PIN.
And this will establish a secure
connection between you and Harvard.
>> Now, that doesn't
necessarily protect you
against any threats that are between
Harvard and Facebook or Harvard
and Gmail.
But if you're sitting
in an airport or you're
sitting in Starbucks or you're
sitting at a friend's place,
and you don't really trust them or their
configuration of their home router,
at least you can establish
a secure connection
to an entity like this place that's
probably a little better secured
than something like a
Starbucks or the like.
And what this does is
it establishes, again,
encryption between you and the endpoint.
>> Even fancier are things like this.
So some of you might already
be familiar with Tor,
which is this sort of anonymization
network, whereby lots of people,
if they run this software, route
subsequently their internet
traffic through each other.
So the shortest point is
no longer between A and B.
But it might be all over the
place so that you're essentially
covering one's tracks and leaving
less of a record as to where your HTTP
traffic came from, because it's going
through a whole bunch of other people's
laptops or desktops,
for better or for worse.
>> But even this is not a surefire thing.
Some of you might recall last year
the bomb scare that was called in.
And it was traced ultimately to a
user who had used this network here.
And the catch there , as I recall, is,
if there aren't that many other people
using a software like this or
using this port and protocol,
it's not that hard for a network to even
figure out who, with some probability,
was in fact anonymizing
his or her traffic.
>> And I don't know if those were the
actual particulars in question.
But surely, realize that none of
these are surefire solutions, as well.
And the goal here today is to least
get you thinking about these things
and coming up with techniques for
defending yourself against them.
Any questions on all of the threats
that await you out there, and in here?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: How secure do
we expect the average
[? website to be, ?] like
the average CS50 project?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: The
average CS50 project?
It is always proved every year that
some CS50 final projects are not
particularly secure.
Usually, it's some roommate or
hallmate that figures this out
by sending requests to your project.
>> Short answer-- how many
websites are secure?
I'm picking on today anomalies.
Like it was just happenstance
that I realized that this website
I've been ordering these frankly
delicious arrangements from--
and I'm not sure I'll
stop using their website;
I might just change my
password more regularly--
it's not clear just how
vulnerable all these various--
this is chocolate-covered actually.
The short answer, I can't answer that
effectively, other than to say it
was not that hard for me to
find some of these examples just
for the sake of discussion in lecture.
And just keeping an eye on
Google News and other resources
will bring all the more of
these kinds of things to light.
>> All right, let's conclude
with this prequel
that CS50's team has prepared for you
in anticipation of the CS50 Hackathon.
And on your way out in a
moment, fruit will be served.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC FERGIE, Q TIP, AND GOONROCK, "A
LITTLE PARTY NEVER KILLED NOBODY (ALL
WE GOT)"]
>> -[SNORING]
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: That's it for CS50.
We'll see you on Wednesday.
[MUSIC - SKRILLEX, "IMMA' TRY IT OUT"]