DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50.
And this is the start of week seven.
So today, perhaps thankfully,
we begin our transition
from the lower level
world of C programming
to the higher level
world of web programming.
And with that, we'll take a look
at exactly how the internet works,
what these machines and these internets
that you've been using for years now
actually do underneath the hood toward
a better understanding of how it all
works, and how you can
make it work for you.
>> Toward that end, why don't we take a
look first at a clip from a TV show
called Numb3rs, that will get us started
as to exactly how the internet works.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-It's a 32-bit IPP4 address.
-IP.
That's the internet.
>> -Private network.
It's Amita's private network.
Oh, she's so amazing.
>> -Oh, Charlie.
>> -It's a mirror IP address.
She's letting us watch what
she's doing in real time.
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: So there's a whole
lot of wrong with that TV show.
So let's tease apart exactly
one of the first such things
and see if we can't wrap
our minds around it.
So the last frame of
that movie, of that show
is this one here, which
seems to suggest that this
is what some hacker is using
to get into some system.
>> But no.
If you zoom in on this
source code, which
is a language called Objective C in
which iPhone apps, iPad apps, and Mac
OS apps are written,
you'll see that this
is for some sort of drawing program
that has a crayon as a variable.
>> So additionally, you might
have noticed this address here.
Now, this is an as wrong.
And this is probably deliberately chosen
to be an invalid address so that it
doesn't actually lead somewhere
if a TV viewer actually visits it.
But this number here,
something dot something
dot something dot something is what's
generally known as an IP address.
And it's actually a good
segue to this topic more
generally, known as
IP, internet protocol.
So you've probably at least
heard this phrase before.
But what is IP, or internet
protocol as you understand it today?
Odds are, if we asked for a
show of hands, most of you
have probably said the
words IP address before.
So what did you mean?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID MALAN: What's that?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID MALAN: Once more.
AUDIENCE: Address of the computer.
DAVID MALAN: The
address of the computer.
So that's exactly right.
It turns out that every
computer on the internet,
and these days, every phone in your
pocket and tablet in your backpack,
has an IP address, internet
protocol address, which
is a unique address that identifies
it throughout the entire internet.
Now, that's a bit of a white
lie because the world's actually
running out of IP addresses.
>> So we've started using
private IP addresses.
But more on that in a moment.
But you can think of an IP address
as like your postal service street
address.
We've use the example of Maxwell
Dworkin, the CS building, before-
33 Oxford Street Cambridge,
Mass, 02138, USA.
That is its unique address in the world.
>> Similarly do computers
have unique addresses.
They just happen to
look a little different-
a number dot a number dot
a number dot a number.
And does anyone actually know
what the valid range of numbers
is for each of those hashes?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: 0 to 255?
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
0 to 255.
And even if you didn't know
that, now draw a conclusion,
how many bits are used to represent
each of these numbers then?
Eight apparently because of
the highest you can count
is 255, that's an 8-bit value.
So in total, an IP address is 32-bits.
So fast forwarding to the
mathematical conclusion,
how many possible IP addresses
are there in the world, then?
>> So that's 8 plus 8 plus 8
plus 8, so that's 32 bits.
And we've always said that
2 to the 32 is roughly?
OK.
I'll field this one.
Four billion.
And we talked about that in week
zero when we talked about phone books
with crazy numbers of pages.
But the sort of it is that there's
a finite number of IP addresses.
And even though four billion
might seem like a lot,
we humans have been
consuming quite a few
of them for all of our servers
and devices and so forth.
>> So this is actually becoming a problem.
Now, there tends to be a
scheme behind who has what IP.
For instance, many of
the computers at Harvard
have unique addresses that start
with one of these two values.
MIT, similarly, has a prefix.
And a lot of companies and universities
have their own unique prefix.
And then most of us for our home
internet connections and the like,
we share some prefix that Comcast
or someone like that happens to own.
And this is only to say that if you
looked at most computers on campus,
they'd probably have an IP
address that looks like this.
>> Now, you might also occasionally see
an IP address it starts like this.
In fact, if any of you grew up
with internet access at home,
and you were ever sufficiently
technically curious to poke around
your own computer settings,
you probably instead
saw an address that looks more like
this, that started with 10, or 172.6,
or 192.168, or some variants thereof.
>> And that just means that the world
is set aside a whole bunch of numbers
to be private, which means
you can use them in your home,
you can even use them on your
campus and within your company,
but you can't use them
on the internet at large.
>> And so these private
IPs have been a solution
toward making sure that at least so
far as the whole world is concerned,
we're not using that many IP addresses.
But at least, we can, on our own
campus, have pretty much as many IPs
as we want.
But who cares?
What's the relevance of all of this
to an actual usage of the internet?
>> Well, let's take a look at
perhaps a simple picture here.
Let me through both of
these up on the screen.
And forgive my handwriting here.
But if we think of ourselves as
being this little laptop here
somewhere on campus,
these days it has Wi-Fi.
>> But in yesteryear and if
you find the right adapter,
it can have an ethernet cable
which would similarly let
you connect to some kind of device.
And you can call this
any number of things.
But I'm going to go ahead and call this,
for now, how about an access point?
>> So this is my laptop.
This is my AP, or access point,
and this is some wireless device,
not unlike the ones that Harvard
has all over the ceilings
and walls around campus
that have blinking lights
and that are what your laptops
used to talk wirelessly
to the rest of the network.
>> So somehow this laptop is talking
to that thing on the wall,
in the dining hall, or elsewhere.
Now, meanwhile, that access point is
connected to something else on campus.
And it's probably something
known as a switch.
And they look a lot more interesting
than just these box diagrams.
>> But somehow, that thing's
connected to a switch.
And in turn, somehow
that switch is connected
to a device that's probably a
bit bigger, called a router.
And then, meanwhile,
Harvard is connected
to the entire internet which
we'll draw as this cloud here,
via some number of wires
or wireless technology.
>> So there's a lot of steps between
me and the rest of the world.
And indeed, even within
this picture here,
there are some other servers
or services involved.
And I'm just going to draw
these somewhat abstractly
just so that we have
the acronyms before us.
>> One is called DHCP.
And another one, a little more
interestingly for today, is called DNS.
So these are servers that are somehow
accessible to my computer as well.
So now, let's tease
apart a bit of jargon.
So the access point is
just this wireless device
often with antennas that actually
let you talk to a wirelessly.
At home, you might call
this a home router.
It might be made by Linksys, or Apple,
or D-Link, or any number of companies.
That, in turn, is connected
to a switch of some sort.
Or back home, what is your Wi-Fi
device probably connected to instead?
Because you probably don't
own all this equipment.
Yeah.
Cable modem or DSL modem back home
that you got from Verizon, or Comcast,
or one of those carriers.
So think of all of this complexity
as supporting a university or really
a business like Comcast.
And really, the stuff
that's in your home
is probably on this side
of the fence plus maybe
one of these home route-- one
of these are cable modems or DSL
modems they might provide.
>> So a switch is just a device with
a whole bunch of data jacks in it.
In fact, if you recall that news
report we played on the big screen
a couple of weeks ago where we
were talking about shell shock,
and how bad this was?
And there were of these
photographs of cables, and jacks,
and things that look technical?
Those were just dumb switches that
just internet connects computers
by plugging cables into them.
>> So that's all a switch is.
Now, these devices get a
little more interesting.
DHCP.
If you've poked around your
computer at home or even on campus,
you might have seen this acronym.
Does anyone know what a DHCP server is?
Dynamic host configuration protocol?
Not the kind of thing you
really need to write down.
DHCP.
anyone at all?
All right.
So let's rewind the story.
If the story here at hand is predicated
on my having a unique address
in the world, an IP address,
where does that come from?
In yesteryear, when
you've got to campus,
you actually had ask someone at
Harvard, what should my IP address be.
And you would manually
type it into your computer.
But more recently, technologies
exist that allow you to dynamically,
DHCP, get an IP address simply when
you plug into campus wirelessly
or with a wire.
So DHCP server is just a server
that gives your computer a unique IP
address, somewhat randomly
or via some algorithm.
But if you think back a
few weeks or a few years,
when you first registered
your computer on campus,
you were telling Harvard, authorize
me to give me an IP address.
Now DNS start to get a
little more interesting.
Domain name system.
Does anyone want to take a stab
at what this thing is here?
>> It's one or more servers that
perform a fairly simple task that's
kind of important.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Translates URLs [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
It translates URLs to IP
addresses and vice versa.
Consider, after all, that
when you go on the website,
you type in something like facebook.com,
or google.com, or harvard.edu,
you certainly have never typed
most likely a numeric IP address.
>> And you can think of the reason why.
Back in the day, even
now to some extent,
when you make a telephone
call to a company,
they really try hard to buy themselves
an 800 number that actually has words
in it, like 1-800-collect or something
that's memorable like that so that
people don't have to remember what
C-O-L-L-E-C-T actually expands to.
So we've seen this
heuristic in the past.
And indeed, that's what IP addresses
and what we'll call host names
or fully qualified
domain names do for us.
It allows us to address servers
by words instead of numbers.
So how do we actually
see this conversion.
I'm going to go ahead
and open up a program.
I'm just going to go ahead
and open up a terminal window.
And I'm going to go ahead and
show you what a DNS server does.
For instance, if I wanted to see
what the IP address is of Facebook,
I can type at a terminal
prompt like this--
and you can do this even
inside of your appliance.
And that's lookup facebook.com.
>> And I see a bunch of things.
This first response is
Harvard's DNS server--
that picture that I've
drawn there. --that's
telling me that Facebook's IP
address is apparently this.
So let me go ahead and
copy that 173.252.120.16.
And let me open up Chrome on my Mac.
And let me go to http:// and paste
that IP address in and hit Enter.
>> And indeed, I find myself at Facebook.
So somehow that conversion,
indeed, happened.
And if I do this again, let's
do nslookup, www.google.com.
I get back a whole bunch of responses.
And indeed, there's different ways
that companies implement this.
Sometimes, they tell the world
they have one IP address.
>> But that one IP address gets resolved
or mapped to multiple servers.
Or in the case of Google,
they tell the world,
we have a whole bunch of IP addresses.
Your laptop is welcome to talk
contact any one of these servers.
So all of that's been going
on underneath the hood.
>> When you type in www.google.com Enter
into your browser, your browser,
and in turn your operating, Mac
OS, or Windows, or Ubuntu Linux,
ask the nearby DNS server, what is
the actual address of this server.
Because the last device
in this picture, a router,
is the one whose purpose in
life is to route information,
route packets so to speak,
envelopes of digital information
containing zeroes and ones from
sender to destination, from origin
to receiver.
>> And so a router routes stuff.
So why is this all
particularly relevant?
Well, let's take a look
at how this might be used.
Suppose that I have here
a picture of Rob Boden.
So suppose that I want to
send this picture of Rob Boden
into Dan in the back
of the lecture hall.
>> So I am a computer
like my laptop, and Dan
is some other computer on the internet.
And I want to send a packet
of information from me to him.
That begs the question, how do I
actually route this packet to him.
Well, in human terms, I would say,
hey, can you pass this to Dan?
>> And then, a bunch of you
would probably pass it back
and forth back and forth until
eventually makes its way over to Dan.
But that's a little imprecise.
Computers probably need to
be a little more methodical.
So probably, Dan has an IP address.
So what really I should do is I should
take, for instance, a blank envelope
like this.
And I don't know what
Dan's IP address is.
>> So I'm just going to
generalize it as Dan's IP.
And I'm going to put this in
the to field of my envelope.
And meanwhile, I have an IP address.
It doesn't matter today what it is.
So I'm just going to say My
IP in the back corner there.
And then, I'm going to go ahead and put
this picture inside of this envelope.
>> And then, each of you, presumably,
as routers on the internet,
have been preconfigured by
humans generally or sometimes
by automated algorithms to know that
if Dan's IP address starts with a 1,
it should go that way.
If Dan's IP address starts with
a 2, it should go that way.
Maybe a 3 goes that way.
Maybe a 4 goes that way.
And that's a little overly.
Simplistic but that's the general idea.
Each of these routers-- and there might
be as many as 30 between me and Dan.
--have some kind of spreadsheet
inside of their memory,
a database table, that just says,
IP address that looks like this,
goes this way.
An IP address that looks
like this, goes that way.
And that's how it makes
fairly simplistic decisions.
>> But it turns out that these routers do
something more than that, potentially.
They allow computers to
guarantee delivery, at least
with high probability.
So you might, too, have heard, even if
you've never quite cared or wondered
what it is, you might have heard
of something by this acronym.
Let's go back over here for
just a moment and pull up this.
>> TCP, transmission control protocol.
Another technical way of just
describing another technology
that's used on the internet.
So IP, internet protocol
is used for addressing.
It some standard that the
world came up with that said,
you put one IP address here for Dan,
and one IP address here for yourself,
and then you put some
information in an envelope.
>> But TCP is another technology,
used in conjunction with IP.
And indeed, if you've ever
seen these acronyms before,
you've probably seen
TCP slash IP which just
means people tend to use them together.
Well, TCP is kind of
cool because it allows
you to increase the probability
that the data is actually
going to get from me to Dan.
>> In fact, the internet is a crazy place.
There's no guarantee that
if I send data this way
that it's going to go
that way next time around.
It might go that way or that way.
The shortest distance between
two points is not necessarily
a straight or the same line.
>> Moreover, some of you
guys might make mistakes
or get overwhelmed with too
many envelopes coming your way.
So you just going to
give up and literally
drop some of these
envelopes on the floor.
And in that same way can data be
dropped on the internet by routers.
So to decrease the
odds of this, I'm going
to take my little safety
scissors here and cut Rob
into, let's say, four
pieces, four segments.
>> And now, I'm going to go ahead and
put one more piece of information
on this envelope.
I'm going to say something like, 1 of 4.
So now, my final envelope, at
least the first, looks like this.
I'm going to go ahead
and put this one in here.
And for time's sake, I'm going to
label the others identically as 2 of 4,
3 of 4, 4 of 4.
>> Again, with Dan's IP address in the
front of it and with my IP address
on the back left, but I
can't send them just yet.
Because it turns out
that on the internet,
servers can do multiple things.
In fact, we all might use the web
quite a bit, the worldwide web,
http:// whatever.
But there's other
services on the internet.
What are some other services, sort
of user, consumer-friendly services
that spring to mind besides
a web browser-type program?
AUDIENCE: Email.
DAVID MALAN: Email.
OK.
Good.
What's another one?
AUDIENCE: Chat.
DAVID MALAN: So chat, whether
it's Skype, or Gchat, or something
like that.
>> AUDIENCE: Storage.
DAVID MALAN: So some kind of
storage service, certainly.
Something like Dropbox,
or Box, or the like.
So there's different
services on the internet.
And it turns out that Dan,
if he is indeed a computer,
doesn't have to be dedicated
to one thing in life.
He can actually do multiple things.
And indeed, he can be an email server.
He can be a web server.
He can be a chat server.
>> But that seems to suggest
that Dan needs to know
in advance what are the
contents of these messages.
Is this a web page I'm sending him?
Is it an email I'm sending him?
Is it an instant
message I'm sending him?
So we need one more piece of
information on these envelope
so that Dan, when he
receives this envelope,
knows what program to use to display it.
>> Is it a browser?
Is it Google?
Is it Skype?
Or is it Outlook or some
other program altogether?
And so, with TCP comes
just a human convention.
The world decided some years
ago to associate unique integers
with the most popular services.
>> One's called File Transfer Protocol,
FTP, though it's a little dated now.
But its unique identifier is 21.
SMTP for outbound email, its unique
identifier is 25 just because.
DNS, the thing we talked about earlier,
uses the number 53 for its queries.
Like what is the IP
address of google.com?
>> And now, the more familiar you
might have somewhere at some point
seen the number 80 and maybe 443.
Those are the unique
identifiers for HTTP,
which is the language
we'll soon see used
for web traffic between
browsers and servers.
And 443 is for the
secure version thereof.
>> So the one last detail I'm
going to put on my envelope
is that I'm not going to
send this just to Dan's IP.
I'm going to send it to say,
:80, if what I'm trying to send
him is a web page, a web page
that contains Rob Boden's picture.
So I'm going to do the same
thing on these other envelopes.
>> And then ultimately, I'm going to drop
these off with the nearest router,
recognizing that that
router might not necessarily
take the same path every time.
In fact, I might have the
first packet going this way.
Second packet might go that way.
Third packet-- start routing.
--might go over here.
And in theory-- can't keep it.
In theory, all four of these packets
should eventually route their way,
however efficiently or inefficiently,
all the way to the back.
>> At which point, Dan, upon
receipt, can reassemble them
based on-- the funny thing is,
we all know what the outcome here
is going to be.
Dan's going to get a picture of Rob.
But let's see how this works out.
Well, rather, Dan's going to
get part of a picture of Rob.
Very good.
Everyone's participating today.
All right.
So as Dan starts to receive these
packets, let's ask one question.
What if one of you gets lazy,
overloaded, malicious, or just powered
off, and one or more of the
package doesn't make it to Dan?
>> How is Dan going to know he did not
receive one of the segments of the four
I sent him?
Just intuitively, what can we do?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Because I've uniquely numbered them, and
I've specified how many segments there
should be, he can infer from that
which, if any, of the segments
he's actually missing.
And what TCP tells computers to
do, if computers, like Mac OS,
and Windows, and Linux support
and understand TCP, which they do,
TCP's documentation essentially
says that Dan should send me
a message back saying, hey, David,
I'm missing packet number 1 of 4,
or 3 of 4, whichever it is.
>> And then, my job is to take
another picture of Rob,
which we have extras of for later today
if you'd like to take one with you,
and then I can resend that segment
of Rob all the way to the back.
>> So as simplistic as
this mechanism is, that
is what's happening almost any time
you do something on the internet,
particularly for these
most popular of services.
There are other protocols,
other technologies besides TCP
that work a little differently.
But so many of the services we typically
use actually rely on these protocols.
>> So Dan, did you get the
full picture back there?
Yes.
We have reassembled Rob in the back.
Thank you so much to the routers.
Suppose, I actually want the
see the routers between me
and MIT, much like you guys were
the routers between me and Dan.
>> Well, rather than nslookup
for name server lookup,
I can instead type trace route, which
is actually going to do what it says.
And I'm going to do and
quiet mode with dash 1.
It's a command line argument
that just says, try this
once and not multiple times.
>> And now, I'm going to type www.mit.edu.
Now, the output is
fairly quick and cryptic.
But what's neat about this
is that each of these rows
essentially represents a
student in this audience
if you were the path between me and MIT.
What you see up here, first, is
the domain name that I typed in,
or fully qualified domain
name as it's properly called.
>> And this apparently is the
IP address of www.mit.edu.
My computer figured that out for me.
This here is a promise
that we're only going
to try to reach MIT within 30 hops.
There better be no more than
30 students between me and Dan.
And now, each of these rows
represents literally a router
between me and Dan,
literally one of you guys.
>> And so this one doesn't seem
to have a name, a domain name.
It just has an IP.
And it only took 0.662 milliseconds
to get from me to that first router.
The next one wasn't
that much farther away.
It only took one
millisecond to get there.
And now, thankfully, things
get a little more user-friendly
with names that are cryptic
but a little more telling.
>> This apparently is a router in the
core of Harvard's network housed,
only because people have told us
this, in the Science Center, SC.
And GW is just a shorthand notation for
gateway which is a synonym for router.
So this is some system
administrator's superscript way
of naming one of the servers
in the Science Center.
>> Meanwhile, that server is apparently
connected by some kind of cable
to another router that's nicknamed
the border gateway one dash
something, whatever those numbers mean.
And then, apparently,
Harvard has a connection
that's another millisecond
away to something
called the northern crossroads
which is a common peering point
between big places like Harvard
where lots of cabling goes in
and allows interconnections
among different entities.
>> Step six, unfortunately,
doesn't have a valid name.
And step seven gets interesting.
I have no idea what most of these mean.
But NY does jump out at me.
And what does that probably signify?
It's not even technical.
Just New York.
So indeed, what's common human
convention not guaranteed
but common convention is to name routers
by nature of the city or the airport
code that they're nearest to.
>> So with some probability,
this router number seven
is probably, indeed, in New York.
And this seems to corroborate
that assumption because it's
six milliseconds instead of just one
or so to something here on campus.
But now take that into account,
right on Megabus or whatnot,
it might take four, five, six hours
to get a human from here to New York.
>> To get a piece of data, it
takes just six milliseconds
to get a packet from me to Dan if
he were all the way in New York.
Then finally, this apparently is the
actual domain name for www.mit.edu.
They've apparently
outsourced their web servers
to a company called Akamai which means
some other company runs their servers.
And that's why we're seeing
that weird thing there.
>> Well, let's do this once more.
Let's go ahead and do a trace
route to our friend Professor Nick
Parlante at Stanford who has a
server called nifty.stanfor.edu.
Enter.
And now, we'll see probably
a slightly longer path
that goes through a few more cities.
So here these nameless
Harvard servers here.
We're in the core of Harvard,
the border gateway of Harvard,
the northern crossroads,
wherever this is.
And now, it's getting a
little more interesting.
I'm guessing that router
number eight is in what city?
AUDIENCE: [INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID MALAN: Chicago probably, based
on this, based on this thing here.
And now we have Salt Lake City maybe,
maybe Los Angeles here, and then LAX,
yep, this probably is LA by the bottom.
Until finally, it goes
from southern California
all the way up to northern California
to where Stanford is in Palo Alto.
So pretty cool.
And let's take this one step further.
It apparently would
take you 82 milliseconds
to send a message to Dan if you were
in California instead of New York.
Let's do something
like trace routes, one
attempt to www.cnn.co.jp for the
Japanese version of CNN's website.
And now, we're still in
Boston it seems at the moment.
>> A couple servers six and
eight aren't responding
because they're being a little private.
But eventually, there seems to be
something interesting going on between,
let's say, step seven and nine.
What is probably between
seven and nine, and certainly
between seven and step 17?
There's a huge jump
in the amount of time
it's taking for data to go from one
of these hops, one of these routers
to another.
>> So odds are, somewhere in
here, there's probably,
especially right here, there's probably
a very large body of water that
has some trans Pacific or trans
Atlantic cable that actually requires
even more time for data to
get from one point to another.
But again, imagine the hours
it would take the fly to Japan.
Here, in some 200 milliseconds,
boom, your message is actually there.
So you can play around with
this on the appliance or even
in Windows or Mac OS with
slightly different commands.
Sometimes, you will get these stars,
like in rows six and eight, which
just means the routers
are configured not
to give you an answer
for privacy's sake.
But generally, this technique
would, in fact, work.
>> So it turns out too there's other
juicy information lurking in tools
that you take for granted every day.
So for instance, if you receive
an email, frankly as some of you
may have recently, of questionable
origins, if you've never
looked at Gmail interface
before, whether it's
for the college interface
or your personal one,
you might see your
inbox looking like this.
>> And in fact, this is an email
I sent, malan@harvard.edu,
to jharvard@cs50.harvard.edu
this morning just
so I could take a screenshot.
But it turns out, all
this time in Gmail,
there's that little triangle
toward the top right
there next to the Harvard crest that if
you click, you can click Show Original.
And if you do that, you'll actually see
a bunch of very esoteric information
like timestamps, and IP
addresses, and domain names.
>> But you'll see, in short, the
headers that all this time have
been hit in each and every
email you send and receive.
And it's these headers that people can
use, computer scientist or otherwise,
to actually infer with
some probability where
and from whom an email actually came.
>> In fact, we'll talk in
later weeks about how email
itself can be generated
programmatically which
is a very good thing for a website
that wants to send emails to users.
But we'll see, too, just how trivial
it is to forge emails from someone
to someone else, unless you actually
know how to verify the headers.
And even that is a losing
proposition these days.
>> So with that said,
let's go one layer up.
We started with IP which
addresses packets for us,
gives them unique addresses.
TCP, which, in short,
guarantees delivery or at least
increases the probability thereof by
adding things like segments, 1 or 4,
2 of 4, 3 of 4, and 4 of 4.
>> And now, let's layer on top
of that another protocol.
All of these things are
protocols, computer conventions
that dictate how two
computers talk to one another.
HTTP, finally today, is
hypertext transfer protocol.
And this is the protocol
that web browsers
use when speaking to web servers.
>> So when you pull up a browser like
Chrome, or IE, or Firefox, or Safari,
or whatever, and you type in something
like facebook.com and hit Enter,
not only does your computer first
translate facebook.com into what?
An IP address.
It then converts-- it then sends a
message to that IP address saying,
give me today's homepage or give
me the login screen of Facebook.
>> Or if you're already logged in, give
me the default view of my timeline.
So that's what HTTP says.
And more colloquially, if I am a web
server and you are-- what's your name,
again?
>> AUDIENCE: Margot.
>> DAVID MALAN: Margot is a web
server, and I'm a web browser,
and I simply want to retrieve my
timeline from Margot, margot.com,
I would say, hello, I'm David.
>> AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Margot.
>> DAVID MALAN: And you would then respond
with additional information to me.
So we have this stupid human
convention for instance-- thank you.
--of shaking each other's hands.
And computers have that same idea
where a client, like a browser,
asks a server to do something
on his or her behalf.
>> And so here's a picture, for instance.
On the left is a computer laptop,
desktop, whatever, or even a phone.
And on the right is a very
dated view of a server.
They typically looks smaller
and sexier these days.
But the point is simply that
there's some kind of communication
between client and server.
>> And clients in the sense
of someone in a restaurant
and the waiter or waitress,
same idea with computers.
Clients and servers, one
asks for information,
one responds with information.
Now, how does that
information come back?
Well, consider this.
Get is sort of the default way--
and it's a super simple term.
--that just dictates how a browser
gets information from a server.
>> In other words, rather than just
goof-ily extending my hand to Margot,
if I really were a browser, I
would stuff inside of an envelope,
as I did with Rob's photo before, a
textual message that literally says
something like this,
get/http/1.1hostwww.google.com
or margot.com or whatever the
server's name might happen to be.
And then, dot dot dot, some other stuff.
>> But literally, inside
of an envelope would
be fairly simple textual
message like that.
That upon receipt, Margot would
open up, read the content,
and respond accordingly.
Now, it's a little
non-obvious with this example.
But get/, what is the slash
probably referring to, just based
on your familiarity with
browsing the web in daily life?
What's the slash?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: An escape sequence.
Not a bad idea but generally
escape sequences go the other way.
That would be a backslash usually.
But not a bad thought.
Yeah?
A pointer.
Also good thought but
even simpler than that.
The home directory.
The root of a hard drive, so to speak.
Most of us don't type this.
But technically, if you wanted
to be super proper these days,
you would go to something
like http://www.facebook.com/.
>> Now, I said most of us wouldn't
bother typing the slash.
And frankly, most
browsers, Chrome included,
don't even bother showing
us the slash these days
just because they like to
be simple and succinct.
But the slash just means go
to www.facebook.com and get
slash, the root of the hard drive,
the default page in facebook.com.
Using what protocol?
Well, using version 1.1 of
this thing known as HTTP.
>> The server, or Margot--
and by the way, do
you mind that I'm using you in these?
OK.
So we're good now.
So Margot response now with an
envelope of her own, inside of which
is a similarly textual message.
The first line of which is,
yep, I speak HTTP version 1.1.
200 is the status code
which just means all is OK.
I have the page you're looking for.
>> Meanwhile, Content-Type: text/html, this
is Margot's semi-arcane way of saying,
what you have requested is a web page.
And it's type, so to speak--
almost like a variable sense,
but this is much higher level now.
Its data type is text
but specifically HTML.
The language we'll soon see.
>> And then, there's some other stuff.
So other stuff is literally what
Facebook is responding with.
So let's see this, too.
Let me go ahead and open
up Chrome on my laptop
which you can do on your
own computer as well.
And I'm going to go ahead
and open up www.facebook.com.
Enter.
And I get this familiar screen here.
But now, I'm going to do something else.
I'm going to go ahead and
go to View, Developer.
And go to Developer
Tools, which you should
have within Chrome on your computer,
at least within your appliance.
I'm going to scroll this
thing up here, and you're
going to see a whole bunch
of cryptic text here.
>> It turns out that what Margot put inside
of that envelope in response to me
is a language called HTML,
HyperText Markup Language.
It's not a programming
language because you can't, it
doesn't have loops, and conditions,
and functions, and things like that.
It's a markup language.
In that, it has special syntax
called tags and attributes
that tells a browser what to display
on the screen and how to display it.
Should be centered?
Should it be bold-faced?
Red, green, blue?
It's a markup language.
In that, it tells a browser
what to show on the screen.
So this is, literally, all of the
HTML and more that Facebook server
is spitting out and that
Chrome, and IE, and Firefox have
been designed by their
respective authors to understand.
>> And in fact, it's a
little messier than that.
If you, instead, go to View,
Developer, View Source,
this is actually what
Facebook is out putting.
Sort of zero for five
for style, right, if we
infer that this probably isn't the best.
But frankly, they can get away with
it because if you're serving up
billions of web pages
per day, you really
don't want to waste time, and bytes,
and money ultimately in transmitting
things like new line
characters, and spaces, and tabs
because you're spending for bandwidth
unnecessarily with your ISP.
>> So indeed, this is meant
to be minified in this way.
But what Chrome is doing
for us is, it's taking
this HTML, which completely looks like
a mess and unintelligible to human,
and it's just formatting it.
It's pretty printing it so that
we can wrap our minds around it
a little more readily.
But more interesting is this.
If I now click in Chrome,
not elements but network,
I'm going to see a little
logging screen that's
going to show me all
of the HTTP requests
that are actually going back and
forth between me and Facebook or me
and Margot if I make
more than one request.
>> So I'm going to go ahead and click
the reload icon up here in Chrome.
And now, a whole bunch of
stuff flew past at the bottom.
I'm going to scroll
back up to the very top.
And now, notice this, the
very first request my browser
made was to www.facebook.com.
>> It's using the get
mechanism which just means
it's speaking the textual language
that we saw an example of a moment ago.
And moreover, it turns out
that the response that Facebook
gave me is 200 OK, which means I
found the web page in question.
>> If I click on this row, I can actually
see those headers a little more
clearly.
These will make more sense before long.
But notice that my browser sends a
whole lot of information like host,
and method, and cookies.
We'll come back to those before long.
And you'll finally understand
what a cookie actually is
and how you soon will be sending them.
>> And you can see what
Facebook is sending back,
including the content type of text
HTML, the current date time, its privacy
policy, or lack thereof, and
then, finally, a number of cookies
that are being set on
your computer as well.
But we'll tease those apart before long.
>> But in short, every time you
visited a web page, now for years,
you've been sending messages to
the one I sent in an envelope
to Margot and to Dan.
And you've been getting back
responses like this from Facebook.
But moreover, guess what's being
disclosed to Facebook, and Google,
and everyone else every
time you visit a web page?
What is on the outside of every
envelope your computer has been sending?
Your IP address, right?
Maybe not your name per
se, but your IP address.
And just, let's connect the dots
later, if you're using services
like the web, or
BitTorrent, and the life,
and you've registered a computer
at a place like Harvard,
someone somewhere knows that John
Harvard's IP addresses this, dot this,
dot this, dot this.
>> And indeed, logs can he kept both on a
campus like this, on a Comcast network,
on Verizon, or frankly, at the
NSA as we've recently learned,
that logs pretty much everything
that you are doing on the internet.
And we'll come back to
this the future class
on the implications of these
design decisions and security.
>> But the truth is, you really
don't have all that much privacy.
Every time you've been visiting anywhere
on the web, you been showing your hand
and revealing at least your IP address.
So scary note aside, what can we do to
embed things like cats in a web page?
>> So we have a bunch of responses that
might come back from the server.
And we won't see all of these today.
But 200 is good.
And you're probably not seen
all of these as a human before.
But you've probably seen
at least one of these.
Which one of these might look familiar?
AUDIENCE: 404
DAVID MALAN: So 404.
File not found.
And indeed, you're going to see
this programmatically yourself.
404 just means the file you requested,
slash or slash something, simply
doesn't exist.
And a web server typically
responds with 404 as a result
>> Meanwhile, we'll soon see that
the contents of that message
are this language known as HTML.
And this is a super
simple snippet of HTML
that does nothing other than
display hello world on the screen.
Indeed, you see at the top of this
something called a document type
declaration which just says, hey, world.
This file contains HTML.
And then, the next bit of HTML
that you're going to write,
it has an open bracket,
and then the word HTML,
then a closed bracket, and then
open head, and close bracket.
So in short, let's actually
do this more mechanically.
Let me go into my appliance,
but you can do this anywhere
that you have a text editor to.
>> I'm going to go ahead and
save a file called hello.html.
I'm going to put it on my desktop to
keep things super simple right now.
And I'm going to do
exactly what I just saw.
So doc type HTML, open bracket HTML.
And now, notice, I'm going to
do the opposite preemptively.
And by opposite, I mean
the same tag, so to speak,
but it starts with a forward slash.
And then, over here,
I'm going to say, head,
because it turns out that every
web page has a so-called head which
is stuff that goes in the title
bar, at the very top of the page.
In the title is just
going to be hello here.
And now, I'm going to have
a body to this web page.
So every web page has both
a head up top and a body
which is the guts of the page.
And here, I'm just going to
say something like hello world.
And I'm going to save this file.
If I now minimize gedit,
look, there's a little file
on my desktop called hello.html.
Now, that's not on a server
yet, per se, Indeed, it's
just on my own personal desktop here.
But if I open up Chrome and hit Control
O-- there's the cat in question.
--and I go to my desktop.
>> And I open up hello.html, there, in
fact, is my super simple web page.
The body of my page
and this white window
here is the body with hello world.
And the title in the head of
the page is in the tab there.
And we're going to see
soon that it's super
simple to open up other pages as well.
For instance, I'm going to go
into some of the distribution code
for this week, source
seven, and I'm going
to open up not the JPEG
which this guy is here.
But I'm going to open up image.html,
which ultimately looks like this.
But let me now open this up in gedit,
and go into Dropbox source seven,
and image.html.
>> Most of this is just
comments as we'll soon see.
But if I want to put Grumpy
Cat inside of this web page,
it suffices to put another open bracket,
and then the keyword image or img
for short, and then alternative
text for accessibility reasons
if someone has a screen
reader or something like that.
Source which is, what's the
name of the file, cat.jpeg.
>> And then, because this
tag's a little special,
we put the forward slash, as
we'll see, inside of the tag.
But the end result is a web
page that looks like this.
So in short, what we're going to be
doing now over time is using the web
and creating web pages to
ultimately be containers
not only for silly things like
images, and links, and tables,
and bulleted lists, and the like,
but also to give us ourselves
a graphical user interface, a GUI,
not unlike what we did we Breakout.
>> But within this environment, we're
going to start using languages like PHP,
and JavaScript, the database
language called SQL,
a client-side scripting language
called JavaScript to actually create
all the more dynamic interfaces but
in a much, much more familiar context.
But before then, let's
conclude today with a look,
as promised, of what's really going on
underneath the hood with the internet
itself.
>> Stipulate for today
that the internet can
be used to transfer things
like web pages over HTTP
much like I shook Margot's hand earlier.
But there's so many other
services that use TCP and IP
that we take for granted
that work as we'll see here
in this film that'll
take us to the end today.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -For the first time in
history, people and machinery
are working together, realizing a dream.
A uniting force that knows
no geographical boundaries.
Without regard to race, creed, or color.
A new era where communication
truly brings people together.
This is The Dawn of the Net.
>> Want to know how it works?
Click here to begin your
journey into the net.
Now, exactly what happened
when you clicked on that link?
You started a flow of information.
This information travels down
into your personal mail room
when Mr. IP packages it, labels
it, and sends it on its way.
>> Each packet is limited size.
The mail room must decide how to divide
the information and how to package it.
Now, the package needs a label
containing important information,
such as sender's address, receiver's
address, and the type of packet it is.
>> Because this particular packet
is going out onto the internet,
it also gets an address
for the proxy server, which
has a special function
as we'll see later.
The packet is now launched onto
your local area network or LAN.
This network is used to connect
all the local computers,
routers printers, et cetera
for information exchange
within the physical
walls of the building.
The LAN is a pretty uncontrolled
place and, unfortunately, accidents
can happen.
>> The highway of LAN is packed
with all types of information.
These are IP packets, Novell
packets, Apple Talk packets.
They're going against traffic as usual.
The local router reads the
address and, if necessary,
lifts the packet onto another network.
Ah, the router.
A symbol of control in a
seemingly disorganized world.
>> There he is, a systematic,
uncaring, methodical, conservative,
and sometimes not quite up to speed.
But at least, he is
exact for the most part.
>> As the packets leave the
router, they make their way
into the corporate intranet
and head for the router switch.
A bit more efficient than
the router, the router switch
plays fast and loose with IP packets,
deftly routing them along the way.
A digital Pinball Wizard if you will.
>> -Here we go.
Here comes another one.
And it's another.
Watch this, Mom.
Here is goes.
Whoops.
Around the back.
Hey.
In there.
Over to the left.
Over to the right.
You got it.
Here it goes.
He shoots.
He scores.
It's going.
Hey, wait.
Hey, watch out.
Here comes another one.
Oh, here we go.
>> -As packets arrive at
their destination, they're
picked up by the network interface,
ready to be sent to the next level,
in this case, the proxy.
The proxy is used by many
companies as sort of a middle man
in order to lessen the load
on their internet connection
and for security reasons as well.
As you can see, the packets
are all of various sizes,
depending upon their content.
>> The proxy opens the packet and
looks for the web address or URL.
Depending upon whether
the address is acceptable,
the packet is sent on to the internet.
There are, however, some
addresses which do not
meet with the approval of
the proxy, that is to say,
corporate or management guidelines.
These are summarily dealt with.
We'll have none of that.
For those who make it,
it's on the road again.
>> Next up, the firewall.
The corporate firewall
serves two purposes.
It prevents some rather
nasty things on the internet
from coming into the intranet.
And it can also prevent
sensitive corporate information
from being sent out onto the internet.
>> Once through the firewall,
a router picks up the packet
and places it onto a much narrower
road or bandwidth, as we say.
Obviously, the row is not
broad enough to take them all.
Now, you might wonder, what
happens to all those packets
which don't make it along the way.
Well, when Mr. IP doesn't
receive an acknowledgement
that a packet has been
received in due time,
he simply sends a replacement packet.
>> We are now ready to enter the
world of the internet, a spider
web of interconnected networks
which span our entire globe.
Here, routers and switches
establish links between networks.
Now, the net is an entirely
different environment
than you'll find within the
protective walls of your LAN.
>> Out here, it's the Wild
West, plenty of space,
plenty of opportunities, plenty of
things to explore, and places to go.
Thanks to very little
control and regulation,
new ideas find fertile soil to push
the envelope of their possibilities.
But because of this freedom,
certain dangers also lurk.
>> You'll never know when you
meet the dreaded ping of death,
a special version of a normal request
ping which some idiot thought up
to mess up unsuspecting hosts.
The path our packets take maybe via
satellite, telephone lines, wireless,
or even transoceanic cable.
>> They don't always take the fastest
or shortest routes possible,
but they will get there, eventually.
Maybe that's why it's sometimes
called the worldwide wait.
But when everything is
working smoothly, you
could circumvent the globe five
times over at the drop of a hat,
literally, and all for the
cost of a local call or less.
>> Near the end of our destination,
we'll find another firewall.
Depending upon your
perspective as a data packet,
the firewall could be a bastion
of security or dreaded adversary.
It all depends on which side you're
on, and what your intentions are.
>> The firewall is designed to let in only
those packets that meet its criteria.
This firewall is operating
on Ports 80 and 25.
All attempts to enter through other
ports are closed for business.
>> Port 25 is used for mail packets.
While Port 80 is the entrance for
packets from the internet to the web
server.
Inside the firewall, packets
are screened more thoroughly.
Some packets make it
easily through customs,
while others look just a bit dubious.
>> Now, the firewall officer
is not easily fooled,
such as when this ping
of death packet tries
to disguise itself as
a normal ping packet.
-Move along.
It's OK.
No problem.
Have a nice day.
Let me outta here.
Bye.
>> -For those packets lucky
enough to make it this far,
the journey is almost over.
It's just a line up on the interface
to be taken up into the web server.
Nowadays, a web server can run on many
things, from a mainframe, to a webcam,
to the computer on your desk.
Why not your refrigerator?
>> With the proper set
up, you could find out
if you have the makings
for chicken cacciatore
or if you have to go shopping.
Remember, this is The Dawn of the Net.
Almost anything's possible.
>> One by one, the packets are
received, opened, and unpacked.
The information they contain, that
is your request for information,
is sent on to the web
server application.
>> The packet itself is recycled.
Ready to be used again and filled with
your requested information, addressed,
and send out on its way back to you.
Back past the firewalls, routers,
and on through to the internet.
Back through your corporate firewall.
And onto your interface.
Ready to supply your web browser
with the information you requested.
That is this film.
>> Pleased with their efforts and
trusting in a better world,
our trusty data packets
ride off blissfully
into the sunset of another
day, knowing fully they
have served their masters well.
Now, isn't that a happy ending.
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: That's it for CS50.
We will see you next week.
>> [MUSIC - KATY PERRY, "DARK HORSE"]