DAVID MALAN: All right.
So this is CS50, and this is
now the start of week three.
>> So up until now, we've
been writing programs in C
that look a little
something like this here.
So we've got a couple of
sharp includes at the top.
We've got int, main, void, and
then something to do in the middle,
some bit of code inside
of that function.
But key has been the fact that
we've been saying void here.
So void, all of this time, specifies
that this program, when run,
can only be run via its name.
You cannot type any other words or
numbers after the program's name when
running it.
So, for instance, if the program were
compiled into a file called hello,
you could do ./hello, but that is it.
>> The only way that you could
provide input to this program
is by calling a function.
For instance, what function
have we been using thus far
to get input from the user?
>> AUDIENCE: Get string.
DAVID MALAN: To get string, or
get int, or you've seen others,
even if you haven't used them yet,
like get long, long and the like.
But suppose that we
actually want to start
writing programs that are little more
versatile, and, frankly, a little more
like the commands that you've
been getting, hopefully,
a little bit accustomed to.
Like cd space Dropbox.
This, of course, changes
your directory, assuming
you're in John Harvard's home
directory, to your Dropbox folder.
Meanwhile, a command like this
creates a new directory called pset2,
as you might have already or
will soon for problem set two.
Make Hello, of course, is a command
that builds a program called hello
from a file called hello dot c.
And in each of these
cases, now, we've had
provide an argument on the so-called
command line, the blinking prompt,
so that make knows what to build, and so
that mkdir knows what folder to create,
and so that cd knows
where you want to go.
But up until now, we keep saying
that main, your default function,
has a void expression
inside of those parentheses,
which means that it
cannot take any arguments.
>> So starting today,
what we're going to do
is, we're going to start
supporting things like this even.
In fact, in this case, which you
don't typically manually type,
Make has been doing this
for us, there are not
one but one, two, three additional
strings after the program's named
clang.
So how do we achieve this?
>> Well, starting today,
in cases where we want
to provide input via the
so-called command line,
we're going to start adding
here what's in yellow--
replacing void with int argc comma
string argv open bracket close bracket.
Now this is interesting
for a couple of reasons.
One, it's going to let us write
programs that are a little more dynamic.
But, more compellingly,
it's going to open up
now a conversation as to
what arrays can really
be used, for what a string
really is underneath the hood,
until next week when we start diving
in even deeper as to how the machine is
making all of this stuff work.
But for now, let's draw,
perhaps, a picture.
>> When you write a program
with main declared
in this way, such that main
takes two arguments, an int
and-- what data type
is the second argument?
>> AUDIENCE: Array.
DAVID MALAN: Array.
So it looks at first glance like it's a
string, but notice the square brackets.
Recall last time we introduced
the notion of an array.
And arrays use square brackets
in a couple of contexts.
You might use the square
brackets to go into an array
and get a particular element, like
bracket 0 or bracket 1 or bracket 2.
But we saw, if briefly,
last week that you also
use these square brackets to
declare the size of an array,
if you know in advance how many ints
or how many strings or whatever you
actually want.
So it turns out there's
a third context here
that has no number inside
of the square brackets.
When you specify, as I have here,
the name of something like argv,
which is just a fancy way of
saying argument vector, which
is another fancy way of
saying an array of arguments,
open bracket close bracket just
means that you don't necessarily
know in advance how big
the array is going to be,
but you know it's going to be an array.
So if you don't know the
number don't put it in there,
for open bracket close bracket
means that argv is not a string,
but an array of strings.
So syntactically, if you
think back last week,
it's very similar to saying
something like int ages open bracket,
and then something thereafter.
So what does this look like?
Let's actually draw a picture.
So when you run this program with Main
having two arguments defined inside
of those parentheses, you
essentially have at least two chunks
of memory handed to you
underneath the hood.
One, as I'll draws as this rectangle,
is going to be called argc.
And just as a quick recap,
what is the data type of argc?
So it's an int.
So a number is going
to go in argc-- turns
out that stands for argument count.
Meanwhile, I've drawn argv as an array.
And I don't really know
how long it's going to be,
so for today's purposes dot dot dot.
It might get of some length.
But I've pictured here
at least four rectangles.
So argv a chunk of memory that stores
string string string dot dot dot,
and argc is just one chunk
of memory for an integer.
>> So now, let's be a little more precise.
If, when I have strings
in this array, called
argv, I want to get at them
individually, just like last week,
we're going to use notation
like argv bracket 0
to get the first thing an array.
Argv bracket 1 to get the
second thing, and so forth.
The key here being we're still 0
indexed-- we're still counting from 0.
So now let's actually
put something in this.
If I were to compile a program called
hello from a file called hello dot c,
and then I run that program
with dot slash hello,
what does my computer, my laptop,
look like underneath the hood
the moment I run dot
slash hello and hit Enter?
Well, this is perhaps
what we could describe
as the content of your computer's
memory, or RAM-- Random Access Memory.
In other words, the computer,
somehow for you magically,
puts the number 1 in argc, AKA argcount,
and it puts literally the string
./hello in argv bracket 0.
I have no idea, frankly, what's
in argv bracket 1 or 2 or 3,
because if the user has not
typed anything besides ./hello,
we're going to assume that these
are most likely garbage values,
so to speak.
Those chunks of memory
exist, but it's not up to us
to look at them, because
the argcount is only one.
>> Now, meanwhile, if I
write run another program,
cd, which is more properly a command,
in your blinking prompt-- cd space
Dropbox-- when I run that, effectively,
when the cd program is run, argc,
inside of my computer's memory, is for
the most briefest second the number 2.
And then argv bracket o has
cd, argv bracket 1 has Dropbox,
and then of course the command
completes, so all of this memory
essentially goes away and
is used for something else.
And that's why I say
just a split second.
>> Meanwhile, if we do mkdir pset2,
the picture looks almost the same,
but with different strings inside argv.
If I do clang dash hello
hello dot c, same idea.
More stuff is filled in for
argv, and argc, of course, is 4.
So in other words,
even though this array
might be dot dot dot, of some
variable length, so to speak,
you always know where the end of it
is, because argc is going to tell you
at what point you have to stop
looking at elements in argv.
You can only look at four
in total in this case.
>> So let's now take a look at,
perhaps, a simple program.
One that just says hello
to someone like Zamyla.
So I claim I'm going to write a program
in just a moment via which I could do
./hello space Zamyla, and then I want
my program to print out something
super-simple like "hello, Zamyla."
Now in the past we've used getstring.
So in the past, even if
you're new to programming,
odds are you could whip up a
program that uses getstring
and then uses printf
to say hi to Zamyla.
But let's not use getstring this time.
Let me instead go into the Appliant
and do include standard I O dot h.
Let me also include CS50 dot h.
Now int main, and now I'm
not going to do void today.
Instead, I'm going to do int argc
string argv open bracket close bracket,
not specifying a number.
And now here is my so-called to do.
What I'm going to do now is, I'm
going to do a bit of a leap of faith,
I'm going to assume that the user's
going to use this program correctly,
and I'm simply going to
do printf hello, %sn.
So nothing new there.
But I want to now put whatever word the
user types after the program's name.
So if I do ./hello space Zamyla, I
want to somehow programmatically access
quote unquote "Zamyla." so I
can go into my argument vector,
my array of strings, and if the command,
again, was ./hello space Zamyla,
what number do I want
to put in argv here?
AUDIENCE: 1.
DAVID MALAN: 1, because
bracket 0 turns out
is going to be the
program's name, as we saw.
So bracket 1 is the first word
that I, the user, have typed.
I'm going to go ahead and save this.
I'm going to go into my folder
where I've placed this file.
I'm going to do make hello 3.
Comp IO's OK.
./hello Zamyla Enter.
What did I do wrong?
I was caught by surprise
myself for just a moment there.
What did I do wrong?
>> AUDIENCE: Name.
>> DAVID MALAN: The file's
actually called hello3.c.
And I did that just for
consistency, because we've
had hello.c's in the
past in the online code.
So let's fix this ./hello
bracket dash 3 Zamyla.
Enter.
And now we have hello, Zamyla.
Meanwhile, I can change this to
be Rob, or really any other word.
>> But let's consider a corner case.
What might you expect will happen if
I don't type anyone's name at all?
>> AUDIENCE: Error.
>> DAVID MALAN: An error
of some sort, perhaps.
Let's see.
Enter.
Null.
So printf is actually being
a little protective of us
here, and literally printing open paren
null, but even worse things can happen.
And just to demonstrate
something you absolutely
shouldn't do, let's go in
here and start poking around.
Right?
If I know that the picture in
memory is essentially this,
argv bracket 1 has Zamyla, argv
bracket 0 has ./hello, or ./hello-3.
What is in bracket 2?
So I can answer that
question myself, right?
I can just change the 1 to a 2.
I can now recompile hello 3,
./hello3 Let's zoom in and hit Enter.
Whoops.
No quote mark.
Interesting.
So that's kind of cool to
see what else is in here.
>> So what else is inside of my laptop?
Let's save it with bracket 3.
Make hello3, ./hello-3.
Curious.
And now let's get really bold-- 50.
So that's really diving deep
into my computer's memory.
50 indexes in.
So make hello 3 ./hello-3.
Curious.
All right, now I'm just
going to get reckless.
Let's go to 5,000.
All right.
So let me recompile.
Make hello3, ./hello-3.
OK.
Now some of you, there might
be a light bulb going off.
How many of you have
seen this message before?
OK.
So, why?
>> Odds are-- and there's different
things that can cause this,
and clearly you're in good
company-- we have clearly
caused what's called
a segmentation fault.
And long story short for today, I
have touched a segment of memory
that I shouldn't have.
Where a segment just means a chunk
of memory that I shouldn't have.
Now the computer guarantees that if I
run ./helloZamyla that I can touch argv
be bracket 0 and argv bracket 1.
But argc is value 2, that means I am
only allowed-- it's sort of the honor
system-- to touch
bracket 0 and bracket 1.
If I go any farther, there's
absolutely going to be memory there.
My RAM exists physically
in the computer.
But who knows what's there?
Indeed, I'm running multiple
programs at one time.
I might have seen-- if I weren't
doing this on the Appliant
but on my Mac or PC-- I might have
seen the contents of an email.
I might have seen an instant
message I've recently sent.
Anything that might be
lingering around in memory
could have been accessed by way of
this arbitrary square bracket notation.
Or, worse yet, you might have
found one of my passwords
that I'd recently typed in, that a
program had stored in memory so as
to authenticate me, and
then just kind of left it
in RAM until I quit that program.
>> And indeed, this is one of
the danger and one the powers
of using a language like C.
You have unfettered access
to the entire contents
of a program's memory,
and what bad guys can
even do in those cases--
especially when we
get to web programming
toward the end of the semester, we'll
revisit this topic-- is poke around,
potentially, someone's computer's
memory and find such curious things
as we saw there.
Or even worse yet, passwords that he
or she can then use to do bad things.
>> So clearly I shouldn't have done this,
because weird things start to happen.
Indeed, this is a program crashing.
This would be the equivalent
of Mac OS or in Windows
a program window just disappearing.
An unexpected error has occurred.
In the command-line environment
we see something like this.
But that's why, is I'm simply touching
memory that doesn't belong to me.
>> So let's defend against this a
little bit in a different way
by looking at this program here.
So, again, the skeleton
that we saw earlier--
and I've highlighted this time int.
And all this time main has
indeed returned a value.
Even though in most of our lecture
examples we've never once used
return anything in main.
We just write printf close
curly brace and that's it.
But for free, what the
compiler been doing for you,
effectively, is returning 0 for you.
Turns out-- and it's a little
counterintuitive-- that 0 is good.
It doesn't mean false per se.
0 is good, and any non-0
value, the world has decided,
can signify an error.
So if you've ever messed
something up on your computer,
or a program has just died on you and
you've gotten some erroneous window
on your screen, saying error
negative 49 or error 23--
some seemingly arbitrary value-- that's
because a programmer has hard-coded
a value like negative 49 or positive
23 to represent any number, dare say,
of 4 billion possible things
that might go wrong in a program.
>> So how might I take
advantage of this myself?
Well, let me open up a program
that I wrote in advance,
and poke around online called hello 4.
And it's almost identical, except that
its got a little bit of error-checking.
In this case, I've again declared
main as taking two arguments,
but this time, on line 17, notice
I'm doing a bit of a sanity check.
I'm making sure that
argc equals equals 2.
Because if it is, that
means I can safely
touch not only bracket 0, but bracket 1.
And I go ahead and print out,
in this case, Zamyla or Rob
or whatever word I typed out.
And now just to get
a little more proper,
I'm going to explicitly return
0 to signify all is well.
Nothing bad happened.
>> But by convention, I'm going to
return 1, or frankly any non-0 value,
if something went wrong.
Now the user is not going to
really notice what's going on.
Indeed if I go into this directory,
we zoom in and do make hello 4,
./hello-4 Zamyla behaves as I expect.
But if I instead don't type
anything, nothing seems to happen,
but it doesn't crash.
And if I instead do something
like Rob is a proctor
in Thayer-- sharing
arbitrary information.
But notice, argv 1, 2, 3, 4, and
5 should now exist in memory.
That, too, is not what
my program expects,
because I've checked whether
argc equals equals 2 or not.
So I'm now defending against this.
>> Now, as an aside, we the
programmer-- or rather we the users--
never see that 0 or 1 but using a
tool called Debugger, or other tools,
as we'll see before
long, you the programmer
can actually see what might be
going wrong inside of your program.
>> So, any questions on argc?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: I've seen where they
haven't had the character, [INAUDIBLE]
just said string star d, like
character asterisk comma.
Are they equivalent here?
>> DAVID MALAN: They are.
So the question is, you have
occasionally seen programs
like this that don't
say string argv bracket
but instead say something
like char star argv bracket.
And there's even other
variants that you might see.
They are indeed equivalent.
For now, we have these
sort of training wheels
on in the form of string in the CS50
library, but in just over a week
or so we're going to remove that
obstruction altogether and actually
look at what the char and the star
are, and how those pertain to memory
representation more generally.
So we'll come back to that.
>> Other questions on our argv or argc?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Why did it return
an error [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID MALAN: Why did it
return an error only-- oh!
In the previous case, when we
were futzing around with memory,
why did it only return an error
when I really typed a big number?
Short answer is, we just got lucky.
Generally speaking, a computer
allocates memory in chunks,
and it gave me a big enough chunk that
I got away, without being noticed,
of touching bracket 2, bracket 3,
bracket 50, but as soon as I pushed
my luck, I went beyond the
boundaries of the chunk of memory
the operating system had given me.
And that's when it
clamped down and said, no.
Segmentation error.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: How does the computer
know the value of argc?
>> DAVID MALAN: How does the
computer know the value of argc?
When you run a program, that program,
by nature of the blinking prompt,
is handed the array of
words that were typed
at the prompt, that was
typed at the prompt.
And so it is your operating
system that essentially
populates main's arguments for you.
So that's one of the services
that you get, sort of secretly
underneath the hood of
an operating system.
Other questions?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: What does core dump mean?
DAVID MALAN: What does core dump mean?
So that's a good question.
And let me go back into
this directory here.
And you'll notice that
I have a new file there.
It's indeed called core, and it's
actually typically a decent-sized file.
That is essentially a snapshot of
the contents of my program's memory
or RAM when it crashed.
And this will be useful,
potentially, diagnostically,
once we talk in a future lecture
and section about debugging,
because you can actually do the
equivalent of a digital autopsy
on that file to help figure out
what you did wrong in your program.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Is argc a command in
itself, or can you name it anything?
>> DAVID MALAN: Good question.
Is argc a command in itself,
or can you name it anything?
It's definitely not a command.
It's simply a variable's
name or an argument's name,
and so absolutely we
could call this foo,
we could call this bar, which tend
to be the go-to words that a computer
scientist goes to.
But by convention, we use argc and argv.
But that's just a human
convention, nothing more.
All right.
So turns out, I've been
telling a bit of a white lie--
and frankly, in the future, you'll see
we've been telling other white lies.
But for now, we're going
to peel back one of these.
In this case here when I previously
ran a program like ./hello or ./hello-3
Zamyla, we had the contents of my
computer's memory looking roughly like
this.
But recall what a string is.
What did we say a week ago what a
string actually is underneath the hood?
AUDIENCE: Array of chars.
DAVID MALAN: It's an
array of chars, right?
So we might have an array of
strings, but, in turn, a string
is an array of characters.
So if I really want to be
anal when I draw this picture,
I should really be drawing
it a little more like this,
whereby in each of these
indexes of my argv array,
there is itself a whole string
that itself is in an array.
And now the white lie
we're telling today
is that the picture doesn't
look quite like this.
In fact, the little squares are
typically outside of the big rectangles
there.
But we'll come back to that before long.
But this is ./hello backslash 0,
that being the special character that
demarcates the end of a string,
and we've got another one after
Zamyla's name.
So what does this mean?
>> Well, let me go ahead and
open up two other examples
that are available online.
One is called argv1.c
and the other is argv2.
It's a super-simple program that
is different from past programs
in that now I'm using
argc and argv up here.
And now I'm integrating with a for loop
in line 18, from i=0 on up to argc.
And what am I going to do
with this line of code here?
In English.
This obviously demonstrates use of argc.
But in English, what does
it do if I run this program?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: It's going to print your
screen as many times as you want.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So whatever words I
type at the prompt, it's
going to regurgitate
them at me one per line.
So let's go ahead and do this.
Let me go into my directory
and do make argv1 ./argv1.
And now, let's keep it simple.
Let's do nothing at first.
It did print out one thing, and
that's indeed the name of the program,
because that's in bracket 0.
If I now say foo, it's going to do
those two, and if I say foo bar,
it's going to say those three things.
Now that's somewhat interesting, maybe.
But recall that argv
is an array of strings,
but a string is an array of chars,
so we can take things up a notch
and apply that basic
logic and make code that
looks a little more cryptic, admittedly.
But by having a nested
loop, something akin
to what you might recall from Mario,
for instance, if you did it this way.
>> So now notice on line 19, I'm
again iterating over my arguments,
from 0 on up to argc.
And now in line 21-- I'm
borrowing a trick from last week--
I am checking what is the
length of argv bracket i.
I'm storing that answer in n.
And then I'm integrating from j on
up to n, where j is initialized to 0.
So, convention for counting.
Once you've used i, if you have a
nested loop, you can't use i again,
otherwise you'll clobber, potentially,
the value outside of the inner loop.
So I'm using j by convention.
We might use k.
If you have more than k, you probably
have too much nesting, typically.
But now, notice my printf
line is slightly different.
I'm not printing %s, I'm
printing %c, which, of course,
is a placeholder for a char.
>> And now notice this syntax.
New.
We haven't seen it before.
But logically, this just means
get the ith string in argv
and get the jth what?
AUDIENCE: Character.
DAVID MALAN: Character in that string.
So by using square brackets
followed by square brackets,
this is diving first
into argv's strings,
and then the second
square brackets with j
is diving into the characters of
that particular string in argv.
And then, just for good measure,
I'm printing a new line here.
So now let me go ahead and open
up a slightly bigger window
so we can see this in action.
Let me go into that folder.
And now do make argv-2--
whoops-- make argv-2, ./argv 2.
Enter.
And it's a little hard
to read vertically,
but that's indeed the name of the
program, followed by a blank line.
Now let me go ahead and do foo.
Similarly hard to read, but it's
indeed printing one character per line.
And if I do bar, it's now
printing those line by line.
So the takeaway here isn't so much
that, wow, look at this neat new trick
where you can get at the contents
of an array's specific characters,
but rather how we're taking these basic
ideas like indexing into an array,
and then indexing into an
array that was in that array,
and just applying the same ideas to
slightly more sophisticated examples.
But the basics really haven't
changed, even since last week.
>> Now this is sort of timely,
in that, recall, in week zero
we played with a phone book like this.
And even though this is obviously
physical pieces of paper,
you can kind of think of
a phone book as an array.
Certainly, if you were to reimplement
this pieces these pieces of paper
in a computer, probably
you would use something
like an array to store all of those
names and numbers from A all the way
through Z. So this is nice, because
it allows us an opportunity,
perhaps, to consider how you might
actually implement something like that.
As with a series of doors here.
So if I could-- we need one
volunteer to come on up.
Let's see.
An unfamiliar face perhaps,
unfamiliar face perhaps.
How about in orange?
Here.
Orange shirt, come on up.
>> Let's go ahead now and move
these doors over to the side,
move these out of the way for a moment.
What's your name?
>> AJAY:
>> DAVID MALAN: Ajay.
David.
Nice to meet you.
All right.
So we have behind these six
doors digitally on the screen--
or, rather, seven doors on the
screen-- a whole bunch of numbers.
And I've told you nothing
in advance-- agreed?
AJAY: Nothing in advance.
DAVID MALAN: All I want you to do
now is to find for me, and for us,
really, the number 50,
one step at a time.
>> AJAY: Number 50?
>> DAVID MALAN: The number 50.
And you can reveal what's
behind each of these doors
simply by touching it with a finger.
Damn it. [LAUGHTER]
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Very well done.
OK.
We have a lovely gift
prize for you here.
Your pick of movies we
discussed last week.
>> AJAY: Oh, man.
Oh, I've never seen Spaceballs.
>> DAVID MALAN: Spaceballs.
All right.
So hold on just one moment.
How-- let's make this
a teachable moment--
how did you go about
finding the number 50?
AJAY: I chose randomly.
DAVID MALAN: So you chose
randomly and got lucky.
AJAY: Yes.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
Excellent.
So now, had you not
gotten lucky, what else
might have happened behind these doors?
So if I go ahead and
reveal these numbers here,
they actually are in random order.
And the best you could have
done, frankly, is by, ultimately,
in the worst case, checking them all.
So you got super-lucky, which
isn't what we'd call an algorithm.
Yes, congrats.
But now let's-- humor me, if you could.
Let's go to this tab here.
And here are the numbers in clearly
what seems to be a random order,
and they were.
But now if I instead claim
that behind these doors
are numbers that are sorted.
The goal now is to also
find us the number 50.
But do it algorithmically, and
tell us how you're going about it.
And if you find it, you keep the movie.
You don't find it, you give it back.
AJAY: So I'm going to check the ends
first, to determine if there's--
[LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE]
DAVID MALAN: Here you go.
Let's take a look at one
of Ajay's predecessors,
Sean, who wasn't quite as lucky.
OK, so your task here,
Sean, is the following.
I have hidden behind these
doors the number seven,
but tucked away in some of these doors
as well are other non-negative numbers.
And your goal is to think of this
top row of numbers as just an array.
We're just a sequence of pieces
of paper with numbers behind them.
And your goal is, only using the top
array here, find me the number seven.
And we are then going to critique
how you go about doing it.
Find us the number seven, please.
No.
5, 19, 13.
It's not a trick question.
1.
At this point your score is not very
good, so you might as well keep going.
3.
Go on.
Frankly, I can't help but wonder
what you're even thinking about.
>> SEAN: I can take from only the top row.
DAVID MALAN: Only the top row.
So you've got three left.
So find me 7.
>> [AUDIENCE  SHOUTS SUGGESTIONS]
So both of those were amazing
for very different reasons.
So this is where we
left off a moment ago,
and the key insight here
was these doors had numbers
behind them that were sorted, the ideal
takeaway for which is that you could do
fundamentally better in
this second example--
and, indeed, that was Sean's
first attempt with random numbers
just as before-- but as soon
as these numbers are sorted,
much like the phone book,
what can you obviously do?
Or how can you leverage that knowledge?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: You go halfway [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Exactly.
So Ajay's initial instinct was
to check the ends, as I recall,
and then we sort of finished
the example quickly.
But if we started to do this more
methodically along those lines,
but starting perhaps in the
middle, because they're sorted,
as soon as we reveal the
number 16, we therefore know--
and let's do exactly that-- we
therefore know that 50, in today's case,
has got to be to the right.
So just like in week zero when
we tore the phone book in half
and threw half of the
problem away, same idea here.
We can throw this half
of the problem away.
And probably what you
might do algorithmically,
once you know that 50 must be
to the right, if it's anywhere,
is try there, in the middle
of the remaining doors.
Of course, 50 is higher
than 42, so we can
throw this remaining
quarter of the problem away,
and, finally, identify
something like 50.
But just as with the
phone book, these numbers
were given to us already in
sorted order, which leaves us
with the question, how do you
get things into sorted order?
And, frankly, at what cost?
It's one thing to be
handed the phone book
and then impress your friends by finding
a phone number really quickly, right?
Tearing 32 pages out to find a
person out of 4 billion pages,
we said was one extreme example.
But how much time did it take
Verizon to sort that phone book?
How much time did it take us
to sort these seven numbers?
That's a question that we've
thus far completely ignored.
>> So let's answer this question now.
And we're all out of movies now,
but we do have some stress balls.
If, say, eight volunteers
wouldn't mind joining us up here?
Let's go ahead and do, how about
the four of you, three of you here?
Get some new faces.
And the four of you there?
And now-- let's not bias here-- and
number eight over here on the end.
Come on up.
All right.
So what we have here for
each of you is a number.
If you'd like to go
ahead, take this number.
What's your name?
>> ARTIE:Artie.
>> DAVID MALAN: Artie, okay.
You're number 1.
>> AMIN: Amin.
DAVID MALAN: Amin.
David.
You're number 2.
And go ahead, as I hand
you the sheets of paper,
line yourselves up in front of the music
stands in the same order as up there.
>> ANDY: Hi, Andy.
>> DAVID MALAN: Andy, it's nice to see you.
Number 3.
>> JACOB: Jacob.
>> DAVID MALAN: Jacob, number 4.
Welcome aboard.
GRANT: Grant.
DAVID MALAN: Grant.
Number 5.
>> ALANNA: Alanna.
>> DAVID MALAN: Alanna, number 6.
>> FRANCES: Frances.
DAVID MALAN: Frances, number 7.
And?
>> RACHEL: Rachel.
>> DAVID MALAN: Rachel, number 8.
All right.
Go ahead and get yourself in this order.
Let me put one remaining
music stand in place.
Where do you need a stand?
OK.
Go ahead and just put your numbers
where the audience can see them on,
the music stand facing outward.
And hopefully, our first
sanity check here-- 4, 2, 6.
Oh-oh.
Wait a minute.
We don't have an 8.
I need to evict you from
the example somehow.
No.
No, that's OK.
Let's see.
We can do this.
Stand by.
There we go.
Correct.
All right.
So, now we have 8, 1, 3 7, 5.
OK.
Excellent.
>> So the question at hand is, at
what cost, and via what method,
can we actually sort these numbers here
so that we can kind of work backwards,
ultimately, and decide-- is it really
impressive, is it really efficient,
that I can divide and
conquer a phone book?
Is it really efficient that
I can divide and conquer
those digital pieces
of paper on the board,
if maybe it's going to cost us a
fortune in time or energy or CPU cycles
to actually get our data
into some sorted order?
So let's ask that question.
>> So first off, these numbers are
in pretty much random order,
and I'm going to propose
one algorithm, or process
by which we can sort these folks.
I'm going to approach
this pretty naively.
And I'm going to recognize
that it's kind of a lot for me
to wrap my mind around the
whole data set at once.
But you know what?
I'm going to make some
very simple marginal fixes.
4 and 2 are out of order, if the
goal is to go from 1 on up to 8.
So you know what?
I'm going to have you
guys swap, if you switch
physically positions and
your pieces of paper.
Now 4 and 6, these are in order.
I'm going to leave those be.
6 and 8, those are in order.
Going to leave them be.
8 and1, out of order.
If you two wouldn't mind swapping.
Now 8 and 3, if you guys could swap.
8 and 7, if you guys could swap.
And 8 and 5, if you guys could swap.
>> Now, am I done?
No, obviously not.
But I have made the
situation better, right?
What was your name again, number 8?
>> RACHEL: Rachel.
DAVID MALAN: So Rachel has
effectively bubbled up pretty far,
all the way to the end of
my array of numbers here.
And so that problem is kind of solved.
Now, clearly, 2 still needs to
move a bit, and 4 and 6 and 1.
But I seem to have gotten a
little closer to the solution.
So let's apply this same
naive heuristic again.
2 and 4, OK.
4 and 6, OK.
6 and 1, mm-mm.
Let's swap.
6 and 3, mm-mm.
6 and 7 is OK.
7 and 5, nope.
Let's swap.
And now 7 and 8.
And what's your name again?
FRANCES: Frances.
DAVID MALAN: Frances.
So now Frances is in even a better
position, because now 7 and 8
are correctly bubbled up to the top.
So 2 and 4, OK.
4 and 1, let's swap.
4 and 3, let's swap.
4 and 6, you're OK.
6 and 5, let's swap.
And now those guys are good.
We're almost there.
2 and 1, out of order, so swap.
And now let me do a sanity check.
2 and 3, 3 and 4, 4 and
5, 5 and 6, 6 and 7, 8.
OK, so we're done.
>> But at what cost did I
sort these numbers here?
Well, how many steps did I potentially
take when sorting these folks?
Well, we'll come back to that question.
But, frankly, if you got
a little bored, that's
kind of revealing in that this wasn't
maybe the most efficient algorithm.
And indeed, frankly, I'm sweating
all the more walking back and forth.
That didn't feel particularly efficient.
So let's try something else.
If you guys could reset
yourselves to these eight values.
Good job.
>> Let's take a look digitally, for just
a moment before we try something else,
at what just happened.
Up here, you're about to see a
visualization of these eight humans
whereby blue and red
bars represent numbers.
The taller the bar,
the bigger the number.
The shorter the bar,
the smaller the number.
And what you're going to see is in
random order more than eight of them.
You're going to see these bars
getting sorted by that same algorithm,
or set of instructions, which
we'll call henceforth bubble sort.
So notice, every second or so,
two bars are lighting up in red,
are being compared by the computer.
And then if the big bar and the
little bar are out of order,
they are being swapped for me.
>> Now this is incredibly tedious
to watch this, certainly,
for very long, but notice the
takeaway-- big bars moving to the right,
little bars moving to the left.
Let's abort this process
and speed this up
to be much faster, so we can
get a high-level sense of what,
indeed, bubble sort is doing.
Indeed, it's bubbling up to the
right hand side of the list,
or the array, the bigger bars.
And conversely, the little bars are
bubbling their way down to the left,
albeit at a faster pace
than we previously did.
So, harder to see with humans,
but visually that's indeed what
was happening.
>> But let's try a fundamentally
different approach now.
Let's try a different
algorithm whereby we have you
guys start in these original
positions, which was this order here.
And let's go ahead now.
And I'm going to do something
even simpler, right?
In retrospect, swapping pairwise again
and again, almost a little clever.
Let's do things even more naively,
where if I want to sort these folks,
let me just keep looking
for the smallest element.
So right now, 4 is the
smallest number I've seen.
I'm going to remember that.
No, 2 is better, and remember that.
1 is even smaller.
3, 7, 5.
OK.
One-- what's your name again?
>> ARTIE: Artie.
>> DAVID MALAN: Artie.
So, Artie, go ahead.
I'm going to pull you out of the line.
If you could come back here.
And I need to make room for him.
We have a decision point here.
How might we make room for Artie here
at the beginning where number 1 belongs?
>> AUDIENCE: Shift.
>> DAVID MALAN: OK, we
could shift everyone.
But propose an optimization.
That feels a little annoying
for me to ask four people
to move all the way down.
What else could I do?
>> AUDIENCE: Switch them.
>> DAVID MALAN: Switch them.
And what's your name again?
>> JACOB: Jacob.
DAVID MALAN: Jacob, move.
Much more efficient just to have
Jacob swap locations with Artie,
as opposed to forcing
all four of these folks,
thank you very much, to
their correct position.
What's nice about Artie now,
he's in his correct position.
Let's do this again.
2, that's the smallest number I've seen.
3, 7, 5.
OK.
2 is definitely the smallest.
Don't have to do any work.
Let's do it again.
6.
Smallest?
8.
Nope.
4?
Ooh.
Let me remember 4.
3.
Let me remember 3.
7, 5.
Smallest number I've
seen on this pass is 3.
If you'd come on out.
Where are we going to put you?
And what's your name?
>> ALANNA: Alanna.
>> DAVID MALAN: Alanna, we're
going to have to evict you.
But that is more efficient,
to just swap two people,
than to have multiple people
actually sidestep over.
Now let's do this again.
I'm going to select 4, so come on out.
And who's going to move?
Number 8, of course.
If I now find number 5, come on out.
Number 8's going to get evicted again.
I'm now going to find number 6 in place.
7 in place.
8 in place.
>> What we just did now is
something called selection sort,
and if we visualize this, it's
going to feel a little different.
Let's go ahead and from this
menu here, this visualization--
let's change this to-- come on, Firefox.
Let's change this to selection sort.
And let's speed it up as before,
and start the visualization now.
And this algorithm has
a different feel to it.
On each iteration, frankly,
it's even more straightforward.
I'm just selecting the smallest element.
Now, frankly, I got a little lucky that
time, in that it sorted super-fast.
The elements were random.
It's not, as we'll eventually
see, fundamentally faster.
But let's see a third and final
approach here as to what's going on.
So let's go ahead and reset you guys
one final time to be in this order here.
>> And now, I'm going to
be a little more clever,
just to round out our algorithms.
I'm going to do this.
I'm going to not go
back and forth so much.
Frankly, I'm tired of
all this traversing.
I'm just going to take what I'm
given at the beginning of the list,
and I'm going to sort
that then and there.
So here we are.
Number 4.
I'm going to insert number
4 into a sorted list.
Done.
I claim now, and just to make this more
clear, this part of my list is sorted.
It's kind of a stupid claim, but indeed
4 is sorted in a list of size one.
Now, I'm going to take on number 2.
Number 2 I'm now going to
insert into the right place.
So where does 2 belong?
Obviously, over here.
So go ahead and move back, if you could.
And why don't you guys just take
your music stands with you this time.
And let's forcibly insert you
into the beginning of the list.
So a little more work.
I had to move Jacob around,
and what's your name?
>> AMIN: Amin.
>> DAVID MALAN: Amin.
But at least I didn't go back and forth.
I'm just taking things as I go.
I'm just inserting them
in the right place.
6, this is actually pretty easy.
Let's insert you over there, if you
just wanted to move over slightly.
Number 8, also pretty easy.
Right over there.
Damn it.
Number 1 we can't just
swap with Amin here,
because that's going
to mess up the order.
So we have to be a little more clever.
So, Artie, if you could
back up for a moment.
Let's go ahead and shift now,
unlike our previous algorithms,
to make room for Artie
right here at the beginning.
So at the end of the day, I'm kind of
doing what I wanted to avoid before.
And so my algorithm is sort
of reversed, intellectually,
from what it originally was.
I'm just doing the shifting
at a different point.
Now I'm at 3.
Oh, damn.
We have to do more work again.
So let's push you out.
Let's move 8, 6, 4-- oh oh-- and
3 is going to go right there.
So at least slight savings this time.
7, not too much work to be done.
So if you want to pop
back, let's insert you.
And lastly, 5, if you
want to pop back, we
need to shift you, you,
you, until five is in place.
>> So now to see this at a
high level graphically,
let's do this algorithm
visualization one additional time.
So this we shall call insertion sort.
We'll run it just as
fast, and start it here.
And it, too, has a different feel.
It's sort of getting better and
better, but it's never perfect
until I go in and smooth in those gaps.
Because, again, I'm only taking what
I'm being given from left to right.
So I didn't get so lucky
that everything was perfect.
That's why we had these little
mispositions that we fixed over time.
>> So all of these algorithms seem to
run at slightly different paces.
In fact, which would you say is
the best or the fastest so far?
Bubble sort, the first?
Selection sort, the second?
Insertion sort, the third?
I hear some selection sorts.
Other thoughts?
>> So it turns out that
all of these algorithms
are fundamentally just as efficient as
each other-- or, conversely, just as
inefficient as each other,
because we can do fundamentally
better than all three
of these algorithms.
And that's a bit of a white lie, too.
when I say as efficient
or as inefficient,
that's at least for
super-large values of n.
When we have just eight people here,
or maybe 50 or so bars on the screen,
you'll absolutely notice differences
among these three algorithms.
But as n, the number of people,
or the number of numbers,
or the number of people in the phone
book, or the number of web pages
in Google's database
gets bigger and bigger,
we'll see that all three of these
algorithms are actually pretty poor.
And we can do fundamentally
better than that.
>> Let's take a look, finally,
at what these algorithms might
sound like in the
context of a few others
as well by way of this
visualization here
that will introduce us to
a number of algorithms.
Let's go ahead and congratulate
our participants here, all of whom
sorted themselves very well.
If you'd like to take a parting gift.
You can keep your numbers as well.
And what you'll see,
or rather hear, now,
is that as we put sounds
to each of these bars
and associate it with the software,
different frequency of sound,
you can wrap your mind more audioly
around what each of these things
look like.
The first of which is insertion sort
>> [TONES]
>> This is bubble sort.
>> Selection sort.
>> [TONES]
>> Something called merge sort.
>> Gnome sort.
>> [TONES]
>> That's it for CS50.
We will see you on Wednesday.
>> NARRATOR: And now, "Deep
Thoughts," by Daven Farnham.
Why is it a for loop?
Why not make it better?
I'd make a five loop.
>> [LAUGHTER]