>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: This is CS50.
And this is the start of week three.
So we've got a lot of exciting
things to cover today.
A lot of opportunities for
volunteers up on stage.
And ultimately, today is
not about code at all.
But it's about ideas, and
it's about algorithms,
and actually bringing back some of
the lessons learned from week zero,
wherein recall, we
introduced this monstrosity.
And borrowing inspiration
from that, to start
to solve ever more sophisticated
problems algorithmically.
But first, a couple of announcements.
So one, if you would like to join
CS50's staff and classmates at lunch
this Friday, both here and in
Cambridge, and in New Haven,
please visit the course's
website, where a URL can be found.
Lecture this Wednesday will
not be here in Sanders.
It will be online only, so
tune in at CS50's website,
whether here in Cambridge
or New Haven as well.
>> And then problem set two
is already in your hands.
If you haven't dived in yet, allow me
to offer the strongly worded suggestion
that, especially now, as
the problem sets advance,
you really do want to start now, if not
dabble a bit on the weekend or prior
when they first go out on
Fridays, because you'll
find that they're not necessarily
getting longer or more challenging per
se.
I think you'll find that, in
general, they tend to take roughly
around same amount of time.
But it certainly depends
on the student, and it
depends on the mindset
with which you approach it.
But invariably, you're going
to run up against some wall,
and you're going to hit
some bug, and you're just
not going to be able to
get over it at some point.
And it's hugely valuable to be able
to step away, come back the next day,
go to office hours, post on CS50 Discuss
or the like, to actually get unblocked.
So keep that in mind.
Starting earliest as possible
is the best thing you can do.
So here's where we started
the class, over in week zero.
And can we get a volunteer
here to help me find mics?
OK.
Standing up already.
Come on up.
Guess that's how it's going to work.
What's your name?
ALAN ESTRADA: Alan Estrada.
DAVID J. MALAN: Alan Estrada.
Come on up.
Nice to meet you.
ALAN ESTRADA: Nice to meet you.
DAVID J. MALAN: And you were here
with us in week zero, of course.
ALAN ESTRADA: I was.
I was.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So could you go
ahead and find for us Mike Smith,
as fast as you can?
As fast as you can.
Literally tearing the problem
in half as you need to.
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Um.
DAVID J. MALAN: Literally
tearing the problem in half.
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Oh.
Mm.
Very good.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Good.
Thank you.
ALAN ESTRADA: Very good.
OK.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And so now,
you've whittled it down
to half the size of the problem.
Now, we're down to a quarter.
Are you paying attention to
which side we're keeping?
>> [LAUGHING]
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Yes, I think--
>> DAVID J. MALAN: What section are we in?
ALAN ESTRADA: Mufflers, so.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
But Mike Smith is going
to be after Mufflers.
So--
>> [LAUGHING]
>> All right.
ALAN ESTRADA: Where are we looking?
DAVID J. MALAN: Mike Smith.
ALAN ESTRADA: Mike Smith.
DAVID J. MALAN: Now, we're in surgical.
Now, physicians.
Now--
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Let's- let's go with real.
Real.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Real.
OK.
If you need Real.
Now, which way is Mike Smith?
>> ALAN ESTRADA: This way.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Which way?
ALAN ESTRADA: Wait.
M is-- right?
We started with--
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
They're left.
Your right.
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Yeah.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So Mike's in here.
ALAN ESTRADA: What?
>> [LAUGHING]
>> Bad example, guys.
Sorry.
DAVID J. MALAN: This will teach
you to leap out of your chair.
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Oh.
Oh.
I got you.
This is-- OK, I got you.
Smith right here?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Smith, thank you.
So I'll keep looking up Smith?
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Oh, yeah.
No, no, no.
Oh, no.
This is mine.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, you got Smith.
OK.
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Yeah, I
got Smith right here.
Sorry, guys.
I thought Michael-- we
were looking for Michael.
Sorry.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It's OK.
All right, now we're
into Paccini and Sons.
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Paccini and sons.
DAVID J. MALAN: Only you
and I are in on this.
OK.
Find us Mike Smith.
Smith.
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Smith.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Smith.
We're in R for rubbish.
ALAN ESTRADA: Rubbish.
Oh.
This is going to take a while.
>> [LAUGHING]
DAVID J. MALAN: Shoes.
We're in shoes.
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Now we're gonna--
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
ALAN ESTRADA: Which--
[LAUGHING]
Oh, this is great.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It's OK.
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Oh, this is good.
I don't think I'm going to
have PSAT buddies after this.
DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
Sporting.
ALAN ESTRADA: Sporting.
Um, L, M, N, O, P.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
So let's tear this in half.
It's OK.
This ends poorly anyway, because Mike
Smith won't be in the yellow pages.
>> ALAN ESTRADA: Aw.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: No, it's OK.
But let's pretend like
he's on this page.
So now, you've whittled the problem down
to one page, and we found Mike Smith.
>> [CHEERING]
OK, thank you.
OK.
That was extraordinary.
But it was still faster
than linear search,
wherein we start at the
beginning of the book,
and we move our way from left to right,
eventually looking for Mike Smith.
And so, if the phone book
had maybe 1,000 pages,
maybe it would have taken
us 10 or so page tears.
>> But you may have leveraged
touched an assumption
during all of that, which is to say
that the phone book in advance was what?
AUDIENCE: Sorted.
DAVID J. MALAN: It's sorted.
Right?
It's sorted alphabetically, so
that all of those names and numbers
are sorted from the A's to the
Z's, and alphabetically in between.
But today, we now ask
the question, well,
how did Verizon or the phone
company get it into that state?
>> Because it's one thing to leverage
that assumption, and therefore,
solve a problem with an
algorithm more efficiently.
But we never really
asked in week zero, well,
how much did it cost
Verizon or someone else
to get that phone book in sorted order?
>> Right?
It doesn't matter if
looking up Mike Smith
is super fast, if it takes you a
year to sort the pages initially.
Right?
You might as well just sift
through a randomized phone book,
if it's going to be super
expensive to sort it.
So if we can have another volunteer.
Let's take a look up here at
how we might-- come on up-- how
we might go about sorting these.
>> And if Jordan could actually
join us up here on stage.
Come on up for just a moment.
What's your name?
CAROLINE: Caroline.
DAVID J. MALAN: Caroline, come on up.
And you'll be joined
by me and Jordan here.
Caroline, thank you.
All right.
So what we have here for
Caroline is 26 blue books
that FAS uses to administer
certain final exams.
These are getting hard to find,
but what we've done in advance
is that we've put someone's name
on the front of each of these,
but we've kept it simple by
then putting out full names.
So we would put the person with the name
L, D, J, B, all the way A through Z,
but they're in random order.
And so if you would, talking your
way through the problem as you
do it, can you go ahead and
sort these for us, from A to Z.
>> AUDIENCE: OK, so L is like, the middle.
C is beginning.
B. J before L. B, Q.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Hold that
thought for one second.
Because otherwise, this is only
interesting to you, me, and Jordan.
There we go.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
R.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
What are you doing?
>> CAROLINE: M comes after O.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
>> CAROLINE: O.
DAVID J. MALAN: O, Good.
>> CAROLINE: E.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: E, F. Yeah.
>> CAROLINE: T, U, V.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: V, T, U, V. So it
looks like you're making-- keep going.
It looks like you're making
a big pile over here,
and kind of a big pile over there.
So the first half of the alphabet,
second half of the alphabet.
OK.
Good.
Kind of splitting the problem in two.
M, N, X. Yeah.
CAROLINE: K.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
K. So you're kind of selecting
them one after another,
putting it either left or right,
or Z's going on the floor.
OK.
>> CAROLINE: Z's going on the floor.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Y is going on the floor.
Now we can put X.
>> CAROLINE: G.
DAVID J. MALAN: G's going left.
S is going right.
All right, A is going all the way left.
>> CAROLINE: A, B, C, D.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Now, good.
We've got A, B, C. W's going down there.
All right, T.
>> CAROLINE: H, I , J.
DAVID J. MALAN: H, I, J. Good.
CAROLINE: In the center, I'm gonna--
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
So now, we're going to kind
of merge these various piles.
So A through C, then I see D, and
E, and F, and G, and H, and I. Nice.
J, K. And then, this pile is
upside down, but that's OK.
Sure.
We can cut some corners.
OK.
And then we need W, X, Y, Z.
>> CAROLINE: Yeah.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Excellent.
So a big thank you to
Caroline for sorting these.
>> [CHEERING]
>> Thank you.
Thank you very much.
So now let's consider for a moment
how Caroline went about doing that,
and what exactly we
were able to-- how we
were able to solve that
problem when we were just
given a whole bunch of random inputs.
>> Well, it looks like there
was a bit of a system there?
Right.
So the earlier letters
in the alphabet, she
was putting to the left, and the
later letters in the alphabet,
she was putting into the right.
And as soon as she found
some proximal letters, ones
that go right next to each other,
she would put those in order.
And so we kind of had these small
piles of sorted inputs occurring.
>> And so that's quite like what
most of us humans would do.
We would sort of sift through it,
and we'd kind of have a mechanism.
But it might be hard to write
it down in a formula per se.
It felt a little more organic than that.
So let's see if we can now bound
the problem with fewer inputs.
>> Instead of 26, let's
do something far fewer
with just say, seven, behind
these doors, so to speak.
Are there just seven numbers?
And if the goal now at
hand is to find a value,
let's see how efficiently
we can go about doing this.
And let's see if we can now
start to apply some numbers,
or some formulas with which to describe
the efficiency of our phone book
algorithm, our exam book algorithm, and
more generally, finding information.
>> So for this, let me go ahead, and
on the touch screen over here,
put up a web browser that has
exactly these seven doors.
And if we could get one other
volunteer to come on over here,
I've put these same doors over here.
Quick volunteer.
>> This one-- demos are going
to a quicker and quicker now.
Come on down.
What's your name?
TREVOR: Trevor.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Trevor?
All right, Trevor, come on down.
So Trevor has volunteered here to
do a similar problem, but one that's
narrower in scope, and that's going
to allow us to try to formalize now
the process for sorting these numbers.
>> So Trevor, nice to meet you.
So here is an array, so to
speak, a list of seven doors.
Go ahead and find us the number 50.
And then after the fact,
tell us how you found it.
Should be-- all right.
Yeah, this is the one here?
Uh-oh.
OK.
You clicked that one.
Good.
>> And good.
Now you clicked that one.
And let me give you the microphone,
so that you have it in just a moment.
Go ahead and click the
next door that you intend.
Yes, good.
TREVOR: Can I unclick a door?
DAVID J. MALAN: No, you can't unclick.
TREVOR: OK.
This one.
DAVID J. MALAN: Where do you want to go?
Which one?
>> TREVOR: That one.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: No.
>> TREVOR: OK.
This one.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yes.
That was good.
All right.
So what was your algorithm or
procedure for doing this, Trevor?
>> TREVOR: I just went through
doors until I found a 50.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Excellent algorithm.
So that's fine.
Because in fact, if I reveal what's
behind these two other doors, what
we'll find here is that
we only have random input.
So that was actually as
good as you could get.
And in fact, you got better than
exhaustively searching the whole array,
because it would have been really
unlucky if you had hit the number
50 at the very last door.
But what if we instead
gave you an assumption.
Suppose I sort all of
these doors around,
so that you have the
numbers sorted this time,
but this time it's actually
a different-- this time,
it's actually sorted for you.
And now the goal at hand
is to hit the number 50.
>> TREVOR: OK.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: What's
your algorithm going to be?
>> TREVOR: Well, if it's
sorted, it's either going
to be-- if biggest to largest,
descending, it'll be the first one,
or if it's the opposite,
it will be the last one.
So I'll just tap this door, and
then just tap the last door.
DAVID J. MALAN: Excellent.
All right.
So we found the number 50.
So as soon as you knew
they were sorted, we
were able to leverage this assumption.
So they're too much like
the phone book example.
As soon as you have, even with
a small problem like this,
your inputs pre-sorted, we can
actually find the value arguably
more efficiently.
>> And I didn't tell you if it was
sorted small to big, or big to small,
and so it was very reasonable
to start at one end or the other
to actually find that target value.
So thank to Trevor as well.
And I'll propose-- nicely done.
We have a little clip, actually, that
is among our favorite moments in CS50,
whereby sometimes these demos
don't quite go according to plan.
And indeed right now, I
pulled up the wrong interface
with which to use the touch screen.
So that was my fault there.
>> So this will make for
next year's clip as
to why I was clicking on my own screen.
But let's take a quick look
at what happened last year
with Jay, who came up, much
like Trevor here, volunteered,
and in this short clip, you'll see
how this same demo didn't quite
reveal the same lessons learned.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-All I want you to do now is
to find for me, and for us,
really, the number 50
one step at a time.
>> -The number 50?
>> -The number 50.
And you can reveal what's
behind each of these doors
simply by touching it with a finger.
Damn it.
>> [LAUGHING]
>> [END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: So that went very well.
Those were the unsorted doors.
And Jay, of course,
found it all too quickly.
Trevor did a much better job
in terms of a teachable moment,
so to speak, this year in
taking longer to find it.
Of course, then we gave
Jay a second chance,
whereby we sorted the doors,
just as we did for Trevor,
and Trevor did super well this time.
But Jay did it half as quickly.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-The goal now is to also
find us the number 50,
but do it algorithmically, and
tell us how you're going about it.
>> -OK.
>> -And if you find it, you keep the movie.
If you don't find it, you give it back.
>> -Man.
>> -Oh!
>> -[INAUDIBLE] OK.
So I'm going to check the ends
first to determine if there's-- Oh.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> [END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
So sorting doors clearly
leads to greater efficiency.
And so, twice as fast
is what I meant there.
And so Jay got lucky both times.
And he also got lucky in that last
year, I ordered some Blu-ray discs
to actually give out.
I'm sorry this year, we
didn't have the same, Trevor.
But better still was a few years back.
And some of you might know this
fellow, Sean, who when he was in CS50,
was challenged with the exact
same problem, albeit in SD,
as you'll soon see, back in the day.
And you'll find that not only did
he take a little longer than Jay,
a little longer than Trevor, it was
actually this wonderful opportunity
to engage almost everyone in the
crowd a la Price is Right, encouraging
him to find the number we were seeking.
Let's. take a quick look.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -OK.
So your task here,
Sean, is the following.
I have hidden behind these
doors the number seven.
But tucked away in some of these doors
as well are other negative numbers.
And your goal is to think
of this top row of numbers
as just an array, or just
sequence of pieces of paper
with numbers behind them.
And your goal is, only using the top
array here, find me the number seven.
And we are then going to critique
how you go about doing it.
-All right.
-Find us the number seven, please.
No.
Five, 19, 13.
>> [LAUGHING]
>> It's not a trick question.
One.
>> [LAUGHING]
At this point, your score is not very
good, so you might as well keep going.
Three.
>> [LAUGHING]
>> Go on.
Frankly, I can't help but wonder
what you're even thinking about, so--
>> [LAUGHING]
Only the top row, so
you've got three left.
So find me seven.
>> [LAUGHING]
17.
Seven.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> All right.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So we could
watch these all day long.
And of course, some of
this year's demos perhaps
will now end up in next
year's video as well.
So now let's actually
focus on the algorithms
here, and see if we can't
now start to formalize
how we can go about getting our data
into this state that it's sorted,
so that ultimately, we can actually
search it more efficiently.
And even though we're going
to use fairly small data sets,
like the eight numbers we
have here on the board,
ultimately these same ideas could apply
to 1,000 inputs, a million inputs,
4 billion inputs, because the algorithms
are going to be fundamentally the same.
>> And so this is our last
opportunity for volunteers today,
but perhaps the most involved one,
for which we need eight volunteers
to come up and walk us through the
process of sorting what will soon
be on these music stands here.
Let me start back here.
>> So one in the turquoise-- green is it?
Are you committing?
Two.
Come on down.
OK.
Three.
Four.
Let me-- OK, five.
You're being nominated by your friend.
Six, seven, and eight.
Come on up.
All right.
Thank you so much.
Come on up.
>> All right.
So what we have here-- and this
is among the more awkward ones,
since this will require that you humor
me for just a little bit of time.
You shall be number one.
What's your name?
>> ANNAN: Annan.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Annan.
David.
What's your name?
>> JOSEPH: Joseph.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Joseph,
you are number two.
>> SERENA: Serena, number three.
Stefan, number four.
CYNTHIA: Cynthia.
DAVID J. MALAN: Cynthia, number five.
[INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: [INAUDIBLE].
David, number six.
MATT: Matt.
DAVID J. MALAN: Matt's number seven.
And?
>> WAVERLY: Waverly.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Waverly, number eight.
All right.
If you could-- whoops.
If you all, as your
first challenge, there
are eight music stands
here facing the audience.
If you could put your numbers on
these music stands in such a way
that they line up with the
same numbers on the board.
So make yourselves look like that by
putting your numbers on these music
stands here.
Excellent so far.
>> Excellent.
OK.
So now, we're going to ask the
question in a few different ways.
How can we go about sorting
these folks up here?
Because we had a few approaches
earlier, whereby we were
kind of making two different buckets.
And then we were generally
piecing things together.
As soon as we saw two numbers
that belonged together,
we put them together.
Two letters that belong together.
>> But let's see if we
can't formalize this,
so that we ultimately have
some pseudo-code you will,
with which you can solve these problems.
So now, I'm looking out
at these numbers here.
And I see a whole bunch of mistakes.
Ultimately, I want one on the
left and eight on the right.
>> And so I'm looking at
these two, four and two.
And what's the problem, obviously?
Yeah.
So.
Two obviously comes before
four, so you know what?
Let me first take a greedy approach,
if you will, much like problem
set one-- if you recall from the
Standard Edition of Problem Set One,
where I just locally solve the problem
that's right here in front of me
and see where it leads me.
>> OK.
So two and four, let me go
ahead and just swap you two.
If you can physically move
yourselves and your paper,
I seem to have gotten the
list in a better state.
>> Now, they're good.
I'm going to move on,
four and six, looks good.
Not a problem.
Six and eight, OK.
Eight and one, another problem.
Because what's true about eight and one?
One comes before eight,
and so what should we do?
Let's swap these two.
One and eight.
And now, I'm going to keep going.
I'm going to keep looking ahead.
And let's see what happens.
Eight and three, of
course, out of order.
Let's swap.
Eight and seven, of course.
Out of order.
Let's swap.
Eight and five, of course, let's swap.
All right.
List is sorted.
yes?
>> OK, obviously not.
But it is a little better, right?
Because notice what happened.
Each time we performed a swap, a smaller
number kind of percolated that way,
and a bigger number
percolated this way, or we'll
start saying bubbled to the
left or bubbled to the right.
>> Now, it's not enough, because
at best a number might
have moved one spot
forward, or at worst,
a number might have
moved one spot further.
So you know what, this kind
of worked pretty well so far.
Let me just try it again.
Two and four, they're OK.
Four and six, they're OK.
Six and one, out of order.
So let's swap you two.
And now, notice the problem's
starting to get a little better again.
Six and three, out of order.
Let's swap you two.
Six and seven, you're good.
Seven and five, of course, out of order.
Seven and eight, in order.
And now, I might need to
do this a few more times.
And in fact, think for yourselves
perhaps how many times maximally
might I have to walk back and forth?
>> We'll come back to that.
So two and four are still OK.
Four and one, nope.
So, let's swap.
And again, notice visually
one is kind of bubbling
to the left, where it should be.
Four and three swap.
Four and six.
Six and five swap.
Six and seven.
Seven and eight are good.
>> Good.
We're getting even better.
So let's see.
Now, we have two and one.
Of course, swap.
Two and three, three and four, four and
five, six and seven, seven and eight.
Good.
And you know what?
Because I made one change there,
let me do one sanity check.
Let me go all the way
back to the beginning.
OK.
One, two-- yup, see?
Something was wrong.
Three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
And in this last pass, are
you comfortable with my now
claiming it is sorted?
OK.
Visually, that's absolutely true.
But functionally, what
did also just happen
in that last pass that allows you
to confirm that this list is indeed
sorted?
>> What did I do or not do this last pass?
AUDIENCE: There were no changes.
DAVID J. MALAN: Sorry?
AUDIENCE: No changes.
DAVID J. MALAN: There were no changes.
So it would be stupid of me to
do that same algorithm again
if I didn't make any
changes the first time.
And the state has not changed.
Surely, I'm not going to make
any changes the second time.
And so, it's safe now
to say, list is sorted.
>> And indeed, this is now
something that we'll generally
call bubble sort, whereby pairwise,
you correct mistakes again,
and again, and again, and you
keep going back and forth,
and back and forth, until you
make no such swaps, at which point
you can be confident, yeah, I
finished fixing all of the mistakes.
Let's reset and try another approach.
If you guys could go back into
the order you were a moment ago,
which looked like this.
Now, let's take an approach a
little more like the exam book,
whereby we were constantly
selecting the letter of the alphabet
that we kind of wanted
to deal with next.
Maybe it was a high letter,
like A, or a low letter Z.
>> So everyone's back in this order.
And now let me do this.
Let's see I know I have
eight numbers here.
I'm going to go ahead and
just deliberately select
the smallest elements.
Right?
This seems intuitive too.
Why don't I find the smallest
element, put it where it belongs,
then get the next smallest element, put
it where it belongs, and just repeat.
>> Because intuitively,
that should work too.
So four, that's a pretty small number.
I'm going to remember where this is.
Wait a minute.
Two is smaller.
Let me now remember where two
is, and forget about four.
We'll deal with that later.
Six, I'm not interested.
Eight, I'm not interested in.
One is my new small number.
So I'm going to remember where one is.
Three, not interested.
Seven, not interested.
Five, not interested.
>> So without falling off
the stage this year,
I'm going to grab number one--
and what was your name again?
>> ANNAN: Annan.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Annan.
And if you could join me at
the beginning of the list,
let's put you where you belong.
Unfortunately-- what's your name?
>> STEFAN: Stefan.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Stefan is in the way.
So before Stefan solves this
problem, what should we do?
What do we do with Stefan?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
So we could do that.
We could sort of take Stefan and his
four, and just put it in a variable
and hold on to it for
some amount of time,
thereby making room for number one.
And that's not bad.
I could suggest, why don't
we just put Stefan here?
Why might this violate one
of the ideas we started
talking about last time, last week?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID J. MALAN: There's no index for it.
If you think of this, indeed, as an
array, this is like negative one,
so there's no memory actually
here if this is indeed an array,
like we declared last week in lecture.
So we shouldn't do this.
We might store it in a variable.
>> Or you know what?
I heard someone else suggest it.
What else could we do with Stefan?
Why don't we just evict him and
put him over where number one was.
So if you want to go over there.
And indeed, this is a
pretty good solution.
Now on the one hand, I've kind
of made the problem worse.
Four is now farther away
from where it should be.
It should be toward this half.
>> But you know what?
That could have been bad luck.
Maybe number eight was here.
And so, maybe we would
have gotten lucky,
and pushed eight closer to the end.
So in the end of the day,
it kind of all averages out.
We don't need to care about four.
All I care about right now is
selecting the smallest element.
>> And now, what I'm going to
do is forget about number one
permanently, because I know the
list behind me is now sorted.
So my list was previously size eight.
Now, it's of size seven.
So my problem is getting
smaller, albeit linearly.
So now, I'm going to select the
current smallest element, two.
Six, eight, four, three, seven, five.
That was the smallest element.
So what am I going to do with--
what was your name again?
>> JOSEPH: Joseph.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Joseph?
We're going to leave Joseph in place.
Now, I'm going to pretend
that these guys are-- well,
I know that these two
are already sorted.
Let's now focus on the
remainder of the list.
Six is the current smallest.
Eight is bigger.
Four is now the current smallest.
Three is now the current smallest.
And so now, I'm going to select three,
who is-- what's your name again?
SERENA: Serena.
DAVID J. MALAN: Serena, if you could
grab your number and swap with--
KALSANG: Kalsang.
DAVID J. MALAN: Kalsang.
Come on back, and we're
going to swap those two.
And now, let's put this on autopilot.
I'm going to go and leave it to you guys
to select the next smallest elements.
Dun, dun, dun, dun.
Number four, what should you do?
Excellent.
Now, I'm going to make another pass.
Dun, dun, dun, dun.
I see five is the next smallest.
Now, I'm going take another pass.
Dun, dun, dun, dun.
Six is the smallest.
Good.
Seven is the smallest.
No change.
Eight is the smallest.
Done.
>> So what we've just done by iteratively
selecting one element after the other
is implement something that we're
going to formalize as selection sort.
And it's perhaps even
simpler to explain,
in that literally all you
want to do is just keep
going back and forth through the list
selecting, the next smallest element,
until you're done.
>> So it's even simpler, perhaps
intuitively, than last.
Let's try one last one.
If you guys could reset yourselves
into the following positions
one final time, let's see if we can't
now formalize one other approach.
In fact, would someone
out there like to propose
how else we might go about doing this?
Without tossing out buzzwords or sort
of answers that are already known,
just intuitively, what could we do?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So there's some great intuition there.
Good things seem to happen thus far
in computer science when we divide
and conquer the problem of dividing
it in half and half and half.
And so indeed, we
could start to do that.
And in fact, that's going to be, we'll
see, one of our best solutions yet.
But let's come back to that before long.
In fact, we're going to do
that a little later this week.
What else might we do to solve this?
So everyone here is in
seemingly random order.
You know what?
Rather than go back and forth,
back and forth, back and forth
each time, this feels like
I'm doing a lot of walking.
Why don't I just start at
the beginning of the list,
and just put four where it belongs?
So let me assume for the moment that
my list is only this first element.
Is four sorted at this moment in time,
if all I care about is everything here?
This is sort of trivially true, right?
Like the list containing one number, and
that number four is obviously sorted.
>> So let me just stipulate
that this list is sorted.
But now I have the rest of this list.
So now, I encounter two.
Where does two obviously
belong with respect to four?
Before four.
So what can I do here?
What's your name again?
>> JOSEPH: Joseph.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Joseph,
if you could step back
for just a moment with your number.
And now what should Stefan do here?
Let's shift Stefan over here.
And now, let Joseph come in here.
And now, let me claim that
everything here is sorted.
So, similar result, but a
fundamentally different approach.
I haven't even looked what's down there.
I just keep taking the elements
as they're handed to me,
and deal with them.
>> So now, I see number six.
Where does number six belong?
We have two, four, six.
Exactly where she is right now.
So let's leave that alone, and now
claim that this part of the list
is now sorted.
And so, this feels fundamentally
different in that I'm just
moving through the list here
linearly, and I'm never doubling back.
Yes.
All right.
So eight, where do you belong?
Right here.
Perfect.
So now, one.
Uh-oh.
This feels like it's
going to be expensive.
Now, in the previous algorithm,
I just swapped people.
So I might put him all the way at
the beginning, but then moved Joseph.
But if I move Joseph, now
what's going to be wrong?
>> Now, I've sort of undone-- I've
taken one step forward and then
one step back, because now
Joseph would be out of order.
So let's do this.
If you could take number one
and step back for just a moment.
How can we put-- what
was your name again?
>> ANNAN: Annan.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Annan in place?
What needs to happen with respect
to two, four, six, and eight?
They all need to shift.
So if eight would like to shift
first, then six, then four, then two.
And then Annan, if you'd
like to come in here, good.
But here, we've just
kind of paid a price
at a different point in the algorithm.
Whereas last time with selection
sort, and even bubble sort,
I'm walking back and
forth, back and forth,
which is certainly adding up
time-wise, and literally stepwise.
>> Insertion sort, at first
glance, looks like it's
super smarter, in that I'm just
making slow, incremental progress,
but I'm not going this back and forth.
But if someone is indeed
out of order, notice
all of the work I just had to do.
I had to move half of the list
just to make room for number one.
So it's the same amount
of work thus far it
feels, just a different type of work.
>> Let's continue.
So now we know that everyone
between one and eight are sorted.
Here, I have number three.
If you like to pick up
number three, step back one.
And what do you guys need to do?
Yep.
So that's another one, two, three steps.
Three units of time that just cost
me, so that three can now fit.
Finally, seven.
>> Let's go ahead and have
you take a step back.
This is only going to cost us
one unit of time, but that's OK.
And now, five's going to
be a little more expensive.
If you'd like to step back.
We need to move eight,
and seven, and six.
And then everyone is now sorted.
So a big hand to our volunteers here.
Thank you so much.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Thank you all.
Thank you all.
So let's see now just how
costly all of that was.
Let's consider perhaps the
simplest of these, bubble sort.
And I say simplest, only because
you can solve it greedily by just
fix the pairwise problem here.
Fix the pairwise problem
here, again and again
and again, repeating as many
times as you actually need to.
>> So it turns out that
with a bubble sort, well,
how many steps do I have to take on
the first pass of that algorithm?
I might take-- let's see-- one,
two, three, four, five, six, seven.
And there's eight elements here.
So it's like n minus 1 steps to
get from the beginning of the list
to the end of the list.
>> But with selection sort, recall that I'm
selecting the elements again and again
and again that's smallest,
I'm putting it in place,
but then I'm not
looking behind me again.
So I think it's a little more clear
then that the first time, I might
have to take all n minus 1 steps
to find the smallest element.
Then I put them in place, and I
evict whoever was here previously.
>> But then I don't have to
keep looking at this element,
because I know it's
already the smallest.
So now, I can look at just seven
elements, then six elements,
then five elements, then four elements.
And so mathematically, if n is
the number of elements or numbers
that we started with, you can imagine
that this is the same as n minus 1,
plus n minus 2 steps,
plus n minus 3 steps,
plus n minus 4 steps, all the
way down to just one step.
And I'm on my last person.
>> And if you recall that a lot
of stats books or math books
have those formulas on the
hardcover back or front of them,
it turns out that this series
can be expressed more simply
as n times n minus 1 over 2.
And it's fine if that's not
at the forefront of your mind.
But this is indeed true.
That's just a simpler way of writing it.
And then if you think
back to grade school,
when you just start multiplying
things out, this of course,
is just n squared minus n divided by 2.
All I've done is expand
the expressions there.
And so let's rewrite this
a little differently.
That's n squared divided by 2 minus n/2.
>> So again, I'm just kind of applying
some arithmetic rules there.
But notice now that the biggest term
in this expression, so to speak,
is that n squared.
So yes, it's n squared
divided by 2, minus n/2.
>> But generally, if n is
going to be a big value,
I'm going to claim that n squared
is going to be the dominant factor.
It's just going to be
a bigger contributor
to the number of steps than n/2.
So what do I mean by this?
Let's try a simple example, even
though the math gets a little big.
>> So suppose we had 1 million people
on stage, or 1 million things
that we want to sort.
Let's plug a million
into exactly that formula
to see how many steps it takes total
to sort a million elements using say,
selection sort.
>> So we'd have the same formula as before.
I'd plug a million, so that I get
a million squared divided by 2,
minus a million divided by 2.
If I do that math in advance
here, we have 500 billion
minus 500,000, which
gives us 499,999,500,000,
which is pretty darn big.
>> In fact, if you compare now
499 billion, 999 million,
500,000 against our original value,
500 billion, it's so damn close.
Right? n squared divided by 2 gives
us-- or rather, n squared divided by 2
gave us 500 billion.
That's pretty darn close
to 499,999,500,000,
which is to say subtracting off 500,000,
or more generally, subtracting off
n squared, not really a big deal.
The n squared makes these
numbers grow really fast.
>> Now, this is important only insofar
as we, as computer scientists,
are generally not going to care so much
about the nuances of these formulas
and exactly what the
precise answers are.
We care only that, you know what?
At the end of the day, this formula
is on the order of n squared.
>> Yes, we're dividing by 2 in there.
Yes, we're subtracting off n minus 2.
But at the end of the day, the term
that really hurts us and costs us
a lot of steps is that square term.
And so what a computer scientist
is going to generally do
is ignore all of those
smaller order terms,
and just look at the one that
contributes the most to the cost.
>> And this is nice, because we can
now talk in much greater generality
about algorithms, and can compare them.
And the fact that I'm
using this O is deliberate.
When I say on the order
of, I'm specifically
referring to something
called big O. And big O
is a notation that a computer
scientist uses to describe
an upper bound on something.
>> So if you say that an algorithm
is in big O of n squared,
as I proposed just a
moment ago, that means
that in terms of its running
time or its efficiency,
it takes on the order
of n squared steps.
Maybe more, maybe less.
But it's on the order of n squared.
And that's the upper bound.
It's not going to be
more painful than that.
It's not going to be n cubed, or 2
to the n, or something much bigger.
This is an upper bound
on whatever that cost is.
So given that, let's
consider just a few examples.
And this is just a finite list
of very common running times
for algorithms that's meant to be
illustrative of some things we've
seen already.
>> So for instance, in the case of
selection sort, what I'm claiming here
is that selection sort's running
time is on the order of n squared.
In the worst case, I'm going to have
a whole bunch of random numbers here.
And as we saw mathematically,
if I keep walking
through the list, through the
list, selecting the next smallest
element again and again, if I
actually write down all of the steps
I'm taking as I proposed formulaically
before, it's on the order of n squared
steps that I'm taking.
>> And it turns out that bubble
sort and insertion sort
are just as slow in the worst case.
Consider, for instance, insertion sort,
the very last algorithm we dealt with,
which had us look at the element,
and then insert it where it belongs.
And then we looked at the next element,
and inserted it where it belongs.
>> So consider the best possible scenario.
Suppose I had my volunteers line up
literally like this, one through eight,
already sorted.
How many steps is insertion sort
going to take to sort eight people,
if they arrive on stage
looking like this?
>> Eight people already sorted.
And I use insertion sort.
That last of the algorithms.
Well, let's reenact real fast.
So if I start here, I see one.
Where does one belong?
It belongs right here.
I see two.
Where does two belong?
Right here.
I see three.
Where does three belong?
Right here.
>> I see four.
Five, six, seven, eight.
There's no reason to repeat myself.
And so, how many steps
is that in terms of n?
It's on the order of n
steps, right? n minus 1.
But I took a linear number
of steps, and now I'm done.
So that's the best case, though.
What about the worst case?
What eight were over there,
and seven were down there,
and one and two were over here, so
that the list were truly reversed?
>> Well, what happens indeed
if this is the number?
And we'll do just a couple of examples.
What if, indeed, the number eight
is here, and the number-- whoops.
So what if, indeed, the number
eight is all the way over here,
and I'm using insertion sort?
>> OK.
I claim at the moment it's in place.
But now, seven-- where does seven go?
Of course, it goes over here.
So I have to move eight over one place.
Now six, where does it go?
Well, all right.
Now, I have to move eight over
a place, and seven over a place,
and then I plop down six.
>> So the first time, it cost
me one step to fix things,
then it cost me two steps to fix things.
How many steps is it
going to take to fix
things to put five in the right place?
Three.
Because now I have to
move one, two, three.
How many steps is it going to take
to put four in the right place?
4 plus 5, plus 6, plus 7.
>> And so it's mathematically identical to
what we described for selection sort.
We have this series
that's just increasing.
1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4,
or conversely, 7 plus 6
plus 5 plus 4 adds up for today's
purposes to on the order of n squared.
>> So let me stipulate too that
bubble sort is also in n squared.
Because with bubble sort, each
time I go through the list,
I'm taking roughly how many steps?
Each time I literally
walk from there to there?
Roughly n steps.
But how many times might I
need to go through the list?
>> Well, roughly n time.
Maybe n minus 1, but roughly n times.
Well, why is that?
Well, with bubble sort, if
we start with bubble sort,
with the list in the worst possible
situation, which again is completely
backwards, what's going to happen?
I go through the list, and number
one belongs all the way over there.
>> But with bubble sort, how far does one
move on my first pass through the list?
How many spots does he get
closer to the correct place?
Just one.
So if you kind of reason through this,
every time through this algorithm,
David's taking roughly n steps.
But how many passes
through the list is it
going to take for one to bubble
to the left where it belongs?
>> He's got to move like,
n spaces this way.
So just to do the sorting of the list,
I have to walk back and forth n times.
And each time, I'm
looking at n elements.
So do n things n times on
the order of n squared.
>> Now, we'll see in some
of the shorts that
are embedded in CS50's next problem
set, another approach at these,
but for now, let's just consider
some other running times,
especially if the sorting ones take
a little bit of time to sink in.
What's an algorithm we've seen already
that takes on the order of n steps?
>> What should take a linear number
of steps that we've seen thus far?
What's that?
The phone directory search.
The first algorithm.
Right?
Where we're linearly
searching for Mike Smith?
Indeed.
From week zero, when I started
turning one page at a time,
and I even said that it was kind
of a linear feeling algorithm,
and we had that picture on the
board with the straight red line
and the straight yellow
line, those were indeed
algorithms that are in big O of n.
>> Because to find Mike Smith in a phone
book of n pages, in the worst case,
might take me n steps.
What about taking attendance?
One, two, three, four, five, six.
What's the running time of this
algorithm for taking attendance?
Big O of n, because in theory I
have to point everyone in the room.
>> Now as an aside, what about the
other optimization from week zero?
Two, four, six, eight, 10, 12.
A computer scientist would
realize, wait a minute,
that's on the order of
n divided by two steps.
Right?
Because I'm doing two people at a time.
But we're going to ignore
those lower order terms,
and we're just going to
throw away the divide by 2,
and just say, big O of n
for that algorithm as well.
>> What about this one?
We'll skip over some of these, but what
was an algorithm that was log of n?
That took roughly log n steps?
The divide and conquer.
Exactly.
Like the phone book example in
week zero and earlier today,
where we divided the problem
again and again and again.
We drew it on the board in week
zero as a curved green line,
and we said that day it was
a logarithmic algorithm.
>> And indeed, the number of steps it
takes to perform divide and conquer,
or binary search as we'll start
calling it, as in the phone book,
is on the order of log and steps.
And this is a bit of a weird one.
>> What takes one step,
or more specifically
a constant number of steps?
Maybe it's two, maybe it's three,
but a computer scientist just
simplifies it as big O of 1,
some constant number of steps.
What's something you could do that
takes a constant number of steps?
>> What's the running time of clapping?
Constant time.
Right?
Like, what's the running time of
doing anything that takes just one
operation, like print F Hello World.
That might be said to be constant time,
unless less corner case with print F,
what might the running time
of print F actually be?
And why?
What is n measuring in that case?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
The number of characters
we want to print.
So it's very context-sensitive.
Today, we've been focusing a lot on
letters and numbers here on the board.
But it might also be
characters in an actual string.
So it turns out there's another
measure that will start caring about,
and that's the opposite
of big O, so to speak.
>> That's omega notation.
Whereas big O means what's, the
upper bound on your running time?
Maximally, how much time
might something take?
Omega-- sorry this keeps coming
up-- is the opposite of that,
whereby it's a lower bound on the
amount of time something might take.
>> So. for instance, what's an algorithm
that takes always n squared steps?
Well, one of the algorithms we've seen
today, in fact, might be that as well.
Selection sort.
Selection sort's pretty stupid.
Even if the algorithm-- sorry, even
if the array is already sorted,
selection sort is going to
keep walking through the list
to make sure it has the smallest
element again and again and again.
And even though you humans in the
audience know that, wait a minute,
you already passed the
smallest element, the computer
doesn't know that until it looks
all the way through the list.
Similarly, a lower bound that
might also be taken into account
might be linear time.
>> How much time does it take to
sort n elements in the best
case using something like bubble sort?
Suppose your list is already sorted.
We said bubble sort takes on
the order of n squared steps.
But what if it's already sorted?
What if you realize after
one pass through the array
that you've made no swaps?
Do you need to keep making more passes?
>> No.
So a lower bound on bubble sort
might be said to be linear.
Omega of n.
And we can look at
others of these as well.
So let's take a quick look
at just a visualization here
to see how these distinguish themselves.
I'm going to go down here into this
page that's available on C50's website,
but it will be a pain to get working,
since it uses a technology called
Java applets, which is a
largely unsupported these days,
at least by Chrome and certain others.
>> And let me go ahead and speed this
up and explain what's going on.
This is a demonstration of bubble
sort, the first algorithm we looked at.
And it's a visualization in that each
of these bars represents a number.
The bigger the bar,
the bigger the number.
The smaller the bar,
the smaller the number.
And what you can see visually, even
though this is going super fast,
is that the red bar is like me,
walking back and forth fixing problems.
You can see that the bigger elements
are indeed bubbling up to the right,
and the smaller elements
are bubbling up to the left.
And down here, if we
actually look more closely,
we can actually count the
number of comparisons and swaps
that were being made.
>> But instead, let's look
at the second algorithm
we looked at earlier with our
volunteers, selection sort.
Visually, it has a
very different effect.
But it's, again, very intuitive, in
that we keep selecting the next smallest
element, and we got a little lucky.
That felt fundamentally faster.
But if we ran this again and again
and again with lots of inputs,
we would see that it's indeed
still in big O of n squared.
>> Let's do one last one
here, insertion sort,
which was the third algorithm
we looked at, and recall
that this one deals with the
elements as it encounters them,
but then it maybe shifts
things over to make room,
inserting elements where they belong.
>> And this too ends up giving the
final result. Now all three of those
felt pretty fast.
And indeed, I ran them
at a pretty good clip.
But fundamentally, they're all
pretty horrible, to be honest.
All of these algorithms thus far
that run in big O of n squared
take quite a bit of
time to run in the end.
>> And indeed, we can see
and feel this lastly
if I pull up this third and final demo.
This is another
visualization that's going
to show bubble sort on the left,
selection sort in the middle,
and something, as one of our
hand raises earlier suggested,
merge sort on the right.
A divide and conquer
strategy on the right.
And that's, in fact, what we're
going to look at on Wednesday.
But let's time these to run in parallel.
It's roughly the same number of
elements, all running at the same time.
Bubble sort vs selection
sort vs merge sort.
>> Now, they're all running
in theory at the same time.
The CPU is running at
the same speed, but you
can feel how boring this is
very quickly going to become,
and just how fast when
we inject a bit of week
zero's algorithms can
we speed things up.
>> And now let's compare
these in one last form.
I'm going to go ahead
to CS50's website, where
we have this final link for today,
where someone on the internet
kindly put together a video that
captures what different sorting
algorithms sound like.
This is insertion sort.
>> [BEEPING]
>> Whereby you're applying a frequency
based on the height of the bar bar.
This is bubble sort.
>> [WARPED BEEPING]
>> Coming up next is-- coming
up next is-- selection sort,
where again, we're selecting
the next smallest element,
and we can see it growing
from left to right.
>> Merge sort, our winner thus far today.
Notice how it's dividing things
into [INAUDIBLE] half and quarters.
Gnome sort, which we have not
talked about, and creates visually
and audally a bit of a
different shape and sound.
Going back and forth,
cleaning things up.
Also check out heapsort
on this guy's website.
>> And that's it.
We will see you next time.
>> [WHOOSHING AND MUSIC]