>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> SPEAKER 1: This is CS50 and
this is the start of week two.
So, let's dive right into something
that is buggy, so to speak.
So, over here is CS50 IDE and I've
pulled up in advance this screen-- damn
it.
Spoiler alert.
All right.
I've pulled up this screen here,
which has a very simple program.
If we scroll down, most
of this is just comments,
but here in lines 13 through
17 we have a program.
>> It's syntactically valid, which means if
I compile it, it will compile and run,
but it's buggy.
This program claims in the comments
up top that it should print 10 stars,
but it does not.
And based on your experience,
or soon to be experience with C,
can you logically discern
why this is, in fact, buggy?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It goes from zero to 10.
That's 11 iterations.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So, it's going from zero
up through and equal to 10,
which of course is 11 iterations.
So, it's going to
print, indeed, 11 stars.
So, the computer science convention
in most programming languages
is, indeed, just to
start counting at zero,
but count up to but not through the
value that you actually care about.
>> Now, this is one thing that
takes a little getting used to
and even Scratch, designed as it is
for non programmers or non computer
scientists and for children
largely, is designed to have
you start counting generally at one.
And that's fine.
You can absolutely start counting
at one if that's more comfortable.
And count up to and through 10, but
you'll realize particularly this week
and beyond that just so
many things in programming
assume that 0 is the first
digit with which you count,
that you're going to find it easier
just to get into this habit of starting
from zero and counting up to the value
you care about right now from the
get go.
>> So, that has fixed that.
We changed the less than or
equals to just less than.
Let's take a look at
a second example here.
>> So, this program too claims in its
comments up top that it should print
ten stars, but it doesn't.
What's the bug here?
>> So, what-- and sorry, let's be clear.
10 stars.
One per line, but it doesn't.
So, in fact, let me go ahead and compile
this one because it's a little less
clear based on that description.
Let me go into our source directory.
Make buggy one dot slash, buggy one.
OK, I see 11 stars, which
is still problematic,
but they're also all in one line.
What's the issue here?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So this is a subtlety that you may
recall me making brief mention of.
Even though everything looks
pretty, and it's nicely indented,
and it kind of looks Scratch-like
in that line 16 and 17 are,
indeed, indented under that for loop.
That's immaterial.
The computer doesn't
know or see white space.
White space is just for
us humans, stylistically.
The computer does know when you have
curly braces, which would, indeed,
fix this problem.
>> So, if we actually went in and
explicitly put in these curly braces
that would fix this problem by
making clear to the compiler
that I actually want to execute
two lines of code again,
and again, and again.
But what's the fundamental explanation?
Right?
We don't strictly need
curly braces all the time,
even though it's probably best
practice to get into that habit anyway
even though it adds two
characters to your code. why?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
SPEAKER 1: Yeah so that's
another solution altogether.
Right?
Especially if at first glance you don't
really appreciate what's going on.
Well, surely we could
just do two things at once
and just avoid the problem altogether.
And that's fine, but now,
for today's purposes, what
is the explanation for the bug?
Why were all those stars on one line?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: It seems that if
you have one line of code,
you can do it without those.
SPEAKER 1: Exactly.
This is just a human convention.
People realize that it's a
little annoying or tedious
to have to put curly braces all
of the time if all you want to do
is execute one line of code.
So, humans decided some
time ago that that's fine.
If you want to put all of your loop
on just that one line like this,
that's fine with the single
semicolon at the end.
But you can only do one such
line without the curly braces.
>> So, when CS50 style guide
as will point you to,
you'll see that generally
it is good habit
to get into this until you're
quite comfortable straying
from these kinds of conventions
and doing your own thing.
So long as you're self consistent.
And we'll talk more about
style a little bit later today.
>> So, let me open up one other program.
Of course, we should
fix that 10 as well.
Let me go ahead and write a real
quick program that I'll call,
let's say, loop dot C. So, loop dot C.
And in loop dot C I'm going to have,
include standard I/O
dot H int main void.
And now let's just do, indeed, a loop.
So, 4 int I gets zero.
I is less than, say, 50.
I plus, plus.
And then in here let's
go ahead and do print F.
And then I want to print I
and a new line, semicolon.
>> And this should print all the
numbers from zero up to 50?
A few head nods.
A few nos.
What's the bug already?
What's the easy mistake I made?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So even though it looks
like this is what I intend,
recall that I is also
just an ASCII character.
>> So, if I say, print "I."
It's literally going
to print I. So, if I
want to plug-in a placeholder
value I actually need to do this
and then plug-in the
value of I dynamically.
Otherwise I'm just going to
get 50 I's on the screen.
>> So, let me go ahead and
make this loop, run it,
and, indeed, we have all
the way up through 49.
And if I scroll back in time I see
the number zero at the beginning.
>> Well, what if I kind of screw up?
What if I do this?
Just because I'm not thinking.
What's this program.
Once re compiled and run,
going to do logically?
>> AUDIENCE: Nothing.
>> SPEAKER 1: Nothing.
Why is that?
>> AUDIENCE: I is designed for zero.
So, the condition is false.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah, exactly.
All the code is correct, syntactically.
This will compile, this
code will run, but it's not
going to do anything useful
because I initialize I to zero.
We then check, is I greater than 50?
Obviously, no, it's not.
So the loop never executes at all.
>> What if we do something
a little more reckless?
So, what if we do like int I gets zero.
And now let me use the while
loop, which was another condition.
And while I say, while I is greater than
or equal to zero, and then in here I
go ahead and save the file, make loop.
And I'm about to run it.
What am I going to see this
time with a while loop?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: An infinite loop?
>> SPEAKER 1: An infinite loop?
Yes, and why?
AUDIENCE: Because it's always zero.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So, I is initialized as zero.
Of course I is always greater
than or equal to 0 as a result.
So, I'm just going to
see this infinitely.
And now, this has come up once
or twice to the course's heads.
What happens when you
have an infinite loop?
>> AUDIENCE: Control C.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So Control C will eventually respond.
Unfortunately, we've printed out
millions and millions of zeroes already
and so the computer has
kind of got ahead of me.
So, it's going to ignore
me for a little bit.
But if you just hit Control C a few
times on your Mac or PC keyboard,
eventually it should, indeed, terminate.
And if not, we'll show you some
techniques before long where you
can actually forcibly kill programs,
much like in Windows and Mac OS,
if need be.
But let's try something else.
Let's actually increment I. Is
this still going to be infinite?
Let me run this.
And now you can kind of
see what's happening.
This, too, is an infinite loop.
But this is a bit of a trick question.
Is this going to print numbers forever?
>> AUDIENCE: No.
SPEAKER 1: No.
Why?
I heard some nos over here.
Someone-- Yeah.
AUDIENCE: You don't have enough
bits to really keep going.
SPEAKER 1: All right.
So I don't have enough
bits to keep going.
So, what's going to happen?
It's just going to stop?
>> AUDIENCE: At some point
it will shut the--
SPEAKER 1: It will shut
the loop down, but why?
What's going to happen at the
very end of its boundaries?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It will cycle
back to negative numbers.
SPEAKER 1: To negative numbers, or
if we were just treating positive,
zero at least.
So yes, absolutely.
Recall that we saw last time that if you
increment your bits one too many times,
and you there fore overflow
the capacity of your int
or whatever the data type is, you're
going to wrap around, probably,
two negative numbers.
Or if you've specify that your
range should only be positive,
which you can do, but
we've not seen that yet,
you might end up at least back at zero.
Although, actually yes.
In this case, negative
numbers, in which case
the loop is going to terminate
because I is not, in fact,
greater than or equal to
zero if it's negative.
>> So, unfortunately, how
long would we have to wait?
Right now we're up to
what, 2 million-ish?
We are like 2 billion,
we're going to have to wait
until we can actually see this symptom.
But we can see it a little faster,
maybe-- let's see if we can interrupt.
Come on.
Even the menus are appearing slowly.
All right.
So, we'll come back to that before long.
It's a good time-- damn it, puppies.
>> It's a good time for some announcements.
So, if you might like
to engage in YHack,
which is an event being
sponsored by our friends at Yale.
And, indeed, some of the course's
TFs at Yale are involved with this.
YHack is an international
hack-a-thon hosted by and held
at Yale, bringing together 1,500
like minded hackers and creatives all
over the world.
If this is of interest,
take a look here.
If this is too briefly on the
screen, take a look at today's slides
for the URL for yhack.org.
So, also a few quick announcements.
So, officially sections will start
next week both here and New Haven.
Keep in mind you'll be getting an
email later this weekend most likely.
It takes a long time
for CS50 to section,
given all the people in the
class and everyone moving around.
And all the Teaching Fellows'
schedules are also still solidifying,
but stay tuned for an email and if need
be, you can re-section there after.
>> Study.cs50.net.
So, even if you are a constant attendee
at sections, realize that almost all
of the resources we use in sections
are publicly available at CS50
Study at this URL here.
So, if you'd ever like to re review
material from section, or read ahead,
or you can't make it some week,
realize that sample slides,
and problems, and definitions,
and more are all there as well.
>> Office hours resume today,
and tomorrow, and Wednesday,
and Thursday check the course's
website for the schedule.
>> And also, now launching
today is CS50 Discuss.
So, if and when you have questions for
each other or for the course's staff,
and are generally working
on some problem set,
realize that you don't necessarily
have to turn to the human next you.
If there's no one there, you can
reach out to us and classmates
online via CS50 Discuss.
So, this is a discussion
board for the course,
and realize that this
is perhaps the best
place to start when you have
questions when outside of office hours
in particular.
>> Lunches will start up this week too.
At Fire and Ice
[INAUDIBLE] in New Haven.
Take a look at the course's
website in order to RSVP.
First come, first serve for that.
If you don't get in this week
we'll do these most every Friday
during the term.
>> OK, and now a word about grading.
Particularly as we enter problem
set one, which is out this week,
and problem set two and thereafter.
How do we go about evaluating P sets
and evaluating the quality thereof?
So, it's four axes that we use in
CS50, and they're these four here.
>> Scope, which captures on a numeric
basis just how much of the P set
did you tackle.
It's roughly corresponds with
effort, and it's our way of capturing
did you try half the P
set, all of the P set.
This is an easy one to get perfect
scores on if you do, indeed,
try every aspect of the P set.
So, keep that in mind.
>> Correctness is exactly that.
Does your code work as the specification
and as the staffs' sample solution
suggest that your code
should, in fact, work.
Check 50, if you haven't met it
yet, is in P set one specification
and will generally
give you yes/no answers
as to whether your code is correct.
At least so far as we're going
to evaluate it based on the tests
that we run within that program.
>> Design is much more subjective.
This is how well written is your code.
And this is something that
you'll get better at over time,
and it's something that we'll
provide more qualitative feedback on.
And by design I might
mean before long you
might be tempted in some P
set to do something loopingly,
but to have maybe three, or four, or
five nested fore loops or nested while
loops.
That generally should
start to make you cringe
and would generally be
considered bad design.
And you'll start to see in class and
out of class good ways of doing things,
bad ways of doing things that
might all be correct, but not
necessarily well designed.
Like writing an essay.
You might be able to put words on a
page that are grammatically correct,
but the essay or the
thesis they're in is just
completely incoherent or unpersuasive.
And so that might be the analog in the
written world of bad or good design.
>> And style, too, is fairly subjective.
But at least we expect consistency.
This is how pretty is your code.
Are things nicely indented?
Are your variables well named/ Are all
of your parentheses and curly braces
aligned as they should be?
We do have a CS50 style guide as
the problem set will point you at.
Those more comfortable are
welcome to stray from that
so long as you are self consistent.
And this, too, is a lesson
we'll reinforce in section.
So, if all of this was a little
fast, realize the P set and sections
will go into more depth before long.
>> But generally we have
very few buckets for CS50.
Scores are generally on a scale
of one to three, or one to five.
We're literally-- and I can't say
this enough in the first week.
Three is good.
So, even though, yes, three out
of five normally, mathematically,
might be a 60 percent or like a D minus.
Three is, in fact, good.
And, in fact, we expect
most students in the class
to start off the term around
twos, and threes, and fours.
Probably not so many fives.
Not too many ones.
But generally to start in
that sweet spot in the curve
so that as time progresses,
there's actually room for,
and opportunities for upper progression.
So, please do not equate three with 60%.
It's much more abstract than that.
The formula with which we calculate
grades is weighted as follows.
Correctness is worth the most.
Design is worth a little less.
Style is worth a little less.
And this generally
captures the amount of time
that goes into getting each
of these axes just right.
Style is super easy,
should be super quick,
but it's an easy habit
to get lazy about.
Correctness might take
you most of the time.
Chasing down some bug might
take that extra hour or more,
and so, the scoring
ultimately captures that.
And so, now a more serious word.
Since CS50 has the
distinction, for better
or for worse, of being
perhaps better acquainted
with the issues of academic
honesty than most any other course.
And indeed, it is to my knowledge that
we send more students, unfortunately,
for disciplinary purposes
every year as a result. So,
in the interest of full
disclosure, let's talk briefly
about what goes on in CS50, and what you
can do, and what you can be mindful of.
>> So, here since 2007, when
I inherited the course,
is the number of Ad Board cases.
Ad Board is Harvard's disciplinary
body, or now the Honor Counsel,
to which cases are referred when
students do something that the course's
syllabus considers unreasonable.
There's no real pattern
here, I would say.
It fluctuates over the
years but generally
this is the number of
cases that are referred.
The number of students
that are involved?
It too varies.
Typically, last year for
instance, 29 students at Harvard
were Ad Boarded, so to speak.
29 of them current students,
two of them prior students,
who were collaborating
in some untoward way.
And then in terms of the
percentage, it's usually about 3%
of the class that, unfortunately,
makes these kinds of decisions.
>> So, last year it was 3.5%
of CS50's student body
that was Ad Boarded, so to speak.
>> So, what does all of this mean?
And what do we actually do?
>> So, for full disclosure, we
absolutely, as computer scientists,
have software tools at our disposal
and it's very easy for us, in fairness,
that other's classmates who are not
crossing these lines to cross compare
every submission this year against every
submission for the past eight years.
Software does this.
And ultimately it's
human eyes that decide
whether or not to refer some
matter for further adjudication,
but software certainly helps.
And this, frankly, is why that I think
we have such large numbers in CS50.
It's not because CS50
students or CS students more
generally are any less honest
than any other students,
it's just we have the
tools and the techniques
with which to take this first pass.
>> But we do keep an eye
on all of these things
as well, again, in the interests of
recognizing the work that's being put
in by a super majority of the class.
And the course's policy
on academic honesty,
even though it's a bunch of paragraphs
long with a bunch of bullets
that are hopefully quite readable, it
really does boil down to be reasonable.
And the best rule of thumb that
we offer up within the syllabus
is this, the essence
of all work that you
submit to this course must be your own.
And indeed, in almost all of those
cases referred for disciplinary action
it was because of some student late one
night typically turned his or her code
over outright to a classmate,
who then adopted it
in its entirety or
significantly thereof.
>> But really, this is OK.
And indeed, at office
hours, the slips of paper
you've been handed if you came by office
hours last week encourages as much.
You're absolutely
welcomed and encouraged
to discuss problem sets with classmates.
To help each other when stumbling.
But generally the rule of thumb should
be this, "when you are asking for help,
you may show your code to others,
but you may not view theirs."
So, in other words, if I'm
struggling with some P set
and I'm sitting there in the
dining hall, or in the library,
or in the classroom
trying to find some fault,
I can certainly show
my code on my screen
to the person sitting next
to me, certainly the staff,
but also a classmate.
But if the solution that
my classmate offers is, oh,
here just take a look at what
I did, that crosses the line.
>> And I would dare say that's generally
a reasonable thing for most people
to very easily spot the line of.
And so, see the syllabus
for more detail.
And now one of the more
controversial aspects
of CS50 syllabus that I thought I
would speak to in conclusion here
is the so-called regret clause.
So, here's all the fine print.
But in general we have seen
over the past 8 plus years
that, indeed, almost all of CS50's
cases of academic dishonesty
have been the result of just poor
decision making late at night.
The result of stress, the result
of lack of eating, lack of sleep,
too many P sets, too many
deadlines, too many commitments.
Stress building up in a 2:00 AM, 3:00
AM, 4:00 AM, with a deadline looming.
Most students in these cases
have just made bad decisions
that they might very well regret the
next morning if not minutes later,
but until last year there was no
release valve that these students could
actually open up to actually address the
problem head on without fear of being
booted from college altogether.
>> And, indeed, we introduced
this regret clause last year,
which says that if within
72 hours, three days,
of crossing some line
prescribed in the syllabus
you come forward to one of the course's
heads and we'll have a chat about it.
There are still be some
outcome, contrary to what's
been reported to the contrary.
There is still some outcome that
is actionable by the course,
generally zeroing a P set
or taking some other action,
but we will, indeed,
handle it ourselves and not
refer it higher were the outcome
might be much more severe.
And, indeed, to share what happened
last year, in the eight years, and now
nine years, of teaching this course
and after tinkering with various knobs,
turning various dials over the past
several years on academic honesty,
and seeing per the data no apparent
impact, even of speeches like this,
this was hands down the best thing
we've introduced pedagogically
in eight years along
these lines in CS50.
>> 19 students came forward
under this clause last year.
We took no action for
seven of those students,
determining that they were
unnecessarily worried.
They had not, in fact,
crossed a line, but it
was a good chat to have nonetheless.
We zeroed 11 of the scores
that were submitted.
And in one case we asked a
student to do a problem set.
But more compelling,
honestly, with these 19 chats,
which was way more than I
expected to have, each of them
10 minutes to maybe an
hour long, also brought
to light a number of issues regarding
familial issues, friend issues,
mental health issues
that we then engaged,
with the student's blessing, resident
dean, or friends, or any other number
of support resources.
So that this was by far one
of the best uses of our time
and one of the best interventions.
>> With that said, it had no
input on the rate of detection
of academic dishonesty more generally.
And I dare say, this subset
of students last year
was a demographic that we
previously never identified before
and had never connected with before.
And so, these were
wonderful success stories
even though they were brought to light
in less than optimal circumstances.
So, keep this in mind
as you make, perhaps,
some poor decision
yourself late at night,
that there is recourse so long
as the student in that situation
own up and come forward so that we can
have that kind of chat and deal with it
in a way that's educational, and then
we can put it behind us the next day.
>> So without further ado, take the
edge off of this conversation,
the reason the puppies are up is
just to break the ice for a moment.
And unfortunately, they're all sleep,
but what was supposed to happen here
was everyone was supposed
to awe and kind of relax
after that very heavy conversation.
But apparently I put
the puppies to sleep.
But if you go to CS50's
website slash puppies,
you can watch them all day long.
Particularly maybe 2:00, or
3:00, or 4:00 AM at night
to see a little stress relief there.
So that is slash puppies.
All right.
Wasn't that fun?
OK.
So, back to some computer
science, if I may.
>> So, recall that last time we started
looking not just at main, which
was the default function, the when
green flag clicked equivalent,
but we also started briefly
writing some of our own functions.
And thus far none of these functions
have been particularly big or meaty.
You'll get into those larger
functions probably, P set 2, P set 3,
definitely P set 4 and onward.
Right now most of your programs,
if not all of them, certainly for P
set 1 can be done entirely in main.
If your program's only
five lines, 10 lines,
even 20 lines long, perfectly
reasonable to write it
all in main and not to over complicate
your code, but what we're doing today
and onward is trying to also
introduce some good design techniques
so that as your code gets more
complicated and as the problems
you want to solve get harder and
more interesting you have, sort of,
the tools in your toolbox with which
to design good solutions to those.
>> So, let's take a quick look back at
this program from my last week, which
was functions zero dot C. And
notice that, quite simply,
it looks like this with two
functions, main and print name.
And thinking back or perhaps
reverse engineering today,
what was the motivation for introducing
a function in line 28 called,
print name?
Or what was this an example of in
terms of a principle or takeaway,
if you would.
Some murmurs.
What?
>> Yeah so Functional Decomposition
is kind of the fancy way of saying,
decompose your program
into its constituent parts
and then use those parts
to assemble a whole.
So, that too is just kind
of a mouthful already,
but this is perhaps even a
better example of something
just called abstraction.
Right?
Abstraction is going to be one
of the recurring themes in CS50
and also computer science
more generally since it's
a technique with which you can solve
problems more effectively because you
can write solutions more
intuitively and in a way that scales
and is understandable by other people.
What do I mean by that?
>> So, arguably it is much more readable
to look at a program like this,
super short though it is.
When you see on line 22 that there's
a function called, print name.
That name alone says what it does.
That function apparently takes
input between its parentheses,
and apparently does something,
presumably prints the name.
And so, even though we
absolutely could have
done what we did a week ago, which was
just take this actual line of code,
get rid of this, and get
rid of this all together,
we sort of abstracted away
the notion of printing a name.
I don't care if you're using print def.
I don't care if you have a
percent S and a backslash N. These
are incredibly arcane details.
What I do care about as a
programmer is printing a name.
And so, what better way to do that
than by calling a function, print name?
And so, that was one of the motivations
for doing something like this.
Making the code more readable, more
reusable, and also self descriptive.
Now, let's take a look
at another example,
which was functions one,
which we had over here.
>> So, this one is perhaps even more
compelling because, in this case,
I don't want to just get an int.
I want to get a positive int.
And it turns out to get a positive
int you have to do a bunch of legwork.
Right?
It's not a simple one line
call like print name was,
which is admittedly less compelling.
>> To get a positive int, logically--
let me scroll back down to hide this.
What do you have to do?
Like all the tools we
have at the moment are
things like print def from Standard
Library and also from CS50 library
we have Get Int, and Get Float,
Get Long Long, Get String,
but the only one, Germane,
right now is Get Int.
So, if the only tool you have
in your tool box is Get Int,
how do we go about implementing
it to get positive int?
>> AUDIENCE: Create a log and check
on whether the input that they gave
was positive or not.
>> SPEAKER 1: Perfect.
Exactly.
Another tool we have in our
toolbox from a week or two ago
is just the looping construct.
And so, yeah, if we use a while
loop, or a do while loop, or a fore
loop we could probably get away
with any of those in some form.
We can implement the notion of get
positive int by just using Get Int,
and then just keep calling it
again and keep pestering the user
until he or she actually
gives us what we want.
>> And so now, this
abstraction of the process
of getting a positive int
into a function called
Get Positive Int is a little more
compelling because look at this.
These are like 10 plus
lines of code that
are involved in getting a positive int,
and I don't really care how you do it.
All I care is that you
can do it, and so I've
hidden all these details behind a
function called Get Positive int that,
indeed, has this do while loop.
>> And see last week for the syntax
there, but it just declares N,
and it prints out the
instruction to the user.
It calls Get Int and then it checks
this condition again, and again,
and again until the user cooperates.
>> So now, a few sanity checks.
For those perhaps familiar
with some programming,
why is N declared, why do I create
N outside of the do while loop?
Why is it on line 29 and not
on like 33, for instance.
>> AUDIENCE: Because when you
declare it outside, it kind
of more, the larger scope--
>> SPEAKER 1: Good.
>> AUDIENCE: --and if you declare
it inside the loop, [INAUDIBLE]
because it doesn't know about it.
SPEAKER 1: Exactly.
If I can simplify--
it's an issue of scope.
And scope refers to the context in
which a variable exists or is usable.
And the nice rule of thumb here is that
generally when you declare or create
a variable you can only use it inside
of the closest embracing curly braces.
So what does that mean?
If I, instead, undo this and go with
something that feels a little simpler.
Right?
>> Line 32 just looks cleaner to me now.
I'm doing both things at
once and then assigning
the right hand to the left hand.
The problem now based on
that definition of scope
is that N can be used in lines
31 and 32 inside of this loop,
but where by that definition
can it not be used?
In line what?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: 35.
>> SPEAKER 1: 35.
Definitely not 35.
And also where else?
AUDIENCE: 34.
SPEAKER 1: Even 34 is
problematic because it's
outside of the curly braces.
And so in fact, let's see what happens.
Right?
This might seem a little
intuitive or might not,
but let's see what the
compiler has to say when
we go into today's source directory.
Make function one.
Oh, my god.
Well, I finally finished
that, by the way.
All right.
And what's the issue here?
Very arcane to look at.
But here's what I typed--
make function one.
Here's what make induced,
which is actually
using the compiler clang
with some of those flags
that we'll see again before long.
And again, always look
at the first error,
because it might just have a cascading
meaningless effect on other lines.
>> So what this means is that the
problem is in function 1.c.
It is on line 32.
And it's at column, or character, 13.
So when your text editor that can
help you identify where the issue is.
So if I scroll up, what is line 32?
That's indeed this one
that's already highlighted
right here-- unused variable n.
But it's not unused.
I'm using it.
But the compiler's confused, because
it only exists inside of this scope.
And so I can't use it here.
I can't use it here.
And the compiler, therefore,
doesn't even care that I'm trying.
It seems to be unused
within its actual scope.
>> So we can broaden the scope by doing
exactly what we started with-- int n.
And even though it doesn't
look as elegant, perhaps,
and we're taking an extra line
here, now it's in scope everywhere.
So let's try again.
So make function one.
Nice.
And now if I if I run function
one, let's give it negative 10,
negative 1, 0, 1, and it indeed works.
>> So there's another solution here.
You know what?
What if I really am wrestling with this?
I don't know where the
n's supposed to go.
You know what?
I'm just going to put it all the
way at the top of my file here.
What would this do, do you think?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So I've made it global, so to speak.
If you have a variable that's outside
all of your functions that is allowed,
and the code should compile, and n
will now be accessible not only in get
positive int, but also in main-- which
is a little worrisome because there's
already an n in main, so more
on that in just a moment--
but this would be considered bad design.
All right.
If you have to resort to
something like, oh, I'll
just put it up here because
the code seems to compile
is generally not the best practice.
Rather you want to choose
the narrowest possible scope
for your variables, which would mean
going with our initial design, which
is right here.
>> Now as an aside, if you did have
an identically-named variable here,
the way c would handle this--
though this won't happen too often--
is that this is still
perfectly fine in here.
But this definition of n in line
22 will shadow the global one.
So this one will work within
main, and the global one
will actually apply when you're in
get positive int But more on that
another time, but just
for those curious.
>> So in short, we fix this here.
Now let's tease apart two other pieces
before we look at one last line of code
in this program.
Get positive int.
On the left-hand side of
its word is the word int.
What does that signify do you think?
Thus far we've mostly seen void.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: It's the type of
variable that you're asking about.
>> SPEAKER 1: Yeah It's the type of, let me
not say variable, but the type of value
that I'm asking back for.
And indeed, that's
intuitive here, hopefully.
Right?
If you want to get a
positive int, what is it you
want the function-- like our
volunteers from last week
to hand you back a piece
of paper with an int on it?
And so we've specified that the
so-called return type of this function
is get positive int.
If we didn't want it to
return anything, you say void.
If you want it to return
a string, you say string.
a float, you say float.
But the only one that applies here
logically, because I'm using get int,
even though I'm restricting it to
positive values, is to return an int.
>> So conversely, what does it mean
that there's a void in parentheses?
What do the parentheses
generally define?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: It means the function's
not actually getting it.
>> SPEAKER 1: It means the function's
not actually getting what?
>> AUDIENCE: An input.
>> SPEAKER 1: An input, whatsoever.
So indeed, if parenthesis
here you specify void,
that just means I don't want any input.
I'll deal with the problem myself.
And indeed, you don't have to
tell get positive int anything.
You just say, get positive int, and that
function will go off and do its thing.
>> But there's been a little trick I've
been playing here this whole time
to make sure this code compiles.
Notice that int-- get positive
int void-- is on line 27.
But for some seemingly weird reason
it's also up here on line 16.
And just for good measure I'll repeat
this so it's perfectly identical.
And I've said prototype with
a little one-line comment.
What happens if I delete that, And
now rerun make function 1, enter.
Whoops.
Wait a minute.
Where's my tab?
Huh?
Standby.
Make function 1.
There we go.
OK.
Hadn't saved it properly.
So, I think there's a little
bug here where I'm not
seeing the tab name at the moment.
So what is going on here?
Implicit declaration of function
get positive int is invalid in C99.
So confusing again.
So what is this indicative of?
Well, it turns out that
C is pretty stupid.
Well, it's the programming
language, or rather the compiler is.
It only knows what you have
taught it, and it's only
going to know something
if you taught it before.
In other words, in
main at the moment, I'm
trying to call a function
called get positive int.
But the compiler is not going
to notice that get positive int
exists until line 26.
And so what the compiler does is just
errors as soon as it gets to line 17,
saying implicit declaration
of get positive int, which
is just a fancy way of saying, I don't
know what get positive int is yet.
>> Other languages like Java and
Python and Ruby might look ahead.
C does not.
And so the way we fix
this is one of two ways.
Either one, if the problem is that get
positive int hasn't been seen before,
well, let me just move it to the top.
That would fix this problem.
But generally, it's
considered better technique
to put your main function at the very
top so that a human reading your code
knows what the program does,
because main is not buried all
the way at the bottom or in the middle.
It's at the very top.
So that doesn't feel ideal.
And you can actually get
into situations where
if one function calls
another, which calls another,
you can get into an issue where neither
can go above the other, logically.
It's just not possible.
>> And so the way to work
around this is to just take
the function's signature, so to speak--
the first line where it's declared--
and just copy, paste it at the
top, but not with curly braces--
just with a semicolon.
It's like a little hint
of what is to come.
And in fact, all of this time when we
have seen things like standard io.h
and cs50.h, similarly, in those dot
h files are there other prototypes.
And we'll see that before long.
>> So in short, when you have a program
in a file with multiple functions
besides main, you almost
always want to declare them
just by way of their first
line, followed by a semicolon,
at the very top of the file.
That was a lot all at once.
Any questions?
All right.
>> So let's move on then
to something like cough.
Oh.
How fitting.
All right.
Cough.
So here is a c
implementation of a program
we did the other day in
Scratch that very simply just
says cough, cough, cough.
All right.
And someone said a few
days ago that there's
a way of cleaning this code up already.
All right?
As soon as you're copying and
pasting probably bad design.
At least once we get to four or five
or 20 coughs, it feels bad practice.
We just keep copy, pasting.
What's the obvious solution
to cleaning this program up?
>> AUDIENCE: Loop.
>> SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So use a loop.
And we can use a for-loop, a while
loop, any number of approaches.
And indeed, that's what
we do in version one here.
I've instead rewritten it
in version one of cough.c
to be just cough within a for-loop.
All right, but there's an
opportunity now to kind of start
to design this a little more like
the lesson we taught a moment ago,
which is this-- suppose that I wanted
to create a function called cough,
let's consider for just a moment
what it's going to look like.
So if I want something
to cough, I just need
to use print f inside the function.
And indeed I am.
And in fact, all this
time, any time you're
printing something to
the screen, a programmer
would call that a side effect.
It's not me handing
back someone a value.
It's me taking some action
that might be visually obvious.
But this function cough, does it return
anything based on its first line?
No, because its return type
is void, which just means
it's not handing me anything back.
It might be doing something
visually, but it's not handing me
back a piece of paper like last week.
>> Does it need any input?
No.
And so it's void here too.
So this too is kind of
over-engineering this problem.
Right?
I've made the program more
complex, more lines of code,
I haven't made it any
more functional, but this
would be a stepping stone,
perhaps, for a broader
context with more complicated code.
But what about this?
What have I done-- just glancing at
this without looking at the comment
at the very top of the file-- what have
I fundamentally done here with my cough
implementation that's different?
Yeah, in back?
>> AUDIENCE: Make it so you can
have a character turn off.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So this feels kind of nice.
Right?
It's like adding a feature to your
program or your function, in this case.
It still returns nothing.
It might have a visual side effect,
because it's calling print f.
But now I have parametrized
the function, which
means I've specified taken
input of type int and call it n,
but I could call it anything I want.
In fact, it could just be
times to be even more explicit.
And then I could just change this here.
But the point is that this is how I
create a function that takes input.
And if you recall flipping
through perhaps online in one
of the walk-throughs, the
fourth and final cough example,
you'll notice here I've generalized
my code further-- kind of abstracted
it further.
Like cough and sneeze, both are
about like saying something or making
some kind of sound.
Save would be the
corresponding Scratch block.
And so what I did in this version,
which we can just glance at,
is cough is just like saying, [COUGH],
cough, and meanwhile, sneezing is
like saying, [ACHOO].
And so I've generalized
the implementation of those
by now implementing
this generic function,
say, which is interesting
for today's purposes
only because it still
doesn't have a return type.
But how many inputs does it have?
AUDIENCE: Two.
SPEAKER 1: Two.
And so if you want to
take in two arguments,
just separate them with a comma.
And if you want to then
call that function,
notice that you just
call say, quote, unquote,
for the first argument, common
n, for the second argument.
So again, we just have now the
building blocks so that we can actually
implement some of our own functions.
All right.
Any questions on these?
>> So now let's peel back a layer if so.
And the goal, ultimately,
is next week's problem set
is going to be on cryptogrophy--
the art of scrambling information.
And specifically, the information
will have you encrypt or decrypt
is going to be text.
And so that kind of invites
the question today like well,
what is going on underneath the hood
with text beyond ASCII from week zero,
and how can we actually
start to manipulate it?
So here is Zamyla's name.
And in text, that might be inputted
into like the get string function.
And starting now, when you see a
string like this-- Z-A-M-Y-L-A--
start thinking of it as though each
of those characters is in a box of its
own.
And indeed, in a week or so's
time, each of these boxes
is going to represent very specifically
a block of memory-- a bite of memory.
So each of these letters,
ultimately, will represent 8 bits.
And we'll actually see what's going
on underneath the hood in my computer.
>> But for not it suffices
just to look at Zamyla
through this lens, whereby each of
these letters is in its own box.
And nicely enough in C we can
access each of these boxes directly.
So if you want to get the first
letter of her name, super easy in C.
If you want to get the last
letter, super easy as well
with a piece of new syntax.
>> So I'm going to go ahead into CS50
IDE and open up the string zero dot C.
And in this example here, there are
a couple of new things going on.
So first in line 19, we've
seen this before-- get string.
So just as a quick sanity check,
if someone could offer up verbally
a layman's explanation of
what's going on in line 19.
Like just translate this into
English that a roommate not in CS50
might understand.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Have the user input a
string and store it in a variable s.
SPEAKER 1: Good.
Have the user input a string
and store it in a variable s.
That's great.
So on the right-hand
side, we call get string.
That returns a value
that didn't get assigned
from right-hand side to left-hand
side into a variable called s that's
designed to store a string.
Exactly.
>> So now line 22, per
the comment in line 21,
obviously prints that string
one character per line.
But how?
So first of all, we initialize I to 0.
And then how do we get to
the end of Zamyla's name?
Well, at the end of
Zamyla's name, I could
manually type in the last character of
her name somehow, or the number of it.
Right?
If we go back here-- Z-A-M-L--
Y-L-A-- so I could type in.
What's the index of
Zamyla's last letter?
If this is 0-- speaking like a
programmer-- 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
I heard-- so indeed, the last letter
in Zamyla's name is the sixth,
but if we count from 0,
it's going to be number 5.
So keep that in mind here.
>> It turns out there's a function in
C called strlen, and back in the day
and to this day still,
a lot of programmers
choose to sync names for their
functions that sound like the words
they're trying to say.
So strlen is string length.
And so what would string length of
S return when Zamyla is the input?
>> AUDIENCE: Five.
>> SPEAKER 1: Z-A-M-Y-L. Six.
Right?
What's the length of Zamyla's name?
And just in reality, six letters.
Right?
And so what does that mean for our loop?
We're going to go from
0 up to six, which
is going to give us five iterations.
What do we do on each iteration?
Well, percent C, someone
guessed the other day,
means a placeholder for what?
>> AUDIENCE: Char.
SPEAKER 1: Just a char.
So a single character-- not
multiple characters like a string.
And then here's the new line
that we've got printing out.
And then here's the new syntax.
If you want to print out the i-th
character in the string S, so to speak,
you can simply say the
name of the string S,
and then open square bracket, and
then closed square bracket, with an i
the middle.
And it's kind of nice in that
it kind of looks like a square
just like the squares in which Zamyla's
characters exist on that picture there.
>> So if I actually run this
now, let's see what happens.
Make string 0 dot slash
string 0, and then I'm
going to type in Zamyla's name.
There's no prompt, because I didn't
use print f, but that's fine.
I just know what to do.
And indeed, it prints out
Zamyla's name, one per line.
>> Now let's be a little reckless.
Suppose that I didn't know
about strlen and I figured,
all right, no one's going to have a
name bigger than like 50 characters.
Let's go ahead and recompile this
and rerun it, and then type in Zamyla
again.
Logically, what is the
program going to try to print?
Z-A-M-Y-L-A then like 45
unknown bytes of memory.
And indeed, we'll come back
to this idea of memory.
But just logically, if
Zamyla's name is this long,
as per the picture
here, what we're saying
is keep printing, keep printing, keep
printing, keep printing, keep printing,
all the way to the 50th character,
which who knows what's going to happen.
So let's actually take a look.
Let's type in Zamyla.
Interesting.
We got lucky.
Just a whole bunch of white space.
Oh.
There's one funky character.
It looks kind of like a weird question
mark there, but there is Zamyla's name.
Let's get really reckless.
How about we print out 500
blocks into the unknown?
Let's go ahead and make this
as well and then re-run.
And let's full screen it, because
we need to see more space.
Zamyla.
Got lucky again.
>> Dare we get more reckless?
Let's get more reckless.
50,000 characters.
This is most surely not a good idea.
All right.
Make string 0.
This will be our last demo.
Zamyla.
Ugh.
OK.
So my memory is really empty right now,
which is actually kind of convenient.
What I'm trying to get to-- all right.
And now I'm just going to get reckless.
500,000.
Make-- let's full-screen it.
Enter.
Zamyla.
There we go.
I have no idea what that
is, but it sounds bad.
All right.
And in fact, soon, if you're among
the fortunate few in office hours
and in problem set one, you
might very well encounter this.
Segmentation fault actually does
have a well-defined meaning.
It means some kind of mistake
relating to a segment of memory.
And in layman's terms,
it means we touched
memory-- we used RAM in my computer
that I should not have had access to.
And that's what's both
powerful and also dangerous
about C is that you actually
have unfettered access
to the entirety of your program's memory
or bytes or RAM, more specifically.
>> So even though Zamyla's name
is only six characters long,
I can still go anywhere
in memory I want.
And as an aside, if you've
ever read some article
over the years about some
server or some program
getting cracked or hacked that's
taken advantage of something
called a buffer overflow
exploit that we'll actually
talk about in a few weeks, that's
generally referring to somehow tricking
a computer into going well
beyond the boundaries of memory
that it should have, and
finding something juicy
in that memory-- a
password, perhaps, a way
of circumventing some serial number
check, or just generally able
to trick the computer is executing
code that wasn't intended.
But let's come back to
reality for just a moment
where this program was
implemented with strlen,
and introduce one thing up here.
What's new among these top three lines?
>> So string dot h.
It turns out there's this library called
String Dot H, or the String Library,
whose header file, so to speak,
is string dot h that gives me
access to this strlen function.
If I omit that, the compiler is
going to yell at me in some form.
But you know what?
Now let's get really nuanced.
In line 22, there's something kind
of inefficient-- badly designed,
arguably-- about this line of code.
Think back to how
for-loop are implemented
and what steps happen again and
again and again-- the initialization,
the condition, the code that
gets executed, then the increment
or the change, then the condition,
then the code, then the change, then
the condition, then the code,
then the change, and so forth.
So what might be a little
worrisome or poorly done here?
Yeah, in blue.
AUDIENCE: Strlen is
called many, many times.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah.
So strlen is called
many times, but what is
the length of Zamyla's name the
first time the loop executes?
>> AUDIENCE: Six.
>> SPEAKER 1: Six.
Well, what is the length of her name
the second time the code executes?
>> AUDIENCE: Six.
>> SPEAKER 1: All right.
It's still six.
Right?
Zarla's name hasn't
changed, even if I'm looking
at only part of the letters in her name.
And so the fact that I'm effectively
asking this question, what's
the length of Zamyla, what's the length
of Zamyla, what's the length of Zamyla,
six separate times, or
seven even, is just stupid,
because that's unchanging that answer.
And so what I could actually
do is this-- in string one
I have a marginally better version here.
There-- whoops-- string two I have
a marginally better version wherein
I do this-- instead of just
initializing i to 0, I also with a comma
declare a second variable called
n-- I don't have to say int again.
I should not, in fact.
But I say n.
And then I initialize n to
the strlen of n, so that now
how many times does strlen
get executed in total?
Just once.
And so this is what we mean
earlier about better design.
Actually once your code is correct,
going back and thinking through,
am I using as little
memory or as few seconds
or milliseconds of computer time as
possible to implement some problem?
And I'm going to scroll
up and just mention
that there's this mention
of null in this version,
but we'll come back to that before long.
Because for now, let's take a look
at where this is going to lead us.
So one, it turns out that
now that we have the ability
to look at individual characters,
we can leverage something
from week 0 that was very arcane and
sort of uninteresting at the time.
But now, and especially when we
get to cryptography in a week,
it's going to be pretty powerful.
It turns out that with some
data types-- ints and floats
and chars and strings and
other things-- some of them
can be very easily converted to another.
>> For instance, when we talked
about ASCII some time ago-- here's
the capital letters A
through M, dot, dot,
dot-- we said that there's a mapping
between these letters and numbers.
And in fact, it holds true
for lowercase letters as well.
Lowercase a is 97, capital a is 65.
And there's a number in ASCII,
which is just this mapping
system for all of those other letters.
So what does that mean?
Well, I'm going to go ahead and open
up real quickly something called
ASCII 0, most of which is comments.
And again online you can always
glance through the comments.
>> And take a look what
this is going to do.
So it's got a main function.
I've hard-coded the numbers just for
now, because I know what I'm doing.
I know what I want to see here.
And I've initialized I to 65.
And I'm counting up
through 26 letters total.
And what am I going to
print one line at a time
if you can interpret
this highlighted line?
What gets printed?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Are you going
to print the letter that
corresponds to the map of the
letter value and integer value?
SPEAKER 1: Exactly.
I'm going to print the letter
corresponding to the integer value,
and vice versa, as follows.
Well this, someone said earlier,
is just a placeholder for a char.
It still is.
This, of course, is a placeholder
for an int-- not a new line.
And now notice, my first value that
I'm plugging in for that placeholder
isn't just I. I'm saying,
in parentheses, char I,
which the parenthetical char is
telling the compiler, treat I
not as what it is, which is a number.
Treat it as an actual character.
Whereas the second value I'm plugging
in-- I-- should just be a number.
>> So if I compile this program--
so this is make ASCII 0,
dot slash ASCII 0-- I just get
this handy little chart that
shows me all of the possible
mappings without having to think it
through or figure it out on my own.
And I'm also printing out,
notice the lowercase letters,
because a few lines later, I
also print out this mapping
as well, which is just to
say that once you understand
what's going on underneath
the hood, can you
automatically convert back and forth.
And in fact, if any of you
ever did this in grade school
or heard about someone
mythically taking a note
and passing it to his
or her friend in class,
but you scrambled the
letters by like A becomes B,
and B becomes C, or something
more complicated than that, well,
how would you go about
implementing that as a kid?
Well, you just kind of know
A becomes B, B becomes C,
but mathematically,
what was that kid doing?
What were you adding to each letter?
Effectively, 1.
>> So when you change A to B, that's
kind of like changing 65 to 66,
which mathematically means just add 1.
And so if you were to implement
that little deceptive technique
for your teacher in code, you
might do exactly that just
by adding a single letter together.
So before long, we're
going to see how we
can take advantage of that to actually
genuinely scramble and unscramble
information.
In the meantime, know that we've started
to introduce a couple other libraries
here-- the string one today.
And a very helpful site
hopefully you'll find
is called reference.cs50.net, which
the teaching staff have put together,
so that if you want to
look up how strlen works,
you can start typing
the function's name,
click strlen there, and then
a less comfortable explanation
is going to appear.
Or if you want the official
Linux-based explanation,
you can click more comfy
at top right, and it
will present the same information,
but in more complex terms.
That's a useful resource to
actually know what everything does.
>> Next time we're going to
take a look at Ovaltine
and more, and introduce ourselves
to the world of cryptography.
Before then, we'll see
you later this week.
And now, Colton Ogden.
See you on Wednesday.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> SPEAKER 1: What the
[BLEEP] are you doing?
>> SPEAKER 1: I am eating my dessert?
How do you eat it?
With your hands?
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]