>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right, this is CS50.
This is the end of week eight.
And today, we start
to fill in some pieces
when it comes to building
things on the web.
So, recall that on Monday
we spend a lot more time
on PHP, which is this dynamic
programming language that
lets us output, among other
things, HTML and other such content
that we'll want to see.
But we haven't really looked at how
we're going to store any information.
Indeed, almost any of that the super
interesting websites you visit today
have some kind of database
on the back end, right?
Facebook certainly stores lots of data
about all of us and Gmail stores all
of your emails.
>> And so, many other sites aren't just
static content that's informational.
It's actually dynamic in some way.
You provide input, it updates
the pages for other people.
You get messages, you send
messages, and so forth.
So today, we look closer at
the underpinnings of a project
that you'll dive into next
week, CS50 Finance, which
is actually going to have you build
something not in C, but in PHP.
A website that looks a
little something like this
that allows to buy and sell
stocks that are actually
going to draw upon real time
stock data from Yahoo Finance.
And so ultimately, you'll have the
illusion for yourself and for users
that you're actually buying and selling
stocks and getting nearly real time
updates, managing a
portfolio, all of which
is going to require having,
ultimately, a database of users.
>> So, in your own words,
especially if you're not
super familiar with computer
science or databases, what
do you know a database to be
right now, in nontechnical terms?
What is it?
How would you describe it
to a roommate or a friend?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
information [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: So, a list of information,
or a store-- a list of information
that you might want to store
about something, like a user.
And what do users have
associated with them?
If you're a user on Facebook or
Gmail, what are the characteristics
that all of us users have?
Like, what might be some of the
columns in the spreadsheet to which we
alluded last time?
Because again, you can
think of a database
really as a fancy Excel file or Google
Spreadsheet or Apple Numbers file.
>> So, what do you think of
when you think of a user?
What do they have?
What's that?
>> AUDIENCE: A name.
>> DAVID MALAN: A name.
So if name, like, David Malan
would be the name of some user.
What else does a user have?
>> AUDIENCE: An ID.
>> DAVID MALAN: An ID.
So, like an ID number, like your Harvard
ID or your Yale Net ID or the like.
What else might a user have?
>> AUDIENCE: Password.
>> DAVID MALAN: A password, maybe an
address, maybe a phone number, maybe
an email address.
So, there's bunches of fields and this
could sort of spiral out of control
quickly as soon as you start
realizing, oh, let's store this
and let's store this and that.
>> But how do we actually do that?
So again, the mental model
to have for today as we
dive into actual SQL,
Structured Query Language,
is a database that looks like this.
It's just rows and columns.
And you can imagine Google Spreadsheets
or any number of other programs.
But what's key about MySQL, which is the
database software we're going to use,
the freely openly
available-- Facebook uses
it and any number of other websites--
database stores things relationally.
And a relational database
just means one that literally
stores its data in rows and columns.
It's as simple as that.
>> So, even something like Oracle that
you might have generally heard of
is a relational database.
And underneath the hood, it
stores data in rows and columns.
And Oracle charges you a
lot of money to do that,
whereas MySQL charges
you nothing for the same.
So, SQL is going to give us
at least four operations.
The ability to select data, like read
data, insert, delete, and update data.
In other words, those are
really the four key operations
that are going to allow us to change
stuff in those rows and columns.
>> The tool that we'll use today especially
to learn SQL and to play with it
is again called PHP MyAdmin.
It's web based tool.
Total coincidence that
it's written in PHP.
But it's going to give us a graphical
user interface so that we can actually
create these rows and columns
and then talk to them via code.
So, let's now start to
what I think is frankly
kind of the fun process of
building the back end of websites,
the parts that users don't
see, but surely do care about,
because that's rather data's going.
So, similar to C and a
little less like PHP,
SQL, or a database that supports
SQL, has at least these data types
and bunches of others.
CHAR, VARCHAR, INT, BIGINT,
DECIMAL, and DATETIME.
And there's a whole
bunch of other features,
but let's do this by
way of actual example.
>> I'm going to go into CS50 IDE
where, in advance, I've logged in
and I've also visited a URL for
this tool called PHP MyAdmin.
And in problem set seven, we'll tell
you exactly how to get to this interface
as well.
On the top left hand corner,
notice it says lecture.
And that just means that
in advance, I created
an empty database called lecture
that has no spreadsheets in it yet.
There's no rows and columns.
Because the first
thing we're going to do
is start to create a table
that's going to store our users.
>> So, literally over
here to the right, I'm
going to tell the database
I want a table called Users.
So, this is like the file that I
want to store all of my data in.
And how many columns?
Well, let's keep it simple for now.
I just want to store like a
username and a name for a user.
We'll start small.
So, I want two columns total.
And I'm going to go ahead and click Go.
And then, for these
columns, what I'm going
to do-- if this internet
cooperates-- all right,
so we're going to try that again.
I'm going to create a table called
Users with two columns, click Go, OK.
Now we've got it really fast.
Thank you, very well done.
All right, so what do we want
these columns to be called?
>> So, one's going to be called Username.
So, all I see here-- and the interface
frankly gets a little ugly eventually,
once you start typing in all this data.
But what's nice is that sort of
paradoxically, I'm creating columns,
but the tool has foolishly
laid them out in rows
so that I can configure these columns.
So, there's two blanks there under Name.
And one of these fields I
want to called Username,
and the other field I want to call Name.
>> And now I have to choose
data types for these things.
So, whereas in Excel
and Google Spreadsheets,
if you want a column, you literally
just type Name or Username, hit Enter.
Maybe you make it bold face
just for clarity, but that's it.
You don't specify the
types of the columns.
Now in Google Spreadsheets or Excel, you
might specify how the data is rendered.
You could go to the Format menu, and you
can specify show this like dollar sign,
show this like a floating point value.
>> So, it's similar in spirit to
that what we're about to do,
but this is actually going to force
the data to be a certain type.
Now, even though a moment ago I
said there's only a few data types,
there's actually a
whole lot, and they're
in varying degrees of specificity.
And as an aside, you
can even do fancy things
like storage geometries
inside of a database.
You can store things
like GPS coordinates
and actually find, mathematically,
points that are close to others.
But we're going to
keep this super simple
and go up to here, all of
the so-called string types.
>> So, here's a list of a
whole bunch of options.
CHAR, VARCHAR, TINYTEXT,
MEDIUMTEXT, LONGTEXT.
And it's kind of overwhelming.
And unfortunately, somewhat
paradoxically to C,
a CHAR is not really a CHAR.
If you specify in a database
that your data type is CHAR,
that means that yes, it's a
CHAR, but it's one or more CHARs.
And you have to specify
how many CHARs you want.
So, what's a typical
length for a username?
Is there a limit typically?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: 16 maybe?
Something like that.
You know, back in the
day, it used to be eight.
Sometimes it's 16, sometimes
it's even more than that.
And so, this doesn't
mean give me one CHAR.
This means I have to specify
the length of the field,
and now I might say something like 16.
And there's a trade off here.
So, we'll see in a moment
that this means one,
every username has to be 16 characters.
But wait a minute, M-A-L-A-N. If that's
my username and I'm only using five,
what would you propose that the database
to do for the other 11 characters that
I've reserved space for?
What would you do?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: Yeah, just
make them all null.
Make them spaces.
But probably null, so a
lot of backslash zeros.
So, on the one hand, we've
now made sure that my username
can be no more than 16 characters.
And the flip side of that is
that if I had a really long name
or wanted a really long
username like some of you
guys might have in that college or
at Yale.edu, you can't have one.
And so in fact, if you've
ever registered for a website
and you get yelled at saying
your password's too long
or your username's too long, it's
simply because a programmer, when
configuring his or her database,
decided that this field will
be no longer than this length.
>> All right, so what if
we proceed to name?
How long should a
typical human's name be?
How many characters, 16?
I'm guessing we could
find someone in this room
where by his or her first plus last
name is longer than 16 characters.
So, what's better than that, 17?
18?
25?
Bigger?
30?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: 5,000, oh my God.
So, that's probably a decent
upper bound, shall we say.
And here we kind of have
to make a judgment call.
Like, there's no right answer here.
Infinite is not quite possible,
because we're eventually
going to have-- we're
going to run out of memory.
So, we have to make a
judgment call at some point.
>> Very common would be, for instance,
to use-- and let me specify CHAR here
as before-- 255 was literally the
upper limit on this database software
years ago.
And so, a lot of humans
would just say, fine.
255's the limit.
Let's just use the maximum.
And this is pretty ridiculous.
Like, if you're typing someone's
name for 200 plus characters,
that a little ridiculous.
>> But, remember that ASCII is not
the only system for characters.
And so, especially in a
lot of Asian languages
where there's characters we can't
express on keyboards like my US
keyboard, some characters actually
take up 16 bits instead of eight bits.
And so, this actually
isn't all that unreasonable
that we need more
space if we want to fit
larger characters than the very US
centric ones we've tended to discuss.
So, we need some upper bound.
I don't know what the best one is,
but 255 is generally a common one.
25 feels low.
16, 32 feel low.
I would err on the side
of something higher.
But there's a trade off, as always.
What is the, perhaps, obvious
trade off of reserving 255 CHARs
for everyone's name in my database?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: What's that?
>> DAVID MALAN: It's a
lot of memory, right?
M-A-L-A-N. I have just wasted 250
characters just to store my name
defensively, just in case someone
in the class has a really long name.
That seems like an undue tradeoff.
>> So, it turns out that SQL,
this database language,
actually supports something
called VARCHAR, or Variable CHAR.
And this is kind of nice in that this
allows you to specify not a fixed
width, but rather, a variable width.
And more specifically, a
maximum width of the field.
So, this means that a name can
be no more than 250 characters,
but it can certainly be fewer.
And the database is going to be smart.
If you do put in M-A-L-A-N,
it's only going to use five,
maybe six bytes for like
a trailing null character,
and not spend an additional
249 or 250 bytes unnecessarily.
>> So, this seems like I should
have started with this story.
But there's always a tradeoff.
So, on the one hand, a username I've
specified to be hard coded at 16,
and maybe that wasn't
the right call, maybe it
is, but why not use
VARCHARs for everything?
>> It exists for a reason.
Why not use VARCHARs for every field
whose length you don't know in advance
if it seems to be a great thing, right?
Use only as much space as
you need up to this limit?
>> AUDIENCE: Slower.
DAVID MALAN: Speller?
AUDIENCE: Makes it slower?
DAVID MALAN: Oh, it's slower.
Good, that's almost always
the answer, frankly.
Like, what's the tradeoff?
It either costs more space
or it costs more time.
So, in this case, it might be slower.
Why?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
determining [INAUDIBLE].
>> DAVID MALAN: Good.
So, you might recall from even
PSED5, playing with your approach
to the dictionary, if you have to
allocate memory dynamically or keep
growing a buffer, that
can actually be slow.
If you have to call malloc
underneath the hood and maybe
that's what MySQL is doing, so
surely that could be the case.
And if you think way
back to PSet-- or even
weeks two, when we did things like
binary search or even linear search,
one of the nice things about every word
in a database or every word in a column
being exactly the same length, even
if a whole bunch of those characters
are blank, is that you can use
random access on your data, right?
>> If you know that every
word is 16 characters away,
you can use pointer arithmetic, so to
speak, and go to us 16, 32, 48, 64,
and you can just jump
instantly using arithmetic
to any of the words in your database.
Whereas if it's a VARCHAR,
what do you instead have to do?
>> [PHONE RINGING]
>> If it's a VARCHAR, you
can't use random access.
What you have to look for or do?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: Look
through the whole-- trace
through the whole list
looking for what, most likely?
What kind of special value?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Looking
for the null terminators
that demarcate the separation of words.
So again, a tradeoff, and
there's no right answer.
But this is where, especially
when your users get to be many
and your load on your servers, the
number of people using it gets high,
these are actually nontrivial decisions.
So, we can leave these as this, but
let's scroll down over to the right
here.
Now, there's a couple of columns
where we have to make a judgment call.
Does it make sense to allow a user's
name, a user's username or a user's
name, to be null?
That is, just blank.
Feels a little nonsensical, so I'm
not going to check those boxes.
But it turns out in a
database, you can say,
someone can optionally have this value.
This column does not have
to actually be there.
>> Now, there's this drop down menu.
And notice I'm still
in the first row there,
so I'm talking about username now.
And it turns out that a database,
unlike a simple mere spreadsheet,
has powerful features called indexes.
And an index is a way of telling the
database in advance that I the human
am smarter than you.
>> I know what kinds of queries, select
or insert or delete or update,
that my code is going to end
up doing on this database.
I want to read a lot of data.
I want to insert a lot of data.
I want to constantly
delete a lot of data.
If I know that I'm going to be
accessing a field like Username a lot,
I can preemptively tell the
database, I know more than you,
and I want to decree that
you should index this field.
Where indexing a field or a column
means that the database in advance
should borrow some ideas from, like,
week four and five and six from CS50
and actually build up
something like a binary search
tree or something
generally called a B tree
that you would learn
in a class like CS124
at Harvard, an algorithms class,
or any number of other places.
>> The database and the smart
people who implemented it
will figure out how to store
that table of information
in memory so that searches and
other operations are super fast.
You don't have to do it.
You don't have to implement
linear search or binary search
or merge sort or selection
sort, any of that.
The database does it for you if you tell
it preemptively to index this field.
>> And you can see too, there's
some other characteristics
we can tell the database to enforce.
What might it mean if I choose Unique
from this menu, just intuitively?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the
username has to be unique.
Is this a good thing or a bad thing for
a database, for a website with users?
Should usernames be unique?
Yeah, probably.
If that's what the
field we use to log in,
you don't really want to people having
the same feel or the same username.
So, we can have the
database enforce that so
that now in my PHP code or any language,
I don't have to, for instance, check
necessarily does this username
exist before I let someone register?
The database won't let two people named
David or Malans register in this case.
>> And as an aside, even though this
menu only lets you select one,
a unique index is one that's
indexed for super fast performance,
but it also enforces uniqueness.
And we'll come back to what the
other two mean in just a moment.
Meanwhile, if I go to
my second row, which
is the user's name, should I specify
that the name should be unique?
No, because you could certainly
have-- there's no two David
Malans in this room, most likely.
But if we choose a different name,
we might surely have collisions.
>> Think back to hash tables and the like.
So, we certainly don't want
to make the name field unique.
So, we're just going to leave
that as dash, dash, dash, nothing.
And I'm going to leave
everything else alone.
Indeed, most of these fields
we won't have to care about.
And when I'm ready to save this,
if the internet cooperates,
I click Save, and very, very, very
slowly does the database get saved.
And now I'm back to this
interface, which admittedly,
is overwhelming at first glance.
But all I'm going to do is click
on the word Users at top left.
I'm going to go up here, click
Users, and by default, it
has executed some SQL, but
more on that in a moment.
Here's just a summary of what I did.
And not to worry that you see
mention of Latin and Swedish here.
Those are just the default
settings, because MySQL originally,
or PHP MyAdmin, one of the two happened
to be written by some Swedish people.
But it's irrelevant in our case here.
>> All right, so why is
this all interesting?
It turns out, I can insert data
into a database by writing code.
And I'm go ahead and
in my file here, I'm
going to go ahead and pretend like
this is wired to that database, which
it isn't at the moment, but it will
be when we get to problem set seven.
And I'm going to go ahead and
execute a function called query,
which we will give you in problem
set seven's distribution code, that
takes at least one argument,
which is just a string.
A string of SQL code.
So, you're about to learn how to
write Structured Query Language.
>> If I want to insert a new row into my
database because someone has submitted
a form to my code, I would literally
write INSERT INTO users the following
fields: username,
comma, name, the VALUES,
and now I need to insert
something like Malan, and quote,
unquote 'David Malan.' And now
even for those unfamiliar with SQL,
why am I using single quotes
inside of this green string?
What might be the reason here?
>> Notice I'm co-mingling two languages.
Query is a PHP function,
but it takes an argument.
And that argument has to itself be
written in another language called
SQL, Structured Query Language.
So, everything that I
have just highlighted here
is this language called SQL.
So, what's with the single quotes,
just as a quick sanity check?
Go ahead.
They're strings.
So, quote, unquote Malan and quote,
unquote David Malan are strings.
And just thinking intuitively now,
knowing what you know about C and PHP,
why did I not do this, which I usually
used double quotes for strings?
Why did I not want to do that?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Because I'm already using
double quotes on the way
outside of the argument
to the PHP function,
I would just confuse the interpreter.
It won't know, do these go together?
Do these go together?
So, I alternate instead.
>> Or I could do something like this,
backslash quote or backslash quote.
Frankly, that just starts to
get very unreadable and ugly.
But that would achieve
the same result as well.
>> So, if I were to execute this
query now, let's see what happens.
I'm going to go ahead now and rather
than execute the PHP code, which
is where you'll play
in problem set seven,
I'm going to instead go to PHP MyAdmin.
And I'm manually going
to go to the SQL tab,
and let me zoom in on the interface.
And I'm going to paste in
the thing I just typed.
And the color coding has
changed a little bit now,
just because the program formats
things a little differently.
But notice that all I've done
is I've said, insert into Users.
I've specified, then, in a comma
separated parenthesized list the two
fields that I want to insert, and
then I've literally said values
followed by another paren,
and then the two values
I want to plug-in, and
now for good measure,
I'll put a semicolon at the end.
So, this is not C. This is not PHP.
This is now SQL, and I'm pasting it
into this web based interface that's
just going to let me,
as soon as I click Go,
execute this query on the database
running inside of CS50 IDE.
>> So this is good.
Notice that said one row
inserted, went super fast,
0.0054 seconds to insert that data.
So, that sounds pretty healthy.
It reformatted my query
for me here just to see it
in sort of color coded version.
But now if I click
Browse, notice that, even
though there's a lot of clutter on
the screen, my table now has two rows.
>> So, let me go ahead and do another.
Instead of this, let me
go to the SQL tab again.
And this time I'll insert something like
Rob and his name will be Rob Bowden.
Bowden.
Let's click Save.
Oops, rather Go.
>> Click Browse again, and
now notice I have two rows.
So, this is just a way more complex
way of opening up Google Spreadsheets
and just typing a row into a column.
But what's key is that
we now have the syntax
with which to write code so that
ultimately, we could actually
do some and this.
Recall that PHP supports
super global variables.
>> What is inside of dollar
sign underscore GET in PHP?
We took a look at one
or two simple examples.
And in PSet6, recall you have hello
dot PHP which uses this variable.
What goes in there?
Or what is it?
A little louder.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: It's a snow
seed of array, which
is just a fancy way of saying an
array that has key value pairs.
And the keys aren't numeric.
They're words or strings.
And specifically, what
are those key value pairs?
Where do they come from?
Sorry?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: No?
Where do those key
value pairs come from?
Say again?
Again?
Am I the only one hearing something?
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> That's right, yes?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, they
come from the query string.
So, if you rewind in time to
when we've played with Google
and we've gone to Google.com slash
search question mark q equals cats,
if I were to hit Enter and if
Google were implemented in PHP,
PHP code that Google wrote
would have access to dollar sign
underscore GET inside of which
is a key called Q and a value
called cats that it can then use
used to do an actual search with.
>> So, in fact, what I'm going to
do now is go back to my PHP code
that you'll again see more of in PSet7.
And instead of plugging
in hard coded values which
doesn't seem like a
very dynamic website,
I'm going to give you a teaser of
what your actual code would do.
You would put in two
question marks like this.
I don't know what the username is.
I don't know what the
name is going to be,
but I do know I can
get them dynamically.
>> So, if the code we're writing now is
the code running on Google's servers,
or if this is hello dot
PHP, which comes with PSet6,
I'm going to pass into
the query function
just like printf, two other arguments.
GET, quote, unquote username,
and GET, quote, unquote name.
And now, notice what the
general structure is here.
I've got on the left
hand side of the call,
this function called query in PHP.
I still have as a first
argument, just a string of text.
>> But that string of text is
written in a language called SQL.
And frankly, it's not a big language.
We're only going to talk about
it formally today, really.
And then in problem set
seven, there's relatively
few features that we're
going to leverage.
The question marks, though, mean plug in
a value here and plug in another value
here.
And notice, I've omitted what
from around the quote-- damn
it-- around the quotation
marks this time.
I've omitted the quotation
marks around the question mark,
sorry, this time around.
>> So, what's nice about this
question mark feature which
PHP tends to support, Ruby and
Python and other languages,
this just means plug in some
value here and you know what?
You figure out whether to use
single quotes or double quotes.
Don't bother me with those
intellectually uninteresting details.
But, make sure it's correct
so that my code is ultimately
operational and safe, which
will have a meaning before long.
>> Now, how many arguments total, just to
be clear, is the query function taking?
Anyone want to vote for more than two?
Three?
Sure, why?
Why three?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
The first part is the string.
The second argument is dollar sign
underscore GET bracket username.
And the third argument is the
same thing, but just the name.
So in other words, now
if I had a web form
that had to text fields,
one for the user's username,
one for his or her name, just
like you would see in a website
when you register for
some website, this might
be the code on the back end that
actually does the insertion now
into the database.
>> Now by contrast, let's fast forward.
Suppose a user is now
logging in and you want
to write PHP code that checks whether
the person who's just logged in
is actually a user, you can
use pretty simple syntax.
You can say SELECT, let's say
star, where star means everything.
I don't know what I
want, so just give me
all the columns from the table
called users where, and this is nice.
Select supports what's
called a predicate, which is
like a way of qualifying what you want.
Where username equals
quote, unquote Malan.
So here too, I've embedded
inside the argument
to a PHP function, a line of SQL code.
And that SQL code this
time is literally going
to search for quote, unquote Malan.
>> Now that's not all that useful,
so I'm going to skip that
and I'm going to put away
this tip from Brady, and go
and plug-in instead
a question mark here.
So, just to be clear, what
should my second argument
be if someone has just logged in and I
want to check if he or she is actually
a user?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
I hear dollar sign underscore
GET quote, unquote username.
And that should return to me
any of the rows in my database
that have a username of Malan.
Now hopefully, I'm going to get back
zero if Malan's never been here,
or one if he has.
I shouldn't get back
two or three or four.
Why?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: I said unique, right?
Simple reason.
Because I said it's got to
be unique, just logically,
you can only have zero or one Malans
in this particular database table.
Now as an aside, just so you've seen
it, even though I keep using GET
and even though PSet6 only used
GET, you can certainly have POST.
And recall that Post is another
technique for submitting information
from a form, but it
doesn't show up in the URL.
It's a little more secure certainly for
things like usernames and passwords,
which PSet7 will, in fact, involve.
>> So, let's do this in PHP
MyAdmin and see what happens.
I'm going to go to MySQL tab.
And notice that the default value for
PHP MyAdmin, just to try to be helpful,
is to select star from users where one.
Well, one is always true, so
this has the silly effective
of just select everything.
But I'm going to be a little
more pedantic and manually
type out SELECT star FROM users.
>> Now technically, you can
quote the name of the tables.
It's rare that you have to,
but notice these are not
your normal quotes on the US keyboard.
This is the so-called backtick, which
is generally on the top left hand
corner of your keyboard.
But it's rare that you'll
actually need to bother with that,
so I'll just omit them anyway.
So now, let me go ahead and hit go.
And how many rows should I get
back when I select star from users?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: The number of rows, sure.
But how many in this
concrete story right now?
Two, because there was
me and there was Rob.
So, if I click Go, I see visually that
I've gotten back, indeed, two rows.
There's a lot of clutter on the
screen, but I only see two rows.
By contrast, if I do this again and do
SELECT star FROM users, where username
equals quote, unquote
Malan, now if I click Go,
I'm only going to get back one row.
And lastly, if I do
something like this, suppose
that I don't care about
getting everything,
which is kind of meaningless now,
because there's only two columns.
It's not like I'm selecting
a huge amount of data.
Suppose I go ahead and
do SELECT name FROM
users, where username equals Malan,
what's nice about SQL honestly,
is that it really just does
what you tell it to do.
It's pretty succinct, but you literally
just tell it what you want to do.
Select name from users where
the username equals Malan.
And it really is that explicit.
So, now if I hit Go, how many
rows am I going to get back?
One, because it's just Malan, hopefully.
Or zero if he's not
there, but one maximally.
>> And how many columns will I get back?
How many columns?
This time, I'm just going
to get one because I didn't
select star, which is everything.
Now I'm selecting just name, so I
just get back one column and one row.
And it looks sort of appropriately
ridiculous, just looking super
small like this.
So, what's really happening?
When you execute a SQL
query using select,
what you're getting
back from the database
is like a temporary table
with rows and columns, maybe,
but that omit anything that
wasn't actually selected by you.
So, it's like if someone had a big
spreadsheet of all the students
registered for some
student group, and you say,
give me all of the freshman who've
registered for our student group, what
your colleague in the
student group might do
is they could just hand
you the whole spreadsheet.
That's like saying select star.
And it's a little annoying if
you only wanted the freshman.
And so, if you instead said,
select star from database table
where year equals
quote, unquote freshman,
it's as though your friend
in the student group
literally highlighted and
copied only the freshman rows,
pasted them into a new Google
Spreadsheet or an Excel file,
and handed you back the
resulting file only.
That's all that's going
on conceptually here.
>> So in the end, we can do
some pretty fancy things
by storing things like usernames
and passwords and the like.
But, it turns out, we should do
a little differently than this.
It's not that smart to only
store a username and a password.
Someone earlier, I think
down here, suggested an ID.
Now an ID could be like a
Harvard ID or Yale's Net ID,
but it could be even simpler
in our database case.
And indeed, the common case
is to have another column.
And I'm going to go
ahead and edit my table.
And if you play around with
this interface for PSet7,
you'll see that you can check
this button here and add
a field at the beginning of the table.
And now if I click Go, it's going
to give me one of those forms
from earlier.
I'm going to add a field called ID.
And I'm going to make it a numeric type.
>> I have a whole bunch
of values for numerics.
I'm just going to choose an INT and
not worry about the disparate sizes.
I don't have to specify
a length or a value,
because it's going to be
32 bits no matter what.
Attributes, we didn't see before.
Any interest in any of these
menu options this time?
For an INT?
What did you propose?
No?
Do any of these make sense?
Yeah.
Yeah, unsigned, right?
>> Generally, if we're going to give
everyone a unique number, which
is where this story is
going, I really only want
a person to have the number like zero
and one and two and three and four.
I don't need to deal
with negative numbers.
It just seems like undue complexity.
I want four billion possible values,
not four billion possible values,
so I just doubled the
capacity of my INT.
As an aside, if you want to relate
this to something like Facebook,
back in sort of my day when
Facebook first came out,
I believe what they were
using in their MySQL database
to store a user's
identifier, was just an INT.
But of course, there's a lot
of real people in the world.
There's a lot of fake Facebook
accounts in the world.
And so eventually, Facebook overflowed
the size of an INT, a four billion
value.
Which is why, if you look
around and there's websites
that can tell you what
your unique ID is.
And if you never chose a username in
Facebook, you'll see your unique ID.
I think it's profile dot PHP
question mark ID equals something.
That is now something like a big
INT, or a long long if you will,
which is a 64-bit value
or something comparable.
>> So, even in the real world do these
issues ultimately sometimes matter.
And it turns out here, if I'm
giving all of my users a unique ID,
I want to be super explicit and
minimally make this field unique.
But it turns out there's one
piece of nomenclature today too
that's a primary key.
If you're designing a database
table and you know in advance
that one of the columns in that table
should and will uniquely identify rows
in the table, you want to
specify it and tell the database,
this is my primary key.
There might be duplicates
in other fields,
but I'm telling the database that this
is my primary, my most important field,
that's guaranteed to be unique.
>> Now, this seems redundant.
I am now proposing that we
add, by clicking Save here,
a field called-- and I'm going
to go ahead and click AI,
we'll come back to
that in a moment, Save.
I am proposing now that
my table look like this.
I have an INT field called ID,
a CHAR field called Username,
a VARCHAR field called Name, but ID,
if it's primary and therefore unique,
why did I just waste
time introducing what
effectively is a second unique
field called ID that's an INT?
>> Username, recall, was
already unique, we said.
So just logically, you don't need
any database experience to reason
through this, why
might I have introduced
an INT as my unique identifier as well?
What's this-- say again?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: Random
access is easier, why?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's
just accessing numbers.
So, if you think of this truly
is a table, like an array,
now I have unique identifiers
that I can jump around.
And better than that still is that
how big is an INT going to be again?
32 bits or four bytes.
>> How big is my username going to be?
Maximally?
16 bytes.
>> So, if you are really caring about
the performance of your code,
think back to PSet5, would you prefer
to search for a four byte value or a 16
byte value, right?
It really is as simple as that.
You have to do four times as much work
to search for usernames because those
are 16 bytes.
So, you have to literally
compare all 16 bytes to be
sure yes, this is username I want.
Whereas for an INT, you can
do it with just four bytes.
>> And as an aside for those
interested in computer hardware,
it turns out you can fit something like
an INT or a 32-bit value in something
called a register in a computer
CPU, which means it's super,
super fast, even at the lowest
level of the computer's hardware.
So, there's just advantages all around.
So, what does this mean?
In fact, when you're designing a
database table, almost all of the time
are you going to have not
only the data you care about,
but also something like
a unique identifier
because this is going to
let us do other things.
And let's trip over one problem here.
>> Suppose that users have not
just usernames and names,
but they also have things like cities
and states and zip codes, at least
here in the US.
So, I'm going to go ahead
and just quickly say,
give me three more columns
at the end of the table.
And this is going to be City,
this is going to be State,
and this is going to be Zip.
>> Now City, what data types
should this be, perhaps?
VARCHAR?
I don't know what the
longest name city is.
Somewhere in America, there's
probably some ridiculously long word,
so let's just go with 255, somewhat
historically or arbitrarily.
State, what you want to do?
Judgment call, right?
What's maybe the most efficient?
How many characters?
Maybe just two, if we can
get away with doing just,
like, MA for Massachusetts and so forth.
So, I'm going to go a CHAR value of two.
>> Zip code's an interesting one.
We're here in 02138, so that
suggests we should use what?
It's an INT, right?
INT, INT, short?
Short would work.
No?
CHAR or five, but I want an INT.
Why push back on an INT?
Persuade me from this.
What's stupid about an INT, my idea?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Take up more memory.
>> DAVID MALAN: Take up more memory.
Four bytes, but you're
proposing a zip code
as five bytes or someone was as a CHAR,
which feels like eh, that's not really
the case.
>> Well, fun story.
Years ago, when I used to use
Microsoft Outlook for my email,
I eventually wanted to switch to Gmail.
And so, I exported all of my
contacts from Outlook as a CSV file.
Comma separated values,
which just meant I
had all my friends names and last
names and phone numbers and zip codes
and all of that.
And then I made the
mistake of opening it up
in Excel, which is a
spreadsheet program that
understands CSV files as we've seen.
But then, I must have hit, like,
Command or Control S at one point.
And Excel apparently at the time
had a feature whereby any time it
saw a number, it tried to be helpful.
And if that number started with
zeros, it would just get rid of them.
Why do you need leading
zeros on integers?
They're meaningless, mathematically.
They're not meaningless
in the US Postal system.
So, I've had for years,
to this day, I still
have friends that when the
rare case that I need someone's
address these days,
I'll still see that I
have a friend in Cambridge,
Massachusetts, 2138.
And it's annoying if you're
trying to sort of programmatically
generate envelopes or just jot it down.
And that's because of this reason,
I chose the wrong data type.
So, I love your idea.
Let's use a CHAR field.
Five characters, except
there is a corner case.
If you still send mail,
sometimes zip codes these days,
they're, like, plus four.
So, we need a hyphen and then
we need four more numbers.
So to be honest, it could
go many different ways.
>> For now, I'm going to keep
it simple and I'm just
going to say that it's a
five CHAR value and we're
going to skip the whole dash plus four.
But these are the kinds of tradeoffs.
And you can think of the
same problems arising
with phone numbers or other fields.
>> And now, this is actually
a foolish road to go down.
Suppose both Rob and I and Hannah
and Maria and [? Davon ?] and Andy
and others on the staff all live
in Cambridge, Massachusetts, 02138.
This actually feel stupid that I'm
adding to my users table, city, state,
and zip.
Why?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: Say again?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: They're always
going to go together, right?
When it turns out, we used to think
this was the case until we exhaustively
searched the whole US,
and turns out that there
are some inconsistencies
where multiple towns have
the same zip, which is weird.
But, if we stipulate for now that 02138
is always Cambridge, Massachusetts,
why in the world would you store in
your database Cambridge and MA and 02138
for me and for Hannah and for Rob and
for [? Davon ?] and for others who live
here in Cambridge, it's
perfectly redundant.
>> We should get away
with just storing what?
Just the zip code.
But then, if we store just the
zip code, I do want, probably,
for my website to know where 02138 is.
So, I need another table.
And that's OK.
And in fact, this is one of the
design processes of designing tables
that you'll do in PSet7 as well whereby
you want to factor out common data.
Just like we've been factoring out
common code and factoring out common
styles from CSS, here
too in the database,
if I only need 02138 to uniquely
identify someone's hometown,
don't store Cambridge, Mass for
every darn user in your table.
>> Instead, have a separate table called
Zips that should have what columns?
Probably an ID field, just because, for
the principles we're talking about now.
Probably a zip field for 02138.
And then probably what other columns?
City and state, but only have one
row for 02138, one row for 02139,
one row for 90210.
And that is literally
all the zip codes I know.
>> So now, what can you do?
This is problematic, because
now I've got two tables.
So, my users are mostly over here,
but their city state information's
over here.
So, it turns out with SQL, there's
actually a way to join information,
and you'll see this in the PSet.
>> But it turns out you can
do something like this.
SELECT star FROM users, JOIN zips ON
users dot zip equals zips dot zip.
Which is a little wordy,
admittedly, but this just
means select everything from the
process of taking my users table
and my zips table.
Join them on the one
field they have in column.
So, literally doing something
like this, and give me back
a new temporary table
that's wider, that's bigger,
that has all of the
columns from both of them.
And that, quite simply, would be the
syntax for doing something like this.
>> So, there's this ahead,
but there's going
to be other design decisions you'll
have to make, not only with indexes
but also running into challenges.
In fact, there's a challenge
in any database design
whereby sometimes two people might want
to access the same rows of the database
table.
So, this is something that we'll
encounter in PSet7 as well.
>> But I thought I'd look at one
attack that's possible in SQL.
What are some of the
problems that can arise?
So, you'll encounter this in PSet7.
And we tell you outright what the
coding solution for this problem is.
But if you take a higher level class,
especially in operating systems,
you're going to encounter
an issue of atomicity,
the problem of trying to do
multiple things all at once
without interruption.
>> And I thought I'd introduce this
idea for PSet7 with a metaphor
that I learned myself in Margo
Seltzer's CS164 operating systems
class years ago.
Suppose that you have one of these dorm
fridges in your dorm room or house,
and you have a real penchant for milk.
And so, you come home from classes
one day, you open the fridge.
Oh, damn it.
There's no milk in the fridge.
So, you close the fridge,
lock the door, lock your dorm,
walk around the corner
to CVS, get in line,
and start checking out for some milk.
And it's going to take a while,
because those damn self checkout
counters take forever to use anyway.
So meanwhile, your roommate comes home.
He or she really likes milk as well.
They come into the dorm room,
open the fridge, oh, darn it.
There's no more milk.
>> So, he or she also
goes around the corner.
But now, since there's like two
or three or four CVSes nearby,
they happen to go to one of the
different ones in the square.
And so now, a few minutes
later, both of you
come home and ugh, worst problem ever.
Now you have too much milk
because it's going to go sour.
And you like milk, but you
don't really like milk.
>> So now, this was an expensive
mistake because both of you
made a decision based on the
state of some variable that
was in the process of
being changed by you,
the initiator of going to get milk.
So, what is perhaps a human
solution to that problem?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Leave a note, right?
Always leave a note, if you're
familiar with that show.
Yes, there are two of us.
So, always leave a note, or
literally lock the refrigerator
with some kind of padlock or
something over the top like that.
But that's actually going to be
key problem with database design,
especially when you might have
multiple browsers, multiple laptops,
multiple users all trying to
update information at once.
Particularly sensitive information
like financial information,
whereby with a stock trading
website like you'll be building,
what if you want to check how much money
you have and then if you have enough,
buy some stock?
>> But what if someone else who
has a joint account with you
is simultaneously trying
to buy some stock?
So, he or she is checking the
account balance, both of you
get back the same
answer, there's no milk.
Or both of you get back the answer,
you have $100 in the account.
Both of you try to make the decision
to buy one share of some company stock.
>> And now, what happens?
You have two shares?
You have no shares?
Problems like that can arise.
So, we'll encounter that.
SQL injection attacks, thankfully,
are something we'll help you with,
but these are atrociously
common these days still.
So, this is just an example.
I make no claims that
Harvard PIN system is
vulnerable to this particular attack.
We've tried.
But, you know that we
have a field like this.
And Yale's Net ID has a similar
looking screen these days.
And it turns out, that maybe the
PIN system is implemented in PHP.
>> And if it were-- it's not-- they
might have code that looks like this.
They have two variables.
Give me the username and password
from the post super global variable
that we talked about earlier.
Maybe Harvard has a query
like SELECT star FROM users
where username equals that
and password equals that.
And notice that I'm just
plugging it in using
the curly brace notation from the other
day, which means just plug in a value
here.
I'm not using the
question mark technique.
I don't have any second
or third arguments.
I'm just literally
constructing the string myself.
>> The problem, though, is that
if someone like a scroob,
which is a reference to a film,
logs in with something like this,
and I've removed the dots
that usually cover up
passwords, what if he is
particularly malicious
and his password maybe is 12345,
per the movie called "Spaceballs,"
but he critically types a
single quote after the five,
then literally the word or
in the space, and then quote,
unquote one equals quote one,
but notice he's omitted what?
He's omitted the quote on the right
and he's omitted the quote on the left.
>> Because if this attacker
scroob's presumption
is that the people who wrote
this PHP code weren't so bright,
maybe they just have some single
quotes around the interpolation
of a variable in curly braces?
And so maybe, he could kind
of complete their thought
for them, but in a way that's going
to let him hacked into the PIN system.
In other words, suppose
that this is the code
and we now plug in what scroob typed.
And it's red, because it's bad.
>> And the underlying text
is what he typed in,
scroob could trick Harvard's server
into constructing a SQL query
string that looks like this.
Password equals 12345 or one equals one.
The result of which, logically,
is that this will log scroob
in if his password is
12345 or if one equals
one, which is of course always true,
which means scroob always gets in.
>> And so, the way to fix
this, as in a lot of cases,
would be to write more defensively.
To use something like our
actual query function, which
you'll see in PSet7, where we plug in
something like question marks here.
And the beauty of the
query function that we
give you is it defends against these
so-called SQL injection attacks, where
someone is tricking your code into
injecting his or her own SQL code.
Because what the query function
we give you will actually do,
if you use the question mark syntax
and a second and a third argument here,
is what did it add to the
input that the user provided?
Those backslash quotes.
>> So, it escapes any potentially
dangerous characters.
This looks weird now,
but it's not vulnerable
because it doesn't
change the logic anymore
because that whole password is
now a single quote that's not,
in fact, scroob's password.
So, there's been some jokes
about this over the years.
So, this was a photo taken
of some geek in a parking lot
whereby you might know that some cities
and states try to scan your license
plate to bill you or to ticket you
if you go through without, like,
the E-Z Pass thing.
So, this person presumed that maybe
the people writing the E-Z Pass system
were not so bright, and maybe they
just concatenated together a string,
so that he or she couldn't maliciously
not just complete their thought,
but actually execute a bad command,
which we've not mentioned yet,
but you can probably guess.
That in addition to delete and
insert and update and select,
there's also a keyword called drop,
which literally deletes everything
in the database, which
is particularly bad.
>> We can zoom in on this if
it's a little tough to see.
This, now, is a famous cartoon
that's wonderfully clever now
and understandable.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> Yeah, cool.
Kind of geeking out.
So these, then, are
SQL injection attacks.
And they're so easy to avoid by using
the right code or the right libraries.
And you'll see in PSet7, that's
why we give you the query function.
So, a couple of teasers
that we thought we'd
give you here in our
remaining minutes together.
So, as you remember from week zero, we
introduced these two light bulbs which
are nice, not just because
they're pretty and are colorful,
but because they support something
called an API, an Application
Programming Interface And
in CS50 thus far, we've
mostly focused on GET and
POST, but it turns out
there's other HTTP verbs like PUT.
>> And in fact, this was
a slide from week zero
whereby if you write code that sends
a la PSet6 an HTTP request that
looks like this with this chunk of text
at the bottom, which is called JSON,
or JavaScript Object Notation
that we'll talk about next week,
you can turn on or turn off or change
the color of lights like those.
So if CS50 also has in addition to some
of those light bulbs here in New Haven
if you'd like to borrow
them for final projects,
also some Microsoft
Bands, which are like
watches that you wear around your wrist
that similarly have an API so that you
can write your own software for them.
>> We have an account with
Apple's iOS code so
that if you have an Apple Watch or
an iPhone or an iPad or an iPod,
you can write code that
actually runs on those.
We have a whole bunch
of Arduinos, which are
tiny little computers
without cases, essentially,
that you can connect via USB,
typically to your own Mac or PC,
write code that runs on these physical
devices that often have sensors on them
so you can interact with the real world.
We have a whole bunch
of Leap Motion devices,
which are USB devices for Macs and
PCs, here and again, in New Haven.
And if you connect it to your Mac,
you can actually control your computer
by writing software
that via infrared beams,
figures out where your human hands are,
even without touching your keyboard.
We thought we'd share a quick
glimpse at this, for instance.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
So, we have a whole
bunch of these things,
too, called Myo arm bands
which you put over your forearm
and then you can control the real
world or the virtual world like this.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
Or, we also have some Google
Cardboard, which is literally, like,
a cardboard box you could put on your
face, but slide in your phone into it
so that you put the glass of your
phone really close to your eyes.
And Google Cardboard is
pretty cheap at $10 or $20.
And it has little lenses
that slightly off shift
the image on the screen for your human
eyes to give you a sense of depth
so that you actually have a 3D
environment in front of you.
We also have some Samsung Gear, which
is the more expensive version of this,
but that can similarly slide in an
Android phone and give you the illusion
of-- or give the experience
of virtual reality .
And in our final two minutes,
we thought we'd try to do this.
If I can project what Colton has
here just to whet your appetite,
let me go ahead and throw
up on the big screen here.
Let me kill the lights.
Colton, do you want to go ahead
and put on your cell for a moment
and come on over to the
middle of the stage?
And do you want to project--
this is what Colton sees.
>> Now, the Wi-Fi in here is
not so strong for this device
that this is super compelling,
but Colton is literally
in this magical futuristic place.
He only sees one image.
You are seeing his left and right eye
that his brain are stitching together
in a three dimensional
environment on his face.
He's just selected a menu option here.
And so again, he's wearing this headset
with a Samsung phone on it that's
wirelessly projecting to our overhead.
Now you're on Mars, I think?
COLTON: I think so.
I'm not sure [INAUDIBLE].
[LAUGHTER]
>> DAVID MALAN: Turns out
Mars has these menus.
>> COLTON: [INAUDIBLE] some cool
places if we want to go to--
>> DAVID MALAN: Where do we want to go?
>> COLTON: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: And let's see
where Colton's taking us now.
COLTON: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID MALAN: So, there's so many
different places you can take yourself.
There's FAPIs via which you can
write games or interactions that
run, ultimately, on the phone.
So, you really just
writing a mobile phone app.
But thanks to the software
and the graphics capabilities,
now Colton is in this
tiny little cottage.
And at the risk of
overwhelming ourselves,
Colton and I'll stick around for
while at the end of class here today
if you'd like to come up and play.
And we'll bring them
back next week as well.
Without further, ado
that's it for today.
We'll see you next week.
>> [MUSIC - RAGGA TWINS, "BAD MAN"]