>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: This is CS50.
This is the end of week nine, and we
have so much fun stuff to do today.
And in fact, not only are we going
to demonstrate some three dimensional
technology for you in virtual
reality with a very special guest,
we're also shooting today's
lecture in virtual reality.
In three dimensions with a camera
here, with a set of cameras here.
And so just so that we can approximate
the experience of having one of you
come up on stage, could one of
you actually come up on stage?
Standing in-- let's go right here.
I think I saw your hand among the first.
>> Come on up.
What's your-- [AUDIO OUT].
Arianna.
Come on up and-- [AUDIO OUT] What
I'm going to do is you come on up
is throw onto our screen
over here-- what the headset
that Colton has ready for you.
Nice to see you.
And if you want to go
ahead and put this on.
Colton, what do we have that Arianna
is going to be putting before her eyes?
>> COLTON: You're going to be
watching a movie trailer.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: A movie trailer.
And as I recall, this is a
fairly scary movie trailer.
ARIANNA: Really?
DAVID J. MALAN: For at
least one of us in the room.
No one saw that.
All right.
And in a moment it should be
projecting onto Colton's laptop an
in turn the screen here.
Let me go over here to that input,
and here's what Arianna seeing.
So she sees it as one image, whereas
we see it, of course, in two.
Left eye and right eye.
Let me go ahead and I'll
toss it on the overhead too,
even though it's a little bright.
>> In this virtual reality there's a big
play button in the middle of the room.
>> COLTON: Make sure it's highlighted.
Hit the play button.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: There you go.
>> COLTON: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, we're hitting Play.
It's very scary.
Very scary movie.
Here we go.
All right.
Loading.
Loading the very scary room.
COLTON: So now you should
just be in a dark room.
DAVID J. MALAN: Now
she is in a black room,
which is scary and very realistic.
There we go.
All right.
Go ahead and look around.
The wi-fi's being a
little slow for us here.
Oh, that's scary.
Who's she?
Very scary menu keeps coming up too,
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> Notice that it certainly
figures out where she's going.
Time is passing.
Something very creepy.
Oh, my goodness.
Blood in the shape of the movie's logo.
And I think if we wait long
enough, Arianna, something
will start crawling toward you.
You see it yet?
ARIANNA: Yeah.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
There we go.
That can't be good.
OK, careful.
Now you're going to-- [INAUDIBLE]
a big round of applause.
Sorry.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> It's me.
It's me.
OK, thank you to Arianna for coming up.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> We'll show you--
We'll see if we can share
some of that footage with you.
So let's take a quick look at a couple
of announcements, a couple of examples,
and then we'll turn the stage over to
our friend, Professor Peter Manuelian,
who's going to talk to us today
about the use of technology
and the application of computer
science to the world of archaeology
in just a bit.
So first, doughnuts are
available today at 4:00 PM
if you are hungry for that, and
advice about concentrating in or doing
a secondary in computer science.
Maxwell Dworkin is just down
the road at 33 Oxford Street.
Do feel free to join a bunch of
the staff and CS concentrators
and faculty for some tips.
>> So recall that last time we left
off with a somewhat technical topics
but that syntactically are
pretty easily implemented.
One was an anonymous function, and
the name kind of says what it means.
But just in relative layman's terms,
what is an anonymous function?
>> [LOUD NOISE]
>> That was scary.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
It literally is that.
It's a function to which
you don't give a name.
And that seems a little weird because
if it has no name, how do you call it?
How do you call a
function that has no name?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Bind it to an event.
So this is a fancy way of saying you
tell the [? web ?] browser in advance
that when something interesting
happens, call this function.
And in fact, there's another buzz word
for this, which is simply a callback.
So indeed a callback
function is a function
that gets called when some data is
ready or when some event has happened.
And so in particular,
when we did something
like an [? oncommit ?]
handler or an onclick handler,
you might actually want some function
to get called when that event happens.
And it doesn't matter what
its name so long as you
told the browser in advance
what function to call
and how that code should look,
which we'll see again in a moment.
>> And we'll also now take a
look at one other topic, Ajax,
which once upon a time stood for
Asynchronous JavaScript and XML
but now it stands for really just a more
general technology or technique whereby
a browser, by way of JavaScript,
can request more data from a server
even after the web page
has initially loaded.
So you're not using Ajax in pset seven.
Every time you click a button
or hit Enter or fill out a form
and then send it to the server,
the whole page is refreshing,
the URL is probably changing, and
some dynamic output is happening.
In problem set eight we'll use
JavaScript and a bit of Ajax
as well so that things happen much more
seamlessly and a lot less deliberately
step by step by step.
>> But first, let's take
a look at JavaScript
by way of this super simple example.
This is just a web page where
I've got a big div in the middle
of the page and really big text.
And with what language did I
probably make the text really big?
HTML, but in CSS.
CSS properties allow me
to specify really big.
I could specify colors or
any number of other things.
>> But back in the day--
actually, around the time I
was making those terrific personal
websites I showed you on Monday--
there was actually an HTML tag called
the blink tag, whose purpose in life
was to do exactly that.
If you do open tag blink,
some text, close tag blink,
the text would just blink on the screen.
So web pages in the
'90s did a lot of this.
Literally.
>> Worse yet, there was a marquise
tag whereby your text would just
scroll across the screen As though
that was a good idea as well.
So amazingly, one of the few things that
browser manufacturers like Microsoft
and Mozilla and Google
have actually agreed on
is to kill off tags like that.
So they don't then exist any longer,
but if we're really insistent
we could probably re-implement this.
>> So let me show you the bottom of
a file here called blink.html.
And there's obviously some HTML here,
and it's a pretty simple web page.
Indeed, there's that div I mentioned.
I've given it a unique identifier so
that either in CSS or in JavaScript
I can uniquely refer to it so that I'm
not confusing it with any other divs
if there were actually any.
And now notice at the top I've got
a style tag in the head of the page,
though I could certainly factor that
out and put it in a styles.css file
as you have in pset seven.
>> And this just why it's big.
It's 96 point, it's got a big margin
around it which pushes it down
toward the middle, and
it's aligned in the center.
But now, I've also got
a script tag up top.
And even though some
of the syntax is new,
let's take a look at how we
could re-implement this atrocity
from years past known as the blink tag.
So here's a function,
and I have named it.
So it's not an anonymous
function in this case,
but it does have a name blank.
Takes no arguments.
Now this first line here is
the first interesting one.
And what is this return to me?
On the left hand side it gives
me a variable called div,
and what is that div ultimately?
How would you describe this to
a somewhat technical roommate?
What is that line of code doing?
What's that line of code doing?
So it declares a variable
on the left called div,
and then what is the right hand
side of the expression return?
What's a good way to think about it?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Say again?
>> AUDIENCE: The value stored in greeting.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: The
value stored in greeting.
Not quite.
So if you think of the HTML
page as a tree in memory,
the so-called dom or
document object model
whereby you just have a whole bunch--
like a family tree draped down
from some root node.
The element that has an ID is
literally referring to the HTML element
down here that has an ID of greeting.
So if you think of this div tag
as being a node in a tree, what
get element by ID is doing quite
simply is returning to you,
if we were using C, a pointer
to that node in the tree.
A pointer to that node
in your data structure.
We don't have pointers anymore.
Now we just think of things more
higher level, like variables,
but stored in div right now with
some kind of reference or pointer
to that node in the tree.
Now this is interesting
because that's the node
that we want to make blink on or off.
On or off.
And we have a technique for
changing the style of a tag,
of course, which is CSS.
And what's nice today is
that we see that there's
this bridge between
JavaScript and CSS whereby
you can use JavaScript to change the
CSS properties of existing elements.
You don't have to hard code
all of your CSS in advance.
You can actually dynamically change
the aesthetics of your page as follows.
>> Notice here, and you might not have
ever seen this property before,
but it turns out in CSS there's
a property called visibility.
And for reasons that have never been
clear to me, the opposite of hidden
is visible and the
opposite of visible is
hidden, as opposed to it
being invisible but so be it.
But what I'm doing here is I'm checking.
If div.style.visibility-- so we've
seen this dot notation a lot,
and it's common in JavaScript because
objects like these nodes that we're
talking about have properties.
And those properties might
have properties inside of them.
So relate it to data.
>> So if that div style has a visibility
property that equals hidden,
what do I want to do if I
want to make this thing blink
and that div is currently hidden?
I want to make it visible.
Else, if it's not hidden-- ergo it's
visible-- I want to make it hidden.
So these six or so lines of code
here-- eight lines of code--
simply have the effect of making
something hidden or visible.
Hidden or visible.
But just once because
there's no kind of loop here,
so it doesn't feel like
it's blinking quite yet.
>> But down here, notice
I've got this line.
It turns out that built into browsers,
and JavaScript specifically, there
is a global variable called window.
And we've seen another
global variable called
document, which we used a moment ago.
There's another one called
window that generally refers not
to the contents of the page but just
the general idea of the whole browser
window.
And window.setInterval, you can
kind of guess what this means.
It's going to do something maybe
cyclically every some number
of milliseconds apparently,
according to my comment?
>> So in English I'm saying,
blink every 500 milliseconds.
But a little more technically, what
is this highlighted line of code
telling the browser to do?
It's making it blink, but why?
What's it doing technically?
Yeah?
No?
[? Put that instead. ?] Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
It's calling a function every 500
milliseconds, or half a second,
and that function is called blink.
And so recall on Monday that we said
that just like variables, functions,
because they have names or
symbols associated with them,
you can pass those around just
like their pieces of data as well.
So here we're just saying,
hey, browser window.
Set the following interval.
Every 500 milliseconds
call that function.
And the browser doesn't even
have to care what the function is
so long as it's defined somewhere.
>> So the net effect, if I go ahead and
save this and go back to this page
and reload now that I've
enabled that function,
is that this is literally what a lot
of websites looked like in the 1990s.
You reach here.
Hello.
Welcome to my creepy web page,
as I recall, it was on Monday.
So the goal here is not to
re-implement the blink tag
but to show this convergence between
JavaScript, a language, and CSS,
this sort of stylization.
But now let's do something
a little more interesting.
>> In problem set seven,
you have already been
or will soon be implementing a quote
page, whereby you can type in a stock
symbol, hit Submit, and
then the page reloads
and you see a share of Google costs
such and such dollars or something
like that.
And that's not Ajax.
That's just HTTP.
A form submits from one page to
another, and you get back a response.
But what if I wanted a
slightly more elegant approach?
Let me go ahead and type in
goog and click Get Quote.
Now, this is not the prettiest
user interface to be sure,
but notice that just like on
Monday, I got this pop up.
But the contents of that pop
up, though wordy, tell me
that the price is apparently $731.37.
Not all that elegant, but let's
see a slightly better example.
>> Let me now go to version
one of this, if I may.
Version one looks like this.
Same very ugly form.
But if I type in goog
here-- so similarly,
it's just giving me this prompt.
But we can make it even prettier.
So this is a little more interesting.
I clearly didn't put all that
much effort into the aesthetics,
but this is much more akin now to what
Gmail would do or Facebook would do.
You don't get some stupid pop up.
Instead, the contents of the
existing page change like that.
>> So what's going on?
If I go ahead and reload this page,
the contents go back to the default
and I can do something like
FB for Facebook, Get Quote,
and it looks that up as well.
So what's going on?
Well, let me go into Ajax0.html
and first look at the HTML part.
So notice, like Monday, I'm using
the on submit handler, or on submit
event handler, but we've seen
other ways of doing this.
So we're just keeping
things simple for now.
And on submit is telling me, call
the quote function then return false.
And just a sanity check.
Why return false?
What does that prevent?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: The whole
page from reloading,
which would put us back into pset
seven territory, which is not the goal.
We're trying to make things a little
better, a little more seamless
for the user.
So now I just have HTML,
and it's kind of long.
It wraps over the edge
of the screen there,
but I've got an input whose type,
if I keep scrolling, is text.
But what's important is that
it has a unique ID of symbol,
and then I have a Submit button.
So this is the very first version.
>> But if I now scroll up-- let's
take a look at the quote function.
It's kind of neat that now, if
you understand or are reasonably
comfortable with HTTP
from pset six or prior,
all that we need to
do really intuitively
is create a URL that contains
the symbol we want to look up.
>> So it turns out that
I wrote in advance--
and we won't look at the code for this,
but I wrote in advance a file called
quote.php that works as follows.
Let me go back into my file directory.
It's not going to work if I just click
on it, but if I go up to my URL here
and go to quote.php and I do
question mark symbol equals goog
and then hit Enter, notice
that I get just this back.
It's not a web page.
It's just text.
But it's text that's formatted
in an interesting way.
What format is this text, if you recall?
JSON.
JavaScript Object Notation.
And so it's just a bunch
of key value pairs.
It's a little hard to read
when it's a long line,
but I see a bunch of quotes
and colons and curly braces,
and that's just the general structure
of associating one piece of data
with one particular value.
>> So if I now have a file called quote.php
that clearly, much like pset six,
supports very simple HTTP get
requests, what if in JavaScript I
use my budding skills
with this new language,
construct a URL that
looks exactly like that,
and behind the scenes send
a request from my browser
to the server to get that JSON data?
And that's exactly what we do here.
>> So here's my quote function.
I'm declaring a variable called URL.
On the right hand side
I'm using single quotes,
but you could use double quotes as well.
Notice I'm doing quote, unquote--
that's no pun intended--
quote.php?symbol equals.
And then, even if you're not
quite familiar with this syntax,
and indeed most of
you wouldn't be-- this
is using that special
library called jQuery
that you'll see more
on in online resources,
perhaps in the final project.
What am I concatenating onto question
mark symbol equals apparently?
Just generally speaking.
>> AUDIENCE: The symbol.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, the symbol.
Whatever the human typed into the form.
That is apparently the code in
JavaScript for going into my HTML page,
finding whatever element, whatever
tag, has a unique ID of symbol,
and this hashtag in HTML
just means the unique ID.
So whatever element has a unique
ID of symbol that means go get it.
And .val is a jQuery
function, it turns out,
that just says give me
the value of that field.
>> And then finally, and the
syntax is a little funky--
so it turns out that jQuery, this
library to which I keep referring,
literally has a special
global variable called jQuery.
But it turns out in JavaScript,
somewhat confusingly,
the dollar sign is not a special symbol,
whereas in PHP it's a special symbol.
If you have something with a dollar
sign it means it's a variable.
In JavaScript, a dollar sign
is just like A, B, C, or Z.
It's just a letter of the alphabet
that you can use in variables.
So the people who invented
jQuery just thought
it would be kind of cool to lay claim
to a global variable called dollar sign,
but it just is an alias for jQuery.
>> So $.getJSON is calling a function
that comes with this popular library,
whose purpose in life is to go get
JSON data, issue an HTTP request,
and get back the response.
The first argument is apparently the URL
from which you want to get that data,
and the second argument, just to tie
things together, is apparently what?
Generally speaking?
What kind of function
is this, if you will?
Yeah, an anonymous function
because there's no name.
And using another piece of jargon
from today, it's also a call back.
>> And the purpose here is
that the web can be slow,
and just because you ask
JavaScript and the browser
to go get you some data
from a website via HTTP get,
it could take half a second,
it could take five seconds
if your internet
connection is really slow.
And you don't want the
whole web page to just hang
and some stupid spinning
beach ball to come up,
blocking the user from doing
absolutely everything else.
>> And so the way JavaScript works is
that it's generally asynchronous,
whereby you can do
multiple things at a time
so long as you tell the
browser, hey, browser, when
you are done getting this JSON data.
Even if it takes five
seconds, call this function.
Don't make the user wait.
Don't hang the browser
until this happens.
Rather, call me back,
almost like a phone call,
when you're ready and
have the data for me.
Now what does that function do?
It's super trivial.
All it does is it displays
the data that comes back,
and specifically the price
field inside of an alert.
That's all.
And so that's why, to be clear,
when we go to this example, which
was [? Ajax0 ?] and I typed in goog and
hit Enter, I got this simple, simple
little prompt.
Now it turns out we
can make this better.
And our final example here changes
the quote function as follows.
It's almost identical, but this
was that new and fancy version
whereby I had a placeholder.
This was version two.
And instead of just printing
some silly prompt like that,
I instead changed my actual web page.
And to be clear, let me go
into Chrome's Inspector.
Let me go down to the bottom here.
And notice, if I zoom in on this bottom
part, this is the HTML of the page
currently.
And notice that right now I've
got a span, which is like a div
but it's a thinner div, if you will.
A span whose ID is priced that
literally says, to be determined.
>> If I go into this form, type
FB, and click Get Quotes,
watch the bottom of the page.
The actual HTML of the page changes.
So this is like when you get a Facebook
message and it suddenly pops up,
or a new Gmail row in your inbox.
That's literally what's happening.
Someone wrote JavaScript
code at Facebook or Google
that actually changes the web
page that you have already
downloaded to reflect that new content.
>> And if you really want to be fancy and
understand this, noticed what happened.
Let me reload again
and clear all of this.
And now notice I'm on
Chrome's Network tab.
If I do FB here and click Get
Quote, notice just ala pset six,
you can see the HTTP request, and
you can see that my browser requested
quote.php?symbol equals something.
And then if I scroll down here,
if you really want to geek out,
you can see all of the HTTP headers that
my server, Cloud 9, has returned to me.
It's more headers than you guys
were spitting out for pset six
because we kept it simple, but in
there is a whole bunch of information,
among which is that 200 OK message.
And below that's going to be the JSON.
And so all we needed to do to make this
happen is tweak my quote function ever
so slightly.
>> Instead of calling the pretty lame
alert function, I simply do this.
Which admittedly, syntactically it
looks frightening at first glance
because there's so much
new syntax going on.
But the ideas are pretty simple.
This means, hey, browser, go
call the special jQuery function
that returns to me a pointer to or
a reference to the node in my tree
whose unique identifier is price.
That's that placeholder.
Then it turns out that jQuery comes
with a special function called .html,
whereby if you want to update the
contents of a node in your tree,
you literally just grab that
node, you call the HTML function,
and you hand it whatever you want.
>> So if I wanted to be
sort of silly here I
could do something like ha ha, nothing
here, save it, go back over here,
and now if I click Get Quote up top
left, you just get something-- whoops.
If I reload the page
and search for Facebook,
you get something stupid like that.
But I'm dynamically changing
the content [INAUDIBLE].
Any questions?
>> SPEAKER 1: Stop touching your mic.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: The team
is telling me to stop
touching my mic which keeps
falling out of my ear,
so it's just as well that
we're out of material here
and we have time now
for our special guest.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: If there's an opportunity
to change the actual HTML of the page,
does that make it
vulnerable to an exploit?
DAVID J. MALAN: If there's
not-- say that again?
AUDIENCE: Since there's an opportunity
to change the actual HTML of the page,
does it make it
vulnerable to an exploit?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, yes.
So because you are able to
change the HTML of a page,
is it vulnerable
potentially to an exploit?
Potentially yes.
If you're not sanitizing your inputs
or [? scaping ?] them in the right way,
absolutely could you end up triggering
theft of cookies, which is actually
a good segue to what we'll
be talking about on Monday,
which is security topics.
And indeed, that's going to be
one of the exploits we discuss.
Tricking a browser into
injecting something malicious
into its source code.
Any other questions?
>> All right.
Well, I'm so excited today.
So I did my PhD in
computer science, but about
halfway through my degree
in computer science
my eye started wondering
academically and so I
started taking-- I think as an auditor
or non-credit status-- anthropology
1010.
It was me the grad student and a whole
bunch of freshman and sophomores here.
But it was amazing class
ever, and to this day
I continue to subscribe to archaeology
magazine, which comes once a month,
and sort of introduces me to what's
going on in the world of yesteryear.
>> And we're so happy today to have our
friend, Professor Peter Manuelian,
to talk to us about the convergence of
computer science and the application
thereof to this amazing
field of archaeology.
Professor Manuelian.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> PETER MANUELIAN: Thank you, sir.
Great privilege to be on
this stage with the maestro.
Thanks so much for having me here today.
I'm going to try to show a little bit
of a real world application of some
of the skills that you've already
been amassing this semester
and to try to get you excited
about the human past as well.
So we're going to go
to my favorite place,
outside of Harvard Square, of course,
which is the Giza Pyramids, just
west of modern Cairo.
And if you're wondering what BCE
stands for, it's before computer era.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> So three pyramids built by three
famous pharaohs of Egypt's Old Kingdom
or fourth dynasty.
Think about 2,500 or so.
But what's all around them are
hundreds and hundreds of tombs as well.
So think of Giza as
two amazing data sets.
One data set is what's still there.
These incredible tombs
surrounding the pyramids that
have these amazing decorations inside.
There are statues, they
are inscriptions-- frozen
moments, if you will, of just about
every aspect of life in ancient Egypt.
So anything you want to study come here.
It's not just a cemetery
full of dead people.
It's a document on how the Egyptians
lived, and as well as how they died.
So that's the data set out at the site.
>> The other one, of course, is
everything that came from Giza.
Things you'll see in the
Peabody Museum, things
you'll see in the Museum of Fine
Arts, and in museums and collections
all over the world.
It's mummies, it's statues,
it's steely, it's jewelry,
it's objects of daily life.
All kinds of cool stuff.
>> So what makes this place so special is
that right here at Harvard University
this is the major excavation that
worked at the site of the Giza Pyramids.
And this is the guy who did it,
my predecessor George Reisner.
1867 to 1942.
Died at the pyramids in the
middle of the Second World War.
And if you're wondering
where this photo was taken,
this class photograph, at the end of
class leave by that door, go out there,
and yes, you'll see right
outside this theater,
right against the wall-- that's where
class photos were taken in that day.
>> So an amazing individual, one of the
greatest archaeologists of his time,
way ahead of his time in many ways,
and this is what's called Harvard Camp.
It was a collection of simple mud
brick huts to the west of the pyramids.
And in the courtyard at any particular
day you would see amazing things,
and people came to discuss with the
master about all sorts of topics.
Here are pieces of giant statues.
You can see those in the
Museum of Fine Arts today.
And down below is our computer
model of Harvard Camp.
That's something you might
want to get involved with.
If you're searching for a final project,
some kind of simulation or website
introduction to Harvard
Camp, the dig site.
>> By the time George Reisner was done,
the Harvard University Boston Museum
of Fine Arts expedition
worked at 23 different sites.
All the ones that you see in red here.
So 40 years, 23 sites.
He only came back here to teach
about three or four semesters
over that whole time, so you know
what he enjoyed doing the most.
>> What happens with the massive
archaeological backlog
that a responsible expedition produces?
So 45,000 glass plate
dig photos, diaries,
register books, maps, plans,
small drawings, big drawings,
thousands of pages of manuscripts--
some published books, some unpublished.
All this stuff.
And this is where the computer and the
databases and the websites come in.
How do you organize all of this?
Try to get a travel grant to Boston and
in a couple of days study this stuff.
You will be overwhelmed.
>> So this is a project that
I started way back in 2000,
and the team here at Harvard
has been working on it ever
since the last several years.
First at the MFA, the
museum, and now at Harvard.
What we had to do is look at
Giza as one big Manhattan.
One gridded site.
And thanks to Reisner,
he numbered all the tombs
in a wonderfully systematic manner.
So we're looking from the air
down at the three pyramids here,
and we realize that it's not even enough
just to master this one expedition.
The areas you see in red are
the Harvard expedition sites,
but the German Austrian
expedition worked
there-- those are the blue areas--
and the Egyptians dug as well.
>> So holistically, trying to understand
an ancient site in all of its functions
and all of its
chronological development,
you've got to take the whole place.
So that sent me on a worldwide tour
with all the colleagues in Egyptology
and the museums at all
these places and gathering
all of their diaries, their photographs,
their documents, their notes--
gathering it at all here
electronically at Harvard.
And the next step is.
How do we put this all together?
>> This is sort of our site
map, and right in the middle
is an individual tomb known
in Arabic as a [? mastaba, ?]
this sort of bench like shape.
And so for every tomb, you've got
x number of this type of data.
So many old photographs, so many objects
registered in the register books.
Diary entries that mention that tomb.
Objects found, drawings
made, plans and sections,
published books on published books,
and more recently, visualization.
3D computer models.
>> And there's just a
sample of an aggregation
of a search for a particular monument.
You see all the different things
that are gathered together.
1,012 finds, 45 diary pages that
mention this particular temple.
Ancient people, modern people,
publications, the whole bit.
Downloadable PDFs all gathered
together from a SQL database.
Why is this important?
Just take the comparison of
these two images then and now.
This is happening at Giza, this
is happening all over Egypt,
and more dramatically, happening
all over the Middle East.
And sometimes not by accident,
not the elements of time,
but obviously intentional damage.
>> Let me ask you, which
of these two things
you're going to be able to
read in a couple of years?
Which one of these will survive?
Which one will have a device that can
access it in a couple of years time?
So I think the Egyptians
got something right here.
Put it on stone.
We can still translate
the hieroglyphs there.
I'll bet you anything
this hard drive is going
to fail sometime in the near future.
So maybe they understood
something that we didn't.
So that's why we've got
to preserve this stuff.
>> And from all the databases,
all the aggregations
and the websites and things, the natural
next step, of course, is visualization.
Put you at the site.
Give you access in 3D to some of these
tombs and temples that you might not
be able to see otherwise.
It's a research tool, it's a
teaching tool, it's edutourism,
it's even edutainment.
And a lot of this goes back
to the really simple stuff.
You see that old, wooden stereo
viewer in 3D photography?
Just what we were seeing
a little bit before.
It's the same principle, right?
We're just putting it
together with things
like GoPro cameras over here and
Gear VR and Oculus Rift headsets,
and anything is possible now.
>> So we're moving from teaching in special
customized classrooms-- visualization
center labs.
We have one above the
Geological Lecture Hall.
Now we're trying to
bring it to the people.
Get it into these headsets.
So imagine all of you or
everyone watching live
or everyone in HarvardX
donning one of these headsets
and we're all standing together
in front of the Sphinx,
listening to someone like
me drone on all about it.
And we're all there in real time
able to look around in 360 degrees.
You can kill the audio on that.
We don't need it on the model.
I'm going to show you how we can go from
visualization and a visualized world
to a real physical world too.
This is a find that George
Reisner made at Giza right
beside the Great Pyramid in 1925.
And way down at the bottom
of 100 foot deep burial shaft
there was an unfinished room with
millions of bits of tiny fragments.
All the wood had decayed.
It was a real mass.
So the photos you're seeing show
the original condition of that tomb,
and now we're going into
our 3D computer model.
And we're able, thanks to
meticulous documentation,
to put that whole tomb's
contents together.
>> And you see all this furniture-- that
curtain box and chairs and tables.
I want you to focus on that chair
that has the falcon arms there.
So this material was actually
reconstructed in modern wood,
and it's on display in
the Cairo Museum and used
to be on display in the Boston MFA,
although they've taken it off view
to use that gallery for something else.
Nobody, however, has
been able to reconstruct
that fancy chair with the falcon arms.
Thanks to this computer
model and this simulation,
though, we can actually
start to do that.
>> So in the upper left you
see the reproductions
of some of that furniture.
And it turns out to belong to a queen.
Not any queen, but the mother of the
king who built the Great Pyramid--
Queen Hetepheres.
Big, mysterious burial.
All this stuff deteriorated.
What do we make of it?
But we were able to
take our computer model
and reproduce this chair with
the beautiful falcon arms.
So now you're seeing this
rotating 3D of the model.
Then we decided to go to the real world.
>> We looked at photographs of all
the teensy, tinsy fragments.
The gold, the gilding, the [INAUDIBLE]
inlay tiles, the desecrated wood.
All of this is on trays in the
basement of the Cairo Museum.
And from there, we were able
to move to a shop bot, which
is a 3D milling machine or router.
And you can see a simple [? Mac ?] with
a 3D model is driving the drill here,
and it's actually
carving those falcon arms
that will go on the sides of the chair.
So this has been an exciting project
put together by my colleagues,
Russ [? Gant ?] and [? Dave Hopkins ?]
of the Giza Project.
And we're almost done, and we
hope to have this on display
in a couple of months in
the Harvard Semitic Museum,
which I have the privilege to direct.
>> So from that arm, there you go.
You see some of the pieces
already coming together.
For those of you who have
been across the river,
the Harvard Ceramics Center
has donated their time,
and we've been baking [INAUDIBLE]
tiles in these wonderful plaster molds.
We just ordered the gold
today because the whole thing
has to be wrapped and gilded.
And eventually, we hope
to put this on display.
>> From there, the question is holistically
again, how do we treat the entire site?
How do we build computer
models of all of Giza?
Not just one tomb here or
there, but the whole thing.
The pyramids, the landscape, the
[INAUDIBLE] tombs, the royal temples.
And I'm part of a project
that just got permission
from the Egyptian
authorities about a week ago,
and we'll start this
month doing all kinds
of pretty interesting experiments.
So take a look at this video.
Maybe the music could come up a little
bit just to add a little bit of drama.
Just a minute or so.
>> So these are some of the tools we'll
be using to explore inside the pyramids
and survey the entire site.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
This is my favorite part.
It's right out of The Terminator with
the drones hovering over the place
and scanning the entire landscape.
Something I've been dreaming
of doing for many, many years.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> So with that kind of comprehensive
accessible to the whole place,
everything is possible.
And our ultimate vision is to put it
all together so you have a navigable,
immersive, 3D model of the whole site.
You can dive down burial shafts, you
can go into tombs, click on walls.
The 100-year-old photography pops up.
You can read the diary
entries, you can virtually
replace statues and things
that were found inside.
It all comes together.
For those of you who want to
explore what's online so far
we have a slightly old and outdated
website up above. gizapyramids.org.
We're working very hard to
replace that with version 2.0.
We could use your help
in various aspects of it.
And then the 3D models that
we're about to take a look at
are down on this other website, which
unfortunately does not work on Macs,
which kills me but nevertheless.
PCs only and no www there.
Take a look at that, and you'll
see the 3D models there as well.
>> There is our new layout.
You can see how massive
amounts of data like this
have to be organized clearly because
it's not all Egyptologists out there.
We've got to make this
understandable and accessible
to all kinds of audiences.
And maybe a mock up of what our
future website might look like.
Hopefully a lot more elegant
and not like those creepy
blinking websites from the 1990s
that I remember oh so well,
even from my own days.
>> So I just thought I'd put together
a list of the kind of projects
that you might be interested in if
you're hovering around and looking
for a final project.
I know due dates are
coming up pretty soon.
Something like these might
be of interest to you.
Obviously you want to bite off
something that you can chew and swallow.
Not too ambitious.
But if this is something up your
alley, get in touch with me,
get in touch with the
professor, [INAUDIBLE]
get in touch with [? Russ Gant ?]
and the other Giza team
and maybe we can help you out
and build something together,
which might be kind of fun.
We can post this list, so you don't need
to jot everything down instantly right
now.
And check it out later on.
And if you really like Ancient Egypt
and want to get into more of this stuff
next semester, there's
a Gen Ed class which
surveys 3,000 or 4,000
years of Egyptian culture,
and you might want to
look into that as well.
>> So that is just a quick overview.
And I thought if my
model is behaving now
we might take a look at
what Giza looks like in 3D.
And this is what you would
see on that second website.
So welcome to the Giza Pyramids.
And in this case, we had to study
not just the layout of the site
but of course the ancient landscape.
Look at the Nile and how
close it is to the pyramids.
Today, the Nile is way far away.
It's much closer to Cairo itself.
But in those days, in
the third millennium,
it was hovering and flowing
much closer to the site as well.
So we had to take away modern
archaeological debris dumps and houses
and all kinds of things and
really study the site carefully.
>> So what we have built so far
you can just hover around.
And you see things blinking red, and
you can visit various places such
as the Temple of [? Kingman ?]
[? Kalray ?] here.
This is an interesting one
because it allows us to study
the place at multiple points in time.
This is a temple that was built by
[? Kingman ?] [? Kalray, ?] the builder
of the third and smallest pyramid, but
he died too soon and his son had to try
to finish it not in
stone, but in mud brick.
So I can go to my little free cam here.
Different ways to navigate.
And I can just hover
around and cruise inside.
We've got to go visit the kitty cat.
One of my favorites.
There he is.
Try to build one of those
for your final project.
>> But the interesting thing
is this particular courtyard
underwent a lot of change.
And so this is how it looked at
one point, and then as I mentioned,
the King died too soon.
Later, priests move in and
actually settled the place
and turned it into a
kind of sacred slum.
And you can see all the
settlements now filling
the courtyard with silos and
ovens and other storage place.
[? It's ?] a very, very
different kind of location.
>> So this is an interesting research tool.
You can visit these places
at different points in time.
You can even see the pyramids being
built, or you come into the courtyard.
And if I can get to
that photograph, you can
see what those statues
there actually looked
like when the excavators found them.
Here it is in one of those
glass plate negatives.
Beautiful dig shots.
Or you can come back to the main
site and visit something else.
>> Let me take you inside a
beautiful tomb found in 1927.
Of course, on the last
days of the dig season.
Isn't that always the way?
So clicking these buttons will
either give you a narrated tour,
you can see some photos,
you can see wire frames
of how we put some of
these things together,
or of course, you could wander
right into the monuments themselves.
So this is a beauty because a lot
of the original color was preserved,
and that let us restore
the tomb completely.
It's another navigation
system I'm using.
So how cool is that?
And again, you can click on photos
and up popped the actual images
for comparison's sake.
>> So trying to put this all together--
take a comprehensive view of Giza,
the ancient site of Giza, the
history of the excavations,
the 3D visualization, a teaching
tool, a research tool-- basically,
there's no end to it.
And of course, it's Giza past, it's
Giza present, and it's Giza future.
There is work being done
at the site nowadays too,
and we want to capture all that as well.
So the goal is to try to create a
center, if not an actual physical space
but at least online, that anyone
can come and study, have access
to all this material.
You don't need a special
travel grant and permissions
to get into some dusty museum archive.
You can access whatever you need to.
>> Let me take you to the Sphinx here.
And again, imagine wearing these 3D
headsets and everybody having access
to the same file at the
same time and all of us
meeting at the Sphinx for a lecture.
And then push the button.
We'll go down a burial
shaft or go someplace else.
The interesting thing about these
models too, once you simulate them,
is they bring up interesting questions.
For example, no one in my
field really thinks too
much about how the Sphinx was painted.
Is that the accurate appearance?
Was the whole thing colored,
or was it just the head
of the Sphinx as we've
chosen to do it now?
Switching my navigation.
There we go.
So it's a little easier
for me to get around.
So this is probably one of the
most accurate reconstructions
of the Sphinx ever attempted, and
again, you don't think of these issues
until you have to build them.
How was the Sphinx originally laid out?
How was it colored?
Where was that beard?
We haven't added things that were added
by the Egyptians in later centuries
when they came back and sort
of resuscitated the site.
>> Or another example.
We have a tomb with a
window in it to the outside.
And in reconstructing that tomb we
realized the sunlight would come right
through that window and illuminate
a kind of sacred offering
place inside the chapel,
and that's something
we wouldn't have realized if
we hadn't simulated the tomb
and put it back together.
And that, in turn, makes you think,
well, what building was right outside
and would it have blocked that sunlight?
And if it blocked that sunlight and that
religious significance of illuminating
a sacred space, does that mean
that our tomb was here first
and the second building came second?
Can we now start to
historically reconstruct
the sequence of Giza tombs just
based on sunlight, just based
on simulations and reconstructions?
>> So those are some of the ways that
we're using these models to study Giza,
to teach about Giza, and more
importantly, to roam the world,
assemble all the material
that we can find, and then
move into the 3D space and
the visualization space
and bring it home to your desktops,
to your phones, to your headsets.
And you'll be able to travel
to the site without even
buying a plane ticket eventually.
Thanks very much.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> Happy to answer a
question or if you have
more headsets you want to demonstrate
or anything we need to do in the time
we have left.
If any of those topics caught your eye
and you'd like to hear more about it,
do come up afterwards and
happy to chat further.
Questions?
Comments?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Do you have
a position on the idea
that there was water
erosion [INAUDIBLE]?
PETER MANUELIAN: Great question.
So water erosion at the Sphinx.
There was a theory by
geologists who thought
that this proved that the Sphinx
was 5,000 or 10,000 years older
than the rest of the pyramids
based on water erosion patterns.
It actually doesn't hold
up particularly well.
You can look at the
erosion patterns in areas
around the Sphinx which pretty
much discredit that theory.
>> There are three geological
member formations of the Sphinx.
The solid one is at the top.
That's why the face
survived so well today.
Others a lot more [? friable, ?] but
it doesn't hold up archaeologically
that the Sphinx is of a different time
period from the pyramids themselves.
There is debate about
who carved the Sphinx.
Whether it was Khafre, the builder
of the second pyramid, or some people
now think Khufu himself, the
builder of the Great Pyramid.
That's an ongoing debate,
but they're all contemporary.
They're all Old Kingdom,
all about 2500 BC.
Great Question.
Yeah, please.
>> AUDIENCE: What was the [INAUDIBLE]?
PETER MANUELIAN: Say again.
The head of the Sphinx painted?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PETER MANUELIAN: Why was
the head of the Sphinx
painted and not the rest of the body?
Great archaeological question,
and we don't know the answer.
It's possible that the
entire body was painted.
It's so deteriorated and the
casing stones around the edge
are not always preserved,
so it may have been painted
and we just don't see
the traces left today.
>> I personally have trouble
believing that the Egyptians would
amass that much paint to cover the
entire body with a reddish brown tinge,
but it's certainly possible.
We've opted for just doing the headdress
and the face where there are traces
of reddish brown color
and there are traces
of the stripes on the
so-called headdress.
And nowadays, you can see a piece of
the Sphinx's beard in the British Museum
and a piece of the uraeus,
the cobra on the brow there,
is actually in the Cairo museums.
So we have some good evidence for that.
In the corner.
Yeah, please.
>> AUDIENCE: You said that the Nile was a
lot more [INAUDIBLE] Giza [INAUDIBLE]
closer to Cairo now.
How does the river more?
>> PETER MANUELIAN: How
does the river move?
There's a lot of meandering.
So a lot of power and pushing
and oxbow lakes and things
are part of river formations.
The Nile doesn't quite do that,
but it has meandered quite a bit.
I could refer you to an article by
some geologists colleagues of mine.
And it's an amazing ribbon over
the last several thousand years
of just where the Nile has moved to.
So once you realize that landscape
issues like where the Nile was,
you start to understand, oh,
that's why they built that causeway
and that's why it turns a corner.
That must be the high ground
they're trying to stay on.
And so you understand
harbors a lot better.
>> You understand how they got
some of the fine casing stones
to Giza from sites across
the Nile, for example.
So these all contribute to
our understanding of the site.
It's a little myopic to just study
the hieroglyphs or study the buildings
and not understand the
landscape and how it changed.
Egypt was a lot less arid at that point
to, so there may even be landscaping
around the pyramids that we should
be putting in and a lot more
growth and vegetation
and interesting things.
Some of the issues in the
models I didn't show you
but we have in our
visualization center classroom
is the ability to put humans into the
scene as avatars performing activities.
And so for example, we can show
the Great Pyramid being built
and take you to the query where a
lot of the stones are being carved.
And that's a model that
as 2,000 avatars all
traveling around the site and hacking
the limestone bits and hauling them
along sleds and things like that.
So it also brings the
site to life and shows you
how the construction process worked.
>> We've also done the re-animation
ceremony of King Khufu.
That's called the opening
of the mouth ceremony.
So in his temple, right beside his
pyramid, we have got his mummy there,
the priest are there.
They're doing their ritual gestures.
They're saying the spells
to magically reanimate
the spirit of the deceased
King for the nether world.
So these are all ways that
the models can actually
show us actual activities
of the ancient Egyptians.
And there again, they
bring up new questions.
Did it occur here?
Did it occur there?
Should it be daytime?
Should it be nighttime?
All of these things you don't think
about when you're writing a journal
article with black and
white line drawings,
but you're doing an
animated 3D simulation.
Yes, please?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PETER MANUELIAN: Little louder, sorry.
Can't hear you.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] do these models
incorporate sounds [INAUDIBLE]?
>> PETER MANUELIAN: Are there
sounds in the model here?
Was that your question?
Yes, there are actually.
Sometimes it's music to certain tastes,
but we do have rumblings of the wind,
for example.
We haven't recreated people actually
speaking in ancient Egyptian.
They could, but we'd probably get
the pronunciations pretty bad.
There are spells and rituals and things
represented on the carved tomb wall
scenes and paintings, so
we could certainly do that.
The occasional cat probably
screeches and things like that,
but otherwise we haven't
done too much with the audio.
Ambiance.
Another question?
Yes, please.
>> AUDIENCE: Why are there exterior walls?
PETER MANUELIAN: Why are
there exterior walls?
These are enclosure walls.
So don't think of the pyramid
as a standalone monument.
Think of it as a pyramid, a temple.
You see that reddish one with
the granite blocks there?
That's called the Pyramid Temple.
It extends down a long
causeway to what's
called the Valley Temple close to
the harbor and close to the Nile.
All of that is part of
the royal pyramid complex,
and it could also
include little pyramids
like you see here for the queens
and even a ritual pyramid,
like you see here,
where no one is buried
but it's just part of the animated
deceased's spirit of the deceased King.
So enclosure walls are
probably to protect it.
>> Who has access to this place?
Remember, these are the upper
echelons of Egyptian society.
Your average, illiterate,
farming Egyptian
is not going to get a tomb like this.
He's never going to see pharaoh.
He can't read hieroglyphs.
So these are the elites of
the elite of the Old Kingdom,
and they get enclosure
walls to protect them.
Got time for one more.
Yeah, please.
>> AUDIENCE: Why were the pyramids built?
>> PETER MANUELIAN: Why
were the pyramids built?
They are basically tombs
for the deceased pharaoh.
So in the popular
literature, in the movies,
you've got this despotic tyrant who
is bringing all these slaves in--
and they're not Hebrew slaves.
They're actual Egyptians.
I tend to stay away
from the word slavery.
These are conscripted Egyptians.
And my view is that
they're actually buying
into this national project in some way.
By guaranteeing a successful
afterlife for this King
they are guaranteeing the
prosperity of the country.
They're paving the way for
the next pharaoh who will
inhabit this institution of kingship.
So these are national pride
projects for the reigning pharaoh,
for the success of the country.
It's almost an investment
in their future in a way.
>> A colleague of mine likes to
say that the Egyptians didn't
build the pyramids.
The pyramids built Egypt.
And by that he means that this is
how state formation came about.
Project management information.
Management.
Of course, these people have to
be fed, they have to be housed,
they have to be organized.
Where does all that come from?
>> Who brings them the meat so
they have good diets so they
have strength to move the blocks?
Who organizes the housing?
Where do they come from in
different parts of the country?
How many people do you need
to haul a certain block?
All of this had to be worked
out, and we're exploring
those aspects of the site today too.
So more chapters about the
pyramids will be written,
more discoveries will be made,
more statues will be found,
and more tombs and inscriptions
will be forthcoming as well.
The place is alive and growing.
Thanks very much.
>> [APPLAUSE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Professor
Manuelian's team
kindly brought some of their own
headsets in addition to ours.
If you'd like to come
up for any demos do.
Otherwise, we'll adjourn here
and we'll see you on Monday.
Thank you so much.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]