>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: So my new Mike is probably
in the latter half of the phone book.
I can now tear the problem in half.
That was actually real, that struggle.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> ROBOT: You humans are so easy to beat.
>> DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50 and this
is the end of week 11.
So we do hope, particularly coming on
the heels of quiz one, that all of you
are relieved but also proud
of just how far you've come.
>> Indeed, so many of you-- 72% if
last year is any reflection--
had no prior experience taking a
computer science course before.
And so even if you were feeling
a little less than excited
as to how quiz zero or one or some
particular piece had turned out,
just consider the delta
from today versus week zero.
>> Indeed, this, recall is
pretty much where we started.
And for many of you, just getting
those darn for loops to work
may have been an initial challenge and
I would encourage you at some point,
if you'd like some
self assigned homework,
go back and re-implement Mario, whether
it's in JavaScript or PHP or even in C,
and see just, hopefully, how readily,
that kind of logic now comes to you.
>> Today we wrap up the
course here in New Haven
and we give you a sense of what
still is on the horizon, even
outside of the classroom.
>> First and foremost is
the CS50 Hackathon,
an epic all nighter during which
you and your classmates in Cambridge
will have an opportunity to dive
into and continue-- not hopefully
start-- final projects for some 12
hours, arriving around 7:00 PM by buses
that we'll provide here
from New Haven to Cambridge.
>> Around 9:00 PM, we'll serve
first dinner around 1:00 AM,
we'll serve second dinner,
and around 5:00 AM,
we'll serve breakfast for
those who are still standing.
And you'll see such memories as these
while working through the evening.
Candy, and as promised
in week zero, vegetables
for the second time in
history, as well 4:00 AM,
things start to look a little like this.
>> And then beyond that,
realize that what's ahead
is the CS50 Fair here at Yale, so
that faculty and students and staff
from across this campus have an
opportunity to delight in exactly how
much you all pulled off this semester.
Will there be in Commons, the
CS50 Fair on Monday the 14th.
So do keep that in mind and more
to come with details online.
But if Cambridge is any indication,
realize that memories like this
here await.
And you should certainly feel free to
invite your friends in the meantime.
>> And if seeing you at the CS50
Fair weren't incentive enough,
we thought we would invite some
of our friends from industries.
If you'd like to chat up alumni
and recruiters from eBay,
ESPN, Facebook, Google, Palantir,
YEI, and YHack, and possibly more,
do come by.
>> And if that's not enough to come see
you or the recruiters from industry,
realize that there will be a raffle
with fabulous prizes, among them, these.
And what will happen is, upon
arriving at the fair, both
you and attendees will be handed a
little program for the day's event
telling you what to do.
When, what is there.
>> There will be some little place
holders for smiley face stickers.
And all of you, the
students, will get some 10
plus smiley face stickers
and anyone who breaks
that social awkwardness and comes
up to you and says, what did you do?
Or can I see a demo of what you did?
You hand them a sticker and
that sticker is an entry
in a fabulous raffle such as this here.
So that should help you break
the ice and give everyone
a little bit of an excuse
to grease those wheels.
>> And you'll see such expressions
and memories as this one
here, this one here, and
then, proudly, will all of you
have your first ever "I
took CS50" t-shirts as well.
So more on that to come.
>> Now in addition to the
course, is very specifically
offered today as to
what's on the horizon,
realize too that among the
handouts, thanks to Megan,
is Yale's first ever
unofficial guide to CS at Yale,
where she's wonderfully diagramed
the various paths that you
can take after leaving CS50 or
112 or other courses here at Yale,
so you can explore things well beyond
CS50 itself, if you would like.
And the diagram you'll
see there is exactly that.
>> And also too, realize that
today, from 3:00 to 4:30
PM is the first ever CS50
Expo here at Yale, over
in Sterling Memorial Library.
And this is an opportunity
to see some of the projects
that our own teaching staff
and some of the upperclassmen
here have created in their classes,
in their research projects,
in entrepreneurial interests of theirs.
So do join us there for snacks and
some amazing opportunities and glimpses
as to what you can now do as
an aspiring computer scientist.
>> And in terms of opportunities now,
with CS50 itself, to get involved,
do realize, if unfamiliar, that
in addition to this college
offering of CS50, the
College Board-- which
you may recall fondly or less fondly--
is in the process of setting up
a new AP Computer Science curriculum.
So some of you, a few of you, might have
taken AP CSA, Computer Science A, which
focused, frankly, very much
on the language Java, sort
of to the exclusion of
inspiration, quite often,
and excitement and problem
solving more generally.
>> What's really nice about a new
curriculum framework that's
being released in fall
2016 from the College Board
is that it will be AP Computer
Science Principles which
is much more akin to more inspiring
CS zero, CS one, CS two courses most
universities might call them.
And there will be a number of
implementations of this course.
UC Berkeley is doing
one. co.org is doing one.
CS50 is doing one.
And so if you have an interest in
getting involved in high school
education and working with
CS50 in the staff capacity,
doing outreach like this, do reach out
to us as well any of the courses heads.
>> And also too, now begins recruiting.
You are all just about to be eligible
to teach this same class here at Yale.
And what's been especially,
frankly, exciting,
amazing this past year
is that truly, with CS50,
have we had a team of some 44 largely
undergraduate staff members who
are serving as undergraduate learning
assistants or TAs more generally,
the first time in Yale's history.
And so you will be the second
generation of exactly that opportunity.
>> So we do encourage you to apply either
as a TA or CA in the teaching role
or in a number of other roles.
Suffice it to say, with
all the songs and dances,
literally, that we seem to
have, there's any number
of ways where you can get
involved creatively, artistically,
as well as educationally.
So do let us know via this URL here.
Now a little while from now,
we'll adjourn with our tradition
just as we began this semester with cake
in the dining hall around the corner.
But we'd like to tie
up a few loose ends.
>> And first and foremost, I'd
just like to recognize one.
This happened last week.
So I've become acquainted with
"Overheard at Yale," where--
if we, shall we say, enhance
this video, or this photo--
you'll see this shirt that I was sold
for $15 and then this photo was taken.
Business, I'm told, has
been good ever since then.
Didn't go over super well back home.
>> But irrespective of how this
weekend goes-- and actually,
one other [INAUDIBLE].
So we made the Rumpus today, CS50.
The hookup Bingo chart, which
is on the back, involves CS50.
I don't really want my words to show up
in the transcript, so I'll just-- OK,
here we go.
OK, so that's one of the squares.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> Won't be able to search
on that word though.
All right.
So irrespective of how this particular
weekend turns out with Harvard Yale,
do know it's been an absolute honor
for us and so terribly exciting
to be working with Scass, with Jason,
with Andy, with the entire team here.
Yale vs. Harvard, we're still
working on that, apparently.
>> [LAUGHTER]
It really has been special.
And as I've said before,
of all the universities
to collaborate with in this way,
it's truly been special for us
to work here with the team
and the students at Yale.
So it's been wonderfully gratifying
and we are forever grateful
for this opportunity to be
welcomed as we have been here.
>> Indeed, let me say
some thank yous first,
before we turn things over to some of
you and some audience participation.
First and foremost, to Scass, to Jason,
to Andy, and the entire Yale team.
Thank you for making this
course so amazing here.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> I'd like to draw your
attention to all of the names
that compose CS50's team
both here and in New Haven.
Over 100 of us, colleagues
in both of these towns.
And so we won't spend time, I
fear, on every one of the names.
I did want to draw your
attention to one fellow,
in particular, for a couple of reasons.
>> Pictured here is teaching fellow Alex,
who, apparently, shortly before he
took four pairs of CS50
Shades from a recent event.
But Alex has been an amazing
character to have on staff.
He was, shall we say, not
the greatest supporter
of CS50 coming to Yale
just over a year ago,
but he's turned into this extraordinary
member of our teaching staff,
an extraordinary Senior
in Computer Science,
and, and, and most importantly, number
one atop CS50's Big Board this year.
So congratulations to
Alex as well, here.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> OK.
Fun fact, so with Rob
Bowden back home, do
he and I run the Big
Board this past year.
And so Rob was so annoyed
that Alex had bested him
that we even did a random
audit of Alex's code
to make sure that it was consistent
with the problem set specification,
and indeed, he bested Andrew and
Rob here in this year's Big Board,
so congrats to him as well.
>> Some quick thank yous to the team
back home, Daven and Maria and Hannah
and Rob, whom we'll soon see.
And also, a number of
the full time members
who work largely back
home behind the scenes,
Doug, who heads up our CS50 AP
program, Dan Armendariz, who,
with our friends at Cloud
9, took to the next level
our use of CS50 IDE this year, Colton,
of course, with whom we've started
music most every day, Aliess,
who is literally in the same
pose right now back in the
cabinet up there, up top.
>> And then Dan Coffey from
our production team,
Scully from our production
team, Ian, Ramon, Jordan.
And, of course, a very familiar
face that, quite humorously,
you see in exactly this
pose or exactly this context
both in Cambridge and
now here in New Haven,
our own Zamyla, whom
if we enhance, looks
more like this on most every laptop
at office hours most every night.
And in fact, not all of the staff,
of course, could be here today,
but I thought what we'd do is
dim the lights for a moment
and allow the staff, both
from New Haven and Cambridge,
to offer some words of their own.
[VIDEO PLAYBLACK]
-There's no other course in which
everyone who works for the course
is as excited to be there and,
like, be involved in it, as CS50.
I don't know, it's like this
really, like, important and special
responsibility and kind of
an incredible experience
and I'm really glad I get to be
a part of peoples' education.
>> -CS50 in my opinion, is amazing.
I love it.
I loved it when I was taking a class,
and I love it even more as a TA.
>> -TFing is a lot of work,
but it's really rewarding
because you get to teach so much.
You really get to know your students.
You get to know the material yourself.
And you get to just want them
become computer scientists.
>> -My students are the
highlight of my semester.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> -And this is CS50.
>> -I've just never felt
as much like a leader
on campus as I have this semester.
>> -This is one of the only
opportunities on Yale's campus
to really get invested in teaching.
>> -It's really cool to see
CS50 from the other side.
-I was surprised at how
excited all the students were.
-It's also nice when, like,
people, like, recover, like,
a picture of Rick Astley
and are like, who is that?
>> -Yeah, I wanted to give back
because I got a lot of support
when I was a student.
>> -All you need is enthusiasm and a love
of teaching or CS, or any of the above
and you'll be able to do it.
>> -All my students keep Rick-rolling me.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
-It's been so much fun to, like,
teach about this thing that I really
love and think is a
lot of fun and, like,
try to get other people
excited about it as well.
I'm Annaleah Ernst and this is CS50.
>> [CHEERS]
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> [END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: All right,
so you may recall
that we began this semester
looking at computational thinking
and solving problems more
efficiently while thinking
a bit more like a computer.
And rather than rehash something
like peanut butter and jelly,
recall that we had the phone book here,
we solved such problems as problem sets
on game of 15.
But we thought we'd try
something a little new
here, whereby we see just to what extent
this idea of thinking computationally
has sunk in.
Whereby we thought we'd try to
offer up, in the form a volunteer,
some instructions and see how
well we can all follow them.
And for this, I need
at least one volunteer.
If you might be-- I see someone being
tapped on the shoulder right there.
Does that qualify?
No?
No, all right.
How about, OK, in the green.
Come on back.
Come on over.
So let's go ahead and do this.
I have some notes up here
that we'll work on together.
And what is your name?
>> ERICA: Erica.
>> DAVID MALAN: Erica?
All right.
Let me give you this.
Erica, nice to meet you.
All right, so in just a moment-- you
all should have a blank piece of paper.
If you don't, just scrounge around
and see if you can grab one.
And find a pen or whatnot.
And we're going to try
something like this.
If you are comfortable
doing so, Erica, I
need you to describe what you
see on this opaque piece of paper
so that the audience here is
only going to do literally what
you say by following your instructions.
And then in just a
moment, I'll come around
and take a random
sampling of some pictures
and we'll see just how accurately
your classmates have done.
>> ERICA: OK.
>> DAVID MALAN: Make sense?
>> ERICA: Yeah.
>> DAVID MALAN: All right.
So you at this point,
as the audience, should
have a blank piece of
paper, a pen or pencil,
and you should do
exactly what Erica says.
Go.
ERICA: Landscape orientation.
In the center of both the vertical
and horizontal axis of the page,
draw a square, not a rectangle, even
sides, about one inch on each side
with the center of the square
in the center of the paper.
Directly above-- thinking landscape
orientation-- above that square
but touching it, you should have
a circle with the same radius
as half of the side of the square.
So the circle should be able
to fit inside the square
and be just touching the top
of the middle, the middle
of the top side of the square.
And then directly below the square,
you should have an equilateral triangle
with one top point touching the bottom
of the square and then equilateral.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
So that was extraordinarily precise.
Let me leave you here
for just a moment and see
if we can get a couple of answers.
Can I grab yours?
OK.
Grab yours, yours.
Now I'm going to fish for one--
I don't know, that's very good.
You're all very good at this.
Can I take this one?
Thank you.
>> [LAUGHTER]
We'll randomize.
Can I take yours, too?
Thank you.
No, that's a compliment.
OK, yes very good.
Thank you.
All right.
And just so I don't
neglect anyone over here.
That's very good, OK.
OK, that's adorable.
All right.
That's enough for this one.
So let's see how we did here.
>> All right so why don't
we go ahead now and I
will spoil, with Erica still here,
what the image was supposed to be.
Wonderfully, precisely
described, I would argue.
Now let me go ahead and take a look
at a random sample of the pictures
that we found up here.
>> So let's go.
The first several I
found were-- here's one.
So very nicely done.
Here's another, very nicely done.
Here's another, and this is where it
was getting awkward because there's
like 50 or a 100 of these out there.
But then I kept searching
and we found this.
So the orientation wasn't quite right.
Another correct one.
We had this one, all
right, so not quite right.
Then there's this one,
maybe not quite to scale.
And then the adorable one,
if I may, very nicely done.
>> Congratulations to Erica
for doing such a good job.
Thank you.
Why don't we get-- can we get one more
volunteer to come and do the same?
Come on up, yeah.
And I'm sorry for taking
the papers from everyone.
If you can try to
scrounge one other piece,
we'll do this once
more in this direction.
>> What is your name?
>> ADAM: Adam.
>> DAVID MALAN: Adam.
Come on up.
All right.
So the task is going to be very
similar, different picture.
Nice to meet you.
Come on around.
All right.
And we're going to do this again,
this time with a different picture
from Adam.
Adam is going to describe to
you, opaquely-- show confidence--
the following.
The floor is yours.
>> ADAM: It is a very large square.
Can I say that?
>> DAVID MALAN: Yes, that's good.
That's correct.
>> ADAM: But very large, like.
But start at the center--
like, from the center,
but it like expands
outward from the center.
So like, the center of the page is
still the center, so keep that in mind.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> Then, divide it in half, but like,
in the center, going hot dog style.
Yeah.
Like.
So then divide it that way,
like up and down, vertical.
Vertical.
And then from the vertical
line, going from the right side
of the center of that
vertical line, go to the right
to divide that rectangle
on the right side in half.
OK.
>> So, but now, it's going to get a
little tricky, so let's hold on here.
You're going to do that
again, but going up from that.
So now you should have a rectangle, a
big rectangle, and two small squares
on the other side.
And then divide your
square in the top right
in half the same way you divided
the big square at the beginning.
OK.
Now, so now you have that square
that's divided into two rectangles.
And then draw that same line you
drew at the beginning from the center
point of the original square
with that line in the center
to the far-- horizontally from
that new up and down line.
And then recreate that square again
in the top right hand quadrant.
I mean, not the quadrant, whatever
the eighth is of a quadrant.
DAVID MALAN: I'm going to go
start getting the sheets, OK?
ADAM: Yes, OK.
So if there's any questions,
I can take those now.
DAVID MALAN: Can I see
just a few examples?
All right, we got this one here.
All right, this one here.
All right, still working.
Very nice.
Yes.
>> ADAM: I'm not good at this class.
DAVID MALAN: Thank you.
Yeah.
OK.
Let me take these two.
Thank you.
All right, and one more from over here.
One more from over here.
Thank you.
Oh, that's perfect.
All right.
>> So Adam, let's see how they did.
And I'll reveal on the screen
what the image was this time.
So what we were looking for this
time, per Adam's precise instructions,
was this.
And what we got was some works
of beauty here, I will say.
>> ADAM: Oh, I-- wow.
DAVID MALAN: You're surprised?
[LAUGHTER]
Then we have this one.
So similar in spirit, but not quite.
Then we have this windowed version.
And then this one.
>> [LAUGHTER]
And then this is maybe my favorite.
This one's just a little skewed.
>> ADAM: That one's not my fault.
That one's not my fault.
>> DAVID MALAN: Well all right,
thank you and congrats to Adam
for being so precise.
>> ADAM: Thank you.
>> DAVID MALAN: So why don't we
try this at least one more time
but kind of flip things around.
So now we need someone who's
comfortable drawing and having a hundred
of your classmates staring down
at your back while you draw,
taking instructions
from your classmates.
OK, how about in purple.
Come on up.
All right.
So in a moment-- what's your name?
ANGELA: Angela.
DAVID MALAN: Angela.
Come on up, Angela.
So Angela's going to stand roughly
here, where she shouldn't be able to see
the overhead, she can
only see the board's.
Nice to meet you, Angela.
Here's your piece of chalk.
I'm going to show the
audience the picture
and then roughly orderly,
kind of like the PBJ,
we'll have you guys shout out,
linearly, exactly what you
would like Angela to draw.
Sound good?
Good.
Yeah.
>> Would someone like to offer
an instruction to Angela?
It's not that-- well, OK.
>> AUDIENCE: Circle?
At the top of the board.
DAVID MALAN: All right, I heard
circle at the top of the board.
AUDIENCE: It's a stick figure.
DAVID MALAN: OK I heard
it's a stick figure.
And here, you want to hold
this in your other hand?
OK, next?
>> ANGELA: Stick figure, all right.
>> DAVID MALAN: Draw a circle
in the center of the board.
It's a stick figure.
Stop!
Only keep the body.
ANGELA: So it's like a lollipop?
DAVID MALAN: Add the two legs first.
ANGELA: Down here.
DAVID MALAN: OK, I heard yeah.
>> ANGELA: So here?
DAVID MALAN: The arm starts
from the body toward the head.
ANGELA: Like that?
What?
>> DAVID MALAN: OK, here,
wait, how about this.
One arm goes up.
>> AUDIENCE: The right arm has the
hand on the hip and the other arm--
>> DAVID MALAN: The right arm has-- I heard
the right arm has his arm on his hip.
>> ANGELA: His right arm?
>> DAVID MALAN: His right.
>> ANGELA: Like that?
>> DAVID MALAN: Yes.
What else?
>> AUDIENCE: The other arm--
The other arm goes up.
>> DAVID MALAN: The other arm goes up.
ANGELA: Oh, like that?
>> DAVID MALAN: All right, and--
AUDIENCE: He's saying something.
DAVID MALAN: He's saying something.
ANGELA: Like a speech bubble?
There's a line, approximately
10:00, that goes out from the head.
A line at 10:00 position that you draw,
like, from the radius, projecting--
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> ANGELA: Like?
>> AUDIENCE: No!
>> DAVID MALAN: There's a line
at 10:00 from the head out.
>> AUDIENCE: See like a line
coming out above the radius.
Don't draw it.
Do what you did originally.
>> DAVID MALAN: Do what you did originally.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: He says hi.
>> DAVID MALAN: Write-- he says hi.
What do we think?
All right.
Congratulations.
If you'd like to take a
look, you indeed got it.
Very nicely done.
>> So we've not try this last opportunity
before-- before we adjourn for cake--
but we thought we'd try
to get all the more of you
involved vs. Some of the staff as well.
And so, if I could-- are
there five staff members
who would like to volunteer
and come on over here?
Stelios, do want to bring
four friends on down?
From the staff.
Come on down.
Yeah.
Andy.
Come on down.
And if you guys would like
to organize yourselves
in a line behind this blue table.
>> Now we need five student volunteers.
OK, so how about you two sitting there.
Three, four, in the middle.
Oh, and over here, five on the end.
Come on up.
Yep, you on the end.
Come on down.
And students shall be over here.
And-- did we lose some-- one, two,
three, four I pointed at someone
who still-- yes, you, you come on down.
All right.
>> So we'll explain the rules here if
you've not heard of this before,
but it sounds a little something like
>> [PLAYS THEME SONG TO FAMILY FEUD]
>> Aw.
OK.
So here we have Family--
Colton, website?
OK.
So here we have Family Feud.
And now you'll have to forgive.
You may recall that
in problem set eight,
we asked you a number of quiz review
questions that are kind of, sort of
in the form of Jeopardy questions,
even though it was question and answer.
We decided after issuing
p-set eight that we
want to play Family Feud instead,
so we've taken some liberties how
to convert Jeopardy
questions to Family Feud,
but the following data may or may
not be reflective of correct answers.
So with that, that said, the
way this is going to work
is that we have the student team here.
We have the staff team here.
We're going to first have two members
of the staff and students face off.
I'm going to ask a question and the
first one to buzz in with this here--
>> VOICE: That was easy.
DAVID MALAN: --Easy Button, which was
the only red buttons we could find.
And according to guy at
Staples, he has never
seen someone actually buy
the Easy Button in Staples.
>> That will be how the two people buzz in.
Whoever buzzes in first not only
gets a certain number of points,
they also get control of the board.
The goal, then, if the students,
for instance, win that toss,
you guys have to come up
with the top several answers
before getting three
strikes by guessing wrong.
I'll re-explain this as we go.
All right.
>> So let's go ahead and begin as follows.
What's your name?
VLAD: Vlad.
Vlad, all right.
Nice to meet you.
And introduce yourself to this team.
>> SHREYAS: Shreyas.
>> DAVID MALAN: Shreyas.
So here we have two Easy
Buttons, one question,
and the following will be revealed
now by Colton, A function declared
in standard io dot h.
>> VOICE: That was easy.
>> DAVID MALAN: You hit it first
so we'll go with the staff.
>> SHREYAS: Print f.
>> DAVID MALAN: Show us print f.
>> [DING]
DAVID MALAN: Very nice.
So now the staff has
control of the board.
Oh, and if we're going
to keep score, we need
someone who's really good at
arithmetic under pressure.
Really?
OK.
I saw your hand first.
Come on down.
What's your name?
>> DYLAN: Dylan.
>> DAVID MALAN: Oh, Dylan, all right.
Dylan, nice to meet you.
So if you could grab a piece
of chalk and to the left
and the right of the
stick figure, keep track
accurately of the following arithmetic.
The staff now have 68 points.
All right.
So next question, specifically
for Andy, is the same.
Andy, what is a function
declared in standard i o dot h?
>> ANDY: Scanf.
>> DAVID MALAN: Colton, show us scanf.
>> [DING]
Very nice, so an additional
12 points for the staff team.
Stelios, same question, A function
declared in standard i o dot h.
Just Stelios, please.
>> STELIOS: Put c.
>> DAVID MALAN: Putc.
Show us putc.
>> [ERROR BUZZER]
>> One strike.
Only two remain.
Staff, a function declared
in standard i o dot h.
>> STELIOS: I mean, it is.
DAVID MALAN: Well, no,
it might be in there,
but these are only the top six answers.
Key detail-- that
doesn't mean it's wrong.
It just means it's not
among the six answers.
>> AUDIENCE: He's foreign.
DAVID MALAN: So it was
bad, just not wrong.
>> STAFF MEMBER: Getc
>> DAVID MALAN: Getc.
>> [DING]
DAVID MALAN: We'll give it to you.
Fgetc.
Five points more on the board.
Staff, a function declared
in standard i o dot h.
>> STAFF MEMBER: F read.
>> DAVID MALAN: F read, show us.
>> [ERROR BUZZER]
>> DAVID MALAN: Two strikes.
Shreyas, you have one last
chance until the students,
simply by getting one of
the answers on the board,
has the chance to steal the points.
You can all--
STAFF MEMBER: Oh, can we?
DAVID MALAN: No, you cannot.
It's just you.
Just you.
>> SHREYAS: Is f open in standard i o?
DAVID MALAN: We shall see.
F open.
>> [DING] It is, for ten points.
Back to Andy.
Make or break here.
Function declared in standard i o dot h.
>> ANDY: F close.
>> DAVID MALAN: Show us f close.
>> [DING]
>> Very nice.
Six?
We have only five.
We only have five answers
on the board, which
means the staff has won this category.
Very nice.
No it's lack of feature.
All right.
>> So now let's go up for our second round.
So we need Andy and what's your name?
BONNIE: Bonnie.
DAVID MALAN: Bonnie, nice to meet you.
All right, come on up to the buzzer.
All right, and here we
have the next question.
Software used while programming.
Name a piece of software
you use while programming.
>> ANDY: The IDE
>> DAVID MALAN: CS50 IDE
>> [ERROR BUZZER]
ANDY: I totally-- what?
Oh, no way.
>> [DING]
>> DAVID MALAN: Text Editor.
Do we want to give it to them?
Yes.
Good job to staff.
Yes-- [INAUDIBLE] the
students look really unhappy.
OK.
So Stelios, name a piece of
software used while programming.
And start thinking of
a way to steal this.
>> STELIOS: GDB.
>> DAVID MALAN: GDB, Debugger.
>> [DING]
>> Very nice for 15 more points.
Frank?
>> FRANK: A terminal.
>> DAVID MALAN: A terminal window.
>> [ERROR BUZZER]
>> Oh, I'm sorry.
Software used while programming.
STAFF MEMBER: Valgrind.
DAVID MALAN: Valgrind, show us.
[ERROR BUZZER]
Oh, Shreyas, the students, you
just need one answer that's
on the board to steal these points.
>> SHREYAS: A compiler.
>> DAVID MALAN: Show us compiler.
>> [DING]
>> Very nice.
Back to Andy.
>> ANDY: This is a lot of pressure.
>> DAVID MALAN: Software
used while programming.
>> ANDY: An operating system.
>> DAVID MALAN: An operating system.
>> [ERROR BUZZER]
>> Students, there are three possible
answers left on the board.
What's going to be your answer?
You can all decide together.
STUDENTS: Interpreter?
DAVID MALAN: An interpreter.
[ERROR BUZZER]
Show us interpreter.
No!
So let's go ahead and reveal now
what answers were on the board.
Number four.
>> [DING]
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> Number five.
>> [DING]
>> Oh, and number six.
>> Spotify.
All right.
So these points stay on this side.
>> I think we have time for
one more round before cake.
Let's go ahead and skip--
let's skip the next one. .
Yes Yeah, skip.
Break, quick.
OK.
We didn't want to do that
to you one last time.
All right.
So the final question here
now for Stelios, thank you.
And who's up next?
SABRINA: Sabrina.
DAVID MALAN: Sabrina, nice to meet you.
All right.
So whoever hits the button first,
the question is Favorite problem set.
VOICE: That was easy.
DAVID MALAN: I hear it
over here, the students.
>> SABRINA: P set zero.
>> DAVID MALAN: Show us p set zero.
Very nice for 26 points.
All right, so students--
who's up next here?
I think you're up next.
What's your name?
>> ALEK: Alek.
>> DAVID MALAN: Alek, nice to meet you.
All right, your favorite problem set.
>> ALEK: Show me p set eight.
>> DAVID MALAN: Show me p set eight.
>> [ERROR BUZZER]
>> I will say, based on actual
data from problem set eight,
so p set eight was not among the
top four answers in this case.
What's your name?
>> BURKE: Burke.
>> DAVID MALAN: Burke, what's
your favorite problem set,
or the top favorite problem set
among all of your other classmates?
>> BURKE: Encrypts or
[INAUDIBLE] p set seven.
P set seven.
>> DAVID MALAN: Show us p set seven.
Number one answer from actual students.
All right.
What do you have for your
favorite problem sets.
>> STUDENT: The one with
the cipher, encrypt.
The one with like crypto.
>> DAVID MALAN: (QUIETLY) P set two?
>> STUDENT: Yes.
DAVID MALAN: P set two!
>> [DING]
>> Very nice.
There's only one answer
left on the board
because we did the top four answers.
So if-- what's your name again?
>> BONNIE: Bonnie.
>> DAVID MALAN: Bonnie.
Bonnie, if you can tell us what the
Harvard and Yale students fourth most
favorite problem set was--
>> BONNIE: I feel like I
have a really skewed view.
>> VLAD: The one with image processes?
BONNIE: No I think
everyone hated that one.
VLAD: Really?
I loved it.
DAVID MALAN: And what
our current totals?
166 to slightly less.
But for 100 points,
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> BONNIE: Oh god, oh no.
Don't put the pressure on me.
Oh, no pressure.
STUDENT: P set one was easy.
Everyone likes easy p sets.
>> BONNIE: P set one?
>> DAVID MALAN: 90 points!
>> DAVID MALAN: Show us p set one.
>> [ERROR BUZZER]
>> Not the fourth favorite problem set.
Vlad?
>> VLAD: I think-- I think-- my favorite
was with photography, but I don't know.
>> DAVID MALAN: I hear forensics.
BONNIE: People are saying forensics?
DAVID MALAN: I hear forensics.
I only heard it.
P set five, I heard.
>> BONNIE: Can we ask the audience?
DAVID MALAN: You want
to poll the audience?
BONNIE: Yeah, let's ask the audience.
P set three.
>> DAVID MALAN: Who wants to
be a millionaire, here.
>> BONNIE: P set three.
>> VLAD: P set four.
>> DAVID MALAN: Three.
I hear four.
>> BONNIE: I see a lot of fours.
STUDENT: OK, we should do four.
>> BONNIE: Three or four.
>> DAVID MALAN: I hear three.
I hear another three.
>> BONNIE: Oh no!
Ken, get out!
>> DAVID MALAN: I hear three.
>> BONNIE: Three, OK, overwhelmingly.
STUDENT: OK.
Let's just do three.
>> DAVID MALAN: The only thing
stopping us from cake.
>> STUDENT: P set three.
>> DAVID MALAN: Show us, for
the game, p set three.
>> [DING]
>> [CHEERS]
All right.
That is it for CS50.
We will see you for cake.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]