>> SPEAKER 1: All right, so this is
CS50 This is the end of week five.
And recall that last time we
started looking at the fancier data
structures that started to solve
problems, that started to introduce
new problems, but the key to this
was the sort of threading that we
started to do from node to node.
So this of course is
a singly linked list.
And by singly linked,
I mean there's just one
thread between each of those nodes.
Turns out you can do fancier
things like doubly linked lists
whereby you have an arrow
going in both directions, which
can help with certain efficiencies.
But this solved the problem?
What problem did this solve?
Why did we care on Monday?
Why, in theory, did we care on Monday?
What does it do?
>> AUDIENCE: We can dynamically resize it.
>> SPEAKER 1: OK, so we can
dynamically resize it.
Well done both of you.
So you can dynamically resize this
data structure, whereas an array,
recall, you have to know a
priori how much space you want
and if you need a little more
space, you're kind of out of luck.
You have to create a whole new array.
You have to move all of your
data from one to the other,
eventually free the old array
if you can, and then proceed.
Which just feels very costly and very
inefficient, and indeed it can be.
But this isn't all good.
We pay a price, what was one
of the more obvious prices we
pay by using a linked list?
>> AUDIENCE: We have to use
double space for each one.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah, so we need
at least twice as much space.
In fact, I realized this picture's
even a little misleading,
because on CS50 IDE in a lot of modern
computers, a pointer or an address
is not in fact four bytes.
It's very often these
days eight bytes, which
means the bottom most
rectangles there in reality
are kind of twice as
big as what I've drawn,
which means you're using three times as
much space as we might have otherwise.
Now at the same time, we're
still talking bytes, right?
We're not necessarily talking
megabytes or gigabytes,
unless these data structures get big.
>> And so today we start to consider
how we might explore data
more efficiently if in
fact the data gets bigger.
But let's try to canonicalize
the operations first
that you can do on these
kinds of data structures.
So something like a linked
list generally supports
operations like delete,
insert, and search.
And what do I mean by that?
That just means that usually,
if people are using linked list,
they or someone else has implemented
functions like delete, insert,
and search, so you can
actually do something
useful with the data structure.
So let's take a quick look
at how we might implement
some code for a linked list as follows.
>> So this is just some C code,
not even a complete program
that I really quickly whipped up.
It's not online in the distribution
code, because it won't actually run.
But notice I've just
with a comment said,
dot dot dot, there's something
there, dot dot dot, something there.
And let's just look at
what the juicy parts are.
So on line three,
recall that this is now
we proposed declaring a node last
time, one of those rectangular objects.
It has an int that we'll call N,
but we could call it anything,
and then a struct node star called next.
And just to be clear, that second
line, on line six, what is that?
What is it doing for us?
Because it certainly looks more
cryptic than our usual variables.
>> AUDIENCE: It makes it move over one.
>> SPEAKER 1: It makes it move over one.
And to be more precise,
it will store the address
of the node that's meant to be
semantically next to it, right?
So it's not going to
necessarily move anything.
It's just going to
store a value, which is
going to be the address
of some other node,
and that's why we've said struct
node star, the star denoting
a pointer or an address.
OK, so now if you assume that we have
this N available to us, and let's
assume that someone else has
inserted a whole bunch of integers
into a linked list.
And that linked list is
pointed to by some point
a variable called list that's
passed in here as a parameter,
how do I go about line
14 implementing search?
In other words, if I am implementing
function whose purpose in life
is to take an int and then the
beginning of a linked list,
that is a pointer to the linked list.
Like first, who I think David
was our volunteer on Monday,
he was pointing at
the whole linked list,
it's as though we're passing
David in as our argument here.
How do we go about traversing this list?
Well, it turns out that even though
pointers are relatively new now to us,
we can do this relatively
straightforwardly.
>> I'm going to go ahead and
declare a temporary variable that
by convention is just going
to be called pointer, or PTR,
but you could call it anything you want.
And I'm going to initialize
it to the start of the list.
So you can kind of think of this
as me the teacher the other day,
kind of pointing at someone
among our humans as volunteers.
So I'm a temporary variable that's
just pointing at the same thing
that our coincidentally named
volunteer David was also pointing out.
Now while pointer is
not null, because recall
that null is some special sentinel value
the demarcates the end of the list,
so while I'm not pointing at the
ground like our last volunteer
was, let's go ahead
and do the following.
If pointer-- and now I kind of want
to do what we did with the student
structure-- if pointer dot next
equals-- rather, if pointer dot N equals
equals the variable N, the
argument that's been passed in,
then I want to go ahead
and say return true.
I have found the number N inside of
one of the nodes of my linked list.
But the dot no longer
works in this context,
because pointer, PTR, is
indeed a pointer, an address,
we actually can wonderfully
use finally a piece of syntax
that kind of makes
intuitive sense and actually
use an arrow here, which means go from
that address to the integer there in.
So it's very similar in
spirit to the dot operator,
but because pointer isn't a pointer
and not an actual struct itself,
we just use the arrow.
>> So if the current node that I, the
temporary variable, am pointing at
is not N, what do I want to do?
Well, with my human volunteers
that we had here the other day,
if my first human is not the one I
want, and maybe the second human isn't
the one I want, and the third, I
need to keep physically moving.
Like how do I step through a list?
When we had an array, you
just did like I plus plus.
But in this case, it suffices to
do pointer, gets, pointer, next.
In other words, the next field
is like all of the left hands
that our human volunteers on Monday
were using to point at some other node.
Those were their next neighbors.
>> So if I want to step through this list,
I can't just do I plus plus anymore,
I instead have to say
I, pointer, is going
to equal whatever the next field is,
the next field is, the next field is,
following all of those left hands
that we had on stage pointing
to some subsequent values.
And if I get through
that whole iteration,
and finally, I hit null not having
found N yet, I just return false.
So again, all that we're doing here,
as per the picture a moment ago,
is starting by pointing at the
beginning of the list presumably.
And then I check, is the value
I'm looking for equal to nine?
If so, I return true and I'm done.
If not, I update my hand,
AKA pointer, to point
at the next arrow's location, and
then the next arrow's location,
and the next.
I'm simply walking through this array.
>> So again, who cares?
Like what is this an ingredient for?
Well, recall that we introduced
the notion of a stack, which
is an abstract data type insofar as it's
not a C thing, it's not a CS50 thing,
it's an abstract idea, this idea of
stacking things on top of one another
that can be implemented in
bunches of different ways.
And one way we proposed was with
an array, or with a linked list.
And it turns out that canonically, a
stack supports at least two operations.
And the buzz words are push, to
push something onto the stack,
like a new tray in the
dining hall, or pop,
which means to remove the topmost
tray from the stack in the dining
hall, and then maybe some
other operations as well.
So how might we define the structure
that we're now calling a stack?
>> Well, we have all of the requisite
syntax at our disposal in C. I say,
give me a type definition of
a struct inside of a stack,
I'm going to say is an array, of a
whole bunch of numbers and then size.
So in other words, if I want
to implement this in code,
let me go and just kind of
draw what this is saying.
So this is saying, give me a
structure that's got an array,
and I don't know what capacity is,
it's apparently some constant that I've
defined elsewhere, and that's fine.
But suppose it's just one,
two, three, four, five.
So capacity is 5.
This element inside of my
structure will be called numbers.
And then I need one
other variable apparently
called size that initially I'm going
to stipulate is initialized to zero.
If there's nothing in
the stack, size is zero,
and it's garbage values in numbers.
I have no idea what's in there just yet.
>> So if I want to push
something onto the stack,
suppose I call the function push, and
I say push 50, like the number 50,
where would you propose
I draw it in this array?
There's five different possible answers.
Where do you want to push the number 50?
If the goal here, again, call the
function push, pass in an argument
of 50, where do I put it?
Five possible-- 20% chance
of guessing correctly.
Yes?
>> AUDIENCE: Far right.
>> SPEAKER 1: Far right.
There is now a 25% chance
of guessing correctly.
So that would actually be fine.
By convention, I'll say with an array,
we would generally start at the left,
but we could certainly
start at the right.
So the spoiler here would be I'm
probably going to draw it on the left,
just like in a normal array where
I start going left to right.
But if you can flip
the arithmetic, fine.
It's just not conventional.
OK, I need to make one
more change though.
Now that I've pushed something
onto the stack, what's next?
>> All right, I have to increment the size.
So let me go ahead and just
update this, which was zero.
And instead now, I'm going
to put in the value one.
And now suppose I push another
number onto the stack, like 51.
Well, I have to make one more
change, which is up to the size two.
And then suppose I push one more
number onto the stack like 61,
now I need to update the size one more
time, and get the value 3 as the size.
And now suppose I call pop.
Now pop, by convention,
does not take an argument.
With a stack, the whole
point of the tray metaphor
is that you don't have discretion
to go get that tray, all you can do
is pop the topmost one from
the stack, just because.
That's what this data structure does.
>> So by that logic if I
say pop, what comes off?
So 61.
So what really is the computer
going to do in memory?
What does my code have to do?
What would you propose
we change on the screen?
What should change?
Sorry?
So we get rid of 61.
So I can definitely do that.
And I can get rid of 61.
And then what other
change needs to happen?
Size probably has to go back to two.
And so that's fine.
But wait a minute, size
a moment ago was three.
Let's just do a quick sanity check.
How did we know that we
wanted to get rid of 61?
Because we're popping.
And so I have this second property size.
>> Wait a minute, I'm
thinking back to week two
when we started talking about
arrays, where this was location zero,
this was location one, this was location
two, this is location three, four,
it looks like the
relationship between size
and the element that I want to remove
from the array appears to just be what?
Size minus one.
And so that's how as humans
we know 61 comes first.
How's the computer going to know?
When your code, where you probably
want to do size minus one,
so three minus one is two, and that
means we want to get rid of 61.
And then we can indeed update
the size so that size now
goes from three to just two.
And just to be pedantic, I'm going
to propose that I'm done, right?
You proposed intuitively
correctly I should get rid of 61.
But haven't I kind of
sort of gotten rid of 61?
I've effectively forgotten
that it's actually there.
And think back to PSET4, if you've read
the article about forensics, the PDF
that we had you guys read, or you
will read this week for PSET4.
Recall that this is actually germane to
the whole idea of computer forensics.
What a computer generally does is
it just forgets where something is,
but it doesn't go in and like
try to scratch it out or override
those bits with zeros and ones
or some other random pattern
unless you yourself do so deliberately.
So your intuition was
right, let's get rid of 61.
But in reality, we don't have to bother.
We just need to forget that
it's there by changing our size.
>> Now there's a problem with this stack.
If I keep pushing things
onto the stack, what's
obviously going to happen
in just a few moments time?
We're going to run out of space.
And what do we do?
We're kind of screwed.
This implementation does not let
us resize the array, because using
this syntax, if you
think back to week two,
once you've declared
the size of an array,
we have not seen a mechanism yet where
you can change the size of the array.
And indeed C does not have that feature.
If you say give me five
Nths, call them numbers,
that's all you're going to get it.
So we do now as of Monday, have
the ability to express a solution
though, we just need to tweak
the definition of our stack
to not be some hard-coded array,
but just to store an address.
>> Now why is this?
Now we just have to be comfortable with
the fact that when my program runs,
I'm presumably going to
have to ask the human,
how many numbers do you want to store?
So the input has to come from somewhere.
But once I know that
number, then I can just
use what function to give
me a chunk of memory?
I can use malloc.
And I can say any number of
bytes I want back for these Nths.
And all I have to store in the numbers
variable here inside of this struct
should be what?
What actually goes into the
numbers in this scenario?
Yeah, a pointer to the first
byte of that chunk of memory,
or more specifically, the address
of the first of those bytes.
Doesn't matter if it's one
byte or a billion bytes,
I just need to care about the first.
Because what malloc guarantees and
my operating system guarantees,
is that the chunk of memory I
get, it's going to be contiguous.
There's not going to be gaps.
So if I've asked for 50
bytes or 1,000 bytes,
they're all going to be
back to back to back.
And so long as I remember how big, how
much I asked for, all I need to know
is the first such address.
>> So now we have the ability in code.
Albeit, it's going to take us
more time to write this up,
we could now reallocate that memory by
just storing a different address there
if we want a bigger or even
a smaller chunk of memory.
So here to a trade off.
Now we get dynamism.
We still have
contiguousness I'm claiming.
Because malloc will give us
a contiguous chunk of memory.
But this is going to be a pain in
the neck for us, the programmer,
to actually code up.
It's just more work.
We need code akin to what I was
banging out just a moment ago.
Very doable, but it adds complexity.
And so developer time, programmer
time is yet another resource
that we might need to spend
some time to get new features.
And then of course there is a queue.
We won't go into this
one in much detail.
But it's very similar in spirit.
I could implement a queue, and
its corresponding operations,
enqueue or dequeue, like add or remove,
it's just a fancier way of saying it,
enqueue or dequeue, as follows.
I can just give myself a struct
that again has a number's array,
that again has a size,
but why do I now need
to keep track of the front of a queue?
I didn't need to know
the front of my stack.
Well, if I again for a
queue-- let's just hard
code it as having like five
integers in here potentially.
So this is zero, one, two, three, four.
This is going to be
called numbers again.
And this will be called size.
>> Why is it not sufficient
to have just size?
Well, let's push those same numbers on.
So I pushed-- I enqueued, or pushed.
Now I'll enqueue 50, and then
51, and then 61, and dot dot dot.
So that's enqueue.
I enqueued 50, then 51, then 61.
And that looks identical
to a stack thus far,
except I do need to make one change.
I need to update this size, so I go
from zero to one to two to three now.
How do I dequeue?
What happens with dequeue?
Who should come off this list first
if it's the line at the Apple Store?
So 50.
So it's kind of trickier this time.
Whereas last time it was super
easy to just do size minus one,
I get to the end of my array effectively
where the numbers are, it removes 61.
But I don't want to remove 61.
I want to take 50, who
was there at 5:00 AM
to line up for the
new iPhone or whatnot.
And so to get rid of 50, I
can't just do this, right?
I can cross out 50.
But we just said we
don't have to be so anal
as to scratch out or hide the data.
We can just forget where it is.
>> But if I change my size now to
two, is this sufficient information
to know what is going on in my queue?
Not really.
Like my size is two, but
where does the queue begin,
especially if I still have
those same numbers in memory.
50, 51, 61.
So I need to remember
now where the front is.
And so as I proposed up
there, we'll have just called
Nth front, whose initial
value should have been what?
Zero, just the beginning of the list.
But now in addition to decrementing
the size, we just increment the front.
Now here's another problem.
So once I keep going.
Suppose this is the number of
like 121, 124, and then, dammit,
I'm out of space.
But wait a minute, I'm not.
So at this point in the story,
suppose that the size is one, two,
three, four, so suppose that the
size is four, the front is one,
so 51 is at the front.
I want to put another number here,
but, dammit, I'm out of space.
But I'm not really, right?
Where could I put some
additional value, like 171?
Yeah, I could just kind of
go back over there, right?
And then cross out the 50, or
just overwrite it with 171.
And if you're wondering why
our numbers got so random,
these are commonly taken computer
science courses at Harvard after CS50.
But that was a good optimization,
because now I'm not wasting space.
I still have to remember
how big this thing is total.
It's five total.
Because I don't want to
start overwriting 51.
So now I am still out of space,
so the same problem as before.
But you can see how now
in your code, you probably
have to write a little more
complexity to make that happen.
And in fact, what operator
in C probably lets
you magically do this the circularity?
Yeah the modulo operator,
the percent sign.
So what's kind of cool about a queue,
even though we keep drawing arrays
as these like straight lines, if you
kind of think about this as curving
around as a circle, then just
intuitively it kind of works mentally
I think a little more cleanly.
You would still have to implement
that mental model in code.
So not that hard,
ultimately, to implement,
but we still lose the size-- rather, the
ability to resize, unless we do this.
>> We have to get rid of the array, we
replace it with a single pointer,
and then somewhere in my code I've got
a call what function to actually create
the array called numbers?
Malloc, or some similar
function, exactly.
Any questions on stacks or queues.
Yeah?
Good question.
What modulo would you use here.
So generally, when using
mod, you would do it
with the size of the
whole data structure.
So something like five or capacity, if
it's constant, is probably involved.
But just doing modulo five
probably isn't sufficient,
because we need to know do we
wrap around here or here or here.
So you're probably also
going to want to involve
the size of the thing, or
the front variable as well.
So it's just this relatively
simple arithmetic expression,
but modulo would be the key ingredient.
>> So short film if you will.
An animation that some
folks at another university
put together that we've
adapted for this discussion.
It involves Jack learning the
facts about queues and stats.
>> FILM: Once upon a time,
there was a guy named Jack.
When it came to making friends,
Jack did not have a knack.
So Jack went to talk to the
most popular guy he knew.
He went to Lou and asked, What do I do?
Lou saw that his friend
was really distressed.
Well, he began, just
look how you're dressed.
Don't you have any clothes
with a different look?
Yes, said Jack.
I sure do.
Come to my house and
I'll show them to you.
So they went off to Jack's.
And Jack showed Lou the box
where he kept all his shirts,
and his pants, and his socks.
Lou said, I see you have
all your clothes in a pile.
Why don't you wear some
others once in awhile?
>> Jack said, well, when I
remove clothes and socks,
I wash them and put
them away in the box.
Then comes the next
morning, and up I hop.
I go to the box and get
my clothes off the top.
Lou quickly realized
the problem with Jack.
He kept clothes, CD's,
and books in the stack.
When he reached for
something to read or to wear,
he'd choose the top book or underwear.
Then when he was done, he
would put it right back.
Back it would go, on top of the stack.
I know the solution,
said a triumphant Loud.
You need to learn to
start using a queue.
Lou took Jack's clothes and
hung them in the closet.
And when he had emptied
the box, he just tossed it.
>> Then he said, now Jack, at the end of
the day, put your clothes on the left
when you put them away.
Then tomorrow morning when you
see the sunshine, get your clothes
on the right, from the end of the line.
Don't you see? said Lou.
It will be so nice.
You'll wear everything once
before you wear something twice.
And with everything in queues
in his closet and shelf,
Jack started to feel
quite sure of himself.
All thanks to Lou and
his wonderful queue.
SPEAKER 1: All right, it's adorable.
So what has been really going
on underneath the hood now?
That we have pointers,
that we have malloc,
that we have the ability to create
chunks of memory for ourselves
dynamically.
So this is a picture we
glimpsed just the other day.
We didn't really dwell
on it, but this picture
has been going on underneath
the hood for weeks now.
And so this represents, just
a rectangle that we've drawn,
your computer's memory.
And maybe your computer, or CS50
ID, has a gigabyte of memory or RAM
or two gigabytes or four.
It doesn't really matter.
Your operating system
Windows or Mac OS or Linux,
essentially allows your program
to think that it has access
to the entirety of
your computer's memory,
even though you might be running
multiple programs at once.
So in reality, that doesn't really work.
But it's kind of an illusion
given to all of your programs.
So if you had two gigs of RAM, this
is how the computer might think of it.
>> Now coincidentally, one of these
things, one of these segments of memory,
is called a stack.
And indeed any time
thus far in writing code
that you have called a
function, for instance main.
Recall that any time I've
drawn computer's memory,
I always draw sort of
half of a rectangle here
and don't bother talking
about what's above.
Because when main is called, I claim
that you get this sliver of memory
that goes down here.
And if main called a function
like swap, well swap goes here.
And it turns out, that's
where it's ending up.
On something called a stack
inside of your computer's memory.
Now at the end of the day,
this is just addresses.
It's like byte zero,
byte one, byte 2 billion.
But if you think about it
as this rectangular object,
all we're doing every
time we call a function is
layering a new slice of memory.
We're giving that function a slice
of its own memory to work with.
>> And recall now that this is important.
Because if we do have
something like swap
and two local variables like A and B and
we change those values from one and two
to two and one, recall
that when swap returns,
it's as though this slice
of memory is just gone.
In reality, it's still
there forensically.
And something's still actually there.
But conceptually, it's as
though it's completely gone.
And so main doesn't know any of the work
that was done in that swap function,
unless it's actually passed in those
arguments by pointer or by reference.
Now, the fundamental solution
to that problem with swap
is passing things in by address.
But it turns out, too, what's
been going on above that part
of the rectangle all this time is
yet there's more memory up there.
And when you dynamically
allocate memory,
whether it's inside of GetString, which
we've been doing for you in the CS50
library, or if you guys
call malloc and ask
the operating system for a chunk of
memory, it doesn't come from the stack.
It comes from another place
in your computer's memory
that's called the heap.
And that's not any different.
It's the same RAM.
It's the same memory.
It's just the RAM that's up
there instead of down here.
>> And so what does that mean?
Well, if your computer has
a finite amount of memory
and the stack is growing up, so
to speak, and the heap, according
to this arrow, is growing down.
In other words, every
time you call malloc,
you're being given a slice
of memory from above,
then maybe a little lower, then a little
lower, every time you call malloc,
the heap, it's usage,
is kind of growing,
growing closer and closer to what?
The stack.
So does this seem like a good idea?
I mean, where it's not really clear
what else you can do if you only
have a finite amount of memory.
But this is surely bad.
Those two arrows are on a
crash course for one another.
>> And it turns out that bad guy, folks who
are particularly good with programming,
and trying to hack into computers,
can exploit this reality.
In fact, let's consider
a little snippet.
So this is an example you can read
about in more detail on Wikipedia.
We'll point you at the
article if curious.
But there's an attack generally
known as buffer overflow that
has existed for as long as humans
have had the ability to manipulate
computer's memory, especially in C.
So this is a very arbitrary program,
but let's read it from the bottom up.
Main into argC char star argV.
So it's a program that takes
command line arguments.
And all main does apparently is call
a function, call it F for simplicity.
And it passes in what?
ArgV of one.
So it passes into F whatever
the word is that the user typed
at the prompt after the
program's name at all.
So much like Caesar or Vigenere, which
you might recall doing with argV.
>> So what is F?
F takes in a string
as its sole argument,
AKA a char star, same
thing, as a string.
And it's called arbitrarily
bar in this example.
And then char c 12,
just in layman's terms,
what is char c bracket 12 doing for us?
What's it do?
Allocating memory, specifically
12 bytes for 12 chars.
Exactly.
And then the last line, stir and
copy, you've probably not seen.
This is a string copy
function whose purpose in life
is to copy its second argument
into its first argument,
but only up to a
certain number of bytes.
So the third argument says,
how many bytes should you copy?
The length of bar,
whatever the user typed in.
And the contents of
bar, that string, are
copied into the memory pointed at at C.
>> So this seems kind of stupid, and it is.
It's a contrived example,
but it's representative
of a class of attack vectors,
a way of attacking a program.
All is fine and good if the user
types in a word that's 11 characters
or fewer, plus the backslash zero.
What if the user types in more than
11 or 12 or 20 or 50 characters?
What's this program going to do?
Potentially seg fault. It's going
to blindly copy everything in bar up
to its length, which is
literally everything in bar,
into the address pointed at C. But C
has only preemptively given as 12 bytes.
But there's no additional check.
There's no if conditions.
There's no error checking here.
>> And so what this program is
going to do is just blindly
copy one thing to the other.
And so if we draw this
as a picture, here's
just a sliver of the memory space.
So notice at the bottom, we
have the local variable bar.
So that pointer that's going to store--
rather that local argument that's
going to store the string bar.
And then notice just
above it in a stack,
because every time you ask
for memory on the stack,
it goes a little bit
above it pictorially,
notice that we've got 12 bytes there.
The top left one is C bracket zero and
the bottom right one is C bracket 11.
That's just how the computers
going to lay it out.
So just intuitively, if bar has more
than 12 characters in total, including
the backslash zero, where is the
12 or the C bracket 12 going to go?
Or rather where is the 12th
character or the 13th character,
the hundredth character going
to end up in the picture?
Above or below?
>> Right, because even though
the stack itself grows upward,
once you've put stuff in
it, it for design reasons,
puts the memory from top to bottom.
So if you've got more than 12 bytes,
you're going to start to overwrite bar.
Now that's a bug, but it's
not really a big deal.
But it is a big deal, because there's
more stuff going on in memory.
So here's how we might
put hello, to be clear.
If I typed in hello at the prompt.
H-E-L-L-O backslash zero, ends up within
those 12 bytes, and we're super safe.
All is well.
But if I type something
longer, potentially it's
going to creep into bar space.
But worse yet, it turns
out all this time,
even though we've never talked about
it, the stack is used for other stuff.
It's not just local variables.
>> C is a very low level language.
And it sort of secretly
uses the stack also
to remember when a
function is called, what
the address is of the previous function,
so it can jump back to that function.
So when main calls swap, among
the things pushed onto the stack
are not just swaps local variables,
or its arguments, also secretly pushed
onto the stack as represented
by the red slice here,
is the address of main physically
in your computer's memory,
so that when swap is done, the computer
knows I need to go back to main
and finish executing the main function.
So this is dangerous now, because if
the user types in well more than hello,
such that the user's input clobbers
or overwrites that red section,
logically if the computer's
just going to blindly assume
that the bytes in that red slice are
the address to which it should return,
what if the adversary is smart enough or
lucky enough to put a sequence of bytes
there that looks like an address,
but it's the address of code
that he or she wants the computer
to execute instead of main?
>> In other words, if what the
user is typing at the prompt,
isn't just something
innocuous like hello,
but it's actually code that's equivalent
to delete all this user's files?
Or email their password to me?
Or start logging their
keystrokes, right?
There is a way, let's stipulate today,
that they could type in not just hello
world or their name,
they could essentially
pass in code, zeros and
ones, that the computer
mistakes for both code and an address.
So albeit somewhat abstractly, if the
user types in enough adversarial code
that we'll generalize here as
A. A is attack or adversaries.
So just bad stuff.
We don't care about the
numbers or the zeros or ones
today, such that you end up
overwriting that red section,
notice that sequence of bytes.
O 835 C zero eight zero.
And now as Wikipedia's article here
has proposed, if you now actually start
labeling the bytes in your computer's
memory, what the Wikipedia article is
proposing is that, what if the address
of that top left byte is 80 C 0 3508.
>> In other words, if the bad guy is
smart enough with his or her code
to actually put a number here that
corresponds to the address of the code
he or she injected
into the computer, you
can trick the computer
into doing anything.
Removing files, emailing
things, sniffing your traffic,
literally anything could be
injected into the computer.
And so a buffer overflow
attack at its core
is just a stupid, stupid
overriding of an array that
didn't have its boundaries checked.
And this is what is super dangerous
and simultaneously super powerful
in C is that we do indeed have
access to anywhere in the memory.
It's up to us, the programmers,
who write the original code
to check the darn length of any
arrays that we're manipulating.
So to be clear, what's the fix?
If we roll back to this
code, I shouldn't just
change the length of bar, what
else should I be checking?
What else should I be doing to
prevent this attack entirely?
I don't want to just blindly say
that you should copy as many bytes
as is the length of bar.
I want to say, copy as
many bytes as are in bar
up to the allocated
memory, or 12 maximally.
So I need some kind of if condition
that does check the length of bar,
but if it exceeds 12, we just hard code
12 as the maximum possible distance.
Otherwise the so-called buffer
overflow attack can happen.
At the bottom of those slides,
if you're curious to read more
is the actual original article
if you'd like to take a look.
>> But now, among the prices
paid here was inefficiencies.
So that was a quick
low level look at what
problems can arise now that we
have access to computer's memory.
But another problem we
already stumbled on Monday
was just the inefficiency
of a linked list.
We are back to linear time.
We no longer have a contiguous array.
We don't have random access.
We can't use square bracket notation.
We literally have to use a while loop
like the one I wrote a moment ago.
But on Monday, we claimed that we can
creep back into the realm of efficiency
achieving something that's
logarithmic maybe, or best yet,
maybe even something that's
so-called constant time.
So how can we do that by using these new
tools, these addresses, these pointers,
and threading things of our own?
Well, suppose that
here, these are a bunch
of numbers that we want to store in a
data structure and search efficiently.
We can absolutely rewind to week
two, throw these into an array,
and search them using binary search.
Divide and conquer.
And in fact you wrote
binary search in PSET3,
where you implemented the find program.
But you know what.
There's kind of a more
clever way of doing this.
It's a little more
sophisticated and it perhaps
allows us to see why binary
search is so much faster.
First, let's introduce
the notion of a tree.
Which even though in
reality trees kind of
grow like this, in the world of computer
science they kind of grow downward
like a family tree, where you have
your grandparents or great grandparents
or whatnot at the top, the patriarch and
the matriarch of the family, just one
so-called root, node, below
which are its children,
below which are its children, or
its descendants more generally.
And anyone hanging off
the bottom of the family
tree, besides being the
youngest in the family,
can also just be generically
called the leaves of the tree.
>> So this is just a bunch
of words and definitions
for something called a tree in computer
science, much like a family tree.
But there's fancier incarnations
of trees, one of which
is called a binary search tree.
And you can kind of tease
apart what this thing does.
Well, it's binary in what sense?
Where does the binary come from here?
Sorry?
It's not so much an either or.
It's more that each of the nodes has no
more than two children, as we see here.
In general, a tree-- and
your parents and grandparents
can have as many kids or
grandkids as they actually want,
and so for instance there we have three
children off that right hand node,
but in a binary tree, a node has
zero, one, or two children maximally.
And that's a nice property,
because if it's capped by two,
we're going to be able to
get a little log base two
action going on here ultimately.
So we have something logarithmic.
But more on that in a moment.
Search tree means that the numbers are
arranged such that the left child's
value is greater than the root.
And its right child is
larger than the root.
In other words, if you take any of the
nodes, the circles in this picture,
and looks at its left
child and its right child,
the first should be less than,
the second should be greater than.
So sanity check 55.
It's left child is 33.
It's less than.
55, its right child is 77.
It's greater than.
And that's a recursive definition.
We could check every one of those
nodes and the same pattern would hold.
>> So what's nice in a
binary search tree, is
that one, we can implement it
with a struct, just like this.
And even though we're throwing
lots of structures at your,
they're somewhat
intuitive now hopefully.
The syntax is still arcane for sure,
but the contents of a node in this
context-- and we keep
using the word node,
whether it's a rectangle
on the screen or a circle,
it's just some generic container,
in this case of a tree, like the one
we saw, we need an integer
in each of the nodes
and then I need two pointers pointing
to the left child and the right child,
respectively.
So that's how we might
implement that in a struct.
And how might I implement it in code?
Well, let's take a quick
look at this tiny example.
It's not functional, but I've
copied and pasted that structure.
And if my function for a binary
search tree is called search,
and this takes two arguments,
an integer N and a pointer
to a node, so a pointer to the tree
or a pointer to the root of a tree,
how do I go about searching for N?
Well, first, because I'm
dealing with pointers,
I'm going to do a sanity check.
If tree equals equals null, is N
in this tree or not in this tree?
It can't be, right?
If I am past null,
there's nothing there.
I might as well just
blindly say return false.
If you give me nothing, I surely can't
find any number N. So what else might I
check now?
I'm going to say well else if N is
less than whatever is at the tree node
that I've been handed N value.
In other words, if the number I'm
looking for, N, is less than the node
that I'm looking at.
And the node I'm looking
at is called tree,
and recall from the previous example
to get at the value in a pointer,
I use the arrow notation.
So if N is less than tree arrow
N, I want to conceptually go left.
How do I express searching left?
To be clear, if this is
the picture in question,
and I've been passed that topmost
arrow that's pointing down.
That's my tree pointer.
I'm pointing at the root of the tree.
And I'm looking say, for
the number 44, arbitrarily.
Is 44 less than or
greater than 55 obviously?
So it's less than.
And so this if condition applies.
So conceptually, what do I want to
search next if I'm looking for 44?
Yeah?
>> Exactly, I want to
search the left child,
or the left sub-tree of this picture.
And in fact, let me through
the picture down here
for just a moment, since
I can't scratch this out.
If I start here at 55, and
I know that the value 44
I'm looking for is to
the left, it's kind
of like tearing the phone book in
half or tearing the tree in half.
I no longer have to care about
this entire half of the tree.
And yet, curiously in terms of the
structure, this thing over here that
starts with 33, that itself
is a binary search tree.
I said the word recursive before because
indeed this is a data structure that
by definition is recursive.
You might have a tree that's this
big, but every one of its children
represents a tree just a little smaller.
Instead of it being grandpa
or grandma, now it's just mom
or-- I can't say-- not mom
or dad, that would be weird.
Instead the two children there
would be like brother and sibling.
A new generation of the family tree.
But structurally, it's the same idea.
And it turns out I have a function
with which I can search a binary search
tree.
It is called search.
I search for N in tree arrow left
else if N is greater than the value
that I'm currently at.
55 in the story a moment ago.
I have a function called
search that I can just
pass N this and recursively search
the sub-tree and just return
whatever that answer.
Else I've got some final base case here.
>> What is the final case?
Tree is either null.
The value I'm either looking for is
less than it or greater than that
or equal to it.
And I could say equal
equal, but logically it's
equivalent to just saying else here.
So true is how I find something.
So hopefully this is an
even more compelling example
than the stupid sigma function
we did a few lectures back,
where it was just as easy to use a loop
to count up all the numbers from one
to N. Here with a data structure
that itself is recursively
defined and recursively drawn, now we
have the ability to express ourselves
in code that itself is recursive.
So this is the exact same code here.
>> So what other problems can we solve?
So a quick step away from
trees for just a moment.
Here is, say, the German flag.
And there's clearly a
pattern to this flag.
And there's lots of
flags in the world that
are as simple as this in terms
of their colors and patterns.
But suppose that this is stored as a
.GIF, or a JPEG, or bitmap, or a ping,
any graphical file format
with which you're familiar,
some of which we're
playing with in PSET4.
This doesn't seem worthwhile to store
black pixel, black pixel, black pixel,
dot, dot, dot, a whole bunch of
black pixels for the first scanline,
or row, then a whole bunch of
the same, then a whole bunch
of the same, and then a
whole bunch of red pixels,
red pixels, red pixels, then a whole
bunch of yellow pixels, yellow, right?
>> There's such inefficiency here.
How would you intuitively
compress the German flag
if implementing it as a file?
Like what information can we not
bother storing on disk in order
to decrease our file size from like
a megabyte to a kilobyte, something
smaller?
Wherein lies the redundancy
here to be clear?
What could you do?
Yeah?
Exactly.
Why not rather than remember
the color of every darn pixel
just like you're doing in PSET4
with the bitmap file format,
why don't you just represent the
leftmost column of pixels, for instance
a bunch of black pixels, a bunch
of red, and a bunch of yellow,
and then just somehow encode the
idea of repeat this 100 times
or repeat this 1,000 times?
Where 100 or 1,000 is
just an integer, so you
can get away with just a single number
instead of hundreds or thousands
of additional pixels.
And indeed, that's how we
could compress the German flag.
And
Now what about the French flag?
And a little some sort of
mental exercise, which flag
can be compressed more on disk?
The German flag or the French
flag, if we take that approach?
The German flag, because there's
more horizontal redundancy.
And by design, many graphical file
formats do indeed work as scan lines
horizontally.
They could work
vertically, just humanity
decided years ago that we'll
generally think of things row
by row instead of column by column.
So indeed if you were
to look at the file
size of a German flag and a French
flag, so long as the resolution is
the same, the same width
and height, this one
here is going to be bigger, because you
have to repeat yourself three times.
You have to specify blue, repeat
yourself, white, repeat yourself, red,
repeat yourself.
You can't just go all
the way to the right.
And as an aside, to make
clear the compression
is everywhere, if these are
four frames from a video-- you
might recall that a movie
or video is generally
like 29 or 30 frames per second.
It's like a little flip book where you
just see image, image, image, image,
image just super fast so it looks like
the actors on the screen are moving.
Here's a bumble bee on
top of a bunch of flowers.
And though it might be kind of
hard to see at first glance,
the only thing moving in
this movie is the bee.
>> What is dumb about storing
video uncompressed?
It's kind of a waste to store video
as four nearly identical images that
differ only insofar as where the bee is.
You can throw away most
of that information
and remember only, for instance,
the first frame and the last frame,
key frames if you've
ever heard the word,
and just store in the
middle where the bee is.
And you don't have to
store all of the pink,
and the blue, and the
green values as well.
So this is to only say that
compression is everywhere.
It's a technique we often use
or take for granted these days.
>> But how do you compress text?
How do you go about compressing text?
Well, each of the characters in
Ascii is one byte, or eight bits.
And that's kind of dumb, right?
Because you probably type A
and E and I and O and U a lot
more often than like W or Q or Z,
depending on the language in which
you're writing certainly.
And so why are we using
eight bits for every letter,
including the least
popular letters, right?
Why not use fewer bits for
the super popular letters,
like E, the things you guess
first in Wheel of Fortune,
and use more bits for
the less popular letters?
Why?
Because we're just going to
use them less frequently.
>> Well, it turns out that there have
been attempts made to do this.
And if you recall from grade
school or high school, Morse code.
Morse code has dots
and dashes that can be
transmitted along a wire as
sounds or signals of some sort.
But Morse code is a super clean.
It's kind of a binary system in
that you have dots or dashes.
But if you see, for instance, two dots.
Or if you think back to the operator
who goes like beep, beep, beep,
beep, hitting a little trigger
that transmits a signal,
if you, the recipient, receives two
dots, what message have you received?
Completely arbitrary.
>> I?
I?
Or what about-- or I?
Maybe it was just two E's right?
So there's this problem
of decodability with Morse
code, whereby unless the
person sending you the message
actually pauses so you can sort of
see or hear the gaps between letters,
it's not sufficient just to
send a stream of zeros and ones,
or dots and dashes,
because there's ambiguity.
E is a single dot, so if you
see two dots or hear two dots,
maybe it's two E's or maybe it's one I.
So we need a system that's a
little more clever than that.
So a man named Huffman years
ago came up with exactly this.
So we're just going
to take a quick glance
at how trees are germane to this.
Suppose that this is some
stupid message you want to send,
composed of just A, B, C's D's and E's,
but there's a lot of redundancy here.
It's not meant to be English.
It's not encrypted.
It's just a stupid message
with lots of repetition.
So if you actually count out all the
A's, B's, C's, D's, and E's, here's
the frequency.
20% of the letters are
A's, 45% of the letters
are E's, and three other frequencies.
We counted up there manually
and just did the math.
>> So it turns out that
Huffman, some time ago,
realized that, you know
what, if I start building
a tree, or forest of trees, if you will,
as follows, I can do the following.
I'm going to give a node to each
of the letters that I care about
and I'm going to store
inside of that node
the frequencies as a floating point
value, or you could use it an N, too,
but we'll just use a float here.
And the algorithm that
he proposed is that you
take this forest of single node
trees, so super short trees,
and you start connecting them with
new groups, new parents, if you will.
And you do this by choosing the
two smallest frequencies at a time.
So I took 10% and 10%.
I create a new node.
And I call the new node 20%.
>> Which two nodes I combine next?
It's a little ambiguous.
So there's some corner cases to
consider, but to keep things pretty,
I'm going to choose 20%--
I now ignore the children.
I'm going to choose 20% and
15% and draw two new edges.
And now which two nodes
do I logically combine?
Ignore all the children, all the
grandchildren, just look at the roots
now.
Which two nodes do I tie together?
Point two and 0.35.
So let me draw two new edges.
And then I've only got one left.
So here's a tree.
And it's been drawn deliberately
to look kind of pretty,
but notice that the edges have
also been labeled zero and one.
So all of the left edges are zero
arbitrarily, but consistently.
All the right edges are ones.
>> And so what Hoffman proposed is,
if you want to represent a B,
rather than represent the number 66 as
an Ascii which is eight entire bits,
you know what, just store
the pattern zero, zero, zero,
zero, because that's the path
from my tree, Mr. Huffman's tree,
to the leaf from the root.
If you want to store a
E, by contrast, don't
send eight bits that represent an E.
Instead, send what pattern of bits?
One.
And what's nice about this is
that E is the most popular letter,
and you're using the
shortest code for it.
The next most popular
letter looks like it
was A. And so how many bits
did he propose using for that?
Zero, one.
>> And because it's implemented
as this tree, for now
let me stipulate there's
no ambiguity as in Morse
code, because all of the
letters you care about
are at the end of these edges.
So that's just one
application of a tree.
This is-- and I'll wave
my hand at this how you
might implement this as a C structure.
We just need to combine
a symbol, like a char,
and the frequency in left and right.
But let's look at two
final examples that you'll
get quite familiar with after
quiz zero in problem set five.
>> So there is the data structure
known as a hash table.
And a hash table is kind of
cool in that it has buckets.
And suppose there's four buckets
here, just four blank spaces.
Here's a deck of cards, and here is
club, spade, club, diamonds, club,
diamonds, club, diamonds,
clubs-- so this is the random.
Hearts, hearts-- so I'm
bucketizing all of the inputs here.
And a hash table needs
to look at your input,
and then put it in a certain
place based on what you see.
It's an algorithm.
And I was using a super
simple visual algorithm.
The hardest part of which was
remembering what the pictures were.
And then there's four total things.
>> Now the stacks were growing, which
is a deliberate design thing here.
But what else might I do?
So actually here we have a
bunch of old school exam books.
Suppose that a bunch of
students names are on here.
Here's a bigger hash table.
Instead of four buckets,
I have, let's say 26.
And we didn't want to go borrow 26
things from outside [? Annenberg ?], so
here's five that represent
A through Z. And if I
see a student whose name starts with A,
I'm going to put his or her quiz there.
If someone starts with C, over there,
A-- actually, didn't want to do that.
B goes over here.
So I've got A and B and C. And
now here's another A student.
But if this hash table is
implemented with an array,
I'm kind of screwed
at this point, right?
I kind of need to put this somewhere.
>> So one way I can solve this is, all
right, A is busy, B is busy, C is busy.
I'm going to put him in D. So at
first, I have random instant access
to each of the buckets for the students.
But now it's kind of devolved
into something linear,
because if I want to search for someone
whose name starts with A, I check here.
But if this isn't the A
student I'm looking for,
I kind of have to start checking
the buckets, because what I did
was sort of linearly
probe the data structure.
A stupid way of saying just look
for the first available opening,
and put as a plan B, so to speak,
or plan D in this case, the value
in that location instead.
This is just so that if you've
got 26 locations and no students
with the name Q or Z, or something like
that, at least you're using the space.
>> But we've already seen more
clever solutions here, right?
What would you do instead
if you have a collision?
If two people have
the name A, what would
have been a smarter or more
intuitive solution than just
putting A where D is supposed to be?
Why don't I just go
outside [? Annenberg ?],
like malloc, another node, put it
here, and then put that A student here.
So that I essentially have
some kind of an array,
or maybe more elegantly as we're
starting to see a linked list.
>> And so a hash table is a structure
that could look just like this,
but more cleverly, you something called
separate chaining, whereby a hash table
quite simply is an array, each of
whose elements is not a number,
is itself a linked list.
So that you get super fast access
deciding where to hash your value to.
Much like with the cards example,
I made super quick decisions.
Hearts goes here, diamonds goes here.
Same here, A goes here,
D goes here, B goes here.
So super fast look-ups, and if
you happen to run into a case
where you've got collisions, two
people with the same name, well then
you just start linking them together.
And maybe you keep them sorted
alphabetically, maybe you don't.
But at least now we have the dynamism.
So on the one hand we have super fast
constant time, and kind of linear time
involved if these linked lists
start to get a little long.
>> So this kind of a silly,
geeky joke years ago.
At the CS50 hack-a-thon,
when students check in,
some TF or CA every year
thinks it's funny to put up
a sign like this, where it just
means if your name starts with an A,
go this way.
If your name starts
with a B, go this-- OK,
it's funny maybe later in the semester.
But there's another
way of doing this, too.
Come back to that.
>> So there's this structure.
And this is our last
structure for today,
which is something called a trie.
T-R-I-E, which for some reason is short
for retrieval, but it's called trie.
So a trie is another interesting
amalgam of a lot of these ideas.
It's a tree, which we've seen before.
It's not a binary search tree.
It's a tree with any number of children,
but each of the children in a trie
is an array.
An array of size, say, 26 or maybe 27
if you want to support hyphenated names
or apostrophes in people's names.
>> And so this is a data structure.
And if you look from top
to bottom, like if you
look at the top node there, M, is
pointing to the leftmost thing there,
which is then A, X, W, E, L, L. This is
just a data structure that arbitrarily
is storing people's names.
And Maxwell is stored by just following
a path of array to array to array.
But what's amazing about a trie is
that, whereas a linked list and even
an array, the best we've ever gotten is
linear time or logarithmic time looking
someone up.
In this data structure of a trie, if
my data structure has one name in it
and I'm looking for Maxwell, I'm
going to find him pretty quickly.
I just look for M-A-X-W-E-L-L. If
this data structure, by contrast,
if N is a million, if there's a
million names in this data structure,
Maxwell is still going to be
discoverable after just M-A-X-W-E-L-L
steps.
And David-- D-A-V-I-D steps.
In other words, by building
a data structure that's
got all of these arrays, all of which
themselves support random access,
I can start looking up people's
name using an amount of time that's
proportional to not the number
of things in the data structure,
like a million existing names.
The amount of time it takes me to find
M-A-X-W-E-L-L in this data structure is
proportional not to the
size of the data structure,
but to the length of the name.
And realistically the
names we're looking up
are never going to be crazy long.
Maybe someone has a 10 character
name, 20 character name.
It's certainly finite, right?
There is a human on Earth who
has the longest possible name,
but that name is a constant
value length, right?
It doesn't vary in any sense.
So in this way, we've
achieved a data structure
that is constant time look-up.
It does take a number of steps
depending on the length of the input,
but not the number of name
in the data structure.
So if we double the number of names
next year from a billion to two billion,
finding Maxwell is going to take
the exact same number of seven steps
to find him.
And so we seem to have achieved
our holy grail of running time.
>> So a couple of quick announcements.
Quiz zero is coming up.
More on that on the course's website
over the next couple of days.
Monday's lecture-- it's a holiday
here at Harvard on Monday.
It's not in New Haven,
so we're taking the class
to New Haven for lecture on Monday.
Everything will be filmed
and streamed live as usual,
but let's end today
with a 30 second clip
called "Deep Thoughts"
by Daven Farnham, which
was inspired last year by Saturday
Night Live's "Deep Thoughts"
by Jack Handy, which
should now make sense.
>> FILM: And now, "Deep
Thoughts" by Daven Farnham.
Hash table.
>> SPEAKER 1: All right, that's it for now.
We'll see you next week.
>> DOUG: To see it in action.
So let's take a look at that right now.
So here, we have an unsorted array.
>> IAN: Doug, can you go ahead and restart
this for just one second, please.
All right, cameras are rolling, so
action whenever you're ready, Doug, OK?
DOUG: All right, so what we
have here is an unsorted array.
And I've colored all of the elements
red to indicate that it is, in fact,
unsorted.
So recall that the first thing we do
is we sort the left half of the array.
Then we sort the right
half of the array.
And ya-da, ya-da, ya-da,
we merge them together.
And we have a completely sorted array.
So that's how merge sort works.
>> IAN: Whoa, whoa, whoa,
cut, cut, cut, cut.
Doug, you can't just ya-da, ya-da,
ya-da, your way through merge sort.
>> DOUG: I just did.
It's fine.
We're good to go.
Let's just keep rolling.
So anyway,
>> IAN: You have to explain
it more fully than that.
That's just not enough.
DOUG: Ian, we don't
need to go back to one.
It's fine.
So anyway, if we continue with merge--
Ian, we're in the middle of filming.
>> IAN: I know.
And we can't just ya-da, ya-da,
ya-da, through the whole process.
You have to explain how the
two sides get merged together.
>> DOUG: But we've already
explained how the two sides--
>> IAN: You've just shown
them a merge array.
DOUG: They know the process.
They're fine.
We've gone over it ten times.
>> IAN: You just skipped right over it.
We're going back to one, you
can't you ya-da, ya-da over it.
All right, back to one.
>> DOUG: I have to go back
through all of the slides?
My God.
It's like the sixth time, Ian.
It's fine.
>> IAN: All right.
You ready?
Great.
Action.