>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So I just
wanted to assuage to.
I would echo exactly what Scaz
said about institutional memory.
CS50 has been around for
some 20 years at Harvard.
And the reality is, from
the seniors on down,
there is annually reassurance
that the freshmen, the sophomores,
and the juniors and
also the seniors taking
CS50, that you end up doing fine.
>> The reality is, students
do not fail CS50.
In fact, in the rare instances
where we've had Es or Fs,
it's really been because of
extenuating circumstances,
whether it's medical or personal.
Ds are incredibly uncommon as well.
And I can say comfortably, though we
typically don't disclose statistics,
but given that there is no
institutional memory here whatsoever,
a majority of students in CS50
do end up getting A range grades.
A significant chunk end up
ending up in the B range too.
>> So even though you might be
equating in your mind threes
with 60% and therefore
Ds, or Cs, or the like,
it really does not line
up with the reality.
In fact, we mean exactly what we
say at the beginning of the term
that so many students in CS50, both
in Cambridge and here in New Haven,
have never taken a CS course before.
And what indeed ultimately matters
is where you end up in week 12
relative to yourself in week zero.
Now we have multiple
tracks in the course
as you know-- less comfortable, more
comfortable, somewhere in between.
And indeed, when you get
statistics on this week's quiz,
don't be discouraged if, especially if
you feel that you're around the mean
or below the mean or the median,
especially since we don't necessarily
take all those demographics
into account mid-semester
with the grading statistics.
>> In other words, we know
statistically every year
that students who are less comfortable,
do a little worse on the quiz.
And students who are more comfortable
do a little better on the quiz.
But per that promise in the syllabus
and also in the first week of lectures,
we take all of that into account.
>> Indeed, at years end,
what we end up doing
is normalizing all scores across
sections, both in Cambridge
and now here in New Haven,
which means taking into account
the disparate styles, the disparate
harshness, the different sort
of personalities that the individual
TAs have here and in Cambridge
so that you're not at a
disadvantage even if you just
happen to have had a TF or a TA
who's been a little tougher on you
in your mind.
>> Two, we take into account comfort
level and actual background, or lack
thereof, when taking
quiz scores into account.
So those two are factored in.
And at the end of the day,
because it's always the case
that a student ended up
in a less comfy section
when he or she really belonged
in an in-between or vice versa,
everything is so
incredibly individualized.
Indeed, you will get annoyed at us at
the end of the term when we are late
submitting your grades because with
Scaz, and Jason, and Andy, and I,
and the team will have done
in Cambridge is literally
have hundreds of emails back and
forth with all hundred of the courses
TAs, here and in
Cambridge, asking them what
they think of all of their students
based on a draft of the grades.
And everything there after
is incredibly individualized.
So to the extent we get to know you
in office hours, sections, and more,
all of that too is taken into account.
>> So though we tend to use this five
point scale, please, detach yourself
from the assumption that
a three is indeed a 60%.
It is meant to be good.
And the teaching assistants
are charged at term start
to try to keep scores
in the twos, and threes,
and fours range so that we
actually have room to grow.
And we actually have
a yardstick by which
we can give you useful
feedback as to how you're doing
and how you're progressing.
So please do take that to heart.
>> Are there any questions I can help
address or concerns I can help assuage?
Or promises I can try to keep?
No?
OK.
>> All right.
So with that said, this is CS50.
This is the start of week
six here in New Haven.
Let's begin with a brief
dimming of the lights
to set the stage for today's content.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
-He came with a message.
With a protocol all his own.
He came to a world of cool firewalls,
uncaring routers, and dangers far worse
that death.
He's fast, he's strong, he's TCP/IP.
And he's got your address.
Warriors of the net.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50.
This is the start of week six.
And this is the start of our look
at the internet and web programming.
And, perhaps most excitingly,
today marks the transition for us
from our command line
world of C to the web
based world of PHP, and HTML,
and CSS, and SQL, and JavaScript,
and so much more that is on the horizon.
>> But first, it has come to our attention
in walking across campus that there
is a certain bathroom here in New
Haven called the Harvard room, which
is a little greyed out here.
But indeed, someone went to the time
and expense of etching in Harvard room
on this here room.
Thank you for that.
I can't say we have an
analogue in Cambridge yet,
but I think we have a little project
for ourselves now when we go back.
So thank you for that.
>> So a quick look back at
where we left off last week
and where you're going this coming
week with problems set five.
So in problem set five, you'll be
challenged to implement a spellchecker.
And to do that, you'll be
handed a pretty big text
file with like 140,000 English words.
And you'll be challenged to decide
on a data structure with which you
want to load all of those words
into memory, and into RAM,
and then implement a few functions,
one of which is going to be check.
Whereby when passed an argument,
a word, your function check
simply is going to have
to say true or false,
this is a word in the dictionary.
>> But you're going to have some
design discretion and challenges
when it comes to implementing that.
In the simplest implementation,
you could certainly
implement a spellchecker in
the underlying dictionary
with what kind of data structure?
You just need to store a whole
bunch of strings in memory?
What's the go to answer
from week two perhaps?
AUDIENCE: Array.
DAVID J. MALAN: You can use an array.
And that's not all that bad.
But you don't necessarily know
in advance how big of an array
you're going to need, if you don't
know the file necessarily in advance.
So you're going to have to
use a little bit of trickery
like malloc, like we started using.
Or we could address
that concern by using
what other data structure that's
been sort of a marginal enhancement
on an array?
AUDIENCE: Linked list.
DAVID J. MALAN: Like a linked
list, wherein we get some dynamism.
But there's a little more expense.
We have pointers to maintain.
And you've not yet coded this
up, but there's definitely
to be a little more complexity
than just using square brackets
and jumping around an array.
>> But an array's running time,
if you're searching for a word,
might be log of n.
But again, it might be
a little non-trivial
to build up that array not
knowing the size in advance.
A linked list though, if you
just store a bunch of strings
in a linked list,
what's your upper bound
on running time going to be to search
for or check a word in that list?
>> AUDIENCE: n.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, big O of n or
linear because in the worst case,
the word is like a Z word
all the way at the end.
And because of a linked list,
because those arrows by default,
in a singly linked list, only go
from one direction to the other,
you can't jump around.
You have to follow all of them.
>> So we proposed at the end of last week,
week five, that there are better ways.
And in fact, the holy grail
would really be constant time
whereby when you want
to look up a word, you
get an instant answer irrespective
of how many words are already
in your dictionary.
>> This is an artist's rendition of
what you might call a hash table.
And a hash table is kind of a nice
amalgam of an array-- drawn vertically
here, just because-- and then a
linked list-- draw horizontally here.
And the hash table can be
implemented in bunches of ways.
This excerpt from a textbook happens
to use these people's birth dates
as the means by which it's deciding
where to put someone's name.
So this is a dictionary
if you will of names.
And in order to expedite putting
names into this data structure,
they look at, apparently, these people's
birth dates with respect to a month.
>> So it's 1 to 31.
And forget about February
and corner cases like that.
And if your birthday is on January
1, or February 1, or December 1,
you're going to end up at
the very first chain up top.
If your birth date is
like the 25th of a month,
you're going to end up
at bucket number 25.
And if there's already someone there
in any of those locations, what
you start doing with these linked
lists is stitching them together
so that you can have an arbitrary
number of people, or anything,
at that location.
>> So you have kind of a mix of
constant time for hashing.
And to hash something means to
take as input like a person,
or his or her name, or his or her birth
date, and then decide on some output
based on that, like looking at their
birthday and outputting one through 31.
>> So then you might have
a bit of linear time,
but in reality, and as in
the case of problem set five,
we're not going to be
working in P set five
so much about asymptotic running
time, like the theoretical slowness
with which an algorithm might run.
We're going to care about
the actual number of seconds
and the actual amount of memory,
the actual number of bytes of memory
you're using.
So frankly, having one huge
chain of like a million people
is pretty damn slow if you're searching
for a name in a list of size million.
>> But what if you divide
that list up into 31 parts?
Searching 1/31 of that
super long list, in reality,
is certainly going to be faster.
Asymptotically, it's the same thing.
You're just dividing
by a constant factor.
And recall that we
throw those things away.
But in reality, it's going
to be 31 times faster.
And that's what we're going to
start to leverage in P set five.
>> So P set five too also
proposes that you consider
slightly more sophisticated
data structure called a trie.
And a trie is just a
tree like data structure.
But instead of having
little circles or rectangles
as we keep drawing
for nodes, it actually
has entire arrays for its nodes.
And even though this is a
bit abstract here to look at,
Zamyla in the P set walk
through will walk you
through in more detail on this.
This is a data structure
that rather cleverly
might have each node being an array
of size 26, A through Z or zero
through 25.
And when you want to insert a person's
name into this data structure or find
him or her, what you do, if the
name is like Maxwell, M-A-X-W-E-L-L,
you first look at M. And then you
jump to the corresponding M location
in the first array.
You then jump to A, the first
location in the next array,
following the arrows.
Then X, then W, then E, then L, then
L, and then maybe some special end
character, some sentinel
that says a word stops here.
>> And what's nice about this-- and
keep in mind that the picture here,
notice how edges of
every array are cut off.
That's just because this thing would
be massive and horrific to look
at on the screen.
So it's excerpted.
What's nice about this approach is
that if there's a million names already
in this data structure, how many steps
does it take me to insert Maxwell?
M-A-X-W-E-L-L-- like seven-ish
steps to insert or look for Maxwell.
>> Suppose there's a trillion
names in this data structure.
How many steps does it take
me to look for Maxwell?
M-A-X-- still seven.
>> And therein lies the
so-called constant time.
If we assume that words
are certainly bounded
by 20 characters, or 46 characters,
or some reasonably small integer,
then it's effectively a constant.
And so insertion and searching
a trie is super fast.
Of course, we never
get anything for free.
And even though you probably
haven't dived into P set five yet,
what price are we probably paying to
get that greater efficiency time wise?
>> AUDIENCE: Memory.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Memory, right?
I mean, we've not drawn
the whole picture here.
This excerpt from the textbook
hasn't drawn all of the arrays.
There's a huge amount of memory and just
null pointers that aren't being used.
So it's a trade off.
And it'll be left to you in P set five
to decide on which way you want to go.
>> Now this idea of hashing, as an
aside, is actually super prevalent.
So to hash a value means, quite
simply, to take something as input
and produce an output.
So a hash function is just an algorithm.
>> And generally, a hash functions purpose
in life is to take something as input
and produce a number as output, like the
number one through 31 or A through Z,
zero through 25.
So it takes a complex output
and shrinks it down to something
that's a little more
useful and manageable.
>> And so it turns out in
a very popular function
that the security world
and the human world's
been using for years is called SHA1.
This is a pretty fancy mathematical
formula that does essentially that.
>> You take a really big
chunk of zeros and ones--
that could be a megabyte
long, a gigabyte long--
and it shrinks it down to
just a few bits, a few bits,
so that you have a number like
one through 31, or A through Z.
But in reality, it's a little
bigger than just A through Z.
>> Unfortunately, we're on the cusp of what
someone playfully called the SHAppening
whereby the world is about to
end in probably a few months
time because researchers,
just this past week,
published a report that contrary to
what security researchers have thought
for some time, by just
spending about, what was it,
I think it was $175,000--
a lot of money,
but not beyond the reach of
particularly bad bad guys,
or particularly bad countries-- $175,000
could buy you a lot of rented server
space in the cloud.
And we'll come back to
the cloud before long.
But it just means renting server
space on like Microsoft's servers,
or Google's, or Amazon's, or the
like where you can pay by the minute
to use someone else's computers.
>> And it turns out if you can pay
someone else to borrow their computers
and run code that you've written
on it and use pretty fancy
mathematics, you can essentially figure
out how someone's hash function is
working, and given its output,
reverse engineer what its input is.
And for today's purposes,
suffice it to say, this is bad.
Because SHA1 and hash functions
like it are super commonly
used in security applications,
encrypted connections on the web,
bank transactions, cellular encryption
for your cell phones, and the like.
And so any time someone
finds a way to reverse
engineer one of these technologies
or break it, bad things can happen.
>> Now the world already knew this.
This was foreseeable.
And the world has since
moved from SHA1 to SHA256,
which is just a fancy way of
saying they use bigger bits.
And in fact, even CS50's own
website upgraded last year to--
not that we face all this many
threats trying to get at the PDFs
and whatnot-- but CS50's website
uses the bigger hash function,
which means that we will be safe.
So all of your PDFs
will be safe, but not
necessarily your money or anything
particularly private or personal
to use.
Sp check out that URL if you'd
like some additional details.
>> So problem set five is
indeed on the horizon.
Quiz one is this coming Wednesday.
But do take advantage of office
hours, both tonight and tomorrow.
And also take advantage of office hours,
if you're available, right after this.
The staff and I'll stick around and do
more casual Q&A in addition to tonight.
And let me strongly note here, for
those of us here in New Haven--
so it's absolutely per Scaz's
remarks felt, I'm sure,
like a bit of an uphill struggle.
And by reputation, if you
haven't learned already or heard
from some friends at Harvard, know
here are some new institutional memory.
P set five kind of sort of
tends to be the hardest in CS50,
or the most challenging
for most students.
>> But what that means is that we're
almost at the top of this hill.
And I really do mean this.
It's the most challenging, but
it's also the most rewarding
in that unlike most every other
introductory computer science
course in the US that we know of,
most students do not finish an intro
course having already implemented
things like trees, and tries,
and hash tables, and the like.
>> And so I do hope, and
we do hope that you're
have an enormous sense
of satisfaction even
if the week or two via which
you get to that satisfaction
does feel a little bit like this.
But let me reassure, we
only have four P sets left.
So sort of that top is in sight.
>> On the other side of it, trust us,
it's just rolling hills and clouds.
And shall we say, puppies
are on the other side.
So you just have to hang
in there a little longer.
I mean, indeed as we start to transition
into the world of web programming,
you'll find that things become--
this is adorable actually.
OK, we'll post this URL later.
You'll find too that we're
reaching sort of a plateau
where everything is
indeed still sophisticated
and challenging by
design, but you're not
going to feel like we are
perpetually going up this hill.
So take some comfort in that.
>> So without further ado, let's start
to make this market transition
in the semester to the world of
the web, and really the world
with which all of us are more familiar.
We've got internet devices
in our pockets, on our desks,
in our backpacks, and the like.
How does all of this work?
And how can we start writing
code that's not super arcane
and in some blinking text prompt
that none of your friends or family
are ever going to want to interact
with, but something you can put
on their phones, or
on their web browsers,
or on any devices with
which they interact.
>> So here is someone's home.
And inside of this home is a couple of
laptops, a couple of old school desktop
computers, something called a
router or hub in the middle,
and then some kind of
cable modem or DSL modem.
And then there's the internet, generally
drawn as a cloud up there in the sky.
>> So this picture, though
a little sort of dated,
certainly captures what most of
you probably have in your homes,
or effectively what all of you have
in your dorm rooms, or apartments,
or the like.
>> So what is actually going on when
you try to use the internet today?
So every computer on the
internet, it turns out,
needs to have a unique address,
much like we in the real world need
a postal address, like 51 Prospect
Street, New Haven, Connecticut, or 33
Oxford Street, Cambridge, Massachusetts.
So do computers on the internet need a
way of uniquely addressing themselves.
>> That is so that when one computer
wants to talk to another,
it can send a message and
inform the recipient to whom
it should send the response back.
So it just makes sort of
intuitive sense perhaps
that everything have an
address of some sort.
>> But how do you get an address?
Well, if you get here on
campus, or you go home
and you turn on your
laptop or desktop computer,
and either plug it in
or connect to Wi-Fi,
it turns out that
there's a special server
on most networks called a DHCP server.
Doesn't really matter
what this stands for,
but it's dynamic host configuration
protocol, which is just
a fancy way of saying, this is
a computer that either Yale has,
or Harvard has, or Comcast
has, or Verizon has,
or your company has,
whose purpose in life,
when it hears someone newly added
to the network, is to say here,
use this address.
>> So we humans don't have to
hard code into our computers
what our unique address is.
We just turn it on, open the
lid, and somehow this server
on the local network just tells me that
my address is 51 Prospect Street, or 33
Oxford Street, or the like.
>> Now it's not going to
be so verbose as that.
Rather what I'm going to get is a
numeric address called an IP address.
IP meaning internet protocol.
And odds are by this time in your life,
you probably heard or seen the word IP,
or generally thrown it around perhaps.
But in fact, it's pretty
straight forward a thing.
>> An IP address is just a
dotted decimal number,
which means it's something dot
something dot something dot something.
And each of those somethings happens
to be a number between 0 and 255.
>> So based on five plus weeks of CS50, if
these numbers each range from 0 to 255,
how many bits is each
of those number signs?
>> AUDIENCE: Eight.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: It's got to be eight.
So in total, how many
bits is an IP address?
AUDIENCE: 32.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So 32.
8 plus 8 plus 8 plus 8 is 32.
How many total IP addresses
can there be in the world?
AUDIENCE: 4 billion.
DAVID J. MALAN: So roughly four
billion because that's 2 the 32 power.
And if you can't sort of
grok that in your mind,
just know that 32-bit values
can be as big as 4 billion
if it's all positive values.
So that means there's 4 billion
possible IP addresses in the world.
>> And funny story, we're kind
of running out of them.
And in fact it's a huge problem in that
the world also saw this problem coming,
but hasn't necessarily responded to
it in the most rapid way possible.
And indeed, once you've
finished CS50 and started
paying attention in
the tech world, you'll
see this is very commonly thematic.
>> For instance, if we go really
old school nowadays, Y2K.
That wasn't really a surprise.
Like everyone knew for
1,000 years that that
was-- more than a thousand years-- that
that was eventually going to happen.
And yet, we responded to it
very much at the last minute.
And that's happening again.
So today we'll talk about IP version 4.
But know that the world
is finally getting
around to upgrading to
something called IPv6,
which instead of 32-bit
addresses, uses-- anyone
want to take a guess, how many bits?
>> AUDIENCE: 64?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Good guess, but no.
We're finally trying to
get ahead of the curve.
>> AUDIENCE: 128.
DAVID J. MALAN: 128, which
is a freaking huge number
of IP addresses, because
that's like times 2, times 2,
times 2, a lot of times
twos up from 4 billion.
>> So if curious.
It turns out-- and I just googled this
to find this out-- Yale computers,
here at Yale, tend to start with
these numbers-- 130.132 dot something,
and 128.36 dot something.
But there's certainly
exceptions across the board
depending on what department and
building and campus you're on.
Harvard tends to have
140.247, or 128.103.
And generally this is
useless information,
but it's something you might notice now.
When you start poking around
settings on your computers,
you might start to notice these
kinds of patterns before long.
>> But when you're at home and have an
Apple AirPort, or a Linksys device,
or a D-Link, or whatever it is
your parents or siblings installed
in your house, well
what you probably have
is what's called a private IP address.
And these were actually a
nice, temporary solution
to the problem of running
short on IP addresses.
>> And what you can do with
home networks, typically--
and frankly, even Yale
and Harvard are starting
to do this in different areas-- is you
can give a whole bunch of computers
one IP address so long as you put
a special device in front of them,
something called a router,
or it can be called
a proxy or any number of other things.
But a certain device that
has that one IP address.
And then behind that
device, within a building,
within a house or an apartment, can be
any number of computers, all of which
have an IP address that start
with one of these digits here.
And so long as that computer
knows how to convert
the public address to
the private address,
everything can sort of work as expected.
>> But the converse of this is that if
you're at home and you have a sibling,
and both of you are
visiting some website,
that website does not know if it's you
or your sibling visiting the website,
because you appear to be the same
person because all of your data
is going through that router
or that central point.
>> But enough on these lower level details.
Let's take a look at how IP addresses
sometimes come up perhaps in the media
and how we can now start to ruin,
frankly, even more shows for you.
If we could dim the
lights for a few seconds.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -It's a 32-bit on IPP 4 address.
>> -IP ES internet--
>> -Private network,
Tamia's private network.
She's so amazing.
-Come on Charlie.
DAVID J. MALAN: It's
a mirror IP address.
She's letting us watch which
she's doing in real time.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
So a few problems with this.
So one, what we're looking
at here on the screen
is a code written in a
language called Objective-C,
which is kind of a successor to
the C language that we're doing.
This has absolutely nothing
to do with programming.
In fact, as best I can tell,
this is a drawing program
that someone downloaded from the
internet somehow involving crayons.
>> Perhaps less egregious is that
this IP address, valid or invalid?
>> AUDIENCE: Invalid.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Invalid, because 275
is, of course, not between 0 and 255.
That too is probably OK though, because
you don't want to bunch of crazy people
who are like pausing TV on their
TiVos and then visiting the IP to see
if there's actually something there.
So that one's a little less egregious.
But realize that too is
sort of all around us.
>> So of course, none of us ever
really type numeric addresses
into our browsers.
It would be kind of a bad thing
if Google, to visit Google,
you had to go to 123.46.57.89.
And the whole world had
to just remember that.
And frankly, we've kind
of seen this issue before.
Back in the day when people don't
have cell phones and contact lists,
and companies actually still-- actually,
I guess companies still have 800
numbers and the like-- but you
generally see numbers advertised
as 1-800-COLLECT, C-O-L-L-E-C-T.
Because no one can really remember,
when seeing an advertisement on a bus
or billboard, what someone's number is,
but they can probably, with higher
probability, remember a word.
>> So we adopted the same
kind of system in the world
of the internet whereby there's a
domain name system so that we humans can
type google.com, facebook.com,
yale.edu, harvard.edu,
and let the computers figure
out what the corresponding IP
address is for a given name.
>> And the way you do this in the
real world is that for $10 a year,
maybe $50 a year, you can buy a domain
name, or really rent a domain name.
And then whoever you're paying
to rent that domain name,
you tell them who in the world
knows what your IP address is.
And we won't go into these
particulars, but many of you
might want, for final
projects, to actually sign up
for your own web hosting
company, either for free
or for a few dollars per month.
Some of you might want to buy, for
a few dollars, your own domain name,
just for fun or to start a business
or a personal site or the like.
>> And realize that all
of that will ultimately
boil down to you telling the world
what your server's IP address is.
And then these DNS
servers actually take care
of informing the rest of the world.
So all a DNS server
has, in short, inside
of its memory is like the
equivalent of a Google spreadsheet
or an Excel spreadsheet with at least
two columns, one of which has names,
like harvard.edu, and
yale.edu, and google.com.
And the other column has the
corresponding IP address or IP
addresses.
And we can actually see this.
So on my Mac-- and you can
do this on Windows computers
as well-- if I open up a terminal window
here, quite like the one in CD50 IDE,
most computers have a command called
nslookup, name server look up.
And if I type something in like
yale.edu and hit Enter, what
I should see if my network cooperates as
it did for multiple tests before class
began-- let's try google.com.
Of course now nothing's working.
That's great.
All right, stand by for one moment.
nslookup google.com.
>> Well, let's see if the
actual internet-- no.
That's what happened.
Oh my god, all right.
The Wi-Fi broke.
>> Hey, want to know what my IP address is?
All right.
YaleSecure.
This is how you troubleshoot
things as a computer scientist.
We turn the Wi-Fi off.
OK.
>> And actually, Scaz, do you mind
logging us into the secure one?
Otherwise more tests are-- OK, thank
you Yale-- or is about to break.
I want to go on YaleSecure.
Oh, and maybe we'll be OK.
Maybe we're back.
And that's how, as a computer
scientist fix a computer.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
So where I was within this
so-called terminal window,
and if I do nslookup
yale.edu, there we go.
So I get back first the IP address of
the DNS server that my laptop is using.
So in addition to a DHCP server that
we talked about a moment ago telling
my laptop what my IP
address is, that DHCP server
also tells me what DNS server to use.
Otherwise I would have
to manually type this in.
>> But that's not all that interesting.
What I care about is that this is the
IP address of Yale's website apparently.
So in fact, let's try this.
Let me go up into a browser and go
to http://, and then that IP address,
and hit Enter.
And let us see.
That is how else you can
visit Yale's websites.
Now it's not all that memorable.
Like, the pre-frosh
probably aren't going
to remember this particular address
if told to visit there after visiting.
But it does seem to work.
And so DNS really just allows us to
have much more human friendly addresses.
But they don't necessarily
just yield one answer.
>> In fact, when you're a
really big tech company,
you probably want to
have lots of servers.
And even this is misleading.
So Yale probably doesn't
have just one web server.
Google probably doesn't have
just 10 or so web servers.
Google especially probably
has thousands of web servers
around the world that can respond
to requests from people like us.
>> But they also use a technology called
load balancing, which long story short,
has just a few devices in the world
spreading the load across more servers.
So it's kind of like a spider web if
you will dispatching the requests.
But for now, all that's
interesting for today
is that a domain name
like google.com even can
have multiple IP addresses like that.
>> But how does all of our data actually
get back and forth then in the end?
Well, it turns out that there's these
things called routers on the internet.
And what is a router to the
extent that you know already?
And I've used the word a couple
times in the context of a home,
but in simple terms,
what does a router do?
Give me just a guess based on its name?
>> AUDIENCE: So a road or a path?
DAVID J. MALAN: So
it's a road or a path.
So a route is a road
or path, absolutely.
And a router, so a device that
actually routes information,
would move data between points A and B.
>> And so in fact-- and
this is perhaps when
you Google depictions of routers
on the world, all you get
are cheesy marketing diagrams.
And so this is sort of the most
representative one I could find
that looked mildly interesting.
Each of these dots or glimmers of hope
around the world represents a router.
And each of them has a line
between some other router.
>> Because indeed, there
are thousands, probably
millions of routers around the
world, some of which are in our homes
and on our campuses, but a lot of
which are owned by big companies
and are interconnected so that if I
want to send some data from here at Yale
back home to Cambridge, Yale probably
doesn't have a single cable, certainly,
going directly to Harvard.
And Yale doesn't have
a single cable going
to MIT, or to Stanford, or
to Berkeley, or to Google,
or any number of destinations.
>> Rather, Yale, and Harvard, and
everyone else on the internet
does have one or more routers
connected to it, maybe
on the periphery of campus.
So that when my data wants
to leave Yale's campus,
it goes to that nearest router,
as depicted by one of these dots.
And then that router figures out whether
to send it this way, or this way,
or this way, or this way based
on another table in its memory,
another Excel file or Google
spreadsheet that in one column
says, if your IP address starts
with the number one, go this way.
If your IP address starts with
a number two, go that way.
And so you can break it down
numerically to have the router sending
data every which way.
>> And we can kind of see this as well.
Let's go ahead into this terminal
window again, and let me go ahead
and trace the route to,
let's say, www.mit.edu,
which is a couple hundred miles away.
That was really damn fast.
>> So what just happened?
So in just seven steps, and
in just four milliseconds,
I sent data over the internet
from here at Yale to MIT.
Each of these rows, you can
perhaps guess now represents what?
>> AUDIENCE: A router.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: A router.
So indeed, it looks like there's
about seven or so routers,
or six routers in between me
physically in Yale's law school here
and MIT's website over there.
And what we can glean from this is
as follows-- and let me clean it up.
I'm going to rerun it with a command
line argument of -q 1 to just say,
just give me one query.
By default, trace route does three.
And that's why we saw
bunches of numbers.
I want to see fewer numbers
just to keep the output cleaner.
And let's see what happens.
>> So for whatever reason,
someone at Yale thought
it would be funny to call it your
default router arubacentral, which
is on vlan or virtual
LAN, virtual local area
network 30-- so you
probably have at least
29 others-- router.net.yale.internal.
And .internal here is kind of a fake
top level domain meant to be used just
on campus.
And notice the corresponding IP address
of that router, wherever it is here
on campus, is 172.28.204.129.
And it took 36 milliseconds
to go from here to there.
>> Funny story.
We'll get back to that in just a moment.
But now the second router-- to
which arubacentral apparently
has some kind of physical
connection most likely--
the humans didn't bother naming it.
The Yale humans didn't bother naming
it because it's inside of your network
it seems.
And so it just has an IP address.
>> But then a third router
here on Yale's network
that's probably a little
farther away still
is called cen10g whatever
that is asr.net.yale.internal.
And it too has an IP address.
>> Now why are these numbers
kind of fluctuating?
2.9, 1.4, 36?
Routers get busy.
And they get congested and backed up.
There's thousands of people on this
campus using the internet right now.
There's a hundred people in this
room using the internet right now.
>> And so what's happening is that
the routers might get congested.
And so those times might
fluctuate a little bit.
So that's why they don't necessarily
increase straightforwardly.
>> But things get kind of
interesting in step four.
Apparently between Yale and
step four is another hop.
And where is the router
in step four probably?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: JFK maybe,
maybe at the airport.
But for whatever reason,
system administrators, so
geeks that run servers for
years have named routers
after the nearest airport code.
So JFK probably means
it's just somewhere
in New York, maybe in Manhattan
or one of the boroughs.
nyc2 denotes, presumably, another
router that's somewhere in New York.
>> I don't quite know where row
six is here, router number six.
quest.net a big ISP,
internet service provider,
that provides internet connectivity
to big places like Yale and others.
And then this last one, it
looks like that MIT doesn't even
have their own website
in Cambridge necessarily,
but rather they've
outsourced their website,
or at least the physical servers,
to a company called Akamai.
And Akamai actually is right down
the road from MIT in Cambridge
it turns out.
>> But realize too that even thought
you're going to www.mit.edu,
we could really be sent
anywhere in the world.
>> And let's see somewhere
else in the world.
Let me go ahead and clear
this screen and instead
trace the route, just once, so
query one, to www.cnn.co.jp,
the Japanese home page
for CNN, the news site.
And if I hit Enter now,
let's see what happens.
We're again starting at arubacentral.
We're then going to the
nameless router, a few more.
So it took 12 hops to
get to Japan this time.
And let's see what we can glean.
>> So same hop, same hop.
Slightly different now.
This one's interesting.
So I'm guessing here, stamford1 is a
few towns away in Connecticut also.
These routers in row six
and seven don't have names.
But this is kind of amazing.
>> So what seems to be between the
routers in step seven and eight?
And why do you say as much?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Ocean.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Probably an ocean.
We know that's true
like, intuitively, right?
But we can confirm as much kind
of sort of empirically why?
What has changed between
rows seven and eight?
>> It took a lot more time to go to
whatever this nameless router seven is,
probably somewhere in the
continental US, to step eight,
which is probably somewhere in Japan
based on the domain name of .jp there.
And so those additional
hundred something milliseconds
or 90 or so milliseconds is
the result of our data going
over a pretty large body of water.
>> Now curiously, it seems that maybe
that cable goes across the whole US.
If we're actually going over
the West Coast to get to Japan,
it's kind of the long way
if we go the other way.
So it's not entirely clear
what's going on physically.
But the fact that every
additional hop indeed
took markedly longer
than every other, it's
pretty good confirmation that CNN's
Japanese web server is probably indeed
in Japan.
And it's certainly farther
away than MIT has been.
And it's worth noting too,
your data is not necessarily
going to travel the
shortest possible distance.
In fact, if you play around
with trace route at home
just picking random websites, you
might find that just to send an email
or to visit a website
that's here in New Haven,
sometimes your data might first
take a detour, go down to DC,
and then come back up.
And that's just because of
the dynamic routing decisions
that these computers are making.
>> Now just for fun, the production team
trimmed one of these videos for us
to just be a little more succinct.
But to give us a quick sense here--
and we can leave the lights on--
as to just how much cabling is
actually carrying all of our data.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: All networking videos
have cool sounding music apparently.
So that's to get just a
sense of just how much have
been going on underneath the hood.
>> But let's look at a
slightly lower level now
at what data is actually
traversing those lines,
and even going wirelessly
in a room like this.
>> So it turns out when you request
a web page, or send an e-mail,
or receive a web page, or an e-mail, or
a Gchat message, or a Facebook message,
or the like, that is not just one
big chunk of bits flowing wirelessly
through the air or
electronically on a wire.
Rather, that request or
response is generally
chunked up into separate pieces.
>> So in other words, when you have a
request to make of another computer,
or you get back a response
from another computer--
like suppose, for instance, if
unfamiliar-- as too many people
seem to be these days--
if unfamiliar with this--
not this fellow-- this fellow.
So suppose this is a message that
I want to send to someone in back.
Who in the very back would like to
receive a picture of Rick Astley today?
OK, what's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Cole.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: What is it?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Holt?
H-O?
AUDIENCE: C-O-L-E.
DAVID J. MALAN: C-O-L-E, Cole.
Sorry.
C-O-L-E.
All right.
So if I want to send Cole this
picture here, you know this
is kind of a big picture, right?
This could be a few
kilobytes, a few megabytes,
especially if it's high resolution.
And I don't really want to stop
everyone else from using the internet
just while I send this really
big, high quality picture
of Rick Astley throughout the room.
I'd like your data to continue to
traverse the network and the Wi-Fi
as well.
>> And so it makes sense-- and this
is recoverable electronically,
not so much in the real world.
Actually, this is going to have multiple
meanings if you take my audio out.
So if I tear this in
the half like this here,
this now can travel the
internet more efficiently,
because it's a smaller piece.
So with lower probability is it going
to collide with someone else's traffic
on the internet.
>> And so what your computer indeed does
when you want to send a message to Cole
is it chunks up a message like this into
smaller pieces, fragments so to speak.
And then it puts them inside of what
we'll call sort of virtual envelopes.
>> So I have four paper envelopes here.
And I've pre-numbered them,
one, two, three, and four.
And what I'm going to do on the front
of this, just like a normal mailing,
is I'm going to put Cole's name there.
And then at the top, I'm
going to put my name there,
David, so that the first such packet
I'm sending out there on the internet
looks a little something like
this, the salient characteristics
of which are that it has a
to address, a from address,
and also a number, so
that that hopefully
is sufficient information for
Cole to reconstruct this message.
>> So let me do the same here, the
same here, and the same here,
writing his name in the
To field on all of them.
And then let's go ahead and
put these pictures inside.
>> So here is one packet
that's ready to go.
Here is another packet
Here is a third packet
that's ready to go.
And here is a fourth
packet that's ready to go.
>> And now what's interesting about
how the internet in reality works
is that even though I've got
four packets, all of which
are destined for the same
location, they're not necessarily
going to traverse the same route.
And so even though I might hand these
packets off to the nearest router
let's say, if you would like to
send them every which way, let's see
what actually happens, the goal of
which is to get them ultimately to Cole.
And indeed, they're already not
necessarily taking the same direction.
And that's fine.
This is a little awkward
and Oprah style today.
>> And now let me deliberately
take that one back.
And now Cole, if you'd like to
reassemble it as best you can.
Of course, we can all guess what
the conclusion here is going to be.
You're going to have 3/4 of
Rick Astley in just a moment.
And what though is the
implication of that?
You want to try to hold it up?
We do have one camera
pointed at you if you'd like
to pose with Rick Astley over here.
There we go.
Lovely.
>> But you seem to be missing
a fragment of Rick Astley.
So it turns out that the internet
is generally driven by not just IP,
but in fact we heard at the very
beginning of lecture in that video--
and you've probably seen this
acronym more often-- what really
is the protocol you tend to hear about?
>> AUDIENCE: TCP/IP.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: TCP/IP,
which is just a combination
of two protocols, one called IP.
Which again, is just the set
of conventions via which we
address every computer in the internet.
And then TCP, which
serves another purpose.
>> TCP is a protocol that you
typically use in conjunction
with IP, that among other
things, guarantees delivery.
In fact, TCP is the protocol that
would notice that one of the packets
apparently didn't get to
Cole, because he seems
to be missing number four out of four.
And so what TCP, a protocol
does, is it tells Cole,
hey Cole, if you receive only
three out of four packets,
tell me which one you
are missing, essentially,
and then my purpose in life
should be to retransmit that.
>> And so if I too, the
sender, are using TCP,
I should then create a new packet--
not this wrinkled one here--
retransmit just this piece of
it, so that ultimately Cole has
a complete souvenir, if nothing else.
But so that ultimately the data actually
gets to its correct destination.
>> But unfortunately, writing Cole's name
on the front isn't sufficient, per se.
And really, I wouldn't write
Cole's name, but probably
his IP address on the envelope.
And I wouldn't write David.
I'd write my IP address on the envelope
so that the computers can actually
communicate back and forth.
But it turns out that computers
can do way more than serve up
pictures of Rick Astley.
They can also resend and
receive emails, chat messages.
They can do things like file transfers,
and any number of other tools
you use on the internet,
servers can do these days.
>> And just because a company,
or a school, or a person
wants to have a web server, and an
email server, and a chat server,
does not mean you need three computers.
You can have just one computer running
multiple services, so to speak.
>> And so when Cole receives
a message like that, how
does his computer know whether to
show that picture in his browser,
or in Gchat, or in Facebook Messenger,
or in any number of other tools?
>> So it turns out also on that
as envelope is additional piece
of information known as a port number.
And a port number is
just a number indeed,
but it uniquely identifies not
the computer, but the service.
And there's bunches of these.
So it turns out that
in the world, humans
have decided on a few such
conventions, some of which are these.
So there's something called
File Transfer Protocol.
It's pretty dated.
It's completely insecure.
A lot of people still use it.
And it uses port number 21.
In other words, if
sending a file via FTP,
the envelope would have not only the
sender and the receiver's IP address,
it would also have the number 21 so that
the receiving computer knows oh, this
is a file, not an email
or a chat message.
>> 25 is SMTP.
How many of you have ever used SMTP?
Wrong.
Almost all of you have.
If you've ever used email, you've used
SMTP, simple mail transfer protocol,
which is just a fancy way of saying,
this is the type of computer or service
that sends your email outbound.
>> And if you've ever seen acronyms like
POP, or IMAP, and there's a few others,
those are for receiving
email, typically.
That just means it's
a different service.
It's software that someone
wrote that sends to or listens
on a specific port number so
that it doesn't confuse emails
with some other type of data.
>> Now the web is HTTP, which is
number 80, and also port 443.
And in fact, even though
we humans fortunately
don't have to do this,
any time you visit
a website like
http://www.yale.edu, the browser
is just being kind of
helpful in that it's
assuming that you want numeric port 80.
We already know that DNS can figure out
what the IP address is of www.yale.edu.
But the computer is just
going to infer that you
want port 80 because you're using
Chrome, or IE, or some other browser.
But I could technically do colon 80.
And then I can explicitly tell
my browser, send a packet or more
of information to www.yale.edu
requesting today's home page.
But specifically, address
it to Yale's IP at port 80
so that I actually get
back Yale's web server.
>> Now it immediately disappears
because browsers just
decide that we don't
need to confuse humans
by having yet more arcane
information like colon 80.
And frankly, browsers
like Chrome don't even
show you HTTP anymore, or the colon, or
the slash slash, or the trailing slash,
in some sense because they're trying
to make things simpler for users.
In another sense, it's just kind
of a user experience thing--
let's get rid of some of the clutter.
But it's hiding some of
these underlying details.
>> And in fact, none of us
probably ever type http anymore.
You just type in something
like www.harvard.edu.
And again, Chrome infers
that you want HTTP.
But there are other protocols
that we could certainly be using.
>> So given all of this, if you now sort
of put on the so-called engineering hat,
how do things called firewalls work?
So you're probably generally
familiar with the firewall,
not so much in the physical sense.
So back in the day,
and still to this day,
if you've got like strip malls for
instance that have a lot of stores,
generally the walls in between
individual stores or shops
are firewalls in the sense that
they have special insulation
so that if a fire
breaks out in one shop,
it doesn't necessarily
spread to the shop next door.
>> The computer world also has firewalls
that do something different.
What does a fireball do?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Basically
they cut off connection
if they encounter something
like, for example,
they have number of id statements.
And if something happens,
they cut the connection.
Like if this malicious attack
[INAUDIBLE] your computer, or--
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK good.
Yeah, and in fact you're
even going a little farther
in describing something that might be
called an intrusion detection system,
or IDS for short, whereby you
actually have rules defined.
And if you do start to see suspicious
behavior, you try to put an end to it.
>> And a firewall, frankly,
at a networking level,
is even dumber and simpler
than that, generally.
And there's different types
of firewalls in the world.
But the ones that operate at
the level we're talking today--
IP and TCP-- work even
more straightforwardly.
>> For instance, if you were Yale system
administrators, or Harvard system
administrators, or some Big
Brother at some company,
and you wanted to prevent all of your
students or all of your employees
from going to facebook.com,
all you have to do
is make sure that all of their
network traffic, first of all,
goes through a special device.
Let's call it a firewall.
>> And that's fine, because
you can make your router
the same thing as a firewall if
you put the same kind of software
on the same machine.
So if all of your students
or employees traffic
is going through this
central firewall, how
would we block people from going
to facebook.com, for instance?
What would the system
administrator have to do?
Anyone else?
Let's try to go around.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Say that again?
AUDIENCE: It should just get
caught up inside the system.
So just put Facebook into 127.0.0--
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, interesting.
So you can actually then
hack your DNS system.
This is indeed a way you could do this
whereby any time a Yale student pulls
up www.facebook.com, all
of us here today on campus
are using Yale's DNS server,
because Yale's DHCP server gave us
that address.
So yeah, you could kind of
break things or break convention
by just saying, yeah,
facebook.com's address is fake,
is 1.2.3.4, which is
not actually legitimate.
Or maybe it's 278.
whatever was in the TV show a
moment ago so that none of us
can actually visit facebook.com.
>> So suppose Yale did that.
Suppose Yale wanted to keep
you out of facebook.com.
And therefore, they
changed the DNS settings
to give you a bogus IP
address for facebook.com.
How do you respond?
Technically, not-- oh, now
everyone wants to participate.
OK, yeah.
AUDIENCE: You just type in the
actual IP address of Facebook.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK, good.
So we could just type in the
actual IP address of Facebook,
much like I did with Yale's website.
And if the Facebook server is configured
to support that, it should indeed work.
It's a minor pain in
the neck, because now we
have to remember some random
32-bit value, but that could work.
What else could you do?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: You could change
those settings [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, you could
even change your DNS settings.
So in fact this is actually
pretty useful, frankly,
if you're in an airport, or if
you're in a cafe, or something that
has flaky internet whereby sometimes
the DNS server just stops working.
So even I occasionally do
this, not for malicious, I
want to use Facebook
purposes, but really
because I seem to have a network
connection, but nothing is working.
And so one of the first
things I try-- and you
can do this on Windows too-- but
on my Mac, if I go to Network.
And I choose my Wi-Fi connection.
And I go to Advanced.
And I go to DNS.
These are the three
IP addresses that Yale
is giving me for three DNS servers.
The purpose then is for me to try any
one of these to resolve addresses.
>> But I can override
these by doing a plus.
And anyone want to propose a DNS server?
>> AUDIENCE: 8.8.8.8?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, you're amazing.
Yes, 8.8.8.8.
So Google, bless their hearts,
bought the IP address 8.8.8.8,
because it kind of looks like Gs
probably, and it's easy to remember.
But indeed, now I have configured my
computer to use Google's DNS server.
>> So now if I go to yale.edu,
it's still going to work.
But I'm not using Yale's
DNS servers anymore.
And if I go to facebook.com,
all of those look ups
are going to go through Google.
>> So on the one hand, I've cleverly
circumvented the local system
administrators just by
understanding how networking works.
But I'm paying a price.
Nothing is free.
What have I just given up?
All of you clever people who have
been using 8.8.8.8, because it's cool
or solves problems, what have
you been doing all this time?
>> AUDIENCE: Traveling farther?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Maybe traveling farther,
because Google's probably not quite as
close as the server down the street.
But more worrisomely.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: So now Google
knows where you're going.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Google knows literally
every website you are visiting,
because you are literally
asking them, hey Google,
can you translate yale.edu for me?
Or hey Google, can you translate
this other website address for me
into an IP address.
And so they're-- I have no
idea what you're talking about.
And so they know everything about you.
So realize that this is a free service
with a purpose from their perspective
as well.
But it can certainly
get you out of a bind.
>> Now just to address one other
issue that often comes up
among students, especially
when traveling internationally
in certain countries like
China, where there indeed
is a Great Firewall of China whereby
the government there blocks quite
a bit of traffic at different levels.
You don't have to just
block traffic at the level
we're talking here, DNS or otherwise,
you can block it at other levels.
>> And in fact, just to
be clear, a firewall
can operate even more simply than just
having the system administrators change
DNS settings.
A firewall, a device in between
us and the rest of the world,
could just block any outgoing
requests to the IP address
for Facebook on port 80, or
the IP address for harvard.edu,
or the IP address of anything.
So a firewall can look at your
envelopes' IP addresses and even port
numbers, and if Yale wanted to,
it could just stop all of us
from even using FTP anymore, which would
probably be a good thing because it
is indeed an insecure protocol.
Yale could even stop us from
visiting the entirety of the web
just by blocking all port
traffic on number 80 as well.
So that might be another way.
And there's even fancier ways as well.
>> But when you're traveling
abroad for instance,
or if you're in an internet cafe,
or if you're anywhere where there's
blockages or threats, what can you do?
Well, if you go down the street to
Starbucks or you travel in an airport,
generally you can just hop
on the Wi-Fi by choosing
like, JFK Wi-Fi of LaGuardia Wi-Fi,
or Logan Airport Wi-Fi, or what not.
And it's not encrypted, right?
There's no padlock icon.
And you're probably not prompted
for a username and password.
You're just prompted
with some stupid form
to say like, I agree to use this only
for 30 minutes, or something like that.
>> But there's no encryption between
you and Starbucks Wi-Fi access
point, the things with
the antennas on the wall.
There's no encryption between you
and the airport's Wi-Fi signals.
>> And so technically, that creepy person
sitting a few seats down from you
in Starbucks or at the airport
could be, with the right software,
watching all of your wireless
traffic on his or her laptop.
It's not that hard to
put a laptop into what's
called promiscuous mode,
which as the name suggests,
means you're kind of
loose with the rules.
And it just listens not only
for traffic meant for it,
but also to everyone else's
traffic within range.
>> And by that logic, it can see
all of the packets of information
you're receiving.
And if those packets
aren't encrypted, you
are putting yourself at risk of
your emails, or your messages,
or anything else getting exposed.
>> So even if you're not abroad
but you're just in Starbucks,
or you're on some random person's
Wi-Fi that's not encrypted,
a VPN is a good thing.
A VPN is a virtual private network.
And it's a technology
that allows you to have
an encrypted, a scrambled connection--
fancier than Caesar or Vigenere--
between your laptop, or
your phone, or your desktop,
and a server elsewhere, like
a server on Yale's campus.
>> And if you're traveling abroad--
and in fact, you find this in hotels
all the time.
And especially as aspiring
computer scientists
where you guys might, as geeks,
want to use ports other than 80,
and ports other than 443-- and
in fact for problem set six,
we are going to play with multiple
TCP ports just by choice-- a lot
of hotels, and shops, and networks
just block that kind of stuff
because they somewhat naively,
or ignorantly, just think
that no one needs those other ports.
>> And so by using a VPN can you
circumvent those kinds of restrictions,
because what a VPN does is
it allows you at Starbucks,
or the airport, or anywhere in the world
to connect encryptedly to yale.edu,
to some server here on campus,
and then tunnel, so to speak,
all of your traffic from wherever
you are through Yale, at which point
it then goes to its final destination.
>> But by encrypting it, you
avoid any of these kinds
of filters or the imposition that
some local network has imposed.
And plus, you have a
much more robust defense
against creepy people
around you who might
be trying to listen in on your traffic.
There could still be creepy people here
back home at Yale watching your traffic
as it comes out of the VPN, but at least
you've pushed the threat farther away.
And it's here too, a trade off.
>> Now of course, if you are in
China or even in the cafe,
and you're tunneling all
your traffic through Yale,
what price are we paying perhaps?
>> AUDIENCE: Speed.
DAVID J. MALAN: Speed, right?
There's got to be some math
or some fanciness involved
in the actual encryption.
There could be thousands of
miles of distance or thousands
of miles of cables between you and Yale.
And it's really bad if you're
in China, for instance,
and you want to visit
a website in China.
And so your data is going to
the US, and then back to China
just because you're encrypting
it through this tunnel.
>> But it solves technical
and work problems alike.
But it all boils down to
these very simple ideas.
And Harvard, for those curious, has
one here as well, at vpn.harvard.edu,
which operates just like Yale's.
>> So with all that said, why
is this whole network useful?
And what can we start doing with it?
Well, let's make this now more real.
This is the acronym
with which most of us
are probably super familiar-- HTTP--
which stands for hyper text transfer
protocol.
And this just means this is
the language, the protocol
that web browsers and web server speak.
>> The P in HTTP is indeed a protocol.
And a protocol is just
a set of conventions.
We've seen IP-- internet protocol--
TCP-- transmission control
protocol-- and HTTP.
But what is this stupid
thing of a protocol?
It's just a set of conventions.
>> So if I sort of come down
here, and I want to greet you.
I would say hi, my name is David.
>> AUDIENCE: Luis.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Luis.
We have this stupid human
convention of shaking hands here.
But that's a protocol, right?
I extended my hand.
Luis extended his hand.
We did this.
And then complete, done.
>> And that's exactly the same
spirit of a computer protocol
where as in HTTP, what happens is this.
If you are the computer on the
left here, and there is some web
server there on the right.
And the computer on the left wants to
request information from that server.
It's kind of a bi-directional operation.
The browser on the left
asks for some web page.
The server on the right
responds with some web page.
And we'll see what form
those take in just a moment.
>> And it turns out that those computers--
that browser and server, or client
and server, so to speak.
Much like a restaurant where the
client is asking for something,
and the server is bringing
him or her something-- get
is kind of the operative word.
Literally inside of the envelope that
my browser sends from here to a web
server is the word get.
Like I want to get today's news.
I want to get my
Facebook news feed, or I
want to get some page from the server.
>> Specifically, this is what's
going on inside of that envelope.
So I, with Cole, essentially
sent Cole a response.
If you imagine that Cole actually
wanted a picture of Rick Astley,
he might have sent me a request
similar in spirit to this.
Inside of his envelope to me, where
I'm now playing the role of Google,
would be a request that literally
says, get, and then a forward slash--
and you've probably seen
forward slashes in URLs before.
It just means give me the default
page, the default Rick Astley
picture in this case.
>> And by the way, Cole speaks the language
HTTP version 1.1, or the protocol 1.1.
And it turns out there's
an older version 1.0.
But computers tend to use 1.1.
>> The second line is a useful thing that
will come back to perhaps before long.
But it's just a specification to me,
the recipient, that the thing I want
is www.google.com.
Because it's very possible
these days for dozens,
hundreds of websites with
different domain names to all
live on the same server.
It's not going to be true
so much in Google's case.
But in a smaller company's
case, could absolutely be.
So Cole is just kind of
putting in the envelope,
by the way, when this reaches
your IP address on port 80,
just be sure that you know
I want www.google.com, not
some other random website
on the same server.
>> What I then respond to Cole with,
at the end of the day, is a picture.
But atop that picture
inside of the envelope
is actually some text, where I say, OK.
I speak HTTP version 1.1 also.
200.
Which is a status code that
most of us have probably
never seen, because it means OK.
And this is good, because it
means I am responding successfully
to Cole's request.
>> What numbers have you probably
seen on the web that are not OK?
>> AUDIENCE: 404.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: 404-- file not found.
So indeed, any time you've seen
one of those annoying file not
found errors, because
the web page is dead,
or because you mistyped
a URL, that just means
that the little envelope that your
computer received from the server
contained a message HTTP
1.1, 404-- not found.
That file or that request
you made is not found.
>> Moreover, inside of the envelope
typically is this line, content type.
Sometimes it's HTML,
something we'll soon see.
Sometimes it's a JPEG.
Sometimes it's a GIF.
Sometimes it's a movie file, an
audio file, any number of things.
So inside of the envelope is just a
little hint as to what I am receiving.
There's other status codes too, some
of which we'll explore in P set six,
and you'll stumble across
in P set seven and/or eight.
But some here, like 404 we've seen.
Forbidden, 403, means like
the permissions are wrong,
like you haven't kind of
configured it correctly.
301 and 302, we rarely see visually.
But they mean redirect.
Any time you've gone to one
URL and you've been magically
sent somewhere else, that's
because the browser has sent back
an envelope containing
the number 301 or 302,
and the URL that it wants
your browser to go to instead.
>> 500 is horrible.
You'll see it before long, probably
in P set six or P set seven.
And it generally means
there's some bug in your code,
because indeed we'll be writing
code that responds to web requests.
And you've just got some
error in logic or syntax,
and the server can't handle it.
>> So let's see how we can now leverage and
understand these requests as follows.
If I go to, let's say, google.com.
Let me go to www.google.com.
And for demonstration's sake, let's
see, I need to go to Settings here.
I'm going to go to Search Settings.
And Google has increasingly annoying
features, but useful features.
So Google has this thing like instant
results where you start typing,
and automatically
things start appearing.
And that's all fine
and technically useful,
and we'll understand
before long how this works.
But for now, I'm turning
off instant results,
because I want my browser to
sort of work old school so
that I can see what's going on.
>> So now I'm back here.
And I want to search for cats.
And notice I'm seeing some suggestions,
some very benign suggestions
thankfully.
And now if I hit Enter,
let's see what happens.
>> So there are some cats.
And the top hit is on Wikipedia.
But today we care about
the technology up here.
So the URL to which I've
been sent is this here.
And there's some stuff I
don't really understand.
>> So I'm going to go ahead, because
I kind of know how Google works,
and I'm going to distill this
URL into its simplest form.
And now I'm going to hit Enter again.
And it still works.
I have a page of results all about cats.
>> But notice the simplicity of my URL.
It turns out this is how
much of the web works.
The web is just a whole
bunch of computers
running software that take input.
It's not get string style input.
It's not command line
arguments like we're used to.
They take input, these web servers,
by way of the URLs quite often.
And any time you've
searched for something,
any time you've logged into
Facebook, any time you've
done anything interactive with
a web page, what you're doing
is effectively submitting a form, so
to speak-- text boxes, check boxes,
little circles, and whatnot that send
information from you to the server.
>> And it turns out that the web
server knows to look at that URL
and parse it, like look at it character
by character looking for anything
interesting after a question mark.
Because after a question mark,
it turns out, is going to come
a bunch of key value pairs.
I mean key=value.
And then if there's multiple-- maybe
an ampersand, some other key=value,
ampersand, key=value.
>> So we've kind of seen this idea
before where something has a value.
It's just a new format here.
And I just know, by convention,
Google uses q for query.
And then if I want to search for dogs, I
can manually search for dogs like that.
And then I'm apparently getting
some search results involving dogs.
>> So that seems to be interesting.
And indeed, what's going on
underneath the hood is this.
Let me do this.
This is a-- let's see.
Let me go back over
here for just a moment.
>> We'll see that there's other
ways to submit information.
So if I'm logging into Facebook, or
Gmail, or any other popular website,
it seems kind of bad if whatever I typed
into the search box ends up in my URL,
in my browser's address bar.
Why?
Why is that mildly worrisome?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Type in a password.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So what if what I've
typed in is my password?
I kind of don't want it so obviously
visible in my browser's address bar.
One, because my annoying roommate
tends to watch over my shoulder,
and he or she can now see, even though
it was bullets when I'm typing it in,
little circles.
Now it's in my address bar.
>> Moreover, what's true about stuff
you tend to type in the address bar.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: What's that?
AUDIENCE: It gets sent out.
DAVID J. MALAN: It gets sent out.
And also, it gets remembered.
Because the next time
you type things up there,
often it autocompletes and it
remembers what you've typed before.
And so there's this veritable history
that your sibling, or your roommate,
or whoever can walk through to
pretty much see every website
you visited because it's
logged in that address bar.
>> Moreover, suppose you want to
upload a photo to Facebook.
How in the world are you
going to put a photo in a URL?
>> Well it turns out you can do it in some
way, but it's certainly non-obvious.
And so there's this other way of
sending information in an envelope,
not via a GET, but via
something called POST.
And in theory, it looks
pretty much the same.
Instead of the word GET, we say POST,
and then the same kind of format.
>> For instance, this is
a screenshot of what
it might look like if I try logging
into Facebook, which sends me to a file
called login.php, which is actually
still to this day named as such.
It's the same filename Mark
gave to it many years ago.
It is the program he wrote in PHP via
which users can login to the website.
>> But you need to send
some additional input.
And rather than it going after the
file name as it did before with cats--
q=cats-- it can go lower in the request,
deeper inside of the envelope if you
will where no one can see it,
and where it does not end up
in the user's browser bar, and therefore
not remember for people to snoop
around.
>> And so here my email address and
my fake password actually go.
And if Facebook is using
not HTTP, but HTTPS,
this will all be encrypted,
scrambled, ala Caesar or Vigenere,
but more fancily so that no one
can actually see this request.
>> And so indeed, any time you have
a URL that starts with HTTPS,
it just means it's encrypted.
But at the end of the day, what's
actually inside of these envelopes?
This was super low level.
And fortunately, we're not
going to necessarily have
to go so low level every time to
start writing interesting software.
We can start to take
the ideas of week one
through five, assume that there
is now this infrastructure that
lets us write software
that operates on the web,
and it's going to allow us
this coming week to start
looking at something called HTML.
This is the stuff that is even
deeper inside of the envelope,
but it's the stuff we're
going to start writing.
And it's the stuff more
interestingly, we're
going to write programs that
starts generating automatically
so that our websites are not hard coded,
but take input and produce output.
>> This is perhaps the simplest web
page you can make in the world.
I can indeed open up
something stupid like TextEdit
on my Mac, which just gives me
a simple text window like this.
PC users have Notepad.ext,
which is very similar in spirit.
>> And I can literally type
out this-- DOCTYPE HTML,
which looks a little cryptic.
But we'll come back to that.
HTML, with these weird
angled brackets and slashes,
inside of which now I'm going to say
here comes the head of my web page.
Inside of that, I just
know, and you'll soon know,
that I can put the title of my web page.
And then below the
head of the web page is
going to go to the so-called
body of the web page.
And I'm just indenting just
like in C to kind of keep
things nicely readable stylistically.
And now I'm going to save this as a
file on my desktop, called hello.html.
>> And I'm going to tell it yes, use HTML.
Don't change it to .txt, even
though all this is a text file,
just like a C program
written with a text editor.
Although not in CS50 IDE at the
moment, just here on my Mac.
>> And if I now go to my desktop,
you'll see hello.html.
If I double click this,
it will open Chrome.
And even though this file
happens to live on my desktop,
that is perhaps the simplest
web page I could make.
>> Notice that the title of the
tab way up top is hello world.
The body of the web page
is indeed hello world.
And all I've done to get
to this point is implement,
or is write a new language, called HTML.
It's not a programming
language like C. There's
not going to be conditions,
and loops, and functions.
It's a markup language, in which
case you just tell the receiving
program what you want to do.
This means hey browser,
here comes an HTML page.
Hey browser, here comes
the head of my page.
the body of my page.
Hey browser, that's it for the body.
That's it for the HTML page.
>> And with those simple definitions
alone, we'll soon see that one,
we can represent this as a tree.
But more on that later.
So this will all interconnect to
our most recent data structures.
Two, we'll introduce this stupid joke.
This is an actual tattoo that
this guy had on his neck.
It's probably funny the first week or
two, and thereafter, maybe not so much.
>> But HTML, and even the web
page I just made, super mind
numbingly disappointing--
just saying hello world
in black text on a white background.
Surely we can do much better.
And we'll do so by introducing
another language called CSS.
This too not a programming language--
no loops, and conditions, or for loops,
but really, just syntax by which
we can say, make this text big.
Make this text small.
Right align it.
Left align it.
Make it pink.
Make it purple.
Make it blue.
Or do any number of
other visual effects.
And so we'll see how to start stylizing
web pages so that they look in a manner
closer to what we want.
>> And lastly, we have indeed ruined
perhaps much of TV and film for you.
I thought we'd end here
with our final seconds
on a final clip that shows you
how hacking on the internet works.
If we could dim the
lights one final time.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -No way.
I'm getting hacked.
>> -Okorsky?
>> -No-- no, this is major.
They've already burned through
the NCIS public firewall.
-Well, isolate the node and dump
them on the other side of the router.
-I'm trying.
It's moving too fast.
>> -Oh, this is not good.
They're using our connection
[INAUDIBLE] this database.
Sever it.
-I can't.
It's a point attack.
He or she is only
going after my machine.
>> -It's not possible.
There's DOD level mine encryption.
It would take months to get--
-Hey, what is that?
A video game?
>> -No Tony, we're getting hacked.
>> -If they get in Abby's computer,
the entire NCIS network is next.
>> -I can't stop him.
Do something McGee.
>> -I've never seen code like this.
-Oh.
-Where's it go?
Abby?
-I didn't do anything.
I thought you did.
>> -No.
>> -I did.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: The best
part is two people typing
on the keyboard at the same time.
>> So that's it for CS50.
We'll stick around for office hours.
And we'll see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING - "SEINFELD THEME"]
This is CS50.
I don't want to be a pirate.
SPEAKER 2: Yarr David.
It is a fine doublet you be wearing.
Lot of luff in that puff.