>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -A triumph of mathematical
and mechanical skill
is this great new automatic
calculator at Harvard University.
Intricate problems in mathematics
put through the machine in coded form
on tape are accurately solved in a
minute fraction of the time required
for human calculation.
Designed to expedite all forms of
mathematical and scientific research,
the giant mechanical brain will work for
the United States Navy until war's end.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: This, is CS50.
The past was a magical
place, but if you've ever
wondered what that device is
in Harvard Science Center,
it is indeed part of the
Harvard Mark I, and it's
on display there now
for the past many years.
And what you'll see
embedded in problem set
one is a look behind the scenes
at what that device did, and does,
from Professor Harry Lewis, who is in
the computer science department here.
So more on that in just a bit.
>> But today we begin to transition
from last week to this,
and we'll bring mention
of one photograph here
that's actually quite famous.
Does anyone know what this
here is on the screen?
At least according to myth.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: The first virus.
DAVID J. MALAN: So it was supposedly
the very first actual bug in a computer.
Now in reality the word bug,
for a mistake in a program,
has been with us for some
time in the physical world,
and this was one of the first
documented times where someone actually
plucked a large moth out of the Mark
II computer, put it in the binder,
and then recorded it
as the first known bug
to have actually been found physically.
So thus was entered
that into today's lore.
Everything from last
week is available online.
In particular resources that you might
not necessarily notice, especially
if coming here in person.
So one of the teaching fellows every
year makes a canonical set of notes,
so you needn't keep
your head down, trying
to transcribe most anything
that might happen here in class.
So realize that those
so-called [? Scribd ?] notes
are online, certainly the slides and
source code that we use in class.
We make full text transcripts
available as well.
So if you vaguely remember some
term, and want to look it up a little
more readily, realize that all
of that is searchable online.
As well as walkthroughs as well.
Indeed, today we begin to look at
a lower level programming language,
soon to be known to us
as C, and it's very easy
to sort of get lost after just a few
moments time, and then sort of wonder
how we actually got to some more
complex example from the simplest.
And so realize we'll cherry
pick during class some
of the representative examples, but
realize that so much more is also
available online so you can work
through it at your own pace,
however you're most comfortable.
>> But we left off with
programs that were just this.
So I click the green flag,
and what does this program do?
Says, hello, world.
It makes the cat say
hello in his little world
on the top left hand side
of Scratch's user interface.
But we started to introduce
some terminology last week.
And so, things like this we called what?
What might be the generic term for this?
Yeah.
A method or a statement.
Sure, it's an action.
Do this.
And yet there were
other shapes to scratch,
besides these so-called
statement, they were also
things like this, which we called what?
Yeah.
So a loop.
And in this case, this thing
repeats, obviously, 10 times.
There's a forever block.
There's a couple of others.
And today we're going to see how to
translate this to a more modern world,
if you will, even though it's
going to appear at first glance
to be much more arcane.
But those were indeed loops.
And then we have things like
this, which had this shape,
and essentially asked questions.
And we referred to these as what?
>> AUDIENCE: Boolean expression.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
Boolean expression.
Something that is either true or
false, yes or no, one or zero,
however you want to view the world.
But we called those Boolean
expressions, and we plug them
into conditions, or branches.
And in the world of
Scratch, everything nicely
interlocks in terms of its shape,
if it makes logical sense to do so,
but you don't have to stop at just
doing one thing conditionally,
you can have a proverbial
fork in the road
and do either this or that if
the condition is true or not.
And then, as you'll see,
if you haven't already,
you can even nest these blocks.
So Scratch grows to fill the shapes
that you might want to insert into it,
so you can actually express most
any logic that you might want to do.
>> Now a few words of announcement
for both here and New Haven.
So sectioning begins today.
The URL for this is on the course's
website, for those unfamiliar.
Sections will be an
opportunity to get together
in a much more intimate environment
than [? Sanders ?] allows,
with 10 to 20 classmates with a
teaching fellow at different tracks,
and different paces, if you so choose.
Indeed the course offers
different sections
for those less comfortable, more
comfortable, and somewhere in between,
and the role of thumb here, is
there's no formal definition,
but if you're less comfortable,
you kind of know it.
You're a bit intrepid about the
idea of stepping foot, perhaps, back
in the classroom, or showing
up to an in between section.
If you've been programming since you
were six years old, more comfortable,
perhaps to you.
And if it's kind of a toss-up,
that's exactly what the in between
is meant to be.
>> Now, in the meantime,
for a class this size,
it takes us quite some time to section
everyone, so we have so-called,
super sections, coming up this
weekend and early next week,
so take a look at the course's website
for those that are course wide,
and also filmed for those
who cannot make them.
And sections themselves will start
in week three of CS50 zero index.
Problem set 0 is already
on the course's website.
And realize that you do have
nine late days this semester.
So this is an upgrade from last
year, when we had five late days.
>> So if you're wondering,
we have nine problem sets.
You have nine late days, each of which
you can only spend one per week on.
That effectively makes all of
the problem sets due Friday,
but the goal is to put a little
bit of psychological pressure
on you to try to get
things in on Thursday
because as you will soon discover,
for better or for worse, most
everything in the software world ends up
taking much longer than you anticipate.
So consider it a sort
of opportunity to help
yourself to target Thursday,
but take comfort in that, yes,
everything is due Friday.
And if you submit them on
Thursday, that's wonderful.
There's no bonus points or extra
credit for meeting that deadline.
It's meant to be a crutch only.
>> And office hours, both
here and in New Haven,
in person, if you'd like to
meet with any of our courses
teaching fellows and CAs for assistance.
>> All right.
So now, let's make this more real.
And for a moment it's going to start
to get a little more arcane, but very
quickly on Friday and
next week we will be
able to do so much more than
we could thus far in Scratch.
So we introduced code last
week, albeit pictoral.
It was puzzle pieces.
And we formalized that it is
something called source code,
but would did look like?
Well, it looked a little
something like this.
And, in fact, just to kind of
tease where we can go with this.
I'm going to go ahead and
open up a window here,
and I'm just going to choose New File.
And I'm going to save this file
as something like hello dot c.
More on that choice of
words in just a moment.
And this is how someone might
go about writing a program.
Include standard I/O dot h, int main
void, and then open curly brace, close
curly brace, printf hello comma world,
backslash n, semicolon, Save, done.
OK.
I've written my first
program, but it's going
to be incredibly underwhelmed
because when I actually
run this program, of course,
by first writing make hello,
and then dot slash hello, and we'll
go through this in much more detail
in a moment, that's all it does.
Doesn't pop open any windows.
It doesn't do anything
particularly fancy.
All it does is what I told it to
do, but how do we get to that?
And how do we build upon that?
Well, let's introduce a few
different concepts here.
>> So one, we're about to start
using a program called a compiler.
A compiler exists for Mac OS, Windows,
Linux, any number of operating systems,
and we'll soon introduce you to the
environment that we will be using,
but a compiler is just a general
term for a piece of software
that takes source code and
produces object code from it.
In other words, if you
have as input your source
code, something like what I just typed,
it ultimately produces object code.
And object code is really just
a fancy way of saying it outputs
zero's and one's.
In other words, source
code, even though it's
going to look a little arcane,
and a little less friendly
than Scratch at first glance,
it's at least something
that we humans can understand.
It kind of looks and sounds like
English even though it's very succinct.
Whereas programming in zero's and
one's, as our predecessors had to do,
some years ago, was not a
particularly fun challenge.
And yet, this is what the
computer still understands.
So compiler gets us from
source code to object code.
It's like opening a file with the
compiler, and when you save it,
you get those zeros and ones.
So we'll see how to do
that in just a moment.
>> But let's now try to provide a
bridge between last week and this,
so that even as we get hung up
on things like curly braces,
and semicolons, and parentheses, and
all of these intellectually interesting
aspects of programming, that very
understandably trip people up early on,
realize that all of the ideas
today, are the same as last.
So last, we saw this example
here, Hello World program.
Well, starting today, if we want
to implement that same program,
it's going to look a
little something like this.
And we'll explain before long what int,
and main, and void, and all of that
is, but at least I see here
already the familiar Hello World.
>> Meanwhile, things like
function, say hello,
is very simply going to be a
very simple statement like this.
Printf hello world, with some
quotes, with a backslash,
with a semicolon, but
more on that to come.
Loops, meanwhile, this is a loop that,
of course, says hello world forever,
and this one's going to look a
little weirder than in the last,
but if I say something
like, while true, I
can then print out Hello world
again and again and again and again.
And then as you can kind
of start to infer here,
this convention of using
curly braces is kind
of like embracing the
indented line of code there.
The printf line of code much like
the yellow puzzle piece up above.
So we're not going to say forever,
we're going to say while true,
but we'll see why that is in just a bit.
>> Meanwhile, if we have a loop like this,
where you repeat something a finite
number times, this one too it's
going to take a little getting used
to, but it's going to say for int
i gets zero, i less than 10, i++,
and then printf again.
But there's going to be patterns.
And for those of you familiar
with AP Computer Science, or Java,
or any number of other languages,
almost all of these constructs
thus far should look mostly familiar.
>> So variable.
So here's a simple Scratch excerpt that
sets a variable called counter to zero,
and then forever says the counter, and
then it changes the counter by one.
So it starts with zero,
and then one, two, three.
Well, how might we introduce that in
this new language a little similarly?
Int counter equals
zero, while true, which
is that same idea from before
of doing something forever,
and I'm just going to printf.
And now it's getting a little strange,
percent i, but more on that to come,
but these ideas are exactly the same.
We just now have to adhere to
the syntax that the computer is
going to demand of us.
>> Boolean expression, something like
sx less than y, or x less than y,
and y less than z.
It's going to look a little something
like this, with parentheses just
like in math for good measure to just
ensure that the order of operations
is as we intend.
And now, conditions.
So if x less than y, say x is less
than y, else if x is greater than y,
say x is greater than y, otherwise
logically, x must be equal to y.
So you might implement
something like this in Scratch,
or you might implement
it in this syntax.
And again, the curly braces are kind of
giving us the same shape as the puzzle
pieces, but the syntax, now, is perhaps
starting to follow some patterns.
>> So, what does this give us here?
So we're back then at our main program.
Let's actually, now,
do something with it.
So in this very first
line we see sharp include,
standard I/O, dot h, and
then some weird angle
brackets below that. int main
void, and then printf hello world.
So just take a step.
Someone who's never programmed before,
at least explain one of these lines.
Using perhaps some of
the jargon of last week.
What is printf, for instance?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
It's a function, or a statement,
from last week's terminology.
And it's an action
that's doing something.
Now this function, or
this statement, does
it appear to take some kind of input?
And in what sense does it
seem to take input, if so?
Input, what do I mean by that?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So Scratch out a few puzzle pieces
where you can parametrize it.
You could tell the repeat
block how many times to repeat,
so that was an input of
sorts, and just like Scratch
had a little white placeholder
for the number you would type in,
so do we use in this
text world parentheses
to give us that circular shape
into which we can plug our input.
After all, tens of years ago
when this language, called C,
was invented no one
anticipated it's one of us,
these some years later, we'd
want a function that says hello.
Right?
It'd be nice if there were a
puzzle piece, or a key words,
that's called hello, that
literally just says hello.
But we don't need that.
We can have something much lower
level, like a generic print
command, that takes input,
and prints whatever we want.
So notice now the pattern
that will start to emerge.
Open paren, close paren is
apparently embracing the input,
and then I see double
quotes on both ends.
There is still weird backslash
n, but hopefully now you
can start to visualize at least that
printf is taking in some form of input.
Not as user friendly as
Scratch, but it's just
like having plugged in some value there.
>> All right, now let's actually
do something with this.
So some of you might know from
having shopped the class before,
chatted with friends,
that for many years
we used something called
the CS50 appliance.
This was a term describing a technology
called the virtual machine, which
is a piece of software that your
predecessors would download off
the course's website for free.
They would also download a free piece
of software called a hypervisor,
something called like VMware,
or VirtualBox, or any number
of other tools, and on their Mac or PC
or whatever computer they had last year
and in years past, they
would double click an icon
to run this software
called the hypervisor.
And then inside of that program
they would open the CS50 appliance.
And the effect was that
whether a predecessor of yours
was running Mac OS or
Windows, he or she then
subsequently had a new window on their
screen running CS50's environment.
So a virtual machine lets you run one
operating system inside of another,
and that's exactly what we did.
Throughout most of the course we
use an operating system called
Linux, specifically
Ubuntu Linux, and this
is a very nice way in years past of
making sure that everyone in the course
just had the same environment.
And you can use any kind of
computer that you actually want.
Among the downsides, though,
were it was like two gigabytes
to download this thing.
It didn't necessarily work super well on
people whose computers that maybe only
had a gig or so of RAM, or not
too many gigahertz of CPU speed,
and so this year, for
this and other reasons,
have we been transitioning
to this environment.
The so-called CS50 IDE, which is
based on open source software,
and a supported platform
that a company called Cloud9
supports in Europe, that
allows us to have essentially
that exact same environment as in
years past, but in the so-called cloud.
>> So what is the cloud?
You've probably clicked
its icon on your Mac or PC.
What is the cloud?
Yeah?
A little louder.
Yeah.
It's just a bunch of computers
elsewhere that store data and run
software and the like.
So it's really just to the word de
jure of describing [? rentable ?]
computers that live elsewhere.
That you, yourself,
don't necessarily own.
So when your data, or your
programs, are in the cloud,
it just means it's on someone
else's computers elsewhere,
and not, most likely, on your
physical laptop or desktop.
And so that's what CS50 IDE now is.
>> Henceforth you'll go to a certain
URL that will introduce you
to, in problem set 1, later this
week, that will then, upon logging in,
give you this environment.
And much like Scratch had a
few different panels involved,
so does CS50's IDE have exactly that.
On the top left hand side here, you're
going to see a familiar file browser.
So any of the files that you
put into this environment
are just going to be listed there.
Files and folders.
On the top right here,
you're going to see a place
where you can actually write your code.
Initially in C, later in the
term in PHP and JavaScript,
and, perhaps for final
projects, Ruby or Java or Python
or any number of languages are
supported in this environment.
It's not at all tied
to CS50 specifically.
>> And then in the bottom corner here,
especially for those more comfortable,
you have something
called a terminal window.
And this terminal window allows
you to execute any command that you
want in this cloud environment.
It allows you to install
any additional software
that you want because you have so-called
root, or administrator privileges.
So in other words, even though this
is ultimately hosted in the cloud,
and even though we have
simplified it to some extent
by default, literally introducing,
thanks to Dan Armendariz, and Dino,
and Dan Bradley on CS50's team over the
past many months, a less comfortable
mode that hides a lot of the
initially confusing distractions.
Everything there exists to
represent a typical computer system
that you might use in the real world.
>> So what does this all mean, and
what can we actually do with it?
Let's actually take a peek at a program.
So I'm going to open up the
actual environment here,
which is just our Chrome
browser, which could be Firefox,
could be Internet Explorer,
or some other browser as well.
It's full screened here for the moment.
And I want to actually tease
apart what this program was.
So let's take a look, by zooming in up
top, at what I did, and how I got here.
So here's those exact
same lines of code.
So this is the statement,
as you mentioned earlier.
The function that says hello.
The curly braces, on
line four and line six,
presumably kind of envelop
that line to associate it
with the essence of my program.
So indeed, this keyword main,
that's up there on line three,
you can think of that as the equivalent
of that when green flag clicked,
block in Scratch.
So that's all we have here, is when
green flag clicked, print, or say,
hello world.
>> But let's take a guess, now, at what
this first, more arcane line, is.
Sharp include, open angled
bracket, standard I/O dot h,
close angled bracket.
What is that perhaps doing,
especially if you've programmed
before in some other language.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
Exactly.
So this is giving you access to a
library, so to speak, of functions.
And a library of functions is
functions that someone else
wrote, either recently
or long ago, so that you
don't have to reinvent the wheel.
For instance, we don't
have to know, in 2015,
how to write code that puts
a character on my screen.
Someone else has figured that
out with the printf function
so that I can sort of abstract
away from that, or layer
on top of his or her
code, and now just take
for granted that any program I write
can print something to the screen.
So this first line there in step one
includes the so-called header file
for the standard library.
So see, the language in
which we're now working
had a standard library
with lots of functions.
Printf is one of them, and
that first line of code
means give me access to
those functions, so that I
don't have to reinvent that wheel.
>> Now let's go to the bottom window
and do exactly what I did before.
A moment ago, when I was
whizzing through the code,
typing it out for the first time,
I very quickly typed, make hello.
What was that all about would you guess?
What was I doing?
Yeah?
Never mind.
It's OK.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Compiling it.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
It was just compiling it.
Right?
Even if this is completely unfamiliar
to you, it's pretty English like.
It's certainly not zeros
and ones, so I still
need to run it through that so-called
program, a compiler, that's going
to take it as input and produce output.
And at least, for now, in
this Linux environment,
but this isn't prerequisite,
this is just where we'll begin,
you generally interact with
computer systems like this
by a so-called command line.
So with a blinking
prompt and your keyboard,
and not so much your mouse, and not
so much windows and icons and menus,
rather everything is textual.
And even though this feels, at first
glance, perhaps, like a step backward,
it's actually a much more
powerful and expressive way
of controlling a computer
especially as you,
yourself, become more
comfortable from less.
It's going to allow you to do a lot
more things than just what Microsoft
or Apple allows you to do with
their graphical operating system.
>> So when I hit Enter, now,
nothing happens this time
because apparently the
program hello is up to date.
And what was the command
I ran after that?
Dot slash hello, and hello world.
Now let's take a step
back for just a moment.
It turns out that make hello is just a
simplified way of compiling a program.
Let's just introduce
one piece of jargon,
but then move away
from it, since it's not
all that interesting
for today's purposes.
The compiler we're going to start using
is called Clang, for the C language.
And this is a program that's run just
like we did at the command line there.
And so if I want to
compile a program that I
have written in a file called hello dot
c, I literally just type clang hello c
enter.
>> The funny thing is,
for historical reasons,
if I don't specify the
name of the program
that I want to output, if I don't
specify a file name for those zeros
and ones, a very weird
convention was adopted years ago
where it felt kind of a
good answer at the time,
well let's just arbitrarily call the
first program we compile a dot out.
A comes first in the alphabet.
Out, it's the output.
So we will call the program
by default a dot out.
And that's fine because if I want to
run the program in this text based
environment, I just type
dot slash a dot out enter.
And it would run exactly as before.
So let's see that real fast.
>> So if I go back to my
source code in CS50 IDE,
and I instead do this, clang hello cot
c enter, notice nothing seems to happen,
but almost always in
this Linux environment,
when nothing bad seems to happen, that
means something good actually happened.
If you don't see an error
message, all is probably well.
And indeed, if I now do dot slash a dot
out enter, I've run my same program.
I still have the hello program
from earlier because indeed, it's
going to be so much nicer just
type make instead of remembering
these incantations of
commands, but let's see how we
might improve upon this, nonetheless.
>> So, this is the command
to compile the code.
This is the command to run
the compiled code thereafter.
How can I specify a file name?
Well let's just introduce
one more piece of jargon.
When you're in this
text based environment,
you're going to want to specify
things called command line arguments.
Which is just a fancy way of saying,
other words at the prompt that
tweak the behavior of whatever
program you're running.
So specifically the program I'm
running, by typing the name clang,
is the program called Clang.
So this is or the old school
equivalent of double-clicking
on Microsoft Word or
some program's icon.
I'm instead just typing its name,
but in this version of the command,
I then have dash o space
hello space hello dot c.
So even if you've never
played in this world before,
just take a guess what
does dash o hello do?
Or what does it tell clang to do?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
It just sets the file's output to be
hello instead of the sillier a dot out.
And, indeed, let's try this.
So if I now do, first
let's do this, r m hello.
That's remove.
And it's going to say remove
regular file hello, which
is unnecessarily arcane, but it just
means do you want to delete the file,
and I type y for yes.
And notice, if you were glancing at top
left, it did disappear from up there.
Let me now do clang dash o, and
I'm going to go ahead and do hello,
in all caps, hello dot c.
Now, if I do dot slash
hello, what would you expect?
>> Maybe it's case sensitive.
Maybe it's not.
Let's see.
No such file or directory.
And we can kind of cheat by
just looking at top left.
What did I obviously
save the program as?
All caps hello.
So indeed, that's going
to make a difference.
So now hello world is back.
Now this is all fine and good,
and all very mind-numbing,
to sort of get bogged down in these
details, but understanding them
is good.
>> Typing out these increasingly
long incantations
is not going to be particularly
fun, so people in the world
invented another program,
some years ago, called
make, that quite simply
allows you to type make,
the name of the program
you want to make, and make
is smart in that it will look in
the current folder, aka directory,
and if you have a file
called hello dot c,
that is the file it will compile
for you into a program called hello.
So it's a much simpler way of
doing the more cryptic commands
that we did earlier.
And we have pre-configured
CS50 IDE to know
that it should do dash o and a number of
other flags, or command line arguments,
that we'll see before long.
>> But let's now actually do
something more interesting.
Just typing out hello world all
the time isn't all that compelling.
So let me go ahead and change
this program and say, hello David.
Now I'm going to go down here.
I'm going to go ahead and do make hello.
And again now you're seeing
make is showing you the longer
sequence of commands that it's
doing because we've pre-configured
it that way, but we
needn't worry for now
what it's doing other than it is
compiling dot slash hello, hello world.
What's wrong?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yes.
So, noobie mistake.
I notice this is super subtle,
but the asterisk here, in the tab,
just means you haven't saved it,
and browsers and other programs
do this sometimes.
So control s or command
s should save it.
Now let me go ahead
and re-run the program.
Recompiled.
Right, so it's a multi-step process.
None of which is particularly complex,
but any time we change the file,
we need to change the resulting
zeros and ones, and dot slash hello.
Wow.
So this is very underwhelming
that we just printed out this.
Let's make things a
little more dynamic, now.
>> Well it turns out, that like
Scratch, C supports variables.
And it turns out if you want
to have a variable that stores,
not a number like we
typically did with Scratch,
but like a word, or a
phrase, or a name, you
can specify a variable
to be of type string.
So we'll see more of
these in just a moment,
but it turns out that C, and
a lot of languages like it,
have very specific types of variables.
It's not just like algebra,
where you get an x, a y, and z
and those are just always
numbers, in a programming language
you can store numbers, you can
store individual characters,
you could store whole words, you could
store whole images, whole sound files,
and the like.
So we need to specify what
the type of our variable is.
And by convention I'm going to call my
variable s just because it's succinct,
and s stands for string.
>> And then I'm going to store
inside of this variable,
just like with Scratch
when I use the set block,
I'm going to use the
assignment operator in C,
which nicely enough is the equal
sign, but the equal sign does this.
It moves something from the right into
the left hand side of the expression.
So what I have done, to be clear in
line five, is I've declared a variable.
I've told the computer, give me
memory for a variable, call it s,
and know in advance that I'm going
to be putting a string in it.
And a string is just a
sequence of characters.
It's a word, or a phrase, or paragraph,
but it's a sequence of characters.
It's not numbers.
What string am I going to be
putting into that variable?
Well, apparently quote
unquote, "Hannah".
Now notice the pattern that's emerging.
There's a left hand expression.
There's a right hand expression,
separated by the equal sign.
And just take a guess, if
unfamiliar nonetheless,
with what the semicolon is doing.
What's it presumably doing for us?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
It's just terminating the line.
Right?
The computers want to be bluntly
told, literally, what to do.
Like the peanut butter and
jelly sandwich example,
if you don't specify
exactly what you intend,
it might be left to judgment or error.
The semicolon means,
that's it for this command.
It's being super precise, and it's
a very easy thing to leave off.
So now this program doesn't seem to
be behaving any differently until I
make it more dynamic.
So rather than hard could my own
name, let me put a placeholder value.
And it turns out that, and I know this
from having read the documentation,
and used the function for years, that
printf was designed to be dynamic.
You don't have to know in advance
what words you want to put in it.
You can instead have a
placeholder, like percent s, which
is going to tell the
computer, put a string here.
>> Which string do we want to put there?
Will turns out that between these
parentheses, which remember, demarcate
the input to a function, if you have
comma separated list of things here,
we actually pass in multiple
inputs to a function.
So just like some Scratch
blocks, you might not
have played with them for
your projects yet or at all,
some Scratch blocks have two inputs.
Two white boxes you can
type numbers or words into.
So to does C have functions like
printf that can take two inputs.
And again, this comma
is separating them.
So in English, again even if
you've never programmed before,
by that logic printf is a function,
takes two inputs, one of which
is a placeholder, what would you hope
printf is going to do with this input?
It's going to say hello
Hannah, hopefully.
So to do this we need to save it.
I'm going to zoom out.
I'm going to go back down here
and say, make hello enter.
Oh.
Something's wrong, and actually
this is quite overwhelming.
I have six lines of code
and like 12 lines of errors.
So, look forward to this.
So what's going on here?
So the best rule of thumb here,
especially when you're starting out,
don't get distracted by
the stuff at the bottom.
In fact, I very deliberately
just scrolled up
because very often, a computer is
not all that bright of a device.
It's going to get confused.
If it sees one thing that
it doesn't understand,
it might mistake other
lines of code as incorrect,
even though they're perfectly fine.
So you always want to work
top down through the errors.
And admittedly this is
super arcane at the moment.
>> Error, use of undeclared
identifier string.
Did I mean standard in?
No, I meant string.
And it's pointing at, maybe it's a typo.
Sort of like, spell-checking in a
very geeky way, but the reason here,
and you'll know this
just by practice, is
that it turns out that string
does not exist in C. In fact, C
is a particularly old language,
and it's very low level,
and it doesn't a lot of features
that you might have grown up
with if you have, in fact, programmed
in Java, as some of you have,
but you can teach it new things.
And indeed, we have done this CS50,
even though by the end of the semester,
all of these training wheels
will have been taken off,
what we do in these
first couple of weeks
initially is we also have
you include CS50 dot h.
Which is a header file.
More on that in the future.
>> It's a file that contains functions
that we have written for you.
And among those functions is
functions for getting input
from the user, like strings, and
numbers, and real numbers, and more.
But it also has a few shortcuts.
It defines a Boolean as a data type.
C does not have true or false.
But we can give it the notion of
true or false by way of this library.
And it also doesn't have a string
built in until we include this line.
So this line of code tells
the compiler, hey, Clang, look
in this file for a whole
bunch of code that CS50
has written so that
anyone using this file
can take for granted the
features they've added.
>> So now let me go ahead
and clear the screen,
and if curious I'm just saying control
l each time to clear the screen,
or you can type clear.
I'm just going to go ahead now and
type make hello, and all is well.
Still an arcane output, but
it's not an erroneous message.
Now if I do dot slash hello, and as an
aside, dot slash is unfamiliar to most.
It just means, dot means
the current directory.
So if you've ever used
DOS, or Linux, or Unix
you might have done something
like cd dot dot, where
dot dot means go backwards in
time, or go backwards, or higher up
in your directory.
Dot just means look in
the current directory.
I want hello, which is right here.
And indeed, now it says hello Hannah.
And if I change it again
to Maria, recompile
it would make hello, dot slash
hello, the program keeps changing.
>> But this is still a
pretty stupid program.
If I want to ship this program,
or give it to a friend,
or give it to Maria or Hannah
for that matter, that's fine.
I can customize it for both of them,
but it's never going to be dynamic.
They can't change it once it's compiled
down into those zeros and ones.
So what we did something smarter?
What if, instead of hard-coding
into the program this person's name,
what if we just get
the string on demand?
>> So in other words, let me do this.
I'm going to recompile this program.
And let me zoom in at the bottom now.
Make hello dot slash hello.
Now nothing is happening.
Can we get a quick volunteer
to make something happen?
Come on up.
What's your name?
>> PANCHO: Pancho.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Pacho?
Come on up.
Once you get up here, this is
going to be very underwhelming,
but it's more interesting
than me typing it.
If you want to go ahead and type your
name, I made this program just for you.
Just type your name.
Enter.
Wonderful.
All right, thank you very much.
>> PANCHO: Thank you very much.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> That was very kind.
Here you Go.
What did we do?
So we finally, at least,
made this program dynamic.
Now it's still certainly
by design underwhelming,
but we finally have the ability
now to write code in advance, much
like the authors of printf,
and then dynamically
adapt based on the input we are
handed, either by the programmer,
or by the human who's actually
interacting with the program.
So let's actually now try
to do a few other constructs
and see if we can't make the programs
themselves more sophisticated.
So let's go ahead and instead of
writing this one from scratch,
I'm going to go into today's
source code, and all of this
is available on the course's
website, and you can drag and drop it
into your own environment
come Friday once problem
set 1 gives you the
instructions, or you could
do it at the command line as
well, but more to come in p set 1.
>> Let's see what's in this program
here called, adder dot c.
Now I've already commented
it, but what's new?
At first glance, what line
of code is absolutely new?
Probably not fundamentally
unfamiliar now.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
so int x equals get n.
We've never seen any of this
before, but int is probably
the symbol for what kind of
variable, [? from ?] an integer.
So int for integer.
It's just being more
succinct. x is just arbitrary.
x and y and z are still
pretty reasonable for numbers,
but generally we'll use words once
our programs get more complex.
Get int, of course,
much like get string,
is probably going to get
an int from the user,
and then we're going to
do the same thing with y.
And apparently, even though this
last line, 24, looks more complex,
it's going to say the sum of this
and that is this other thing.
>> And notice percent i
probably denotes what?
What role does percent
i apparently serve?
It's just placeholders.
Right?
Percent s was for string,
percent i is for integer.
There's going to be percent f
for floating point value, which
is just a number with a decimal point.
In other words, a real number.
So let's actually compile this
program real fast and do make adder.
Whoops.
Good opportunity.
So notice here, all this time my user
name for this account is jharvard.
I am in CS50 IDE, aka IDE50.
And now in blue here, is a mention, but
from the environment, of where I am.
And in fact, if I zoom up to the top
here, notice that I have an IDE50
and I see this word, if you kind of
turn your head to the side, workspace.
In a nutshell, the fact that
I'm seeing tilde slash workspace
means that in this text
based command environment,
I am in the text equivalent of
this graphical folder up here.
So when I do dot slash
adder, it's saying no rule
to make target adder stop.
I don't know what that means,
but it's bad for some reason.
No such file or directory
is even more clear.
Where is it then?
Based on where I clicked
to open the file earlier.
Where might it be?
>> It's probably in source
one w, for Wednesday,
and I can see it, indeed,
if I open that up.
There is adder dot c, but in
this text-based environment,
again, I have to be super explicit.
If I want to change directories into
source one Wednesday, I need to type,
cd space source one
Wednesday enter and now
my prompt changes to
give me a visual cue that
I'm, indeed, elsewhere
in my environment,
but now I can do make
adder, it seems to work,
dot slash adder, give me an integer.
One.
Two.
The sum of one and two is three.
But if I don't cooperate,
let's see what get int does.
Give me an integer.
No.
Retry.
OK.
Fine.
50.
All right.
So it finally cooperates.
And that's some of the
functionality that these functions
can have built in for you.
>> So inside the implementation
of get int, what programming
construct from last week is probably in
there to compel this behavior of retry,
retry, retry?
Yeah, there's probably
some kind of loop.
It's going to look syntactically
different from Scratch's blocks,
but that's indeed
what's inside the file.
And in a few weeks time we'll
actually look at the CS50 library
as to what's inside, but there's
a loop imposing exactly that.
>> Let's play a silly little
game here with this file.
Condition zero dot c.
We're just going to generally
start counting at zero.
And I keep scrolling past
some of the stuff at top.
In blue here, demarcated with all
of these stars and the slashes,
those of you who program
before, what is that?
Why do we keep skipping over it?
What?
>> AUDIENCE: It's a comment.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
It's just a comment.
This is a comment for humans
to read, that in our case,
tells us what the name of the file
is, who wrote it, and what it does,
so that you don't have
to read through the code
to know what this file is all about.
It's just a description, but
functionally it's irrelevant.
And I can even delete it from
my file and it has no impact.
The juicy lines are these
first two here, now.
int main void is the equivalent
of our when green flag clicked,
so we're going to leave that be
for today, and we'll come back,
eventually, as to what
int and void are, but now,
notice what I've done
here too, you can also,
if you have an in line
comment, if you have
a thought you want to share
about a particular line of code,
convention in C is to do slash
slash, and then a few succinct words,
not a full sentence,
generally not a paragraph,
that just explains to you, or your
TF, or other readers or colleagues,
what your code is doing.
So rather than have to look
at this and infer from lines
nine and 10, what is
this doing, in line eight
I just give a comment to
ask the user for an integer,
then I don't have to think too hard
about what lines nine and 10 are.
I just know that that's what
collectively they're doing.
>> How?
Well, here's the prompt.
Here's the getting of the int.
And based on the previous
behavior, it seems like get int
is smart enough to make sure that
the human cooperates and gives it
an integer.
But now we see this.
And this is reminiscent of Scratch.
I'm claiming that I'm
analyzing the user's input,
but somewhat inaccurately.
And this apparently in C is how
we express an if else, a branch,
a fork in the road, but I
say somewhat inaccurately.
What's the bug in this program?
About further back?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] zero.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So if I type in zero, let's consider
exactly that case, or corner case,
if you will.
So if I type in zero, which of the
blocks is going to apparently grab it?
The if or the else?
The else, and it's going to say,
you picked a negative number.
And indeed, zero is not supposed
to be positive or negative,
and so that would be erroneously.
That would be a bug.
So how can we fix this?
Someone who has never programmed before?
Do you want--
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Retracting?
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, you have?
Someone who has never programmed before.
Want to try your hand at
this, in the red shirt?
Come on up.
Oh yeah, come on up, if you don't mind.
So never having programmed
before, what's your name?
LAUREN: Lauren.
DAVID J. MALAN: Lauren, all right.
So fix this bug for us.
You've not seen C, presumably,
and probably no other language.
So fix this program for us.
Nice to meet ya.
No pressure.
LAUREN: Yeah.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: But again, if this
gamble goes according to plan,
the takeaway here will
be, just again, to start
to notice patterns and
infer from existing syntax
how else you might express
yourself, no pun intended, in order
to capture some additional scenario.
So we're saying else if.
printf, good.
And notice with CS50
IDE, and frankly-- IDE
stands for Integrated
Development Environment.
It's just a fancy way of saying
a program that helps you program.
It does user friendly things like
when you type one parenthesis,
it automatically gives you the other.
The presumption being that you're
eventually going to want to type that,
and it also does it with quotes.
>> So I like line 23.
99% of the way there.
Someone want to chime in with a tip?
I heard semicolon from the audience.
Good.
So that completes that.
And now, I just have a little
consternation with line 21.
How do we want to express this?
What question do we want
to ask, do you think?
So previously we asked the question,
if n is greater than zero, do this.
Else, do that.
So we need to choose a
question to ask here.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
So if n equals zero.
Excellent.
So let's pause here.
Thank you so much for braving this.
Let me give you a little well-deserved
stress ball, perhaps there.
So we're almost there.
In fact, Lauren, if you don't
mind, let me make one tweak here,
just to be consistent even with
what we saw in Scratch, what
do I want to do with lines
21 and 24, just again based
on how we did this in Scratch, perhaps?
>> AUDIENCE: Move it up.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, move it up.
So the else condition, the third, or
fourth, or fifth, or final branch,
should indeed come afterward,
and that's just by convention,
just because if you will.
So I do need to make this tweak.
And I need to put my
curly brace back here.
And now, this program will compile.
We're so close, but there's
a very, very subtle bug.
Let's see what happens.
>> First, let me go ahead and zoom out.
I'm going to go ahead and
type make condition zero.
Oh, I lied.
Now the compiler is
actually pretty smart.
And I don't really understand
it's error message.
Using the result of an assignment
as a condition without parentheses,
is apparently bad.
But what does that mean?
>> Well again, looking for patterns
in code that we've seen before,
what is line 17 actually doing,
even though Lauren intended slightly
otherwise?
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So remember the equal sign, apparently
as we've used it before, is not equals.
Its assignment, from right to left.
So line 17 at the moment
is a condition, and it's
executing code inside the parentheses,
but when that code executes,
what is happening to the value of zero?
What is happening to the value of n?
Becoming zero.
So if n is becoming zero,
and again, as per last week,
we generally say that zero
is false and one is true,
or yes is one and no is zero.
So true and false, one and 0.
If n as of line 17 has been
given the value 0, is zero true?
No.
By definition, zero is false.
That's the convention we're
going to cling to moving forward.
So will lines 18, 19, and 20
ever apply now, logically?
They can't.
So we asked the question
but not quite precisely,
and you wouldn't know this unless
you've seen it, the solution in C
is when you want to express
equality, you say equals equals.
So equal sign was already used up
by assignment, from right to left.
Equals equals means equals.
And if you really want your mind
to be bent, in JavaScript and PHP,
there's equals equals equals, which
mean something else altogether,
but we'll get to that before long.
>> So this is a simple fix, but realize
super easy to make this mistake,
and then wonder and struggle
for minutes, if not an hour,
why is my code not
executing as I intend?
It's because you didn't tell
it precisely what you meant.
So that was almost
perfect, and it was great
that we stumbled across these two little
things because now if we fix them,
and I do make condition zero
dot slash condition zero,
I'd like an integer please.
Let's see.
No.
It's going to force me to do it.
So 42.
I picked a positive number.
So now how do I prove
this program correct?
If you're a mathematician, you can't
really prove this by trial and error,
right?
You can't just proof by
example, but at least
as a programmer we're not
going to try to prove for now
that this is actually
correct, but I should probably
test some representative cases.
>> I've tested 42.
I could test 43.
I could test 44.
Test 45.
Right?
But I could do this a really long time.
What would be some more
interesting cases to try?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] zero.
DAVID J. MALAN: So zero.
Certainly.
And good, we've got it this time,
thanks to Lauren's new code.
What's another good case to try?
AUDIENCE: Negative one.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Negative one, and
maybe something a little bigger,
so maybe negative 42,
but in general, when
testing your programs
moving forward, you're
going to want to think
to yourself, like what
are the fundamental different cases.
And I dare say a negative case,
a positive case, and a zero case
pretty much rounds these out.
Let's look at a variant of this though.
Conditions one.
This is a correct solution here,
so that you'll see two and online,
if you walk through the
walkthroughs, will generally
increment these stepwise until we
get exactly the right approach.
What if we wanted to ask
two questions at once?
>> Let me open up this instead.
Non-switch, for reasons
we'll see another time.
What's new syntactically here?
I'm currently playing a game
where the computer is telling
me, give me an integer
between one and 10,
and then I'm judging the user's input.
In English, based on
the code you see here
in blue, what is this program doing?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] picked
a big or small number.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
It's just adjudicating whether
I picked a big, or medium,
or small number based on a very
arbitrary definition of small, medium,
and large here, but notice
the syntax that's new is this.
There's no less than int or equal to
sign, or greater than or equal to sign,
where one is over the other, that you
can express in like Microsoft Word.
So in a programming language you
typically just do two characters,
one after the other.
And what does this probably
represent, ampersand ampersand.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
It just means and because it
turns out that the authors of C
used a single ampersand,
which you might think
would be perfect for the notion
of and, is already used up,
so ampersand ampersand actually
captures the case we actually want.
>> So let's now stumble across two things.
Let me go ahead and open up one.
Something that's a little worrisome.
Imprecision dot c.
Let me introduce two things here.
One, notice that we can do
math, as just as before when
we did plus of two numbers, x and y.
What is this program apparently doing?
I've not commented it yet,
and I've introduced percent f,
but I quickly said earlier
percent f means floating point
value, which is real number.
Something with a decimal
point, which is not an integer.
What do you think this program is
trying to show me on the screen?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: The result of one over 10.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
What's the result of one divided by 10.
Right, because all of you have probably
grown up knowing that one over 10
is what?
Yeah, it's just 1/10 or 0.1.
Right?
So let's see what this actually is.
So let me go ahead and save this.
Let me go down here.
Make imprecision dot slash
imprecision, and notice, too,
in a Linux environment, you don't
have to type out imprecision and take
all day long.
It generally, if you hit Tab, it
will finish your thought for you,
based on the words that are
available in the current directory.
OK.
So you were right.
One divided by 10 is, in fact, 0.1.
But I'm a little curious.
And it turns out printf
supports some features
whereby you can specify more than
the default number of decimal points.
So if I want to see 10 decimal
points I can do percent,
for the placeholder symbol, dot
10 for, give me 10 decimal points,
and then still floating point
value, and, as an aside,
what is this backslash n
apparently we keep using?
It turns out it's a
symbol for a new line.
It's the very explicit way
of saying to the computer,
move the cursor to the next
line after you're done.
And we'll see what happens
when we don't do that.
>> Let me recompile make imprecision.
Now dot slash imprecision.
OK.
Still right.
One divided by 10.
Now I'm getting a
little curious, though.
What if I look 20 decimal
points out, recompile, rerun,
and as an aside for
speed, you can also use
your up and down arrows to
scroll through your history,
so you don't have to keep
retyping these commands, enter.
Huh.
I did not learn that in grade school.
All right, so let me
see like 29 places out.
Maybe it's just a fluke.
Maybe my computer is acting weird.
That's not a thing, right?
It's doing something deterministically.
So make imprecision.
OK, that's messed up.
So what is going on?
>> So apparently your
teacher has been lying
to you all of this time for
reasons that we'll see before long.
But let's end with one other program.
This is a little programs
someone wrote some years ago,
and it's actually part of a contest.
No one actually writes code
like this, and if you do,
this is stylistically a problem.
But people do this for bragging rights.
To write the most confusing
looking program that
nonetheless does something interesting.
And the note I thought we'd leave on
today, before Colton plays us out here,
is to run this program,
which, even in just using
C in this text-based
environment, gives us this.
Dammit.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> Stand by.
[INAUDIBLE] c dash l m.
You're going to see the magical
incantation that we'll see before long.
[INAUDIBLE] All right.
And now you can even
do things like this.
That's it.
For CS50 we, will see you on Friday.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> [APPLAUSE]