>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> PROFESSOR: All right.
This is CS50 and this is
the end of week three.
So we're here today, not in Sanders
Theater, instead in Weidner Library.
Inside of which is a studio
known as Hauser Studio,
or shall we say Studio H, or shall
we say-- if you enjoyed that joke,
it's actually from
classmate, Mark, online,
who suggested as much via Twitter.
Now what's cool about
being here in a studio
is that I'm surrounded by these green
walls, a green screen or chromakey,
so to speak, which means that CS50's
production team, unbeknownst to me
right now, could be putting
me most anywhere in the world,
for better or for worse.
>> Now what lies ahead, problem set
two is in your hands for this week,
but with problem set
three this coming week,
you will be challenged with
the so-called game of 15,
an old party favor that
you might recall receiving
as a child that has a whole bunch
of numbers that can slide up, down,
left and right, and there's one gap
within the puzzle, into which you
can actually slide those puzzle pieces.
Ultimately you receive this
puzzle in some semi random order,
and the goal is to
sort it, top to bottom,
left to right, from one
all the way up through 15.
>> Unfortunately, the implementation
you'll have at hand
is going to be software
based, not physically.
You're actually going to have to write
code with which a student or user can
play the game of 15.
And in fact, in the hacker
edition of game of 15,
you'll be a challenge to implement,
not just the playing of this old school
game, but rather the solving
of it, implementing god mode,
so to speak, that actually
solves the puzzle for the human,
by providing them with hint,
after hint, after hint.
So more on that next week.
But that's what lies ahead.
>> For now recall that earlier this week
we had this cliffhanger, if you will,
whereby the best we were doing sorting
wise was an upper bound of big o of n
squared.
In other words, bubble sort,
selection sort, insertion sort,
all of them, while different
in their implementation,
devolved into an n squared running
time in the very worst case.
And we generally assume that
the very worst case for sorting
is one that your inputs
are completely backwards.
And indeed, it took quite a few steps
to implement each of those algorithms.
>> Now at the very end of class
recall, we compared bubble sort
against selection sort against one other
that we called merge sort at the time,
and I propose that it's taking
advantage of a lesson from week
zero, divide and conquer.
And somehow achieving some kind of
logarithmic running time ultimately,
instead of something
that's purely quadratic.
And it's not quite logarithmic,
it's a bit more than that.
But if you recall from class,
it was much, much faster.
Let's take a look at where we left off.
>> Bubble sort versus selection
sort versus merge sort.
Now they're all running, in
theory, at the same time.
The CPU is running at the same speed.
But you can feel how boring this
is very quickly going to become,
and just how fast, when we inject
a bit of week zero's algorithms,
can we speed things up.
>> So mark sort looks amazing.
How can we leverage it, in order
to sort numbers more quickly.
Well let's think back
to an ingredient that we
had back in week zero, that of
searching for someone in a phone book,
and recall that the
pseudocode that we proposed,
via which we can find
someone like Mike Smith,
looked a little something like this.
>> Now take a look in particular
at line 7 and 8, and 10 and 11,
which induce that loop, whereby we kept
going back to line 3 again, and again,
and again.
But it turns out that we can view
this algorithm, here in pseudocode,
a little more holistically.
In fact, what I'm looking
at here on the screen,
is an algorithm for searching for
Mike Smith among some set of pages.
And indeed, we could simplify this
algorithm in those lines 7 and 8,
and 10 and 11 to just say this,
which I've presented here in yellow.
In other words, if Mike
Smith is earlier in the book,
we don't need to specify step
by step now how to go find him.
We don't have to specify
to go back to line 3,
why don't we just instead,
say, more generally,
search for Mike in the
left half of the book.
>> Conversely, if Mike is
actually later in the book,
why don't we just quote unquote search
for Mike in the right half of the book.
In other words, why don't we just
sort of punt to ourselves saying,
search for Mike in this
subset of the book,
and leave it to our existing
algorithm to tell us
how to search for Mike in
that left half of the book.
In other words, our
algorithm works whether it's
a phone book of this thickness, of this
thickness, or any thickness whatsoever.
So we can recursively
define this algorithm.
In other words, on the
screen here, is an algorithm
for searching for Mike Smith
among the pages of a phone book.
So in line 7 and 10, let's
just say exactly that.
And I use this term a moment
ago, and indeed, recursion
is the buzzword for now,
and it's this process
of doing something cyclical by somehow
using code that you already have,
and calling it again,
and again, and again.
Now it's going to be important
that we somehow bottom
out, and don't do that infinitely long.
Otherwise we're going to
have indeed an infinite loop.
But let's see if we can borrow this idea
of a recursion, doing something again
and again and again, to solve
the sorting problem via merge
sort, all the more efficiently.
>> So I give you merge sort.
Let's take a look.
So here is pseudocode, with
which we could implement sorting,
using this algorithm called merge sort.
And it's quite simply this.
On input of n elements,
in other words, if you're
given n elements and numbers and
letters or whatever the input is,
if you're given n elements, if
n is less than 2, just return.
Right?
Because if n is less than 2, that
means that my list of elements
is either of size 0 or 1, and
in both of those trivial cases,
the list is already sorted.
If there is no list, it's sorted.
And if there's a list of length
1, it's obviously sorted.
So the algorithm only needs to
really do something interesting,
if we have two or more
elements given to us.
So let's look at the magic then.
Else sort the left half of the elements,
then sort the right half of elements,
then merge the sorted halves.
And what's kind of mind bending
here, is that I don't really
seem to have told you
anything just yet, right?
All I've said is, given a list of
n elements, sort the left half,
then the right half, then
merge the sorted halves,
but where is the actual secret sauce?
Where is the algorithm?
Well it turns out that those two lines
first, sort left half of elements,
and sort right half of elements,
are recursive calls, so to speak.
>> After all, at this
point in time, do I have
an algorithm with which to
sort a whole bunch of elements?
Yes.
It's right here.
It's right here on the screen, and
so I can use that same set of steps
to sort the left half,
as I can the right half.
And indeed, again, and again.
So somehow or other, and we'll soon
see this, the magic of merge sort
is embedded in that very final
line, merging the sorted halves.
And that seems fairly intuitive.
You take two halves, and you,
somehow, merge them together,
and we'll see this
concretely in a moment.
>> But this is a complete algorithm.
And let's see exactly why.
Well suppose that we're given these same
eight elements here on the screen, one
through eight, but they're
in seemingly random order.
And the goal at hand is
to sort these elements.
Well how can I go about
doing it using, again,
merge sort, as per this pseudocode?
And again, ingrain this in
your mind, for just a moment.
The first case is pretty
trivial, if it's less than 2,
just return, there's no work to be done.
So really there's just three
steps to really keep in mind.
Again, and again, I'm
going to want to have
to sort the left half,
sort the right half,
and then once their
two halves are sorted,
I want to merge them together
into one sorted list.
So keep that in mind.
>> So here's the original list.
Let's treat this as an
array, as we started to
in week two, which is a
contiguous block of memory.
In this case, containing eight
numbers, back to back to back.
And let's now apply merge sort.
So I first want to sort
the left half of this list,
and let's, therefore,
focus on 4, 8, 6, and 2.
>> Now how do I go about
sorting a list of size 4?
Well I have to now consider
sorting the left of the left half.
Again, let's rewind for just a moment.
If the pseudocode is this,
and I'm given eight elements,
8 is obviously greater
than or equal to 2.
So with the first case doesn't apply.
So to sort eight elements, I first
sort the left half of elements,
then I sort the right half, then I merge
the two sorted halves, each of size 4.
OK.
>> But if you've just told me, sort the
left half, which is now of size 4,
how do I sort the left half?
Well if I have an
input of four elements,
I first sort the left
two, then the right two,
and then I merge them together.
So again, it becomes a bit
of a mind bending game here,
because you, kind of, have to
remember where you are in the story,
but at the end of the day,
given any number of elements,
you first want to sort the
left half, then the right half,
then merge them together.
Let's start to do exactly that.
Here's the input of eight elements.
Now we're looking at the left half here.
How do I sort four elements?
Well I first sort the left half.
Now how do I sort the left half?
Well I've been given two elements.
So let's sort these two elements.
2 is greater than or
equal to 2, of course.
So that first case doesn't apply.
>> So I now have to sort the left
half of these two elements.
The left half, of course, is just 4.
So how do I sort a list of one element?
Well now, that special base case
up top, so to speak, applies.
1 is less than 2, and my
list is indeed of size 1.
So I just return.
I don't do anything.
And indeed, look at what I've
done, 4 is already sorted.
Like I'm already
partially successful here.
>> Now that seems kind of stupid
to claim, but it is true.
4 is a list of size 1.
It's already sorted.
That's the left half.
Now I sort the right half.
My input is one element, 8
similarly, already sorted.
Stupid, too, but again,
this basic principle
is going to allow us to now build
on top of this successfully.
4 sorted, 8 is sorted, now
what was that last step?
So the third and final step, any
time you're sorting a list, recall,
was to merge the two halves,
the left and the right.
So let's do exactly that.
My left half is, of course, 4.
My right half is 8.
>> So let's do this.
First I'm going to allocate
some additional memory,
that I'll represent here,
as just a secondary array,
that's big enough to fit this.
But you can imagine extending
that rectangle the whole length,
if we need more later.
How do I take 4 and 8, and merge
those two lists of size 1 together?
Here, too, pretty simple.
4 comes first, then comes 8.
Because if I want to sort the
left half, then the right half,
and then merge those two halves
together, in sorted order,
4 comes first, then comes 8.
>> So we seem to be making progress, even
though I haven't done any actual work.
But remember where we are in the story.
We originally took eight elements.
We sorted the left half, which is 4.
Then we sorted the left half
of the left half, which was 2.
And here we go.
We're done with that step.
>> So if we've sorted the
left half of 2, now we
have to sort the right half of 2.
So the right half of 2 is
these two values here, 6 and 2.
So let's now take an input of size
2, and sort the left half, and then
the right half, and then
merge them together.
Well how do I sort a list of size
1, containing just the number 6?
I'm already done.
That list of size 1 is sorted.
>> How do I sort another list of
size 1, the so-called right half.
Well it, too, is already sorted.
The number 2 is alone.
So now I have two halves, left and
right, I need to merge them together.
Let me give myself some extra space.
And put 2 in there,
then 6 in there, thereby
sorting that list, left and right,
and merging it together, ultimately.
So I'm in slightly better shape.
I'm not done, because clearly 4, 8, 2,
6 is not the final ordering that I want.
But I now have two lists of size 2, that
have both, respectively, been sorted.
So now if you rewind in your mind's
eye, where did that leave us?
I started with eight elements, then I
whittled it down to the left half of 4,
then the left half of 2, and
then the right half of 2,
I finished, therefore, sorting the left
half of 2, and the right half of 2,
so what's the third and final step here?
I have to merge together
two lists of size 2.
So let's go ahead.
And on the screen here, give
me some additional memory,
though technically, notice that I've
got a whole bunch of blank space up top
there.
If I want to be especially
efficient space wise,
I could just start moving the elements
back and forth, top and bottom.
But just for visual clarity,
I'm going to put it down below,
to keep things nice and clean.
>> So I've got two lists of size 2.
The first list has 4 and 8.
The second list has 2 and 6.
Let's merge those
together in sorted order.
2, of course, comes first,
then 4, then 6, then 8.
And now we seem to be getting
somewhere interesting.
Now I've sorted half of the
list, and coincidentally, it's
all the even numbers, but that
is, indeed, just a coincidence.
And I now have sorted the left
half, so that it's 2, 4, 6, and 8.
Nothing's out of order.
That feels like progress.
>> Now it feels like I've
been talking forever now,
so what remains to be seen if this
algorithm is, indeed, more efficient.
But we're going through
it super methodically.
A computer, of course,
would do it like that.
So where are we?
We started with eight elements.
I sorted the left half of 4.
I seem to be done with that.
So now the next step is to
sort the right half of 4.
And this part we can go
through a little more
quickly, although you're
welcome to rewind or pause, just
think through it at
your own pace, but what
we have now is an opportunity to
do the exact same algorithm on four
different numbers.
>> So let's go ahead, and focus on
the right half, which we are here.
The left half of that
right half, and now the
left half of the left
half of that right half,
and how do I sort a list of size
1 containing just the number 1?
It's already done.
How do I do the same for a list
of size 1 containing just 7?
It's already done.
Step three for this half then
is to merge these two elements
into a new list of size 2, 1 and 7.
Don't seem to have done all
that much interesting work.
Let's see what happens next.
I just sorted the left half of the
right half of my original input.
Now let's sort the right
half, which contains 5 and 3.
Let's again look at the left
half, sorted, right half, sorted,
and merge those two together,
into some additional space,
3 comes first, then comes 5.
And so now, we have sorted the
left half of the right half
of the original problem, and
the right half of the right half
of the original problem.
What's the third and final Step?
Well to merge those two halves together.
So let me get myself some
extra space, but, again, I
could be using that spare space up top.
But we're going to keep
it simple visually.
Let me merge in now 1, and
then 3, and then 5, and then 7.
Thereby leaving me now with the
right half of the original problem
that's perfectly sorted.
>> So what remains?
I feel like I keep saying the
same things again, and again,
but that's reflective of the
fact that we're using recursion.
The process of using an
algorithm again, and again,
on smaller subsets of
the original problem.
So I now have a left sorted
half of the original problem.
I have a right sorted half
of the original problem.
What's the third and final step?
Oh, it's merging.
So let's do that.
Let's allocate some additional
memory, but my god, we
could put it anywhere now.
We have so much space available
to us, but we'll keep it simple.
Instead of going back and
forth with our original memory,
let's just do it
visually down here below,
to finish up merging the
left half and the right half.
>> So by merging, what do I need to do?
I want to take the elements in order.
So looking at the left half,
I see the first number is 2.
I look at the right half,
I see the first number
is 1, so obviously which
number do I want to pluck out,
and put first in my final list?
Of course, 1.
Now I want to ask that same question.
On the left half, I've
still got the number 2.
On the right half,
I've got the number 3.
Which one do I want to choose?
Of course, number 2 And
now notice the candidates
are 4 on the left, 3 on the right.
Let's, of course, choose 3.
Now the candidates are 4 on
the left, 5 on the right.
We, of course, choose 4.
6 on the left, 5 on the right.
We, of course, choose 5.
6 on the left, 7 on the right.
We choose 6, and then we
choose 7, and then we choose 8.
Voila.
>> So a huge number of words later, we
have sorted this list of eight elements
into a list of one through eight,
that's increasing with each step,
but how much time did
it take us to do that.
Well I've deliberately
laid things out pictorially
here, so that we can kind of
see or appreciate the division
in conquering that's been happening.
>> Indeed if you look back at the wake,
I've left all of these dotted lines
in place holders, you can,
kind of, see, in reverse order,
if you kind of look back in
history now, my original list
is, of course, of size 8.
And then previously, I was
dealing with two lists of size 4,
and then four lists of size 2,
and then eight lists of size 1.
>> So what does this,
kind of, remind you of?
Well, indeed, any of
the algorithms we've
looked at thus far where we
divide, and divide, and divide,
keep having things again, and
again, results in this general idea.
And so there's something
logarithmic going on here.
And it's not quite log of n, but
there's a logarithmic component
to what we've just done.
>> Now let's consider how that actually is.
So log of n, again was
a great running time,
when we did something like
binary search, as we now call it,
the divide and conquer strategy
via which we found Mike Smith.
Now technically.
That's log base 2 of n, even
though in most math classes,
10 is usually the base that you assume.
But computer scientists almost always
think and talk in terms of base 2,
so we generally just say log of
n, instead of log base 2 of n,
but they're exactly one and the
same in the world of computer
science, and as an aside,
there's a constant factor
difference between the two, so it's
moot anyway, for more formal reasons.
>> But for now, what we care
about is this example.
So let's not prove by example, but at
least use an example of the numbers
at hand as a sanity check, if you will.
So previously the formula was log base
2 of n, but what is n in this case.
I had n original numbers, or 8
of original number specifically.
Now it's been a little
while, but I'm pretty
sure that log base 2
of the value 8 is 3,
and indeed, what's nice about that is
that 3 is exactly the number of times
that you can divide a list
of length 8 again, and again,
and again, until you're left
with lists of just size 1.
Right?
8 goes to 4, goes to 2,
goes to 1, and that's
reflective of exactly that
picture we had just a moment ago.
So a little sanity check as to where
the logarithm is actually involved.
>> So now, what else is involved here? n.
So notice that every
time I split the list,
albeit in reverse order in history
here, I was still doing n things.
That merging step required that
I touch every one of the numbers,
in order to slide it into
its appropriate location.
So even though the height of this
diagram is of size log n of n or 3,
specifically, in other words,
I did three divisions here.
How much work did I do horizontally
along this chart each time?
>> Well, I did n steps of
work, because if I've
got four elements and four elements,
and I need to merge them together.
I need to go through
these four and these four,
ultimately to merge them
back into eight elements.
If conversely I've got eight fingers
over here, which I don't, and eight
fingers-- sorry-- If I've
got four fingers over here,
which I do, four fingers
over here, which I do,
then that's the same
example as before, if I do
have eight fingers though in
total, which I can, kind of, do.
I can exactly do here,
then I can certainly
merge all of these lists
of size 1 together.
But I certainly have to look
at each element exactly once.
So the height of this process is log n,
the width of this process, so to speak,
is n, so what we seem
to have, ultimately, is
a running time of size n times log n.
>> In other words, we divided
the list, log n times,
but each time we did that, we had
to touch every one of the elements
in order to merge them
all together, which
was n step, so we have n times log n,
or as a computer scientist would say,
asymptotically, which
would be the big word
to describe the upper
bound on a running time,
we are running in a big o
of log n time, so to speak.
>> Now this is significant, because
recall what the running times were
with bubble sort, and selection
sort, and insertion sort,
and even a few others that exist,
n squared was where we were at.
And you can, kind of, see this here.
If n squared is obviously n times
n, but here we have n times log n,
and we already know from week
zero, that log n, the logarithmic,
is better than something linear.
After all, recall the picture
with the red and the yellow
and the green lines that we drew, the
green logarithmic line was much lower.
And therefore, much better and faster
than the straight yellow and red lines,
n times log n is, indeed, better
than n times n, or n squared.
>> So we seem to have
identified an algorithm merge
sort that runs in much
faster time, and indeed,
that's why, earlier this week, when
we saw that contest between bubble
sort, selection sort, and merge
sort, merge sort really, really won.
And indeed, we didn't even wait
for bubble sort and selection sort
to finish.
>> Now let's take one other pass
at this, from a slightly more
formal perspective, just in
case, this resonates better
than that higher level discussion.
So here's the algorithm again.
Let's ask ourselves,
what the running time
is of this algorithms various steps?
Let's divide it into the first
case and the second case.
The IF and the ELSE In the IF case,
IF n is less than 2, just return.
Feels like constant time.
It's, kind of, like two steps,
IF n is less than 2, then return.
But as we said on Monday,
constant time, or big o of 1,
can be two steps, three
steps, even 1,000 steps.
What matters is that it's
a constant number of steps.
So the yellow highlighted pseudocode
here runs in, we'll call it,
constant time.
So more formally, and
we're going to-- this
will be the extent to which we
formalize this right now-- T of n,
the running time of a problem
that takes n somethings as input,
equals big o of one,
IF n is less than 2.
So it's conditional on that.
So to be clear, IF n is less than
2, we have a very short list, then
the running time, T of n, where n is
1 or 0, in this very specific case,
it's just going to be constant time.
It's going to take one
step, two steps, whatever.
It's a fixed number of steps.
>> So the juicy part must surely be in
the other case in the pseudocode.
The ELSE case.
Sort left half of elements, sort right
half of elements, merge sorted halves.
How long does each of those steps take?
Well, if the running
time to sort n elements
is, let's call it very
generically, T of n,
then sorting the left
half of the elements
is, kind of, like saying,
T of n divided by 2,
and similarly sorting the right half
of elements is, kind of, like saying,
T of n divided 2, and then
merging the sorted halves.
Well if I've got some
number of elements here,
like four, and some number
of elements here, like four,
and I have to merge each of these four
in, and each of these four in, one
after the other, so that
ultimately I have eight elements.
It feels like that's big o of n steps?
If I've got n fingers and each of
them has to be merged into place,
that's like another n steps.
>> So indeed formulaically,
we can express this,
albeit a little scarily at first
glance, but it is something
that captures exactly that logic.
The running time, T of n, IF n
is greater than or equal to 2.
In this case, the ELSE case, is T of n
divided by 2, plus T of n divided by 2,
plus big o of n, some
linear number of steps,
maybe exactly n, maybe 2 times
n, but it's roughly, order of n.
So that, too, is how we can
express this formulaically.
Now you wouldn't know this unless
you've recorded it in your mind,
or look it up in the
back of a textbook, that
might have a little
cheat sheet at the end,
but this is, indeed, going to
give us a big o of n log n,
because the recurrence that
you're seeing here on the screen,
if you actually did it out, with
an infinite number of examples,
or you did it formulaically, you would
see that this, because this formula
itself is recursive, with t of
n over something on the right,
and t of n over on the left, this can
actually be expressed, ultimately,
as big go of n log n.
If not convinced, that's
fine for now, just
take on faith, that that's, indeed,
what that recurrence leads to,
but this is just a bit more of a
mathematical approach to looking
at the running time of merge sort
based on its pseudocode alone.
>> Now let's take a bit of a
breather from all of that,
and take a look at a
certain former senator, who
might look a little familiar,
who sat down with Google's Eric
Schmidt, some time ago, for an interview
on stage, in front of a whole bunch
of people, talking ultimately about
a topic, that's pretty now familiar.
Let's take a look.
>> ERIC SCHMIDT: Now Senator,
you're here at Google,
and I like to think of the
presidency as a job interview.
Now it's hard to get a job as president.
PRESIDENT OBAMA: Right.
ERIC SCHMIDT: And you're
going to do [INAUDIBLE] now.
It's also hard to get a job at Google.
PRESIDENT OBAMA: Right.
>> ERIC SCHMIDT: We have questions,
and we ask our candidates questions,
and this one is from Larry Schwimmer.
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA: OK.
>> ERIC SCHMIDT: What?
You guys think I'm kidding?
It's right here.
What is the most efficient way to
sort a million 32 bit integers?
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA: Well--
ERIC SCHMIDT: Sometimes,
maybe I'm sorry, maybe--
PRESIDENT OBAMA: No, no,
no, no, no, I think--
ERIC SCHMIDT: That's not it--
PRESIDENT OBAMA: I
think, I think the bubble
sort would be the wrong way to go.
ERIC SCHMIDT: Come on.
Who told him this?
OK.
I didn't the computer science on--
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA: We've
got our spies in there.
PROFESSOR: All right.
Let's leave behind us now the
theoretical world of algorithms
in the asymptotic analysis
thereof, and return to some topics
from week zero and one, and start
to remove some training wheels,
if you will.
So that you really understand
ultimately from the ground up, what's
going on underneath the hood, when you
write, compile, and execute programs.
Recall in particular, that this was
the first C program we looked at,
a canonical, simple program
of sorts, relatively speaking,
wherein, it prints, Hello World.
And recall that I said, the process
that source code goes through
is exactly this.
You take your source code, pass
it through a compiler, like Clang,
and out comes object code, that
might look like this, zeros and ones
that the computer's CPU, central
processing unit or brain,
ultimately understands.
>> It turns out that that's a
bit of an oversimplification,
that we're now in a
position to tease apart
to understand what's really been
going on underneath the hood
every time you run
Clang, or more generally,
every time you make a program,
using Make and CF 50 IDE.
In particular, stuff like
this is first generated,
when you first compile your program.
In other words, when you
take your source code
and compile it, what's first
being outputted by Clang
is something known as assembly code.
And in fact, it looks exactly like this.
>> I ran a command at the
command line earlier.
Clang dash capital s hello.c,
and this created a file
for me called hello.s,
inside of which were exactly
these contents, and a little more
above and a little more below,
but I've put the juiciest
information here on the screen.
And if you look closely, you'll see
at least a few familiar keywords.
We have main at top.
We have printf down in the middle.
And we also have hello world
backslash n in quotes down below.
>> And everything else in here
is very low level instructions
that the computer's CPU understands.
CPU instructions that move memory
around, that load strings from memory,
and ultimately, print
things on the screen.
Now what happens though after
this assembly code is generated?
Ultimately, you do, indeed,
still generate object code.
But the steps that have really
been going on underneath the hood
look a little more like this.
Source code becomes assembly code,
which then becomes object code,
and the operative words here are that,
when you compile your source code,
out comes assembly code, and then
when you assemble your assembly code,
out comes object code.
>> Now Clang is super sophisticated,
like a lot of compilers,
and it does all of these steps
together, and it doesn't necessarily
output any intermediate
files that you can even see.
It just compiles things,
which is the general term that
describes this entire process.
But if you really want
to be particular, there's
a lot more going on there as well.
>> But let's also consider now that even
that super simple program, hello.c,
called a function.
It called printf.
But I did not write printf, indeed,
that comes with c, so to speak.
It's a function recall that's
declared in standard io.h, which
is a header file, which
is a topic we'll actually
dive into more depth before long.
But a header file is
typically accompanied
by a code file, source code file, so
much like there exists standard io.h.
>> Sometime ago, someone,
or someones, also wrote
a file called standard io.c, in
which the actual definitions,
or implementations of printf,
and bunches of other functions,
are actually written.
So given that, if we consider having
here on the left, hello.c, that when
compiled, gives us hello.s, even if
Clang doesn't bother saving in a place
we can see it, and that assembly code
gets assembled into hello.o, which
is, indeed, the default name
given whenever you compile source
code into object code, but aren't
quite ready to execute it yet,
because another step
has to happen, and has
been happening for the past few
weeks, perhaps unbeknownst to you.
>> Specifically somewhere
in CS50 IDE, and this,
too, will be a bit of an
oversimplification for a moment,
there is, or was upon a time,
a file called standard io.c,
that someone compiled into
standard io.s or the equivalent,
that someone then assembled
into standard io.o,
or it turns out into a
slightly different file
format that can have a different
file extension altogether,
but in theory and conceptually, exactly
those steps had to happen in some form.
Which is to say, that now
when I'm writing a program,
hello.c, that just says, hello world,
and I'm using someone else's code
like printf, which was once upon a
time, in a file called standard io.c,
then somehow I have to take my
object code, my zeros and ones,
and that person's object
code, or zeros and ones,
and somehow link them together into
one final file, called hello, that
has all of the zeros and
ones from my main function,
and all of the zeros
and ones for printf.
>> And indeed, that last process is
called, linking your object code.
The output of which
is an executable file.
So in fairness, at the
end of the day, nothing
has changed since week one, when we
first started compiling programs.
Indeed, all of this has been
happening underneath the hood,
but now we're in a position
where we can actually
tease apart these various steps.
And indeed, at the end
of the day, we're still
left with zeros and ones, which
is actually a great segue now
to another capability of C, that
we've not had to leverage most likely
to date, known as bitwise operators.
In other words, thus far, anytime we've
dealt with data in C or variables in C,
we've had things like
chars and floats and ins
and longs and doubles and the like, but
all of those are at least eight bits.
We've never yet been able to
manipulate individual bits,
even though an individual bit, we
know, can represent a 0 and a 1.
Now it turns out that in C, you
can get access to individual bits,
if you know the syntax,
with which to get at them.
>> So let's take a look
at bitwise operators.
So pictured here are a few symbols that
we've, kind of, sort of, seen before.
I see an ampersand, a vertical
bar, and some others as well,
and recall that ampersand ampersand
is something we have seen before.
The logical AND operator, where you have
two of them together, or the logical OR
operator, where you
have two vertical bars.
Bitwise operators, which we'll
see operate on bits individually,
just use a single ampersand, a
single vertical bar, the caret symbol
comes next, the little
tilde, and then left
bracket left bracket, or
right bracket right bracket.
Each of these have different meanings.
>> In fact, let's take a look.
Let's go old school today, and use
a touch screen from yesteryear,
known as a white board.
And this white board
is going to allow us
to express some fairly simple symbols,
or rather some fairly simple formulas,
that we can then ultimately
leverage, in order
to access individual
bits within a C program.
In other words, let's do this.
Let's first talk for a
moment about ampersand,
which is the bitwise AND operator.
In other words, this is
an operator that allows
me to have a left-hand variable
typically, and a right-hand variable,
or an individual value, that if we AND
them together, gives me a final result.
So what do I mean?
If in a program, you have a variable
that stores one of these values,
or let's keep it simple, and just
write out zeros and ones individually,
here's how the ampersand operator works.
0 ampersand 0 is going to equal 0.
Now why is that?
>> It's very similar to
Boolean expressions,
that we've discussed thus far.
If you think after all, the 0 is
false, 0 is false, false and false
is, as we've discussed
logically, also false.
So we get 0 here as well.
If you take 0 ampersand
1, well that, too,
is going to be 0, because for this
left-hand expression to be true or 1,
it would need to be true and true.
But here we have false
and true, or 0 and 1.
Now again, if we have 1 ampersand
0, that, too, is going to be 0,
and if we have 1 ampersand 1,
finally do we have a 1 bit.
So in other words, we're not doing
anything interesting with this operator
just yet, this ampersand operator.
It's the bitwise AND operator.
But these are the ingredients
via which we can do
interesting things, as we'll soon see.
>> Now let's look at just the single
vertical bar over here on the right.
If I have a 0 bit and I
OR it with, the bitwise
OR operator, another 0 bit,
that's going to give me 0.
If I take a 0 bit and OR it with
a 1 bit, then I'm going to get 1.
And in fact, just for
clarity, let me go back,
so that my vertical bars
aren't mistaken for 1's.
Let me rewrite all of
my 1's a little more
clearly, so that we next see, if I
have a 1 OR 0, that's going to be a 1,
and if I have a 1 OR 1 that,
too, is going to be a 1.
So you can see logically that the OR
operator behaves very differently.
This gives me 0 OR 0 gives me 0, but
every other combination gives me 1.
So long as I have one 1 in the
formula, the result is going to be 1.
>> By contrast with the AND
operator, the ampersand,
only if I have two 1's in the
equation, do I actually get a 1 out.
Now there's a few other
operators as well.
One of them is a little more involved.
So let me go ahead and erase
this to free up some space.
And let's take a look at the
caret symbol, for just a moment.
This is typically a
character you can type
on your keyboard holding Shift and
then one of the numbers atop your US
keyboard.
>> So this is the exclusive
OR operator, exclusive OR.
So we just saw the OR operator.
This is the exclusive OR operator.
What's actually the difference?
Well let's just look at the formula,
and use this as ingredients ultimately.
0 XOR 0.
I'm going to say is always 0.
That's the definition of XOR.
0 XOR 1 is going to be 1.
1 XOR 0 is going to be 1,
and 1 XOR 1 is going to be?
Wrong?
Or right?
I don't know.
0.
Now what is going on here?
Well think about the
name of this operator.
Exclusive OR, so as the
name, kind of, suggests,
the answer is only going to be
a 1 if the inputs are exclusive,
exclusively different.
So here the inputs are the
same, so the output is 0.
Here the inputs are the
Here are the outputs are different, they
are exclusive, and so the output is 1.
So it's very similar to
AND, it's very similar,
or rather it's very similar to
OR, but only in an exclusive way.
This one is no longer a 1,
because we have two 1's,
and not exclusively, just one of them.
All right.
What about the others?
Well the tilde, meanwhile, is
actually nice and simple, thankfully.
And this is an unary
operator, which means
it's applied to only one input,
one operand, so to speak.
Not to a left and a right.
In other words, if you take tilde of
0, the answer will be the opposite.
And if you take tilde of 1, the
answer there will be the opposite.
So the tilde operator is
a way of negating a bit,
or flipping a bit from
0 to 1, or 1 to 0.
>> And that leaves us finally
with just two final operators,
the so-called left shift, and the
so-called right shift operator.
Let's take a look at how those work.
The left shift operator, written
with two angle brackets like that,
operates as follows.
If my input, or my operand, to the left
shift operator is quite simply a 1.
And I then tell the computer to
left shift that 1, say seven places,
the result is as though I
take that 1, and move it
seven places over to the
left, and by default,
we're going to assume that
the space to the right
is going to be padded with zeros.
In other words, 1 left shift 7 is going
to give me that 1, followed by 1, 2, 3,
4, 5, 6, 7 zeros.
So in a way, it allows you to
take a small number like 1,
and clearly make it much
much, much bigger in this way,
but we're actually going to see
more clever approaches for it
instead, as well,
>> All right.
That's it for week three.
We will see you next time.
This was CS50.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> SPEAKER 1: He was at the snack
bar eating a hot fudge sundae.
He had it all over his face.
He's wearing that chocolate like a beard
SPEAKER 2: What are you doing?
SPEAKER 3: Hmmm?
What?
>> SPEAKER 2: Did you just double dip?
You double dipped the chip.
SPEAKER 3: Excuse me.
SPEAKER 2: You dipped the chip, you
took a bite, and you dipped again.
SPEAKER 3:
SPEAKER 2: So that's like putting
your whole mouth right in the dip.
Next time you take a chip,
just dip it once, and end it.
>> SPEAKER 3: You know what, Dan?
You dip the way that you want to dip.
I'll dip the way that I want to dip.