>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> [CAR DOOR SHUTTING]
>> [CAR ENGINE STARTING]
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> -Moving right along in search
of good times and good news.
With good friends you can't lose.
>> -This could become a habit.
>> -Opportunity knocks Let's
just reach out and grab it.
-Yeah!
-Together we'll nab it.
-We'll hitch hike,
bus, or yellow cab it.
-Dammit.
-We're moving right along.
-Footloose and fancy free.
-Getting there is half the fun.
Come share it with me.
>> -We're moving right along.
>> -We're going to share the load.
>> -We don't need a map to
get this show on the road.
-Hey Fozzy, I want you to turn left
if you come to a fork in the road.
-Yes, sir.
Turn left at the fork in the road.
Turn left.
>> -I don't believe that.
>> -Cruising right along we found
the lights on the highway.
>> -And your way or my way.
>> -So trust my navigation.
>> -Movie stars with flashy cars
and life with the top down.
>> -We're storming the big hills.
>> -Yeah, storm is right.
Should it be snowing?
>> -No, I don't think so.
>> -Moving right along.
>> -Footloose and fancy free.
>> -You're ready for the big time.
>> -Is it ready for me?
>> -Moving right along.
Moving right along.
-I think you better pull over.
-Yes, sir.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: This is CS50.
And this is the end of Week 0, but
the start of a beautiful friendship.
We are so excited to be
here at Yale University
for the very first time with our
friend Scaz, and Jason, and Andy.
All 40 of CS50's TF's
and CA's here at Yale.
And all of you.
And in fact, it's probably time to--
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> So, even though most of the lectures
will indeed be in Cambridge this year,
the reality is that by design, and
very much deliberately in CS50,
I do think we're nearing the point
technologically, and pedagogically,
where it can be a superior educational
experience to engage with some
of the course's material online.
Indeed, the reality-- and if I believe
this philosophically-- is that lectures
are not a particularly
effective means for delivering
fairly complex information.
Certainly over hour
plus long spans of time.
And indeed every few minutes--
I remember myself in college--
you zone out for a moment,
you miss some complex topic,
and you're gone pretty much
for the next 45 minutes.
And the reality is that whether
you're here in New Haven or Cambridge
or beyond, the simplicity of having
the ability to pause and fast forward,
rewind, hyperlink to related
resources, search full text transcripts
and the like is an opportunity that
I dare say for our online students
well beyond New Haven,
offers them an opportunity
to really grasp the
conceptual material that we
introduce in lectures all the better.
>> But ultimately in CS50, is
the students' experience
is characterized so, so much more
by the course's problem sets,
or weekly programming projects, the
course's sections led by the teaching
fellows, the nightly office hours led by
the course assistants and the teaching
fellows, and indeed such
events as CS50 Puzzle
Day, CS50's Hack-a-thon, the CS50
Fair, weekly lunches, and so much more.
And so whether you're here in New
Haven, or tuning in from afar,
today in Cambridge, and
we'll see you again soon,
the reality is this is
one and the same class.
And we are so excited to
be here all together today.
And so at the end of the semester,
whether here or afar, well
hopefully you wear proudly, happily,
and perhaps with a bit of relief,
the shirt that bears witness
to you having taken CS50.
>> So where did we leave off on Wednesday?
We took a look at
computational thinking.
And that's toward what we distilled
computer science unto, at least
for now.
But we distilled it little further into
at least three components elements.
>> Inputs, so what is the
problem we're trying to solve?
Outputs, what is the
answer we're hoping to get?
And the representation there of.
And we won't dwell here on
after on binary, or even ASCII,
and the like so much, but
rather take for granted
that we can represent this information,
because the far more interesting parts
of those problems are not just the
inputs and outputs, but the algorithms
that go into solving those problems.
>> And you might recall from
the other day that we
took a fairly traditional
concept of looking someone up
in a fairly large phone book, or
more generally digitally these days,
just a very large data set.
A really big contacts list, with
lots of names alphabetically sorted.
And we realized that while I
could approach this problem simply
by using a linear
approach-- page by page,
or even two's at a time-- we realized
that the more intuitive algorithm--
just kind of dividing and conquering
the problem again, and again,
and again-- halving it with each
time, gave us this green result.
And it's so much flatter
because it suggests
that even as this problem
gets bigger and bigger,
as is the case these days with data
sets and reality-- Facebook and Google
search results and the
like-- does our algorithm
perform just as effectively
with those bigger bites
as it did even with the smaller bites.
>> Now it begs the question, what
can we actually solve similarly
with this kind of intuition?
This sort of division and conquering?
Well, we could do something
like this today here.
We could take attendance.
So maybe like 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11--
not going to be all that efficient.
So wait, grade school.
2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14,
16, 18 and so forth.
But could we do a little better?
>> I'm pretty sure I can't
do this by myself.
So if you'll humor us for just
a moment, we brought with us
an algorithm that's
just got three steps,
but it does require-- if you
don't mind-- all of us stand up,
if you would.
So, with all of us now standing, step
one of this algorithm is the following.
Stand up and assign
yourself the number 1.
So at this point in time,
literally everyone in this room
hopefully is thinking to themselves,
however awkwardly, the number 1.
>> Now step two of this algorithm is
going to involve the following.
Step two, pair off
with someone standing,
add your numbers together, and
adopt the sum as your new number.
Quick sanity check.
What number is everyone thinking of now?
>> So 2, except maybe for one,
awkward, lonesome person.
If we have an odd number
of people in the room.
So one person might still be
the number 1, that's fine.
But step three here, one
of you should sit down.
The other should go back to step
two, and repeat, if you would.
>> So if still standing, you should be
among those going back to step two.
Keep going.
A few people still standing.
>> So, if still standing,
pair up with someone.
All right, dwindling down.
A few people still standing.
I'll help if need be.
Remember the key takeaway here, is how
much faster this is than me counting.
>> So let's see.
I can help out.
So what number are
you still thinking of?
>> AUDIENCE: I'm at 44.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: 44, so
you go ahead and sit down.
What number are you thinking of?
AUDIENCE: 74.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: 74.
All right, go ahead and sit down.
Who else is still standing?
86.
And is anyone else still standing?
>> What number?
I heard 67.
And then in top?
32.
Anyone else still standing
and thinking of a number?
>> Oh, hi.
Sorry.
Be right back.
42.
Anyone else?
>> AUDIENCE: 47.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: 47.
Is anyone else still standing
who hasn't been counted?
So the final number of people in a room
that has 497 seats is-- all of which
are filled-- is 390.
So this is great.
>> We will soon discuss the notion
of a bug in a computer program.
But we'll come back to that before long.
But in theory, what might
have happened just now?
So even though there were three big
steps to this algorithm, each of those
was just kind of one big operation.
And there was this cyclicity to it
in that if you were still standing,
you kept going from step three to two,
step three to two, step three to two.
>> But what kept happening
on each iteration?
Each cycle of this loop?
What was happening
elsewhere in the room?
Not only the same thing, but what
was happening to half of you?
Sitting down.
And so there in lies this insight,
much like the phone book example,
in that if half of you are
sitting down each time,
the problem is starting
with maybe 400 people,
then to 200 people, than 100 people,
then 50 people, and so forth.
>> And so we whittle down in
theory to just one person,
thinking of the total value of everyone.
Now reality, some social dynamics,
and some arithmetic errors
might contribute to that ultimate bug.
But in theory, while I
was still counting away,
taking several dozen
steps, or hundreds of steps
to count yourselves, to count
a roomful of 500 or so people
should have taken far fewer steps,
because you can only divide 500 and 1/2
so many times.
And so just like with the phone
book example the other day,
did we have something
logarithmic so to speak,
whereby if we were all
operating in unison,
and ignoring the
addition errors, would we
have achieved exactly
that kind of running time?
>> Now to be fair, kind of cheated, in
that I leveraged another resource.
Whereas it's just one of me,
I leveraged hundreds of you.
But that might be said to be an
example of parallel processing,
or a state of art very much in vogue
where computers these days have
multiple CPUs, or more
technically, more multiple cores,
and can truly do multiple
things at once, much like you
all we're doing there, in parallel.
But recall that what we
also did on Wednesday
was try to capture this intuition
and formalize it in code.
Something like pseudo-code.
And in fact, and I hope you'll
forgive, it's like 80 degrees in here.
So I'm going to take this
off for just a little bit.
What I thought we'd do is transition
now to an application whereby
we again engage the audience,
but write a program in English
like syntax, with which to
solve this problem here.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-It's peanut butter jelly time.
Peanut butter jelly time.
>> Way ya!
Way ya!
Now there you go!
There you go!
Peanut butter jelly!
>> Peanut butter jelly!
Peanut, peanut butter jelly!
Peanut butter jelly!
Peanut butter jelly with a baseball bat.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: --that video,
but it is a little addictive,
if not a bit annoying.
But to do this, I thought what we'd
do is try to write a program together,
for which we need three volunteers.
Have to be comfortable
on camera and internet.
Sam, come on up.
Purple shirt, right here, come on up.
>> And from over here, let me
go a little farther back.
Crimson and blue shirts, come on up.
Perfect.
Come on now.
Come on up, come on up.
>> And what's your name?
Erica.
David, nice to meet you.
If you'd like to take this seat here.
This is Sam.
>> What's your name?
Antonio.
Antonio, nice to meet you.
Erica and Sam, if you'd
like to have a seat here.
What we've come prepared with,
as these guys are discovering,
is the ingredients with which to make
a peanut butter and jelly sandwich.
>> Now this might be something that
you take very much for granted.
But we've given each
of our three volunteers
here-- two volunteers and Sam here, a
loaf of bread each, a plate, a knife,
a jar of jelly or jam, and
a jar of peanut butter.
And the goal at hand now is
going to be for these three
to make a peanut butter
and jelly sandwich.
But what we're going to do is expect
the audience-- since all of you
surely know how to do
this so well in reality--
are going to provide us with
the step by step instructions.
The pseudo-code, if you will.
>> So I'll play the role of scribe here.
And I've got a little to-do list,
and so as each of you, one at a time,
calls out a potential
instructional, I'll
write it down, repeat it as needed.
And then you guys are going to make
a peanut butter and jelly sandwich
only by doing what you are told.
So think of yourselves as computers.
>> You can only do what you're told.
No assumptions, no questions.
You just need to do it.
So who would like to hazard the first
instruction for making a PBJ sandwich?
On the balcony there.
>> AUDIENCE: Open the bag of bread.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Open the
bag of bread, if you will.
So let's see.
Let's iterate, and get
a little more precise.
>> Good way to begin though.
Step two, someone else.
Now no one wants to volunteer.
Step two, in front.
AUDIENCE: Open the inner
bag of bread as well.
DAVID J. MALAN: Open the
inner bag of bread as well.
Great, we learning.
A little more precise.
Let's get this working.
Yes, in green shirt.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Slices of bread.
Gently remove two slices of bread.
That's good.
Step four, someone else?
Over here, yes?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Place bread on plate.
Step five?
Step five, yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: On top of-- oh, hand.
Place hand on top of peanut butter.
Is that what I head?
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah, and unscrew.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And-- say it again.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And put the
lid next to the peanut butter.
Lightly place hand on
top of peanut butter,
and unscrew, and put the lid
next to the peanut butter.
OK, step six.
Step six, someone else.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Say it again.
AUDIENCE: Repeat step five again.
DAVID J. MALAN: And
repeat step five again,
which is going to create
a bit of a problem
now if we're doing this step by step.
So now we go back to step five.
Lightly place hand on top
of peanut butter and unscrew
and put lid next to the peanut butter.
Then grasp the peanut butter
and repeat step five again.
>> So we'll override that
infinite loop, if you will.
Step seven, someone else.
Yeah, in back.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: --on top of other.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: On the
other hand on the other top.
Do you want to just come up here?
How do I finish the instruction?
What's the rest of the instruction?
>> AUDIENCE: Ignoring that part.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Ignoring that part.
Let's start over.
Step seven.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Grasp with
opposing hand-- this is good.
This is actually good.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And plastic jar--
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And twist--
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: For two seconds.
Just open the peanut butter jar.
I hope you'll forgive.
So let's assume we got there.
Open the peanut butter jar.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Step eight, let's go.
Step eight, yes, in back.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
Step nine, yes?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: --out of
the peanut butter jar.
And-- and what?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And put knife
back into peanut butter.
Step ten.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Put the knife
out, and then remove the seal.
Nice.
Off the peanut butter.
All right, step 11.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: OK, grey computer
follow blue or red computer.
Good.
>> [APPLAUSE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Bring us home.
Couple more steps.
What's next?
Steps 12.
Step 12.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Put one of the slices of
bread gently on one of your hands.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: One of your hands.
And then, step 13.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: --on slice of bread.
Good.
Pretty good.
Step 14, yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: Undo step 13.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Undo step 13.
Let's move on to jelly.
It's a 100- step program,
but we're were on step 15.
Yeah.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: 7 through 13 using
the jelly, because those went so well.
Repeat steps 7 through
13, using the jelly.
So grasp the lower half of the
jelly jar with one hand on top.
On the other hand of the
other top, ignoring that part,
grasp with opposing hands,
the lid and the plastic jar
at the bottom, and
twist for two seconds.
Then open the jelly jar.
And lastly, let's try to
give us something edible.
Step 16.
So why don't we leave it there.
Thank you so much to
our three volunteers.
[APPLAUSE]
>> We have a little CS50
stress ball for you.
It was going to be a
sandwich but-- so what
was the point, beyond having a
bit of fun with the algorithm?
But the reality is that even when
you're programming a computer,
you need to be super precise.
As complex or intimidating
as your own computer
might very well be to you, at
least when something goes wrong,
the reality is it's a pretty dumb
device that was invented by us humans,
and can only do a subset of what we
do-- sometimes certainly faster--
but it doesn't know how
to make assumptions.
It doesn't know how to be on
the same wavelength as you.
>> It will only do precisely
what you tell it.
And you'll be struck,
perhaps, as we start
writing actual code with the
first problem sets and beyond,
just how easy it is to make
an assumption as a human,
and not anticipate I need to handle
that case, or that corner case,
so to speak, that might very well
arise if for instance Sam had the only
squeezable jar of jelly, whereas
everyone else had some glass jars as
well.
So before we turn our
attention to some actual code,
allow me to introduce the
course's heads here at Yale.
Our friends Scaz, Andy, and
Jason to come up and say hello.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> SCAZ: We've lost Jason temporarily.
Hi again, everyone.
My name is Scaz.
I've been teaching at Yale since 2001.
And when I am not teaching,
my research is in robotics
and artificial intelligence.
>> And the announcement that I have today
is that starting in a couple of weeks,
we're going to be bringing some
supplementary material to CS50 to talk
about intelligence software.
We're going to talk about how
places like Netflix and Hulu
can recommend movies which
you might want to watch.
Where we'll talk about how
driver-less cars actually work.
And we'll be able to ground
these things in the concepts
that you're learning
in this class today.
>> Because all of these things are
built upon the same foundation.
And that's what this
series will explore.
So I'm really looking
forward to seeing more of you
all, and you're going to get to
see more from all of us very soon.
Let me then introduce Jason.
>> JASON: Hi everyone.
My name is Jason.
I unfortunately went to
Harvard as an undergrad.
That's going to get cut
out of the actual stream.
>> And now I'm here as a lecturer in
the computer science department.
And I'm helping run the course
with Scaz, David and Andy.
>> ANDY: Hey guys.
My name's Andy.
I am actually the only Yale
student on the stage right now.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> I'm in Berkeley College,
originally from Solon, Ohio.
And I was one of those kids
where, when I came to Yale,
I really thought that I would never
have to look at a number ever again.
And then I realized that you needed
both science and QR credits to graduate.
And so my freshman spring, I took
a class, a CS, intro CS class here
at Yale.
I was like, this is like
actually pretty cool.
>> And while I actually ended up declaring
as a global affairs major, the skills
I learned in CS and programming
are so applicable to any field
you choose to do.
And the staff here at Yale,
we've been so hard at work
to prepare for you guys.
And we look forward to seeing
all in section and office hours.
So yeah.
>> [APPLAUSE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Thank you.
So just before class began,
we had an opportunity
to walk around campus
with a cellphone and take
some selfies in video form of really
my first tour of Yale's campus here.
And so we thought we'd share a rough
cut of exactly this as Scaz and Andy
and Jason took me around campus.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[SIRENS]
-David.
-Welcome to Yale.
-Good to see you.
-Nice to see you.
-Can we go on a tour?
-Let's go on a tour.
-Road tour.
-This sign has been there for a while.
-Whah, CS50.
>> -Hurry!
Go, go, go, go.
You should [INAUDIBLE] Harkness Tower.
>> -And we saw that a couple times.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> -Look out for the bike!
Ahh!
Hi Frank.
>> -What's up, guys?
-How are you?
-Good to see you.
-Welcome to the video.
Don't act too excited.
>> -I love Silliman.
Ahh!
>> -It's been about three hours since
Jason had ice cream and Nutella.
So we've got to stop back at
Silliman for a little bit.
>> -It's not even [INAUDIBLE]
yet, just the fact
that they have it here is so amazing.
Dude, there's Nutella at every meal.
>> -There was last year too.
>> -Yeah.
>> -tell much about Yale so far.
But I do now that's TD over there.
And that's considered off campus.
>> -Here we have gothic architecture.
World famous.
We have some more gothic architecture.
And construction, and
more gothic architecture.
Hi.
This is where we're having office hours
Tuesdays through Thursdays in Hogwarts,
as [INAUDIBLE] .
-All right.
That's it for the tour.
We are at Yale University's
Law School, where
today's lecture is about to take place.
Let's head in.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: And
that brings us here now.
So thus far, we've been
focusing on pseudocode,
which is this English-like syntax.
It has no prescribed specification.
It's just you use some
intuitive language if you
want to explain what you want to do.
>> But let's begin now to transition
to code, as most people would say.
But more precisely, something
known as source code.
This is the language that humans
write that computers ultimately--
possibly after some number of
steps-- ultimately understands
so as to know how to do something.
That you saw a glimpse of
this perhaps on Wednesday.
>> This is an example that
incredibly, underwhelming
when run simply says "hello world."
And it's written in a language called
C, which is syntactically very similar
to a lot of other languages
that you might not know,
but might have heard of like Java,
and C++, and Python, and Ruby,
and the like, and indeed, we'll
spend much of the semester using C,
and then toward the end of the
semester, building upon it,
and introducing any
number of other languages.
Among them PHP, and JavaScript,
a database language called SQL.
But with C, what we'll have
this bottom-up understanding
of exactly how computers work,
what you can do with them,
and how you can solve problems
all the more effectively by this
layering that we discussed
on Wednesday, and standing
on the shoulders of others.
But more on that to come.
>> Today we look at a simpler environment,
but a fundamentally identical
environment known as Scratch by
our friends at MIT Media Lab.
This is a graphical
programming language, Scratch,
whereby you can drag
and drop things that
look like puzzle pieces that
only interlock if it makes
logical or programmatic sense to do so.
But it's going to allow us to
have a conversation about all
of the same programming
fundamentals that some of you
might know already, that
many of you might not
know anything of without having
to get bogged down frankly,
in the intellectually
uninteresting syntax of semicolons,
and parentheses, and
quotes, and the like.
All of which, early
on, are a distraction
to what are interesting
and genuinely useful ideas.
So let's take a quick
glance at the environment
here, so that you know what awaits.
And in fact, among the games we
can play are a few programs written
by CS50's own former students.
One of them, myself, I'll be this one
written in graduate school for me.
>> If I could take one volunteer
who's willing to play
a game for the very first time.
Sure.
Come on up.
What's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Angela.
DAVID J. MALAN: Angela, come on up.
So Scratch has been out for a few years.
And when I was in graduate school,
I was cross registered at MIT,
taking professor Mitchel Resnick's
course on educational technologies.
And we were among the very first
students in the world to actually beta
test Scratch.
And my project was what Angela
has now graciously volunteered
to play called Oscartime.
>> So I'm going to go ahead and
double click the icon here.
It's going to open up a programming
environment that we'll soon dive into.
I'm going to full-screen
it for Angela, here.
I'm going to hit the green
flag in just a moment.
And then a whole lot of trash
is going to fall from the sky.
And you're going to use the mouse
here to actually drag and drop
the trash into Oscar's trash cans.
So if you want to go ahead and click
the green flag, the game will begin.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> Oh, I love trash.
Anything dirty or dingy or dusty.
Anything ragged or rotten, or rusty.
Yes, I love trash.
If you really want to see
something trashy, look at this.
I have here a sneaker
that's tattered and worn.
It's all full of holes holds
and the laces are torn.
A gift from my mother
the day I was born.
I love it because it's--
DAVID J. MALAN: --green these days just
be throwing everything in the trash.
And so what one of
CS50's own staff did--
Jordan, who you might
meet today-- has actually
updated this for today's times.
And so allow me to open up
a remix instead for Angela.
And we'll play this instead for
a few moments where now you're
going to have to decide between whether
to throw something in the trash,
or recycle it or compost it.
So there's a bit of
pressure on you to get
this right in front of your 392 to
497 classmates here in the hall,
if you would.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
-Oh I love trash.
Anything dirty or dingy or dusty.
Anything ragged or rotten or rusty.
Yes, I love trash.
>> If you really want to see
something trashy, look at this.
I have here a sneaker
that's tattered and worn.
It's all full of holes
and the laces are torn.
A gift from my mother
the day I was born.
I love it because it's trash.
>> Oh, I love trash.
Anything dirty, or dingy, or dusty.
Anything ragged or rotten or rusty.
Yes, I love trash.
Here's some more rotten stuff.
I have here some newspaper--
>> [END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: --are
actually compostable.
But thank you to our volunteer, Angela.
We have a stress ball
for you here as well.
So thank you.
>> So this one was written by me.
But now one by an actual former student
who implemented this, which is a game.
All in this language called
Scratch, that we'll soon
peel back the layers of.
But if we'd like-- how
about another volunteer?
Right.
>> Come on up.
What's your name?
Glance?
Lance.
Lance, come on up.
Nice to meet you.
Come on this way.
So this one might have a
theme familiar to some of you.
But you'll see too that
there can be interactivity,
whereby you could actually be the
role of the character moving around.
Nice to meet you.
David.
>> I give you, Pikachu.
Instructions will about
to come on the screen.
But in short, you're going to
want to catch the tasty stuff,
and avoid the bombs and other things.
With the cursors entirely.
So hit the space bar.
-Pikachu.
DAVID J. MALAN: Catch
the stuff on the left,
don't catch the stuff on the right.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> So one last one here.
If we could have one
more volunteer here.
We thought we'd recreate something
from-- in the yellow shirt--
from Wednesday.
What is your name?
Mary, come on up Mary.
>> And recall on Wednesday we introduced
the notion of binary, and binary bulbs.
This is actually now an
implementation of that same interface
that we had on the iPad with the light
bulbs, but here digitally rendered.
And rather than do a stress
ball-- nice to meet you, David.
We brought a few light
bulbs from Cambridge.
>> If you can, clicking on those
bulbs to turn them on and off,
come up with the binary
representation of say 256.
And you'll see in the
middle, the current tally.
So that one's on.
So the leftmost bit is on.
>> MARY: Yeah, [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Well,
so we have just-- oh.
So this is the 128 column.
So we're up to 128.
We got to get to 256.
And you can tinker on
and off, no big deal.
Or you can hit that 128
more times if you want.
>> All right, good.
24.
Yeah, getting closer.
Closer!
Oh, what's the problem then?
So what's the issue?
>> So what do we need to
solve this problem?
So we need another bit.
And this is perfectly
reasonable in reality, right?
If you want to count from the number
1 to 2 to 3 to 4 to 5, 6, 7, 8, 9
to actually roll over to 10, you're
going to need an additional bit.
So let's actually
rewind here, and come up
with-- that was obviously
meant to be a set up.
>> You can't do 256 with just a bulb.
So how about simply the number 50?
Number 50.
Excellent.
A big round of applause
for Mary and hers as well.
Thank you.
>> So this topic-- intentional as
that was-- will actually recur.
The largest value that you can
represent with eight bits, or one byte,
is indeed 256.
But not if you start
counting from 0, as we
seem to keep doing by having
all of those bits off.
But now let's dive into the underlying
implementation of this environment,
and tease apart some of these ideas.
>> So in a moment we're about to see a
few different programming fundamentals.
The first of which we'll call statement.
Sort of verbs, if you will.
Actions.
Things that should be done.
>> And in a moment you'll see
blocks that look like this.
Say "hello world," for instance.
Or wait one second.
Or play sound meow.
And indeed the environment in
which we're going to be doing this
is called Scratch.
>> And if I pull up Scratch without
preloading any actual code,
let's take a quick look at this
user interface, so to speak.
The controls with which we interact.
On the top left here of the
screen, below the menus,
we have the stage, so to speak.
So Scratch is what we'll call Sprite.
It's a character.
>> And he can be controlled by
writing programs against him.
And he'll be able to move up and down
and left and right in this environment,
not just by moving the
mouse, but programmatically.
I can tell him walk right, walk
left, up, down or the like.
And I can introduce other
sprites or characters as well.
>> Indeed, on the bottom here is where
you'll see your list of sprites.
At the moment, I just have
one, but I can create more,
and they'll appear exactly down there.
So if you rewind for a moment, like
Oscartime-- for instance, Oscar,
on the left, the trash
can, was a sprite.
And the thing in the middle, the
recycling bin, was another sprite.
And the compost bin was another sprite.
And every piece of
garbage or recyclables
that was falling from the sky
is also a sprite, each of which
was programmed individually.
>> How do you program?
Well, over here on the right
hand side is the scripts area.
And this is where we can
drag and drop puzzle pieces.
In a week, it's going to be
where we equivalently write code
with more of a keyboard, but for
today it'll be dragging and dropping
puzzle pieces, the
palettes for which can all
be found here right in the middle.
Indeed, in the middle
here there's a whole bunch
of categories of puzzle
pieces or blocks.
One's related to motion, look,
sound, a pen going up and down,
data, events control.
Not quite sure yet
what all of these mean,
but you'll see that they've
been nicely categorized.
And to write a program in
Scratch, let's do exactly that.
>> I'm going to start off under
Events, and drag this one here.
When green flag clicked.
Now why that one?
Well recall that our volunteers
came up, the first thing I
or they did was click that green
flag in the top right hand corner.
And that just means start the program.
>> So when that event happens,
what do I want to do?
I'm going to go under Looks,
and I'm going to do "say hello."
And I'm going to change this and
say something like "hello Yale."
And now I'm going to zoom
out, click the green flag,
and voila, I've written a program.
It's not all that exciting
just yet, but this
is exactly where each
of those author started,
both with Pikachu, and the
binary bulbs, and Oscartime,
and so many more examples.
>> You start super simple, and
then you start to layer,
and add on features and functionality.
So what are these layers
going to consist of?
Well, beyond statements, we'll also
have things that are little more fancily
called Boolean Expressions,
after someone named Bool.
And a Boolean expression is simply an
expression that's either true or false,
yes or no, 1 or 0.
>> Any polar opposites like that.
It's either true or not.
But we're also going to see
ones that might look like this.
So for instance, is the mouse down?
They're sort of questions, if you will.
>> The mouse is either down,
true or it's not, false.
1 or 0, if you will,
tends to be the mapping.
True is 1, false is 0.
Well what about less than this?
Or so, is this less than this?
That's a question of sorts.
>> And if you put two
numbers in there, either x
is going to be less than y or
equal to y, or greater than y,
but this block we'll see, is just
going to answer the question,
is this less than that?
We might also see something like this.
Touching mouse pointers.
So in Scratch, you can ask
the question, is the Sprite
touching the mouse pointer?
Other words, is the cursor hovering
over the cap, or the equivalent?
>> We'll see anding things together.
You can ask two questions, and
make sure that both of them
give you yes or true answers before
making a decision to do something.
But then how do you make decisions?
Well, we have these conditions.
>> And we saw this in our
example of the phone book.
Looking to the left or
right for Mike Smith.
And in the condition, you
do something potentially,
if a Boolean expression is true.
>> And indeed, notice the shapes now.
There's this placeholder right now
on the overhead where we can fit--
if I rewind one slide-- that shape.
It's not quite the same size.
And indeed, you'll see that
Scratch resizes things dynamically
to fit puzzle pieces, but the
shape is what's important.
This thing looks like
that, and indeed it's
roughly the same shape
that should fit in there.
And if we want to do something
this way or that way, if or else,
we have this puzzle
piece in Scratch as well.
>> Now suppose you wanted to
do if, else if, or else.
In other words, a
three-way fork in the road.
Well what can you do
just by glancing at this?
I can take this puzzle piece,
and it doesn't seem to fit,
but again, Scratch is going
to re-size nicely for us.
I could start to layer
these things together.
>> So now I have a three-way
fork if this is true, do this.
Else if this other thing is true,
go this way, else go this other way.
And in The Muppet Movie, the
fork in the road, so to speak,
between Yale or Stanford, was
exactly that, just two conditions.
Either go this way, else go that way.
>> Well, loops also exist in programming.
And we've used these already in
class and in pseudocode code,
and surely in those
Scratch programs forever.
Scratch has this puzzle piece that
will just let you do something forever.
And sometimes you want
to do something forever.
It's not necessarily a bug, it's
because you want a clock to keep going,
or a game to keep playing.
Or you can specify a finite number of
steps, as with this repeat block here,
which will repeat something 10 times.
We can set variables, we'll soon see.
And with variables, similar in spirit
to algebra, like x, or y, or z.
It's something symbolic that can store
some value, some piece of information,
that you might want
to remember for later.
>> Best example of this might be
a game where you have a score,
like in Pikachu.
How many pieces of cake
and whatnot did you catch?
Well, that might be a variable
called score that starts at 0.
And then every time we caught a
piece of cake or candy, or the like,
it gets incremented.
It gets added to one at a time.
And so a variable stores a
piece of information like that.
Then there's arrays, and we'll come
back to these in a week or two time,
but an array is kind of like an
inventory or a satchel, inside
of which you can put virtual things.
It allows you to store more
than one piece of information.
And that might be useful
if in the game, you're
sort of walking around
picking things up.
And maybe you want to keep
all of those pieces of cake
around, and not just eat
them one after another.
And then there's a
fancier construct we'll
come to called functions or procedures.
And though we're going
faster here, we'll
see that these are a very
natural solution to problems
that we're going encounter.
As our programs start
getting bigger we'll
start to notice patterns in
the code that we're writing,
the puzzle pieces we're
dragging and dropping.
And as soon as you notice yourself doing
something again and again, or worse yet
copying and pasting programming
code that you've written,
that's probably an
opportunity to factor out
whatever you keep copying
and pasting, and putting it
in something called a "function."
But more on those in much
more detail before long.
>> And then there's even fancier features.
For those of you more comfortable,
or taking APCS or equivalent,
Scratch actually supports things
like threads and events and more.
So realize that it has
a fairly high ceiling,
even though it's also very
broadly accessible to folks
who have never programmed before.
So indeed, let's take a look
at a simple program or two.
>> We already looked at how we
might say hello with Scratch.
Let me go ahead and open up a
little more interesting program
that I wrote in advance.
And this one's called Pet the Cat.
All of these programs will be
available on CS50's website.
Indeed, already there.
>> So you can download
them, and play with them,
and with Problem Set 0, which
is also on the course's website,
you're encouraged to walk through these.
And moreover, we have a
number of walk-through videos
online in which I and
CS50's team truly walk
through each of these examples at a much
slower pace, a very fast forwardable,
or rewindable pace, so that you can walk
through these at your leisure as well.
So here's Scratch on the left.
Here's a program at the right
that I've already pre-made.
So let me zoom in on this.
And could someone in English, knowing
what you know, just from now as
to how Scratch works, sort of say
in an English phrase or sentence,
what does this program apparently do?
>> Yeah, in orange shirt.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, if your
cursor is on Scratch the cat,
play a meowing sound.
But notice how we express that.
There's apparently a
loop there, forever.
And then there's a
condition, the if expression.
And collectively, what do those mean?
It means this program
is just always running,
and it's just always waiting
and watching and listening
for me to move my mouse over the cat.
>> Because each time I do that, as
you propose, it's going to do this.
Let me start the program.
Nothing seems to be
happening, but notice how
it's highlighted now in a yellow line.
That just means it's running.
And because there's a forever
loop, it's still running.
>> So let me move my cursor over Scratch.
[MEOW] [MEOW] And if I move it off,
[MEOW] now it stops, but the program's
still running. [MEOW] And so, adorable.
[MEOW] So let's open up
slightly more advanced
example called Don't Pet the Cat.
>> And now let's see what
happens here. [MEOW] Meowing.
So it's a little on
auto pilot, if you will.
--pet the cat.
I wonder why.
[ROAR] [MEOW] So how did this work?
Well, you can kind of reason
through it intuitively, perhaps.
>> But let's look at the actual code.
So again, when the green flag
is clicked, do this forever.
What do you want to do forever?
Well, if touching mouse
pointer, then play
a sound that's apparently called Lion
5, that's inside of this project, else
play sound meow, and
then wait two seconds, so
that it's not meowing incessantly.
In fact, you can very quickly start
to annoy yourself and your roommates.
>> Let's remove this block.
And notice what's nice about Scratch.
Things just kind of drag
and drop and interlock.
So again, it grows to
fill what you want.
But if I remove this, and then
hit play, [COMPUTER BLIP SOUND]
>> --it's kind of tripping over
itself, because it's literally
doing what I'm saying.
It's saying forever play this sound, but
I'm not giving it a chance to finish.
And so that would be a bug.
And that's why we had
this thing in here now.
So let's actually start from scratch--
sort of pun slightly intended--
in which we now have the cat move.
>> So I'm going to do this on the fly.
I'm going to zoom in here, just
to get me started on Events.
And green flag clicked.
And there's other ways
to start the scripts.
We're going to keep it simple here.
>> And now I'm going to go
ahead and go under Control.
And again, if you forget where
things are, just click around,
and eventually you find them again.
So I want to forever do what?
I want to use the motion block
that I know exists, move 10 steps.
>> So let's see what happens
here if I play this game.
Thankfully it doesn't go too far.
I can still kind of grab him
by the tail and pull him back.
But the program's still running,
so he's kind of fighting me.
But it'd be kind of nice if I
conditionally fix this in code.
>> Because this is not--
actually this is really
not a fun game for anyone of any age.
So let's try to fix this by
having some kind of conditions.
So I'm going to go under
Control, and then if.
I like this idea.
So after moving 10 steps,
if-- let me sense where I am.
I'm going to go under Sensing,
and then it looks I can go here.
row to the shape matches.
>> Size doesn't, but it's
going to grow to fill.
And now this is a little menu.
And now mouse pointer-- I don't
want the mouse, I want the edge.
So Scratch is smart enough to know
when a sprite is touching the edge.
What do I want him to actually do?
>> Let me go ahead and change motion.
You know what?
I'm going to have him turn around.
So at 15 degrees isn't
really going to help me.
I want him to turn around
and go the other way.
>> So let's see what happens
here, if I hit Play now.
OK, kind of stupid looking, but
it's doing exactly what I said.
And it's rotating the whole sprite.
Now it turns out I can fix this.
And I didn't know how
to fix this at first.
I kind had to futz around and
see the best way to do this.
But if I go to-- let's see, motion.
Oh, I found this.
Actually, Set Rotation Style.
Left, right, or don't
rotate, or all around.
And it turns out that's what I want.
And I'm going to put this is not my
loop, because I don't need to set
the rotation style multiple times.
I'm going put it at the very top of
this program so that it gets set once,
and then remembers.
And now I'm going to try this again.
Let me stop the program.
>> And now that fixed that bug.
So I'm iteratively improving upon this.
The program is getting a
little more complex and bigger,
but I'm taking baby steps so to speak,
and small bites out of the problem
to get it better and better.
But this too, is kind of lame.
>> You know what?
Would ask someone with a really good,
frightful voice like to come up?
Someone with a voice.
Uh, yeah.
Come on up.
In the green shirt.
>> So it turns out there's some other fun
things, aesthetics and sounds alike.
Here's the meow.
I click on the Sounds tab.
[MEOW] There's the meow. [MEOW] [MEOW]
[MEOW] --actually record something
of our own here.
>> So let's do exactly that.
Instead of using this cat sound, let's
go ahead here, and what's your name?
Nick, nice to meet you.
It's David.
So in a moment, I'm going
to hit the Record button.
And if you can just
yell into the laptop,
"ouch," as though you
just walked into the wall,
that will be much appreciated.
1, 2.
>> NICK: Ouch!
DAVID J. MALAN: Awesome.
And now can do a little editing here.
Going to get rid of the quiet parts.
And I think that's good.
Thank you very much.
>> NICK: Pleasure.
DAVID J. MALAN: I've
just renamed it "ouch,"
but now I'm going to
go back to my scripts.
And notice there is indeed sound here.
And I'm going to go ahead
and play the sound ouch,
and I'm going to do that if
it's touching the edges only.
And then I'm going to
have it turn around.
So let's see what happens here.
Let's go full screen.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-Ouch!
Ouch!
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> DAVID J. MALAN: So you realize
that we're getting a little lucky.
I'm going to have him move
like 100 steps at a time.
The effect of which now is going
to be-- [COMPUTER GLITCH SOUND] So
within reason.
So an opportunity to refine that
further if we really want to.
>> So now let's introduce another concept.
To let me go into one called
Counting Sheep and use something
called a variable.
This is an adorable little sheep, and
I changed his costume so to speak.
So even though the default is a
cat, you can upload, you can draw,
you can do any number of
characters on your sprite.
Here's a program that's
going to do what in English?
>> Based again on just what you know now.
What's this program do?
Yeah, it's going to count.
One number at a time.
We have apparently
have this set counter.
>> I don't know what that is,
but maybe it's a variable.
It's just a container, x or y.
But the word counter is more
descriptive than mathematician's x or y.
So we can use English words for things.
Forever, just means keep doing this.
>> Say counter.
Now where did this come from?
Well, it turns out that
counter is a variable.
So it's just another puzzle
piece I created in advance.
And even though it happens
not to be the same shape here,
normally you would say
something like hello here.
>> You can also drag a variable
so that that's what's get said.
Then I wait for a second, I
change the counter by one,
incrementing it by adding one.
So that the net effect is
this adorable counting sheep.
Though he's counting himself.
Now it's very quickly
going to get boring
because he's going to
do this truly forever,
but that's exactly what the
program's design prescribes.
Lets now try another example
that leverages a variable.
This one called Hi Hi Hi, that
does get annoying quickly.
Now this one has two scripts.
And so again, we're taking baby steps.
>> We started with something super
small, added to it, added to it.
Now I want to do something
even more dynamic,
so I want to be listening for
two different things at a time.
So on the left, when
green flag is clicked,
I set a variable that I wrote
in advance called Muted.
And I arbitrarily set it to 0.
So Scratch doesn't have true and
false, but it does have 0 and 1.
>> So I can approximate that same idea.
And then forever, if the space bar is
pressed, then set the variable to 0.
Or sorry.
If the Space is pressed, and
if muted, the variable, is 0,
then set muted to 1,
else set muted to 0.
This seems sort of like we're
just doing and undoing work.
>> But what's the effect?
Every time I hit the space bar,
what happens to my variable
called muted, logically?
Sort of gets flipped.
It changes from 0 to 1, or 1 to 0.
So it took a few blocks
to express that, but all
I'm doing is toggling the state of
this variable to 0 or 1, or 0 or 1
each time I hit the space bar.
Now over here, what's this doing?
Forever, if muted is 0,
so if muted is false.
So if it's not muted, is the
semantics there, play sound sea lion,
and think Hi Hi Hi for two
seconds, wait two seconds.
So notice now these
scripts are effectively
going to run in parallel so that one can
be listening for one action, the other
to make a decision based on that action.
And it can do this forever.
>> [SEA LION BARKING]
>> It's going to do this forever and
[SEA LION BARKING] as I've just done.
And now it's still running
but I've "muted" the game.
[SEA LION BARKING] And that's
all this guy does now too.
>> Let's open another example here.
Let me go into Events,
and now this adorable too.
But notice it has two sprites.
So not just two scripts with
one sprite, but two sprites.
And if I click on the blue guy as I
already have, I see he as one program
up here that literally just says
this, when I receive an event,
say "Polo" for two seconds.
>> So if you've ever played in
a pool, the game Marco Polo,
if the orange guy script is
any indication, apparently
every time I hit the space bar,
what's the orange guy going to do?
He's going to say "Marco."
And then this is a new block.
We've not seen this before,
but broadcast an event.
And I could call it
event anything we want.
>> We'll come back to this
perhaps before long.
But broadcasting an event
is a way for one sprite
to talk to another by
essentially passing it a message.
It's not a message you see.
It's not something visual.
It's sort of a computer message
that the other guy is listening for.
Because indeed, the blue guy, recall
doesn't have when green flag clicked.
>> He instead has, when I receive an event.
When he gets handed this note in class,
so to speak, he should say "Polo."
And so the net effect is that when I
hit the green flag, nothing happens.
But when I hit the space bar, he says
"Marco," he responds with "Polo."
But the only sprite I'm
interacting with is the orange one.
So this is a way of kind of
passing messages between sprites
and having them communicate
with one another.
>> Now let's look at one last
one here called Threads.
And notice this by playing it.
So these are two sprites.
The bird is kind of flying around.
He's bouncing.
There's no "ouch," but same idea.
>> But the cat seems pretty smart.
What is the cat apparently doing?
And wait for it.
It's not just bouncing.
>> He's following the bird.
And so apparently, there's a way
with a combination of blocks here--
and let's look at the cat real fast.
Forever, if touching bird, then play
the sound Lion 4, whatever that is.
We heard it once.
Otherwise, point towards
bird, and move one step.
Now the fact that it's one
step is what gives the bird
a bit of an advantage
initially, but if we instead
make this 10, for instance, so
that every iteration of loop he's
moving 10 steps of time.
So more space.
Let's see what happens then.
[LION ROAR] Not all that much better.
So now let's try to improve
upon these a little iteratively,
and come back to that
notion of a function.
>> And indeed one of the fundamental
takeaways of the class design.
Not just writing programs that work
and that are correct, but are well
designed.
And design is much more subjective,
and you'll get better at it over time.
But let's take some baby steps toward
starting with a program that works,
absolutely, but it's not very good.
It's not very well written.
>> So here's a program that does this.
Cough, cough, cough.
What does the program look like?
Looks correct to me.
It's saying couch for a
second, then it waits.
>> Then it says it again, then it waits.
Then it says it again, then it waits.
And then the program implicitly
ends, because there's no loop.
But why is this a badly written program?
Even if you've never programmed before?
Like, what rubs the
wrong way, perhaps here?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
You're repeating
yourself again and again.
And literally, I copied and pasted
two of those blocks again and again.
And that's exactly the sort of sanity
check that you should be making.
Wait a minute.
Should I really be doing this?
So what's this what's the
obvious solution perhaps?
Have some kind of loop.
And I don't quite recall
what the puzzle piece is,
but if I look at the
next iteration here,
indeed, there's not
just the forever loop,
there's repeat some number of times.
And so I've specified three.
And now notice how much tighter, how
much more succinct this program is.
And in a sense, how
much more maintainable.
If I want to change the word
from cough to something else,
like achoo, like he's sneezing.
Then I change it in one
place, and not three.
So this already feels like
slightly better design.
Let me instead open cough
2, our third example.
>> Notice as a computer scientist,
I start counting at 0, typically.
Now this looks a little scarier at
first, but the effect is the same.
Cough, cough, cough.
But what seems to be fundamentally
new in the top part of the program?
I've removed the say.
>> I've removed the wait.
And what have I plugged in instead?
A function.
A cough block.
I mean, frankly, I seem kind
of an idiot if I didn't just
start with the block
that's apparently called
"cough," if that's all I want him do.
But that doesn't exist in Scratch.
Rather I went to one in the
palette called More Blocks here,
and I drag this big purple thing
here that lets me define a function.
It essentially lets me
create my own puzzle
piece that can be called anything I
want, that can do anything I want,
but it gives it a name.
It gives me a new, purple puzzle piece
that now does whatever I tell it to do.
So this purple piece here
corresponds to this one here.
>> And what does it do?
It says cough for a
second, and then it waits.
And now I've sort of created
my own custom puzzle piece,
so that it behaves
exactly that same way.
So I can keep doing this.
And indeed, there's going to be more and
more opportunities for modularization,
and for layering, complexity
on top of one another.
But this basic idea,
indeed in problem said 0.
What you're going to
be challenged to do is
to download Scratch, or just use it
on the web, and just have fun with it.
We'll give you a set of
requirements, having a sound,
and some number of puzzle pieces.
But you'll do exactly this.
And you'll realize that you're going to
want to take some baby steps initially,
until your program gets
more and more complex.
But considering is this the
best way I could do this?
Can I avoid this instinct
perhaps, to copy and paste?
>> But before Problem Set
0, and before we adjourn,
thought we'd take up one
more volunteer if we could,
for a final program
that's perhaps the most
fitting at all, given today's venue.
Come on down.
Yeah.
Yes.
What's your name?
Uh-oh.
That's OK.
Both come down.
And I've will deal with this somehow
within that next ten seconds.
So come on down.
Come on down.
>> Let me come on up here.
Come on.
All right.
Let's see here.
So notice real fast here,
if you'd like to come on up.
>> We'll do two rounds of this.
And what's your name?
>> SABRINA: Sabrina.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Sabrina and?
>> YING GEE: Ying Gee.
>> DAVID J. MALAN: Ying Gee.
Nice to meet you both.
David.
So our final example here is
called Ivy's Hardest Game.
And why don't we have you do
Level 1, and you do Level 2.
>> And we'll see how far
beyond that we actually go.
Written by a student
last year, remixed by me
so that this would go
over well in New Haven.
And I give you a game that's going to
involve moving the arrows up and down,
and getting Yale to the finish line.
Here we go.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> [MUSIC -- NFL ON FOX THEME SONG]
[MUSIC -- MC HAMMER, "U CAN'T TOUCH
THIS"]
>> -U can't touch this.
U can't touch this.
Can't touch this.
My, my, my, my music hits me so
hard, makes me say, oh, my lord.
Thank you for blessing me with a
mind to rhyme and two hype feet.
>> That's good when you know you're down.
A super dope homeboy from the Oaktown.
And I'm known as such and this
a beat uh, you can't touch.
I told you homeboy U can't touch this.
Yeah, that's how we're living
and you know U can't touch this.
>> Look in my eyes, man.
U can't touch this.
Yo, let me bust the funky lyrics.
Fresh new kicks and pants.
>> You got it like that and
you know you wanna dance.
So move out of your seat and get
a fly girl and catch this beat.
While it's rolling hold on pump a little
bit and let them know what's going on.
Like that.
>> Cold on a mission so pull on back.
Let them know that you're too much
and this is a move uh you can't touch.
Yo, I told you U can't touch this.
Why you standing there man?
U can't touch this.
>> Yo, sound the bell school's in, sucker.
Give me a song, a rhythm making them
sweat that's what I'm giving them now.
They know when you talk about the Hammer
you talk about a show that's hyped.
And tight singers are
sweating so pass them a mic.
>> Or a tape to learn what
it's going to take and now
he's going to burn the charts.
Legit either work hard or
you might as well quit.
Because you know U can't touch this.
U can't touch this.
Break it down.
Stop.
Hammer time.
Go with the flow in a spin
if you can't move to this
then you probably are dead.
So wave your hands in
the air [INAUDIBLE]
>> This is it for a winner dance to
this and you're going to get thinner.
Move slide your rump just for
a minute let's all do the bump.
Yeah.
U can't touch this.
>> U can't touch this.
You better get hyped
boy U can't touch this.
Ring the bell school's back in.
Break it down.
Stop.
Hammer time
>> DAVID J. MALAN: That's it for CS50!
Thanks so much for joining us!
See you outside.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC -- "SEINFELD" THEME SONG]
-Hey David.
-Hey, David.
How's it going?
>> -Good job, today.
-So have you thought about what
you're going to do for the out jokes?
-No, I got nothing.
-What if-- what if this is the out joke?
-Like, unpacking carts?
-Uh-huh.
You know, it's about nothing.
>> -So like, no story, no
conflict, no resolution.
I don't understand.
What's it about then?
>> -Nothing.
>> -So we have out joke is about
nothing, and we have no actors.
Who's going to be in this?
>> -No, no, no.
I mean, I'll be in it.
>> -You'll be in it?
-Yeah!
People are always telling
me I'm a character.
>> -Well, I mean, it's true.
But who else is going to be in it?
It can't just be you.
>> -You will be in it, Gavin, Dan,
Dan, Colton, Z'Myla, Alysse, Doug,
David, everybody.
>> -So it's about nothing,
and everybody's in it?
>> -Absolutely nothing.
>> -This is ridiculous.