>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
>> DAVID MALAN: This is CS50.
This is the end of week 10.
And boy, do we have a
good class for you today.
We are so excited to invite two of
our friends from Yale up to us today
and to look at the intersection of
artificial intelligence, robotics,
natural language processing, and more.
>> And indeed, over the
past few weeks, we've
certainly spent a lot of time,
especially in the earlier psets,
focusing on pretty low-level details.
And it's very easy to lose sight
of the forest for the trees
and get hung up on loops and conditions
and pointers, certainly, and the like.
But the reality is you guys now have the
ingredients with which you can really
solve some interesting problems, among
them those that our friends at Yale
work on just shy of Cambridge.
>> So allow me first to introduce our head
teaching assistant from Yale, Andy.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> ANDY: First of all, just thank
you for allowing a couple Yalies
to pop on down to Cambridge today.
We really appreciate it.
Secondly, to our friends
back home-- Jason,
thanks for staying and running lecture.
Hope it's all good in New Haven.
>> So yeah, I'm super excited
to introduce Scaz today.
Scaz runs the robotics lab.
He's a professor of, like, five
different departments at Yale.
In his lab, he has many, many
robots that he likes to play with.
He has, like, the
coolest job in the world.
And he gets to kind of mess
around with that all day
long and do some work, as well.
>> And so we actually brought one
of them down with us today.
So without further ado, Scaz is
going to go ahead and introduce us
to his robot friend.
>> [APPLAUSE]
BRIAN SCASSELLATI: Thanks, David.
Thanks, Andy.
It is so wonderful to be
here with everyone today.
I want to first be very clear that
the CS50 staff here in Cambridge
has been incredibly hospitable to us.
We are so thankful for everything
they've done to support us.
And so we'd like to be able
to return the kindness.
>> So today, we get to announce
that we're going to have a new,
one-of-a-kind CS50 event
happening in New Haven next week.
And this is the CS50 Research Expo.
So we're going to be inviting
everyone-- CS50 students,
staff from both Harvard and Yale-- to
come down and visit with us on Friday.
We'll have a wide variety of over
30 different people presenting
and exhibiting-- upperclassmen showing
off some of their research products.
We'll have some startups, even, looking
for a little bit of new tech talent,
startups from both Harvard and Yale.
And we'll have some student groups
looking for some new membership.
>> It's going to be a very exciting time.
Hopefully those of you who are
coming down for the Harvard-Yale game
will be able to stop
by a little bit early,
right in the center of campus,
Sterling Memorial Library.
We're going to have a set of
exhibits that range from autonomous
sailboats to ways of using software
to preserve medieval manuscripts.
>> We're going to have ad
hoc networking and people
teaching software coding in Cape Town.
We'll have computer
music demonstrations.
And we'll of course have more robots.
So we do hope you'll
join us for this event.
It should be a lot of
fun, a little bit of food,
and a lot of interesting
things to talk about.
>> So today, we're going to talk
about natural language processing.
And this is the attempt for us
to build a new way of interfacing
with our devices because
for the last few weeks,
you've been focused on how it is that
you can write code, write software
that is a way of being able to say to a
machine, this is what I want you to do.
>> But we shouldn't need to
expect that everything
that's out there that's used
by everyone in the world
is going to be proficient
in this kind of instruction.
So we distinguish between computer
languages and natural languages--
that is, things that humans use
to communicate with other humans.
And we try to build interfaces that use
these natural communication mechanisms.
>> Now, just like every other topic
that we've started with in CS50,
we're going to start with the simplest
bit of natural language processing
that we can imagine.
We're going to start with the
historical part of natural language.
And then we'll build up to
more and more recent systems
and have some fun demos along the way.
>> So we're going to start with what was
probably the first natural language
processing system.
This was a software system written in
1966 by Joseph Weizenbaum called ELIZA.
And ELIZA was designed to
replicate the kind of interaction
you would have with a
Rogerian psychotherapist.
Now, the Rogerians, they had
an idea that psychotherapy
involved being able to mirror back
to a patient and talk to them,
basically, by only giving them a
tiny little bit of the therapist.
That is, everything
that the therapist said
was supposed to be just a reflection of
what the patient was telling to them.
>> So let's try and demo this.
Do we have a volunteer who'd be
willing to share their deepest,
darkest, and/or fake secrets with ELIZA?
Sure, why don't you come on up.
Fantastic.
And your name?
>> MILES: Miles.
>> BRIAN SCASSELLATI: Miles.
Nice to meet you, Miles.
If you would hold onto that.
And we're going to
use a version of ELIZA
that we've replicated
within the CS50 IDE.
And we'll look at the source
code to this in a little while.
But for right now, we're just
going to invoke it by typing eliza.
>> And ELIZA is going to give you responses
that are going to be in all capitals.
And going to ask you some questions.
And we'll respond and type
in responses to ELIZA.
So ELIZA has said, "Hi, I'm ELIZA.
What's your problem?"
What would you like to
tell ELIZA about today?
>> MILES: I can only fall asleep
if I have bunny slippers on.
>> BRIAN SCASSELLATI: All right.
All right.
>> [LAUGHTER]
>> "I can only fall asleep
with bunny slippers on."
And ELIZA says, "Say, do you
have any psychological problems?
Maybe this is a good indicator."
>> OK.
So what would you like to respond?
>> MILES: Yes.
>> BRIAN SCASSELLATI: Yes.
Man of many words.
I enjoy that.
Eliza says, "You seem quite positive."
>> MILES: No, I am, in fact, an electron.
>> BRIAN SCASSELLATI: "No.
In fact, I am an electron."
"Did you come to me
because you are an electron?"
Now, we can see some of
the things-- I'm going
to pause you for just a second, Miles.
Don't go anywhere.
We're not done with you yet.
ELIZA is, in some ways,
responding to certain things
that he's saying but without
any real understanding.
And it's also parroting back some
of the parts of his sentence.
>> So we said, "No.
In fact, I am an electron."
Eliza responded back, "Did you come
to me because you are an electron?"
All right.
Let's give it one more response here.
Give it a good one, Miles.
>> MILES: Good one?
>> Yes, please help me.
BRIAN SCASSELLATI: "Yes.
Please help me." "Are you sure?"
MILES: No.
BRIAN SCASSELLATI: No.
"What does that suggest to you?"
>> MILES: I may not be an electron.
>> BRIAN SCASSELLATI: "I
may not be an electron."
"Are you saying no just to be negative?"
>> All right.
So Miles, thank you so much.
>> MILES: Thank you.
>> BRIAN SCASSELLATI: Thanks very much.
[APPLAUSE]
>> So this ELIZA program, in many ways,
is responding just to the pieces
that we're providing without any deep
understanding of what's happening here.
This is a kind of system
called pattern matching, where
we're looking for certain
bits of text that we're then
going to take out of what
was provided as input,
convert it, potentially, in some way,
and then give it back to the user.
>> Do any of you think
that ELIZA is actually
performing valid psychoanalysis here?
One person, maybe.
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
BRIAN SCASSELLATI: And how
does that make you feel?
Yes, in fact, it does.
And we're going to see, actually, the
source code for it in just a moment.
And so you're going to be
able to do exactly this.
>> Now, ELIZA is one form of what
we would call today a chat bot.
It just goes through the
text that you're providing,
provides the bare minimum amount
of understanding or processing,
and then parrots it back to you.
So let's take a look,
conceptually, and talk about what
it is that ELIZA is actually doing.
>> ELIZA is taking a sentence-- let's
say, "I want to impress my boss."
And ELIZA is looking
through that sentence
and trying to find and
match certain patterns.
So, for example, one of the patterns
that ELIZA is looking for are the words
"I want."
And any time it sees something
that has "I want" in it,
it formulates a response.
And that response is a fixed string.
In this case, it's "why do you want?"
And I put a little star at
the end because that's just
the beginning of our response.
And the star indicates that
we're going to take the rest
of the user's utterance--
"to impress my boss"--
and we're going to append that
onto the end of this string.
>> So now, rather than saying, "why
do you want to impress my boss,"
there's a little bit of additional
processing that we'll do.
That is, we'll have to
convert some of the pronouns
here from "my boss" to "your boss."
And there might be a few other
changes that we need to make.
So rather than just sticking it
directly onto the end, what we'll do
is we'll take the rest of the
user's utterance-- in white here--
and we'll take it one piece at
a time and convert each string
token, each word, into the sentence.
>> So we'll take the word "to."
There's no conversion
that we need to do that.
"Impress."
There's no conversion
we need to do there.
"My" will convert to "your."
And "boss" we'll just leave as "boss."
And then finally, anything
that ends with a period,
we'll convert it into a question.
>> This very simple pattern matching
is actually quite successful.
And when this was introduced
in 1966-- Joseph Weizenbaum
programmed this on a computer.
Now, computers at that time
weren't desktop models.
They were shared resources.
And his students would
go and chat with ELIZA.
Eventually, he had to
restrict access to it
because his students weren't
getting any work done.
They were just chatting with ELIZA.
And, in fact, he had to
fire his assistant, who
spent all of her time talking to ELIZA
about her deep and worrisome problems.
>> Everyone who used these systems
started to anthropomorphize them.
They started to think of them as
being animate and real people.
They started to recognize some of
the things that they were saying
were coming back to them.
And they were finding out
things about themselves.
And, in fact, even the experts,
even the psychotherapists,
started to worry that, in fact,
maybe ELIZA would be replacing them.
And even the computer
scientists worried that we were
so close to solving natural language.
>> Now, that wasn't anywhere close to true.
But that's how impressive
these systems can seem.
So let's start to look
underneath and try
to get a little bit of a question
of where this code actually happens.
So we'll make this code
available afterwards.
And this is a very
simple and direct port
of the original ELIZA implementation.
>> So some of these stylistic
things that you'll see here
are not stylistically what
we would want you to do
or what we've been teaching you to do.
But we've tried to keep them
the same across the many ports
that this has had so that it
has the flavor of the original.
So we're going to include
a bunch of things,
and then we'll have a
set of keywords, things
that ELIZA will recognize
and respond to directly.
So if you have words like
"can you" or "I don't" or "no"
or "yes" or "dream"
or "hello," then ELIZA
will respond selectively to those.
We'll also have a
certain number of things
that we will swap, like
converting "my" to "your."
>> And then we'll have a set of responses
that for each of these keywords,
we'll rotate through
these different responses.
So if I say "yes"
three times in a row, I
might get three different
responses from ELIZA.
Our code, then, is
actually remarkably simple.
If I scroll down past all of these
responses that we have programmed in
and we get down to our main,
we're going to initialize
a couple of different variables
and do a little bit of housekeeping
in the beginning.
But then there's absolutely a set
of code that you can understand.
One big while loop that says I'm
going to repeat this over and over.
I'll read in a line, and I'll
store that in an input string.
I'll check and see if it's the
special keyword "bye," which
means exit the program.
And then I'll check and see whether
somebody is just repeating themselves
over and over.
And I'll yell at them if they do.
I'll say "don't repeat yourself."
>> As long as none of those happen, we'll
then scan through and loop through,
on lines 308 to 313
here, and check and see
are any of those keyword
phrases contained in the input
that I was just given?
If there is a match for them, well
then, I'll remember that location.
I'll remember that keyword.
And I'll be able to build a response.
>> If I don't find one, well then,
the last thing in my keyword array
will be my default responses,
when nothing else matches.
I'll ask questions like "Why did you
come here?" or "How can I help you?"
that are just partially appropriate
no matter what the input is.
>> We'll then build up ELIZA's response.
We'll be able to take
that base response,
just as we did in that
"my boss" example.
If that's all that there
is-- if it's just one
string that I'm supposed to respond--
I can just send it back out.
If it has an asterisk at
the end of it, then I'll
process each individual token in
the rest of the user's response
and add those in, swapping out
word for word as I need to.
>> All of this is absolutely
something that you could build.
And in fact, the ways in which we
have processed command line arguments,
the way in which you have
processed through HTTP requests
follow the same kinds of rules.
They're pattern matching.
>> So ELIZA had a relatively important
impact on natural language
because it made it seem like it was a
very attainable goal, like somehow we'd
be able to solve this problem directly.
Now, that's not to say that ELIZA does
everything that we would want to do.
Certainly not.
But we should be able
to do something more.
>> Our first step to go
beyond ELIZA is going
to be able to look at
not text being entered
into the keyboard but speech, actual
speech recorded into a microphone.
So as we look at these
different pieces, we're
going to have to build a set of models.
We're going to have to be able
to go from the low-level acoustic
information-- pitch,
amplitude, frequency--
and convert that into
some units that we're
able to more easily manipulate
and, finally, manipulate them
into words and sentences.
>> So most speech recognition
systems that are out there today
follow a statistical
model in which we build
three separate representations of what
that audio signal actually contains.
We start with a phonetic model
that talks about just the base
sounds that I'm producing.
Am I producing something that is
a B as in boy or a D as in dog?
How do I recognize those two different
phones as separate and distinct?
>> On top of that, we'll then build
a word pronunciation model,
something that links together
those individual phones
and combines them into a word.
And after that, we'll take the words
and we'll assemble them with a language
model into a complete sentence.
>> Now, we're going to talk about each
of these independently and separately.
But these three models are all
just going to be statistics.
And that means when we
work with them, we'll
be able to work with
them all simultaneously.
All right.
Let's start with our phonetic model.
So phonetic models rely on
a computational technique
called hidden Markov models.
These are graphical models in which I
have and recognize a state of the world
as being characterized
by a set of features.
And that state describes one part
of an action that I'm engaged in.
>> So if I think about making
the sound "ma" like mother,
there are different
components to that sound.
There's a part where I draw in breath.
And then I purse my lips.
And I roll my lips back a little
bit to make that "ma" sound.
And then there's a release.
My lips come apart.
Air is expelled.
"Ma."
>> Those three different parts would be
represented by states in this graph--
the onset, the middle, and the end.
And I would have transitions that
allowed me to travel from one state
to the next with a certain probability.
So, for example, that M
sound might have a very,
very short intake at the beginning--
"mm"-- and then a longer,
vibratory phase where I'm holding my
lips together and almost humming--
"mmmm"-- and then a very short
plosive where I expel breath-- "ma."
>> The hidden Markov model is
designed to capture the fact
that the way that I make
that sound "ma" is going
to be slightly different in
its timing, is frequency,
and its features than
the way that you make it
or the way that I might
make it when I'm talking
about different uses of the letter.
"Mother" and "may I" will
sound slightly differently.
>> So to recognize a
particular sound, we would
build Markov models, these hidden Markov
models, of every possible phone that I
might want to recognize,
every possible sound,
and then look at the
acoustic data that I have
and determine statistically
which one is the most likely one
to have produced this sound.
OK.
With that model, we then
start to build on top of it.
We take a pronunciation model.
Now, sometimes pronunciation
models are simple and easy
because there's only one
way to pronounce something.
Other times, they're a
little bit more complicated.
Here's a pronunciation guide
for that red thing that is
a fruit that you make ketchup out of.
People don't think it's a fruit.
Right?
>> Now, there are many different ways
that people will pronounce this word.
Some will say "toe-may-toe."
Some will say "toe-mah-toe."
And we can capture that with
one of these graphical models
where, again, we represent transitions
as having a certain probability
and associated probability with them.
>> So in this case, if I were to follow
the top route through this entire graph,
I would be starting at the letter
on the far left, the "ta" sound.
I would take the top half,
the "oh," and then a "ma,"
and then an "a," and then a
"ta," and an "oh." "Toe-may-toe."
If I took the bottom path through
this, I will get "ta-mah-toe."
And if I went down and then
up, I would get "ta-may-toe."
>> These models capture these
differences because whenever
we deploy one of these
recognition systems,
it's going to have to work with
lots of different kind of people,
lots of different accents, and even
different uses of the same words.
Finally, on top of that,
we'll build something
that looks really complicated,
called the language model,
but in fact is the simplest of
the three because these operate
on what are called n-gram models.
And in this case, I'm showing you
a two-part n-gram model, a bigram.
We're going to make physical the idea
that sometimes, certain words are
more likely to follow a
given word than others.
If I just said "weather forecast,"
the next word could likely be "today"
or could be "the weather
forecast tomorrow."
But it's unlikely to be "the
weather forecast artichoke."
>> What a language model does is
it captures those statistically
by counting, from some very large
corpus, all of the instances
in which one word follows another.
So if I take a large corpus--
like every Wall Street Journal
that has been produced since 1930,
which is one of the standard corpuses--
and I look through all
that text, and I count
up how many times after
"forecast" do I see "today"
and how many times do I see
"forecast" followed by "artichoke,"
the first one is going
to be much more likely.
It's going to appear
far more frequently.
And so it'll have a higher
probability associated with it.
>> If I want to figure out the
probability of an entire utterance,
then, I just break it up.
So the probability of hearing
the sentence "the rat ate cheese"
is the probability of the word
"the" starting a sentence,
and then the probability that the
word "rat" follows the word "the,"
and the probability that the
word "ate" follows "rat,"
and the probability that
"cheese" follows "ate."
>> This sounds like a lot of
statistics, a lot of probabilities.
And that's all that it is.
But the amazing thing is if you do this
with a large enough sample of data,
it works.
And it works tremendously well.
We all know these technologies.
Most operating systems come with
voice recognition at this point.
We use Siri and Cortana and Echo.
And these things are based upon
this type of three-layer model--
a phonetic model at the bottom, a
pronunciation model in the middle,
and a language model on top of them.
>> Now, they have to do a little bit more
than that in order to answer questions.
But the recognition of what you're
saying depends exactly on that.
So let's take an example here.
So I have my phone sitting up here
underneath the document camera.
And we're going to asks
Siri a few questions.
All right?
>> So let's wake up my phone here.
Siri, what is the weather
like in New Haven today?
>> SIRI: Here's the weather for
New Haven, Connecticut today.
>> BRIAN SCASSELLATI: OK.
So first you saw that Siri recognized
each of the individual words
and then produced a response.
We'll talk about how that response
comes about in a little bit.
But now that we know
that this is just based
on the raw statistics and this
pattern matching type of approach,
we can play some games with Siri.
>> So I can try again.
Siri, what is the weather
hippopotamus New Haven, today?
>> SIRI: OK.
Here's the weather for New
Haven, Connecticut for today.
BRIAN SCASSELLATI: Siri's
not daunted by that
because it's found the pattern--
"weather," "today," "New Haven."
That's what it's responding
to, just like ELIZA.
All right.
Let's give it one more even
more ridiculous example.
Siri, weather artichoke
armadillo hippopotamus New Haven?
>> SIRI: Let me check on that.
Here's what I found on the web
for what are artichokes armadillo
hippopotamus New Haven.
>> BRIAN SCASSELLATI: OK.
So if I go far enough
away from this model,
I'm able to confuse it because it no
longer matches the pattern that it has.
And that statistical
engine that's saying,
what's the likelihood that you've got
the words hippopotamus and artichoke
together, and armadillo?
That's got to be something new.
>> So these technologies we use every day.
If we want to take them one step
further, though, if we actually
want to be able to talk about what it
is that these systems are responding to,
we have to talk, again, about a
more fundamental set of questions.
And that's a topic in communication
that we call question answering.
That is, we want to be able to-- yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
BRIAN SCASSELLATI: Do we get
into latent semantic processing?
So yes.
There are a lot of things that are
happening below the surface with Siri
and in some of the examples
I'm going to show you next
where there is quite a bit
in terms of the structure
of what you're saying that's important.
And, in fact, that's a great
precursor for the next slide for me.
>> So in the same way that our
speech recognition was built up
of multiple layers, if we want to
understand what it is that's actually
being said, we're going to again
rely on a multi-layer analysis
of the text that's being recognized.
So when Siri is actually able to
say, look I found these words.
Now what do I do with them?
The first component is often to
go through and try to analyze
the structure of the sentence.
And in what we've seen
in grade school, often,
as sort of diagramming
sentences, we're going
to recognize that certain
words have certain roles.
These are nouns.
These are pronouns.
These are verbs.
And we're going to recognize
that for a particular grammar,
in this case English grammar, there are
valid ways in which I can combine them
and other ways that are not valid.
>> That recognition, that structure,
might be enough to help guide us
a little bit.
But it's not quite enough
for us to be able to give
any meaning to what's being said here.
To do that, we'll have to rely on
some amount of semantic processing.
That is, we're going to have to look
at underneath what each of these words
actually carries as a meaning.
And in the simplest way of doing this,
we're going to associate with each word
that we know a certain function,
a certain transformation that it
allows to happen.
>> In this case, we might label the
word "John" as being a proper name,
that it carries with it an identity.
And we might label
"Mary" as the same way.
Whereas a verb like "loves," that
constitutes a particular relationship
that we're able to represent.
Now, that doesn't mean
that we understand
what love is but only that we understand
it in the way of a symbolic system.
That is, we can label
it and manipulate it.
>> With each of these types of approaches,
any type of semantic processing
here is going to require a little
bit of knowledge and a lot of work
on our part.
We're no longer in the realm
where just plain statistics
are going to be enough for us.
Now, in order to go
from this point to being
able to talk about the inside of
what's actually happening here,
to being able to manipulate this
structure and understand a question
and then being able
to go out and search,
that requires a more
complex cognitive model.
>> The way in which these systems are built
is for the most part very, very labor
intensive.
They involve humans
spending a great deal
of time structuring the ways in
which these kinds of sentences
can be represented in some logic.
It gets even a little
more complex, though.
>> Even once we've dealt
with semantics, we'll
still have to look at the
pragmatics of what's being said.
That is, how do I relate the words
that I have to something physically out
there in the world or at
least some information source
that I can manipulate?
>> Sometimes, these lead to
wonderful bits of ambiguity.
"Red-hot star to wed astronomer."
OK.
Now, we read that as the
funny type of headline
that we would see on late night TV
because we don't interpret "star"
to have its celestial body meaning.
We know that it means the more
commonplace actor or actress
with high amounts of visibility.
>> "Squad helps dog bite victim."
Is it that the squad is actually
out there assisting a dog
in going around and biting victims?
Or is it that there was
an individual who was
bitten by a dog who needed some help?
Just from looking at the syntax
and the semantics of the sentences,
we can't determine that.
>> "Helicopter powered by human flies."
Are there, in fact, actual
little things flying around that
are people with wings powering
helicopters for the good of mankind?
Or is there one mechanical device
that derives its power from a person?
>> When we look at question
answering systems,
these are the layers that
we need to deal with.
Now, the best and the most sort
of prevalent of these systems
today are able to do
things at a level that are
far beyond what we had 10 years ago.
Here's one of the best systems
that's out there today.
And this is a system
from IBM called Watson.
This is from our friends at IBM.
This is Katherine banks, Jia Chen,
and Priscilla Moraes giving us
a demonstration of Watson
yesterday in IBM Yorktown.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-How are you?
>> -I am well.
I am always happy when I am
thinking, especially when I
can stay cool in these server rooms.
-Who is your favorite actress?
>> -My favorite actress
Angelina Jolie as Lara Croft
in Tomb Raider because her original
form was as a virtual character like me.
>> -How can Watson help patients?
>> -Is the plan for patients to
have access to Watson directly?
Access to Watson advisory
applications will vary by use case.
But currently, Watson will only provide
possible diagnosis and treatment
options to medical professional.
Where appropriate, patients
may provide information
to Watson, perhaps through a
portal web interface, tablet,
or even a mobile phone.
For example, a patient may be
asked to describe their symptoms
in natural language directly
into a Watson solution,
allowing the physician to focus on
diagnosis and not data collection.
>> -Who assassinated Abraham Lincoln?
>> -John Wilkes Booth.
>> -In what year did the Arizona
Diamondbacks win the World Series?
>> -2001.
>> [END PLAYBACK]
>> BRIAN SCASSELLATI: So
these kinds of systems
have to rely upon first of all
recognizing the speech; second,
converting it into a meaningful internal
representation; and then, third,
being able to go out and find
the information source that
allows them to answer that question.
This level of complexity involves
the same types of programmatic things
that you have been
doing in problem sets.
>> We're able to parse HTTP requests in
the same type of low-level pattern
matching that ELIZA can do.
We're able to convert those
into an internal representation,
and then use them to query some
external database, possibly using SQL.
All of the systems that
are being built today
to do this type of natural
language communication
are being built upon
these same principles.
>> Now, even a system like
Watson isn't complex enough
to be able to answer arbitrary
questions about any topic.
And in fact, they have to be
structured within a given domain.
So you can go online and you can find
versions of Watson that operate well
within medical informatics.
Or there's one online
that just deals with how
to make good recommendations about
what beer will go with which food.
And within those domains,
it can answer questions,
find the information that it needs.
>> But you can't mix and match them.
The system that's been trained
with the database of food and beer
doesn't work well when you suddenly
put it in with the medical informatics
database.
So even our best systems today
rely upon a level of processing
in which we are hand coding and
building in the infrastructure in order
to make this system run.
>> Now, the last topic I want
to be able to get to today
is about nonverbal communication.
A great mass of information that
we communicate with each other
doesn't come about through the
individual words that we're applying.
It has to do with things like
proximity, gaze, your tone of voice,
your inflection.
And that communication is also
something that many different interfaces
care a great deal about.
It's not what Siri cares about.
I can ask Siri something in one voice
or in a different tone of voice,
and Siri's going to
give me the same answer.
But that's not what we build for
many other types of interfaces.
>> I want to introduce you
now to one of the robots.
This was built by my longtime
friend and colleague Cynthia
Breazeal and her company Jibo.
And this robot-- we're going
to have a couple volunteers
come up to interact with this.
So can I have two people willing
to play with the robot for me?
Why don't you come on up,
and why don't you come on up.
If you'd join me up here, please.
>> And if I could have you
come right over here.
Thanks.
Hi.
>> ALFREDO: Nice to meet you.
Alfredo.
>> BRIAN SCASSELLATI: Alfredo.
>> RACHEL: Rachel.
BRIAN SCASSELLATI: Rachel.
Nice to meet you both.
Alfredo, I'm going to have you go first.
Come right up here.
I'm going to introduce
you-- if I can get this off
without knocking the microphone--
to a little robot named Jibo.
OK?
>> Now, Jibo is designed to be interactive.
And although it can give you speech,
much of the interaction with the robot
is nonverbal.
Alfredo, I'm going to ask you to
say something nice and complimentary
to the robot, please.
ALFREDO: I think you look cute.
>> [WHIRRING SOUND]
BRIAN SCASSELLATI: OK.
Its response isn't verbal.
And yet it gave you both
a clear acknowledgement
that it had heard what you said
and also somehow understood that.
OK?
Step right back here for one second.
Thank you.
>> Rachel, if you would.
Now, I'm going to give
you the much harder job.
If you'd stand right here,
back up just a little bit so
we can get you on camera
and look this way.
I'm going to ask you to say something
really mean and nasty to the robot.
>> RACHEL: What you just seemed
to do was completely absurd.
>> [HUMMING SOUND]
>> That was even more absurd.
What's going on with you?
Aw, don't feel bad.
I'll give you a hug.
BRIAN SCASSELLATI: All right.
Thanks, Rachel.
Alfredo, Rachel, thanks guys very much.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> So this kind of interaction has in
many ways some of the same rules
and some of the same
structure as what we
might have in linguistic interaction.
It is both communicative and
serves an important purpose.
And that interaction, in
many ways, is designed
to have a particular effect on the
person interacting with or listening
to the robot.
>> Now, I'm lucky enough
to have Jibo here today.
Sam Spaulding is here helping
us out with the robot.
And I'm going to ask Sam to give
us one nice demo of Jibo dancing
that we can watch at the end here.
So go ahead, Jibo.
>> SAM: OK, Jibo.
Show us your dance moves.
>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
BRIAN SCASSELLATI: All right, everybody.
Thanks to our friends at Jibo.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> And thanks to our friends at
IBM for helping out today.
Communication is something
that you're going
to see coming up more and more as
we build more complex interfaces.
Next week, we'll be talking
about how to interface
with computer opponents in games.
But if you have questions about this,
I'll be around at office hours tonight.
I'm happy to talk to you about AI
topics or to get into more detail.
Have a great weekend.
>> [APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]